But now I'm just going to start and talk about the movie.
And the one more thing I want to say, you should know Graham Green is a religious Catholic, and it's a deeply Christian book, though he says in his introduction, he thought it was an entertainment and just a light entertainment.
That's why they thought she should put her arm through her hand through on his arm, because that's how light entertainments are supposed to end.
But author is right out of understanding that they have, even if they don't know they have it, and even if they don't know they're expressing it.
And this is a deeply, brilliantly Christian book.
And Graham Green was expressing something that he undoubtedly felt, even though he didn't know he was.
So now we're going to just talk about it until at the end of today we get back to the scene and why at the end and why it's so important.
But to start with, you get the entertainment side of it.
It's a very funny book in that there are all kinds of reversals in it, which are funny and sad and surprising and scary.
And I'm just going to remind you of them because the movie is structured around reversals like this.
Well, to begin with, of course, Holly arrives in Vienna to find that his friend Harry is dead.
That's a big surprise and reversal.
Then it turns out he isn't dead, which is another surprise and reversal.
He's the third man.
And then in the end, Holly kills him.
That's pretty surprising, too.
A more perfect example of the entertainment is the kidnapping in the taxi, where it looks like he's been taken away from the hotel by this cab driver who's driving like a maniac and who won't speak to him.
And everybody is just having to get out of the way of the taxi.
And it looks like he's, and he looks like he's going to be in some sinister, taken to some sinister castle where they might torture him or even kill him.
And then, and he tries to escape when he, when the cab door is open, but the cab door gets in the way, and then the door to this sinister-looking place out in the country opens.
And what is it?
It's the meeting of the literary society that he's promised to talk to in order to get money to stay in Vienna.
And the reversal is that they torture him with questions about James Joyce and the crisis of faith, that he looks absolutely miserable.
And then these thugs arrive and try to kill him.
So that's what it looked like it was going to be all along.
So another one, remember the shadow that comes around the corner when they're waiting for Harry Lyme?
It's an amazing thing, this big shadow.
But then the shadow turns out to be a balloon man, but then the balloon man, the camera dwells and dwells on the balloon man.
So you think, well, there must be something special.
Maybe it's Orson Welles that is Harry Lyme in disguise.
And then it turns out he really is a balloon man, and he sells a balloon to Payne, has to buy the balloon to get him to go away.
So that, and then, at the last reversal, I told you first, it looks like they're going to get together, and then at the last, and she gets closer and closer to him, and then it turns out she doesn't, she walks right by him.
And as we'll go back to this, he lights a cigarette and throws it away with a gesture, the same gesture that he used earlier to express sort of total incomprehension.
And if they had walked off in the sunset together, the whole movie would have made absolutely no sense.
But the way it ends is exactly how it has to end.
And now I'm going to try to convince you that.
Oh, look what I found.
It's just as well to tell you here that this is what it was going to end like.
He caught up with her and they walked side by side.
I don't think he said a word to her.
This is Calloway narrating.
It was like the end of a story, except that before they turned out of my sight, her hand was through his arm.
And that they disagreed about that.
And I already told you this disagreement, which I won't read, but this much.
Graham Green thought that an entertainment of this kind was too light an affair to carry the weight of an unhappy ending.
And Carol Reed, the director, thought it would strike audiences as unpleasantly cynical.
And so they decided to not have it happen that way.
And then you see what happens.
So I'm going to try to convince you.
I don't think it's hard.
I think you can help.
I mean, you can give me more evidence or tell me I'm not convincing you.
I'm going to make the case that Hannah and Holly could never get together.
They are diametrical opposites.
It's even wrong, really, to say that they're opposites, because opposites have to be in the same dimension at different ends of the dimension.
You get to see real opposites in your next movie when you see Breathless at different ends of a dimension.
But this is really even more extreme.
They're in different worlds.
They are, we'll have to explain bit by bit what worlds they're in.
But they are in incommensurate spheres of existence, to call it therapy guard chart.
They're just two different ways of understanding what a human being are and what human beings should do and what the world is there for and so forth.
And so the question then is: if you're just seeing the movie, you want to know at the end, well, why does she just walk past him?
And to find out, we've got to talk about all of the four main characters: Holly Martens, Harry Lynn, and Anna and Calloway, and what sphere of existence they are each in, and why they can't possibly even communicate or understand each other.
Okay, let's start with Holly.
Holly is, in a certain way, maybe another reversal now that I think of it, because in a cafe, Anna says to him with disgust, honest, sensible, sober, harmless Holly Martins.
And in fact, he does tell the truth, and he is most of the time sober, and certainly sensible and boring.
Even the cat just yawns, remember, when he tries to play with the cat and runs off to play with Harry who's waiting under the window.
And there's one place where he says, I could stand on my head and make funny faces at you between my legs, and she looks like such a pained expression.
But that's the best he can do.
But the interesting thing is, is he harmless?
And you ask yourself the question: given the deaths in the movie, who's responsible for the kid, the kids that die outside the movie, we know Harry Lyme has killed lots of them.
But there are three, well, let's go, three people who get killed in the movie.
Who are they?
Harry Lyme gets killed.
The porter gets killed.
Who else?
I can't think of the other one myself.
Oh, Payne.
Yes, Payne gets killed.
Now ask yourself, who's responsible for all those deaths?
Well, who killed the porter?
Well, Harry killed the porter, really.
That's why you have this weird look on the porter's face.
I had to see the movie a few times before I realized that the porter wasn't looking just good grief, somebody's coming to kill me.
You see that scene of him just before he did.
He's thinking, I'm seeing a ghost, because he believes that Harry Lyme is dead.
But anyway, Harry Lyme kills the porter, but who's responsible for that murder?
Yes, Holly, for talking to Kurtz or whoever it was and saying, you know, the porter has seen that there was a third man.
And the proof that Holly is the murderer, do you remember what the little, I think maybe it's only in German, the little kids going around saying something while they're wh while when the police are there.
Is it in German or is it in English?
The little kid is saying, he's the murderer, he's the murderer, and pointing it at at Holly.
And in Graham Greene movies in general, little kids know what's going on, really know.
Oh, anyway, so so there he's responsible for the death of a porter.
He's responsible for the death of Payne because Payne runs out to try to protect Holly, who's stupidly run out with in the into the sewer without any taking any cover.
And for now, I've lost the last.
Oh, and of course, Holly kills Harry, Feynman, Harry's with Harry's permission.
But anyway, he's not harmless.
And even his kind of honesty is dangerous because it's because he tells these bad guys all the time when they ask sort of what he knows and what's going on that he gets everybody else into trouble.
So he's relatively easy to talk about.
So let's go on to Harry.
Harry's much more interesting and complicated.
Harry is just the opposite of Holly in many, many ways.
In fact, you could write them on the board.
I'm going to give you this chart at the end, but I don't want you to have it now because it will just get you ahead of the story.
And it's important to follow it step by step.
So there is something here which is Harry, and over here is Holly.
And what are we going to find out?
Well, we found out already that over here is harmless, which is really dangerous.
Well, I don't want to write more on it right now.
Over here, he's funny, entertaining.
Everything is such fun with him.
He's dangerous too, in a different way.
And, okay, I'll write the next when we get there.
Let's go back to where we are.
Okay.
He is ruthless.
Absolutely ruthless, selfish.
He, he meaning Harry Lynn.
Ruthless and selfish as you can get.
The clearest thing is he's ready to kill his best friend if he to save his own skin.
That happens in the Ferris wheel, remember how it goes, how he's very glad to see Holly, and it looks like Holly's the only one.
Then he discovers that Holly knows that he, obviously Holly knows that he's alive, and he discovers that Holly's the only one who knows that he's alive.
Then this not so subtle thing happens.
I think this movie is a lot easier to follow than Hiroshima.
Then immediately he threatens to shoot him.
He says, well, nobody will find the bullet when your body hits the ground down there.
And he's just ready to shoot him when Harry, who's, I'm sorry, when Holly's, who's sort of smart about, says to him immediately, I've told Calloway and Anna.
And then Harry switches immediately from this ruthless, selfish attitude back to being very affectionate and friendly and so forth.
And what you see in there is that, but it's more, I mean, it's, I've got to explain it better.
It isn't as if he doesn't really care about Holly.
In fact, he cares about Holly so much that he's ready to risk his life just to see Holly.
Remember, he says, I'll meet you in the international zone, but don't come with any police.
But it's taking a big risk to do that.
And in fact, it ends in getting Harry killed.
But even more interesting and strange, and I'm not even sure my view of this is right, what's he doing under Anna's window?
Well, I take it it's because he really loves her in his way and cares about her and misses her and wants to see her that he's out hanging around under her window.
And so what is his character?
What is his problem?
Well, his problem is only this, that he cares about himself more than anybody.
I think he loves her.
We know that he's written her very good love letters, good meaning she doesn't want anybody else to read them, intimate love letters.
We know that he's hiding there in the doorway.
I think there's every reason to think that in a certain sense he loves her, but she is not his unconditional commitment.
He loves her that there's one person he loves more, namely him, Harry Lyme.
He's ready to sacrifice his best male friend and his girlfriend to save his own skin.
He is totally self-love, totally self-centered, like a child.
But nonetheless, he's not a child.
He understands affection for his old buddy, and he understands something almost like as near love as you can get for Anna.
But as soon as his life is threatened, he'll betray and kill his closest friend and the woman he loves.
And that is, in a way, absolute evil in the Catholic perspective.
The people who are at the bottom of the inferno in Dante are people who have betrayed people they love.
The idea that they love themselves more than anybody is exactly the ultimate sin.
And it's not just lower immediacy.
Children don't get to the bottom of hell.
It's because they betray the people that they're intimate with and love that they get to the bottom of hell.
And he has actually, it goes by very fast, betrayed Anna, literally.
You know, how many realize that he turns her over to the Russians in order to be protected in the Russian zone?
It goes very fast, and presumably what they want from her is to understand how she got this passport, this illegal passport.
But it says, at one point, just as things are going, Martin, that Holly says, you informed on her.
Harry, with a smile, don't be a policeman, old man.
I didn't believe the police when they told me about you.
Were you going to cut me in on the spoils and so forth?
Anyway, he has just done the ultimate thing.
And I just realized how interesting he's really complicated.
Because what does he put on the window of the Paris wheel at the bottom?
Remember, in the sort of steamy window, he puts something when he's talking about Anna.
He puts a heart with an arrow through it.
And that's not irony.
That's a Valentine.
I mean, he is, he loves Anna, and he turns her over to the Russians to save his skin.
That's the kind of person he is.
And that's absolute selfishness.
And it leads to a kind of despair.
If you are a religious sort of person who understands love and betrayal then you are going to feel despair when you trump your love with your to save your skin and there is this fascinating conversation on page 112.
I give these pages not because I think you all have them, but some of you will be writing on this and want to know where I said these things.
So he says, Martin says to him, you used to believe in God.
A shade of melancholy crosses Harry's face.
Oh, I still believe, old man, in God and mercy and all that.
And then he says something which isn't in the script.
Orson Welles is just so amazing.
He says, and what do you believe in?
And the answer is, of course, that Holly doesn't believe in anything.
We'll go back to that.
In fact, we could go to that right now.
By the way, on 113, the script is wrong.
It says in the film, there's a dialogue here where Martin's, that is, Holly, says, what do you believe in?
And that's not, of course, isn't what happens.
It's Harry who says to Holly, what do you believe in?
And it's that.
But all I want to stress now is that Harry is certainly in the religious dimension.
And we could put in some other things now.
He's betrayed the person he loves.
And he's got this kind of melancholy I just read about when asked about what he believes in.
I take it melancholy is some form of despair.
I mean, he knows that what he's doing is wrong, and he can't help doing it.
And Holly, do I want to add anything more?
Well, he also betrays his best friend.
How does he betray his best friend, just to keep the plot in mind?
He's the one who acts as the, quote, dumb decoy duck that gets Harry Lyme to show up in the international zone and thereby be captured.
Although it turns out he ends up being killed, that that wasn't part of the plan.
And he wants him to be captured.
But now the interesting thing is, both of these betrayers are in the negative form of something.
This is the negative religious.
And this is, I haven't explained this at all yet, the negative ethic.
All I'm saying right now is that the way they betray their loves, let's call them, their intimate other, is totally different.
And it begins to make you begin to realize how different they are.
So we see Harry Lyme betrays Anna out of selfishness.
And why does Holly betray Harry?
That is, why does he agree to turn Harry over to the police?
It isn't selfishness for sure.
Yeah, exactly.
Halloway shows him the children.
When he sees the children, he sees that it's right to turn over Harry because he's a murderer, even though it means hurting somebody he cares a whole lot about.
He still cares about him.
She says, Hannah says, Anna says to him, you loved him, I loved him, and now look what we've done for him.
But anyway, so what is from the point of view that Holly has, this betrayal is not only okay, it's good, it's honorable.
It's like, what, Agamemnon killing Ephigenia?
That is a lower immediacy or a lower ethical, either way you want to put it, a feeling for Ephigenia or the duty of father, and here a feeling, a warm feeling for Harry or the duty of friend, trumps, sorry, gets trumped by a higher duty, namely turn in murderers.
And so he does it.
So they do it for this, he does it for a bad reason, betrays his love out of sheer selfishness, love of himself, betrays his best friend out of a painful, tragic choice from his point of view, and rightly from his, that is, of having to subsume him under a higher ethical.
Well, I think I've got enough there.
I can put that up there, yes.
We'll get more people in a minute.
So where are we now?
So in a way, Harry is in hell already in melancholy, in despair, and he's sort of at the bottom of the inferno, the nearest thing being the sewer.
Most of the time we see him at night, and by the end of the movie, most of the time we've seen him is in the sewer.
But there's an interesting thing that he's reaching up, obviously trying to escape, but it's as if he's also reaching up from the lower depths to, when you see his hands sort of groping out of the grating, I think you can't help seeing him sort of reaching for freedom but not being able to make it, and reaching for sort of God but not being able to make it.
In the religious dimension, you're always, well, even sinners are possible saints and could be saved up to the last minute.
And even saints are possible sinners that could be saved up to the last minute.
It's a reversible dimension.
And he's sort of striving upward from the bottom of the sewer, from the bottom of hell, but of course he can't do it.
And he can't do it because, again, he's stuck on protecting himself.
And now I should say someplace, something about names.
So let me say something about names right now.
I could have started with Holly, who has, well, for one thing, the book is sort of obsessed with names.
Everybody's concerned about their name.
Calloway doesn't like to be called Callahan.
Holly certainly doesn't like to be called Harry.
Dr.
Winkle doesn't like to be called Dr.
Winkle by people who don't know how to talk German.
And there's a place where Holly actually calls attention to his name.
Calloway says, be sensible, Martin.
And Martin says, I haven't got a sensible name.
And that's true.
Whatever Holly is there, it was Rollo in a script, but I think they very cleverly turned it to Harry so that, to Holly, so that she could mix him up with Harry all the time.
But what do you think of when you think of Holly?
Is it a, I mean, anything come to mind?
There's no great, big secret here.
I'm just trying to give a feel for these various things.
Let's try the others because they're clearer.
Let's, well, Harry Lyme.
Oh, that's a crazy one, too, but I can't resist.
A very smart student, perhaps too clever by half, I'm not sure, pointed out to me that this lime fits perfectly for Harry Lyme, particularly in the sewer scene, because there's a line from Hamlet.
Does anybody know Hamlet well enough to know the line, O limed soul that struggles to be free, art more engaged?
That's what Claudius, a big sinner who's killed off the king and so forth, is trying to pray, but he can't pray because he's too happy with his good fortune, having taken over the kingdom and taken over the guy's wife and so forth.
But lime is a sticky substance used to catch birds, and the more the bird struggles to be free, the more it's trapped.
Now, it does fit perfectly for Harry Lyme.
I just don't know whether to believe that that could have been going through the conscious or unconscious of Graham Greene or not.
But Talloway is an easy one.
I mean, what does Calloway make you think of?
Tallus, exactly.
Now, is he really Tallus?
Not at all.
But it looks callous, like when he takes the love letters.
He's just professional, as Payne says.
He says, we're like doctors.
We just have to do this job, but we don't really, we don't, you know, read the letters to hear your, to find out your private life.
So, but Calloway looks callous to Anna because in his doing his professional duty, he doesn't respect her letters or her life or her point of view at all.
We'll come back to that.
And Anna, I mean, it's easy to say that Anna is religious.
She's capable of total love, complete devotion, will sacrifice herself for Harry if she could.
And she's named Anna.
Anna's a saint.
Anna's, what, the mother of Mary, I think.
Was that right?
And Anne, St.
Anne.
And so, and that name fits for her.
Now, Holly's guy is back to Holly.
The most I can say about Holly is that it sounds plastic, it sounds sort of like Hollywood.
Maybe again, the same very, very clever student says, Holly looks nice, but it's really poisonous.
That's true.
I don't know whether that's what was on their mind.
But anyway, all these names mean something.
But why am I saying this?
I guess I'm saying it just because I was saying that Harry is in a certain way already sort of in hell, striving to get out into the out and not being able to.
Let's see.
Yeah, this reversible religious dimension comes out in the very beginning in a funny way.
The mixture of entertainment and deep religion is just amazing in this movie.
You remember what the porter says about Harry Lyme, who's dead?
He's either in heaven, no, sorry, he's in heaven or in hell.
That is, he just reverses the dimensions.
And the movie immediately cuts to the next scene where they're burying Harry Lyme, and the priest is saying descended into hell for three days and rose on the third day.
That is, there is a constant sort of traffic between sinners and saints, heaven and hell, going on in this Christian dimension.
And so where are we now?
Descended into hell and rose on the seventh day.
I said third, but I wrote it down here.
Now, let's do Anna.
Put Anna.
Okay, Anna's over here.
She's clearly the positive religion.
Well, she's so she's got unconditional commitment.
I'm going to give you this handout so you don't have to read my writing.
She's selfless.
She doesn't think about herself at all when she's being carried off by the Russians to their headquarters because she's been turned in.
And then she hears that Harry is still alive.
She completely forgets her problem that she's about to be exported, or what is it, extradited or something back to Czechoslovakia.
And she's only interested in, is Harry all right?
Is he hurt?
Where is he?
And so forth.
Now, something I haven't mentioned here, well, let's bring it up first.
You might ask yourself, and I'm sort of warning you about what I think is a danger in writing a possible paper, but you can still trump me, but you've got to at least be aware that it might be misleading.
In Kierkegaard terms, what kind of person do you think she is?
I mean, is she a night of faith or a night of resignation?
Well, it's hard to tell that you're having a sensible reaction.
It's too soon to tell because she's in grief, and she says that he will always be a part of her.
But, well, you have a hand up.
Go ahead.
Yeah, well, I thought she said that he would always be a part of her.
That's right.
And you're going to give someone back in.
Oh, good, good.
That's interesting.
Yeah, that's what I think is the trap.
I think it's misleading, but let's go through it.
One thing is that they both sound the same in this business of, or even not, I mean, she says he's a part of me.
He's in me.
And it certainly always will be a part of me.
I think of that as the interiorizing that goes on in grief, but it's too early to tell.
But it isn't as if she's saying, I'll always remember him.
It's that she's letting go, I think, of remembering him.
I think maybe she is when she's in his bedroom and she's looking at the comb and putting it back in the drawer.
I think it's clearer that she's letting go of him, that is, accepting the fact that he's dead and gone and just second and put away.
But the first time he's buried, she does not throw dirt into the grave.
It's interesting.
She does not, somehow, with a kind of mystical intuition, I don't understand, she senses that he's not really dead, or she senses that she's not ready to accept him as really dead or something.
But the second time, she does throw the dirt in the grave.
And I think that's also saying, this is now over.
I'm putting it in the past.
It's changed me.
It's part of me.
But I'm not going to dwell on it.
I'm going to dwell in it, to use this kind of slogan I use.
And I think she'll find another, I think she's a knight of faith, and I think she'll find another lover when she gets over her grief.
Let me just say, well, first, he had a handout.
Yeah.
She keeps calling Holly Harry once he insists on getting the love letters back then.
Nice point.
I don't know.
I like that.
I mean, the mixing up and calling him Harry and Holly, again, I just think that's so soon.
What happens when they're ready to go for a drink?
She says, you know, Holly always, or Harry always said, let's go for a drink.
And she, she, I mean, I can understand that.
Getting the love letters back, when does she insist on getting the love letters back?
Well, she doesn't say, am I going to get them back?
The pain says, don't worry, you're going to get them back.
Isn't that what happens?
I want to say she doesn't care whether she gets them back, but I don't know.
We'd have to, I don't want to take time in the lecture because I don't think I can flip to it.
But but if you're interested, it's important, he's right, to ask yourself the question, what is her attitude toward those love letters?
I have another very funny reason why I think she's a knight of fate, but it's very important for this course, so I have to go into it.
What does she play when she plays in the theater?
She's a singer and an actress.
Comedies or tragedies?
Comedies.
Do you understand what that means?
What is a comedy?
Of course, it's something funny and people laugh, but that's not the essence of comedies.
You may have learned this in school when you were learning about tragedies and comedies.
Supposedly, in comedies, the problems are reconciled and everything turns out all right.
That should remind you of Kierkegaard saying that in the world of the spirit, he who is ready to suffer anguish gets the bread.
I think that she's in this dimension where everybody gets what they deserve, and she certainly suffers, she seems to be, or she may well be suffering grief in the right way, in which case she'll get another lover in due course.
Wait, first he had his hand up.
Yeah.
She does.
Very good.
I was going to mention that, but forgot.
That's, from my point of view, the trap will lead you into thinking she's in resignation when I think she has to be, just for the structure of the book.
She has to be the highest form of Christian.
She has to be, I think, a total lover.
She's, you know, she's at the top of, you know, she lives in the attic while he lives in the sewer, so to speak.
She has to be the top sort of Christian, I think.
But of course, grief, she has to go through grief in the right way.
And all of you always seem to look at me with resistance when I try to say that grief is the paradoxical emotion in which you naturally think that this is the last time.
There's no other way to think about it.
You can't, this is the defining relation, and it defines all the characteristics of what counts as sexy and funny and good-looking and so forth.
You won't have another opportunity, it feels like, when you've lost them and you're in grief, until you've made the movement complete of interiorizing them.
But so we can't tell.
I'm neutral.
I mean, I'm not saying, look, she says, I don't want to fall in love again.
I can't say that proves that she's going through grief in the right way.
I just want to say you can't tell when she says that.
I mean, if she had said, I still love him and I will always love him, that would be getting to be suspicious.
But all she says is, I don't want to love anybody else.
And I think I understand what that means.
Go ahead.
By virtue of the impossible, so to speak.
But who's the clue?
Who's clear than I got?
Holly?
Perry.
A knight of resignation.
What did you say?
I just misunderstood you.
I don't get my virtual.
Harry Lyme?
No, he's a total sinner.
And with complete an unconditional commitment to himself.
That is not what a knight of resignation has.
Let's get this straight.
A knight of resignation has a condition, is self-contained, but they have a condition to the memory of the lover, not to themselves, but to the remembering, preserving the meaning of this relationship, whether they're in it or whether the person is dead.
To be a knight of resignation is a high-level thing.
It's a form.
I mean, the Harry Lyn is just a villain.
I mean, the Lemiula puzzle.
I mean, he has no redeeming features.
I'll be interested, yeah?
I work to whether you could have.
Yeah, well, the answer is no.
But, well, that's no.
Let me take that back.
The important thing is: would it give you the vulnerability that comes with the finite and the temporal?
And the answer is no.
It wouldn't, because you couldn't lose yourself, or at least if you did, you wouldn't be around to be vulnerable about it.
And you don't have, there wouldn't be a certain moment when all of a sudden you fell in love with yourself and it was the instant.
And from then on, you understood that you had been in love with yourself all along.
That's just not sensible phenomenology.
So it's, but Kierkegaard does say that the knight of resignation discovers that they're sufficient unto themselves because they've taken over and incorporated the meaning of their involvement.
But you can't define yourself in terms, I think we have a paper topic on that, don't we?
So I better stop talking about it.
Is there a paper topic that says, can you have a defining relation to the ethical?
Can you have a defining relation to yourself?
It may be the first one.
Well, that's just as well.
Then I can talk about it.
So you can't define yourself in terms of the ethical because it's not vulnerable.
And you really can't see the sword hanging over the head of the beloved if the beloved is you and live as if it's the surest thing of all.
I mean, you could say what that meant was.
You could see that you could be killed, but you live as if you wouldn't be.
But that'd be a funny way to think about it.
Let me see if I can say anything more.
It seems so obvious to me, that's hard.
Well, Kierkegaard thinks, anyway, let's get that straight.
That you've got to have a defining commitment to something outside yourself.
And he says it in the thing I've handed out.
Well, I can know.
That would be very confusing.
Never mind.
We'll get to it next time.
But you've got to have an unconditional commitment for something outside of specifically for Kierkegaard.
But that's because it's got to do with the finite and temporal.
I don't know what more to say, but I see that people are confused and not satisfied with this.
Let me see.
Being a sinner, an ultimate selfish sinner, is very, very different than being a knight of resignation, who is admirable, who loves God, who is in a kind of serene state and so forth.
It just doesn't fit.
Yeah.
Good thinking.
Well, it's not above the universal.
But both of you, you're absolutely right.
It's not just lower immediacy.
The way he's related to himself, remember, I said isn't just like a child.
If it were, I would have an easy answer to you.
But it isn't like that.
He's like the Knight of Resignation.
He understands the attraction of the ethical.
Harry does.
It's just that he finds his own well-being higher.
And the other thing you said was important, too.
What was it?
Oh, yeah.
It's funny.
I was going to say that, and then I thought I could get away with not saying it.
I was going to, you got me.
I was going to say, and look, the night of resignation isn't in despair, but of course, the night of resignation is sort of in this is in despair, as we discovered at the end of Hiroshima Monomore, or because the night of resignation, get the finite and temporal related in the right way.
So it's a topic.
I mean, I see that I can't make a case that is knocked down and drag out convincing.
But my intuition is untouched.
I mean, if you look at her, Anna, and where she lives and the way she lives and how she reacts, everything she does is sort of saint.
She is a saint.
And in Kierkegaard language, that would have to be a night of faith.
It's really a Catholic book.
That's part of the problem.
We have trouble sort of mashing the Catholic book into Protestant categories here.
But insofar as being a knight of resignation is, so to speak, second best, Anna can't be a knight of resignation.
Anna is best.
She is the absolutely positive.
If you could make the case that there isn't anything higher than resignation, I would begin to worry.
But it's clear that there's something higher than resignation.
There is total devotion and total devotion to an actual other person.
And that's what she's certainly got.
Okay, I think that's fascinating, but now I've got to go back to this or I'll run out of time.
Let's see.
But let's read what she says.
She says things, I've listed them here, that sound like resignation, but they could equally sound like grief.
She says, I want to be dead too.
And that's, and she says, I don't want to fall in love again.
And all I can say is everybody, any, if you don't go through that kind of grief, you couldn't become a knight of resignation or a knight of faith.
So she's got to go through that grief.
Okay, I can't do more.
And so let me go on.
So she says, however, also that Harry is a part of her.
He is in her.
I mentioned that.
She's not trying, I don't think she's trying to remember him, his voice, his hands, and so forth.
And now, but I've said, oh, I can.
I shouldn't even have started falling back into it again.
But another way to put it, and now we better get to the crucial thing.
Yeah, let's talk about one more important thing about her.
And it has to do with how she reacts when she sees that Harry has killed lots of children with the doctored penicillin.
Now, we said that when Harry, sorry, when Holly sees the evidence, then he moves to a higher ethical and he helps turn in Harry.
He does the heroic thing, he subsumes loyalty to Harry under a higher ethical, and he goes out to help catch the murderer.
Now, what does Anna think about that?
That's what gets interesting.
She says, you're beginning to get a clue when we start thinking about this, about how the movie has to end.
What does she say to Holly in the important conversation in the cafe in the railroad station when she's telling him how much she detests him, in effect?
She says, there's a name for faces like yours.
What's she saying?
What's the name?
What is he doing from her point of view when he's there in that railroad station?
Well, she's helping the police, he's helping the police catch Harry.
He's betraying Harry.
The name for that face is police informer, but more generic name for it is betrayer.
She's got a view about betrayal, which is utterly different than Harry's, who just does it because he can't help being a sinner and feels despair about it, or Holly, who betrays because he rightly sees that he's making, or from his point of view, rightly sees, a heroic choice of suspending the lower ethical for a higher ethical.
What's her view?
Her view is that once you love somebody unconditionally, you can't betray them.
It's not even, and now let me read you the kinds where it becomes.
So when she finds out that Harry is a murderer, what does she say?
Very important lines on 93 and 94.
They're so important that I'll just read them.
And then we have to understand them.
She says, there are so many things you don't know about a person you love, good things, bad things.
And then she says, a man doesn't alter because you find out more.
That's the crucial line.
Why is that important?
Well, that's important because what she's saying is: if you love somebody so that they're the paradigm, then everything gets its meaning through that relationship.
And everything.
So that even being a murderer is relative to the fact that it's Harry Lyme, the most important, not only the most important thing in the world, the person who defines what matters in the world and defines what counts as important in good and bad.
That person, no matter what properties you find out about him, good things and bad things on 93, you don't alter your relation because you find out more.
Nothing, and it's almost a tautology.
Nothing trumps an unconditional commitment.
That's what she's saying.
Nothing you could find out about somebody, no property of Harry Lyme, could trump the fact that he's her unconditional commitment, her savior, the one who gave her her identity.
Another bride student pointed out to me that he gave her her identity papers, too.
And that crucial person is just, if you have a real unconditional commitment, you can't betray them.
You can't, there's no position from which you could hurt them.
And she said, and this is the moment, really, in the movie, when her view and Holly Martin's view just simply diverge.
She's got this unconditionally commitment.
No possible, while all the others have their mode of betrayal, selfish betrayal, ethical betrayal, and so forth.
For her, it's impossible.
And now, and let me, I'm trying to keep track of all these things.
So that means, so total, I guess, totally faithful.
I'm not anything about faith.
I'm just saying once your love has been made in heaven, you can't go against it without despair and destroying your whole identity.
Okay, now when you see that, you see how far it is from Holly Martin's, because Holly Martin's has got a view that when you find out something else about somebody you sort of loved in his sense of love, she says, What do you mean, love?
How do you spell the word?
Because when he, so, because his view of love is, it's just another strong relation which gets trumped when you discover that the guy's a murderer.
She says, and Martin is done.
He says, you still love Harry, don't you?
But then this is the crucial moment when they sort of, you see the utter difference.
He says, I hate, well, she says, a man doesn't alter because you find out more.
And he says, I hate the way you talk.
I've got a splitting headache, and you talk and you talk.
You make me cross.
At that point, he's really saying, I can't understand what you're saying.
I can't even picture what that world would be because he's over here in his kind of ethical.
Okay, I'm going to put that aside for a while, but I'll come back to it.
I have to see where we are.
So what she's doing is incomprehensible to him.
She thinks that betraying one individual you love is worse than being a mass murderer.
You realize that.
She's saying that you, she's saying to Holly, you are worse than Harry.
You betrayed somebody you loved.
And that is, and I more detest that, I more hate that than I do somebody whom I love who's a mass murderer.
Now, I want to test her intuitions because I'm always interested in sort of where the world is in these issues, and you are where the world is.
So, yeah.
Ah, you have, yeah, yes, she does, because she's been told.
So, he's betrayed her.
Right.
Isn't that interesting?
I wasn't going to bring it up because I thought it would maybe cross too many people's wires, but that's important.
Because you could ask, but how come she so much hates Harry for betraying her?
And she forgives Holly for betraying her.
And what's the answer?
Yeah.
That's a good move.
I hadn't thought of it that way.
One, you could say, well, he doesn't have an unconditional commitment to her.
He just likes her a lot.
I would rather say yes to Harry.
And what follows from that, I'm not sure we're saying the same thing.
But all I want, and the simple thing to say is, well, being a betrayer is just another property you can find out about somebody.
No property, even the ultimate property, that they're a sinner who belongs at the bottom of hell, can trump the fact that they're your defining commitment that gives you your identity.
Because that defining commitment determines the significance of all possible properties of that person, including, and that's why it's such an interesting thing, like Beatrice asks, including being a betrayer.
She knows it, and because it's Harry who's the betrayer, she forgives him.
She doesn't have a universal kind of ethical conviction, don't betray.
That's another way to put it.
If she had the principle, don't betray, then we'd have to say, well, how come she's holding it against Harry that he's a betrayer?
Why doesn't she hold it against Holly that he's a betrayer?
Why doesn't she hold it against Harry that he's in a betrayer?
That was what Beatrice rightly asks.
And the answer is, because she's not ethical.
Because if she were ethical, she would have to, you know, do the ethical is don't make a special case out of it.
Do what any person does, obey the universal.
That means detest, in this case, betrayers.
But she's not in the universal business.
She's in the individual business, and that's totally different.
Now, I wanted to say something more about her.
Well, I don't know, but I'm sure I'll get back to it.
It's just another way of saying the same thing.
So, oh, yeah, I got back to it right away by looking at my notes.
Okay, the ultimate thing is that she really, how would this relate her to the ethical?
Well, if she were in contact with the ethical at all, she'd have to be suspending the ethical, but not in a higher ethical, but just suspending the ethical from some other absolute way of understanding things.
And of course, she does suspend the ethical.
What does she do that is anti-ethical?
Well, she's obstructing justice.
Just as Holly is a police informer, she could go to prison because she says look out the police and so forth.
She warns Harry, and that's how he starts, and he almost gets away, and that causes finally the death of pain and everything.
It's all in a way her fault.
But she would do it again.
She just believes that you can just suspend the ethical if you have an unconditional commitment.
You can't help but suspend the ethical if you have an unconditional commitment.
That's the crucial thing.
Now, we're doing okay, but I have to get more about, oh, she says Harry the police.
And now, Holly again.
Back to Holly, because we haven't said enough about.
Well, I'm going to say quick things about Holly.
Just that he's totally outside the religious.
So he has no answer when Harry says, and what do you believe in?
He has nothing to say when he has to lecture on the crisis of faith.
He doesn't even know what it is.
He's very funny when he's blowing the dust off the religious relics in Dr.
Winkle's waiting room.
And he says, nice, nice stuff you have here.
He doesn't even know what it is.
Because he's no more secular than Calloway.
Now we've got, and Callaway is the positive ethical.
In what way now is Calloway, oh sorry, Holly, not the negative ethical.
Well, because he's dangerous and he's dangerous, and this is interesting, because he's so innocent that he can't really understand any of the motives of any of the evil people.
He can't understand Anna.
Oh, what happened to Anna?
Here, Anna.
And we've seen that.
She gives him a headache.
He can't understand.
Well, Harry, he doesn't even try to understand.
What am I doing here?
The positive ethical.
Okay.
He brings the negative ethical.
Yes, why?
He just can't understand anything in the ethical dimension.
But I'm not doing well.
That's true, but that's not important.
Because Callaway can't understand anything outside of the ethical dimension either.
But Hannah says about Calloway that you're a fool.
And she says you've got it all upside down.
And what does that mean?
Well, that means that he trumps unconditional commitments with his professional devotion to the ethical.
And for him, that is the highest.
And so that I want to see where she says that, Halloway here.
It looks like he's callous, but he's not, that he's being professional.
He really feels compassion for and love sort of for pain, and he almost forgets his duty, which is his duty is to keep people from getting hurt.
And then he gets, when pain gets killed, he forgets for a minute that he's trying to keep Holly from getting hurt.
And then he starts running after him.
He's very, he's not sort of a happy upbeat at all.
He says, death is at the bottom of everything.
Holly, leave death to the professionals.
So he, and the simplest way to think about it is the negative ethical is a kind of, I haven't said anything about it, there isn't much said about it, but it's a kind of vigilante ethical.
That is, he hasn't got, he doesn't go, he isn't going to take people to court.
He's a cowboy ethical.
He just thinks that he trusts his own intuition, he trusts his own honesty, and he decides on who are the bad guys and who are the bad guys on his own.
And that makes him very dangerous.
Calloway does his duty, tries to keep people from getting hurt, makes sacrifices of his personal sentiments for the ethical.
That's how he drops Payne's body to run and try to help Holly.
And that's so there are two kinds of ethical: there is the sober, realistic kind, and this cowboy kind.
Now, are we?
So, Calloway is not heroic, he's not tragic, he just does his job and he does, and he follows the law and so forth, and he gets his criminal.
Okay, oh, now I wanted to tell you something important here, just a second.
Oh, yeah, I almost forgot.
Too many things to keep crackling.
I was about to ask you the question: I want to know how it's going in the world of the spirit, and you guys know.
How many think that you should remain faithful to the person you love or to the cause, to your unconditional commitment, even if it turns out that they're a mass murderer?
I mean, in other words, how many are going to identify with honor?
Nobody are used to, I mean, I hope there are some.
I feel very unhappy.
Okay, there are some.
Few.
Oh, it was 50-50 the last time we did it, only two years ago.
How many think that if you discover somebody's a mass murderer, even if you love them, you have to turn them in, even though that looks like betrayal?
Well, well, well, okay.
You're all getting more and more secular by the minute.
But I will worry about that.
And then see if I can figure out how to get.
I was happy when it was 50-50.
I think that you see why I was happy when it was 50-50?
Because that's the Greek versus the Hebrew Christian.
And I was really asking you: how many are in the Greek tradition of ethics and universal principles and so forth, and how many are in the religious tradition of unconditional commitments to something like a Savior?
And it looks like the religious side is not strongly represented.
I hope this culture stays committed to both sides.
It's a very rich culture.
I saw a hand.
What was it?
Yeah.
What's that?
Holly was what?
A tragic hero, Holly.
Yeah, I said he thinks he is, I meant.
He thinks he sacrificed, he has to suspend the ethical of loving Harry for higher ethical, namely get mass murderers out of this world.
Okay, let me quickly do what I want to do, the last thing, because I'm kind of proud of this thing I wrote.
I want to talk about what each person is thinking as the movie ends.
Okay, I think I've got ready to talk about that.
Yes.
Okay, so Calloway, one more thing I have to say first, I guess.
Calloway thinks, doesn't understand unconditional commitment any more than Holly does.
He thinks that by offering to save Anna from the Russians, he can get her to come over to his side and help turn Harry in.
And she says, you're wrong about everything.
You have everything upside down.
You're a fool because he thinks that.
Now, here's what each is thinking.
I want to say, what is each thinking at the end of the movie?
Calloway says to himself, I got my man.
The pain is dead.
It's a hard job being a professional policeman and keeping people from getting hurt.
Death is at the bottom of everything.
Now, all I have to do is get that dangerous cowboy out of Vienna.
He's rushing him to the plane.
Holly thinks, I'm like the sheriff of Santa Fe.
I've come into this corrupt town and cleaned things up.
I killed the bad guy.
I made a fool of the bad sheriff.
Now all I have to do is save the damsel in distress, and we'll walk off into the sunset together.
That was also what Graham Greene and Carol Reed were thinking.
Anna's thinking, I'm glad Harry is dead.
I would not want to have seen him again anyway, that I would never betray him.
Holly turned out to be even worse than Harry.
Harry was a murderer, but Holly was a betrayer.
Now, with all that in mind, what happens in the last scene?
Well, it looks like there's something not even tragic, because that would require that they be in the same world and in the same dimension.
There is no dimension that can bring the two spheres of existence, the religious and the ethical, in their good or bad forms, together.
So you get the most moving of all the reversals in this perfect movie.
Holly gets out and waits for Anna.
Halloway drives away.
Now he's driving his own Jeep because Payne is dead.
Holly stands there and lights a cigarette, waiting for her, expecting them to walk off together.
She approaches him and gets closer and closer and closer and closer, so slowly.
And the music rises to a climax, and just at the moment we expect her to turn and she doesn't.
This happens to me every time I see the movie.
And you think, well, she's about to turn.
She's about to turn.
And finally, you realize, oh my god, she's passed him already.
And she didn't even look at him.
And now we know why.
We know why, because she's in this totally different understanding of what it is to be a human being and to relate to other human beings than he is.
But he, naturally, has understood nothing.
And the last gesture he makes, he lights a cigarette and then he throws it away in this special gesture, which you see once before in the movie, which you won't realize, I think, if you've only seen it once or twice.
It's the same gesture he makes after he chases Harry Lyme into that big empty space, and all of a sudden Harry Lyme has disappeared.
Remember, he's gone in the sewer.
We don't know that.
Then he puts his hand in some water, he puts his water on his face, and then he goes like that.
That's a gesture of total and annoyed, isn't the right word, infuriated incomprehension about what just happened.
And that's the end of the movie.
And it turns out to be an amazing movie because that's a very deep movie, and it's also a very entertaining movie.
And that's that.
Okay.
Now, don't go away, because we have one more.
Now I'll give you out the chart.
I just didn't want to have so many different pages running around at once.
Here's the chart and an old page from long back that I promised and never gave out.
You know, yeah, we should.