I've got my hands full telling you about the existentializing that's going on like mad in the last few pages of the book.
And for the plot, you can figure out yourself finally who did it, though it takes a lot of figuring before you figure before it finally gets to be clear.
And in a certain way, that's really part of the existentializing story, because so many people are involved in the murder and are responsible for the murder that it sort of supports Zothama's claim that everybody's responsible for at least a lot more of the evil in the world than they realize.
Now he may go too far and claim to be responsible for all the evil in the world.
That does seem a bit crazy and it comes, I think, from spending your life in the monastery instead of in the world.
But the idea that everybody is not only responsible for the good things they do to people that they know they're doing and the good things, the bad things they do to people that they know they're doing, but they're doing all sorts of good and bad things besides.
And the murder is the sort of prime example of how many people are involved in it and feel responsible for it.
But now I'm not going to talk about that more because that's a plot issue.
I'm going to start with the devil.
We have two issues to deal with today.
One is the Yvonne's encounter with the devil and then the last illusion's funeral in which Dostoevsky, in an amazing tour de force, answers about four of the unanswered issues that he's raised in the book.
But first let's do the encounter with the devil.
Remember where we are.
At the end last time, we talked about the fact that Yvonne had an impulse to confess and to pick up the peasant.
And he did it.
And it was very un-Ivan-like involvement with people and everything.
Did everybody, oh, can you take this to the here are the sign-up sheets.
People said they wanted two so that they'd be sure and get their name on at least one of them.
So now, where was I?
Oh, yeah.
Okay, so the important thing that Dostoevsky is stressing at that point is that you can only really do these loving agape things impulsively, because as soon as you stop and reflect, then all the dangers and all the other reasons and considerations that come in make you stop.
And I didn't quote because I didn't know where it was.
I couldn't find it.
One of the places of the most clear account is when Dostoevsky's talking about Dmitry on page 588.
I didn't read it partly because it's got to do with Dmitry's feeling for the suffering baby that he's been dreaming about.
But the main thing is just the last sentence, bottom paragraph.
He wanted to help everybody, help everybody who was suffering.
And it says, he wanted to do this all at once, at once, regardless of obstacles, with the recklessness of the Karamatsovs.
That's going to turn out, that's already important, because that's an example of doing this kind of crazy, loving, positively sacrificing thing and doing it in a impulsively.
And it's and that that kind of impulsiveness belongs particularly to Karamatsov's.
We will come back to that.
But as soon as Yvonne loses his spontaneous resolution to confess immediately, then all of his pride and his sense that he's guilty and he shouldn't be guilty because he's too good a person to be guilty and he's going to go to the trial in a way that's going to show that he's better than everybody instead of by humbling himself.
Demetrius constantly taking on the guilt and humbling himself, and Yvonne is constantly denying his guilt or saying, Well, they're all guilty.
They all want to kill their father, or just saying, Look, I'm honest enough to confess, all of which just to show that he's better than everybody.
But now, as soon as Yvonne hesitates, he's lost.
He reflects, and as soon as he reflects, he says, Well, I'll go and confess tomorrow, because he can't really bear the thought of confessing because that would be to be publicly admitting that he's not impeccable.
And so, as soon as he does hesitate, then when he goes into the home, his house, he feels that there's something cold and strange in his own house on 7:33 at the bottom of the top paragraph.
As he entered his room, he felt something like a touch of ice on his heart, like a recollection, or more exactly a reminder of something agonizing and revolting that was in that room now at that moment.
They've been there before.
Now, what is this revolting something that's in his room?
Well, it's really him, or it's the lackey bad part of him, but it's not, that's not how he experiences it, and he's because he's getting his brain fever and cracking up.
It's in his experience, is that the devil is in his room now.
And all I want to note is the interesting fact that the devil is associated with ice.
This is a Catholic thing, probably, I mean, obviously Russian Orthodox and obviously Roman Catholic too.
When Dante goes down and deeper and deeper in hell in the divine comedy and gets to people who are more and more bad, they're more and more cold-blooded people, heartless people, who have betrayed the people around them.
And at the very bottom of the ice are the really worst sinners, all of whom are frozen in the ice, period.
And the idea is that, and it's just a Zosima-like idea, too, that non-loving, non-impulsive, non-agape living is hell.
And the more you don't relate to people warmly and with love, the more you're in hell.
So naturally, this fantasized Satan is like a refrigerator.
Well, in Dante, Satan is like a big refrigerator.
He flaps his wings, and that's what keeps hell cold.
And here, the room is cold.
It's the same intuition.
And so, Yvonne, yeah, it might, except it doesn't make sense, except by a weird association, because why shouldn't if he took the peasant out of the cold, how would that get him to be having this cold, awful thing in his own living room?
What?
Yeah, but why would he be thinking about the peasant in the snow?
He doesn't seem to think about him.
And I would sort of think hard about what you're saying if it weren't for what I just said.
I mean, it's just plain Dante Catholic and sensible tradition that the bad people are the cold people.
And the colder, the worse, or the worse, the colder.
I think that's all you need.
It's not, and Dante does, and Dostoevsky doesn't make a big deal out of it.
He just says there was something cold in his house, and this thing that was cold in his house turns out to be the devil.
And on 749, the devil connects with Yvonne's reflecting and having not gone immediately and impulsively to confess.
He says at the bottom, I swear to you by all that's sacred, I long to join the choir and shout Hosanna with them all.
The word had almost escaped me, had almost broken from my lips.
You know how susceptible and impressionable I am.
The common sense, almost unhappy trait in my character, kept me in bounds, and I let the moment pass.
So, I mean, the devil, of course, is Yvonne talking to himself, and he's telling himself that he's such a good person, but he really has this bad tendency to reflect.
But he tells himself he's really a good person on 749.
The devil says, I am perhaps the one man in all creation who loves the truth and really desires good.
I mean, that's a very strange thing for the devil to say, but it's not a strange thing for Yvonne to say through the devil.
And now we have to go on in the more interesting details.
So the devil is clearly, and Yvonne says so, his own lackey side.
If you've got a self with a bad and a good, or a spiritual and a dark side, the devil is connected with, just how it's connected with, we haven't got clear yet, we will, with what the funky side, the lackey side of everybody, and in this case, of Yvonne.
You can see that on 737, where he says to the devil in the middle of the page, Never for one minute have I taken you for reality, Yvonne cried with a sort of fury.
You're a lie, you're my illness, you're a phantom.
And then skipping a little, you were the incarnation of myself, but only one side of me, of my thoughts and feelings, but only the worst and most stupid of them.
And now that's right.
Yvonne's got it right.
And he's right that this is a phantom.
The devil isn't real.
It's his hallucination.
But, and this is now where it gets to be interesting, Dostoevsky, he, strangely enough, although you can understand it, I'm sure, when you think about it, he says at the bottom of 746, not for a minute, cried Ivan, would take him to be real.
But I would like to believe in you, he added, strangely.
So now we find out that he would like to think the devil was real.
So now the question is for you all, somebody, why, given all we've said so far, would Yvonne risk sort of madness to believe that the devil was real?
Exactly.
I'll repeat it because they wouldn't hear you.
If it was the real devil in his house, then it wouldn't be Yvonne's lackey side.
It would be, and he could still consider himself impeccable.
Or he could think that there was this bad other force that maybe took him over sometime, but really, Yvonne isn't that lackey devil.
And it gets clearer that that's what's going on.
That Yvonne is externalizing the lackey side.
That if the devil were real, then Yvonne could say that anything that looked lacy about him was really caused by somebody else.
And he says it on 741.
Okay, just so that it's clear that he both wants the devil to be real and understands that if he takes the devil for real, he's going crazy.
At the top of 741, he was exerting himself to the utmost not to believe in the delusion and not to sink into complete insanity.
So he wants to be, he doesn't want to go crazy, but he does want the devil to be real.
And of course, that's impossible to get these two things together.
And he tells it to Alyasha on 756.
Alyasha, the angel, has run in and chased away Satan, just as he chases away Rakitin, who is a kind of minor devil.
Let me say right now, in case I might forget, it's interesting that Rakitin is a little devil, and he's an existentialized version of all the little devils that Christianity at one point believed were running around in the world causing trouble.
And Rakitin is what's devilish about him is, remember, he's his main, gets his main kick in life by seeing the fall of the righteous.
So that's how you know.
And he does it by sort of waiting till somebody's almost despairing because of their terrible situation they're in, and then bringing out the worst in them so that they really are destroyed.
That's what he's trying to do to Grushenka.
So, but I want to just contrast that with Satan.
It isn't as if Satan, the big deal devil, is being existentialized by Dostoevsky.
He doesn't believe there's a big deal devil down in the middle of the earth, coogling things or wherever.
That's why it's clear that the devil is a hallucination.
And there's nothing to existentialize for him there.
He just, there isn't this sort of personified pure evil.
There's just this kind of person who brings out the worst in people, and that's the devilish kind of person, and that's what he's interested in existentializing.
So now I want to go back to where I am.
But Yvonne is torn.
I mean, now never mind about existentializing.
Yvonne is torn between believing in this Satan figure and not.
And he says at the top of 756, about 10 lines down, you would have driven him away.
He's talking to Alyasha.
You did drive him away.
He disappeared when you arrived.
I love your face, Alyasha.
Did you know that I love your face?
And he is myself, Alyasha.
All that's base in me, all that's mean and contemptible.
Well, that's clear, but now there's something new coming in, skipping a little.
He kept taunting me with believing in him.
And that was how he made me listen to him.
He followed me like a boy.
He told me a great deal.
Followed me?
I wonder if that's a mistranslation of some other word altogether.
How could it be he followed me like a boy?
I never noticed that before.
He told me a great deal that was true about myself, though.
I would never have admitted it to myself.
Do you know, Alyosha?
Yvonne added in an intensely earnest and confidential tone.
I would be awfully glad to think that it was he and not I.
Well, that's what he just said.
And again, Dostoevsky never letting you miss it, has now said exactly what he wants to say.
And a funny way to put this, but maybe it's helpful.
Remember that R2 in the diagram of the self, both in Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky, is the self relating to itself by excluding half the self.
And it can be the material self excluding the spiritual self as a bunch of superstitions, or it could be the spiritual self excluding the sensual self as something that's only you're only stuck with, but it isn't really you.
And here, it's again, Yvonne has this stand on himself, that he's trying to eliminate the half of himself that he doesn't like, that is not up to his proud, impeccable standards.
And that's and what Dostoevsky is doing is just sort of dramatizing that attitude.
So Yvonne is going mad, and he's by trying to get rid of half himself, and the only way to get rid of half yourself would be to externalize it, and then you would be crazy because that's just exactly what's going on.
And there seem to be three different views about devils.
There is a crazy person who really just believes in devils and sees them behind the door and slams the door on their tail.
You know who remember that is?
That's Father Farrapont.
And everybody knows he's crazy.
He just completely externalized the devil side of himself.
And then there's Alyasha, who has Rakitin as his devil.
Everybody has a devil and an angel fighting for their soul.
But Alyasha certainly doesn't think that there's a Satan around.
He's naturally quite rational.
He's rational about something which is a problem.
But I'll tell you, just because maybe somebody here knows the answer, though, for all these years I've taught Dostoevsky, nobody noticed the answer yet.
The puzzle on 757, if anybody noticed it, the devil says to Yvonne on 757, in the middle of the bottom big paragraph, but now Smerzhikov's dead, he's hung himself, and who will believe you without him?
And now, what's strange about that?
How many got this far?
Okay, well, I'm not going to get help from very many people, and I can see that.
I can give you this to think about, and you should run into office hours if you figure it out.
Smerzhikov has indeed hanged himself, but you know what?
Yeah, how exactly.
How in the world does Yvonne know it so that his devil can know it?
It looks like something really magical.
But Alyasha is such a sensible person with reality, and he doesn't believe in anything magical.
So he says, next paragraph.
Yvonne said, said Alyasha, his heart sank with terror, but he still hoped to bring Yvonne back to reason.
How could he have told you of Smerzikov's death before I came?
No one knew of it, and there was no time.
Well, that's pretty weird.
But we're certainly not supposed to think that he really is a devil, and he really is magical.
What do you think?
All the things he was taking on the devil told him before all of them?
I think, good, good.
That's what I think.
I'd expect Dostoevsky somewhere to leave us a hint of that.
But what it looks like is he's so crazy that he reads back what Alyasha told him, namely that Smerzhikov is dead, into what the devil told him.
Am I understanding you?
And therefore says to Alyasha, the devil told him that, but he must have really heard it from Alyasha.
Where else?
Right.
We were there.
Good point.
We were in on the conversation, and the devil never said that.
What's the name of this movie of the guy who's got the short-term memory?
Memento.
Yeah, in Memento, more and more the guy begins to remember things that didn't really happen.
And it gets very confusing toward the end of the movie.
He remembers having written things on his body which he never did write on his body and so forth.
It's sort of like that.
Yvonne is getting just confused about reality and what happened and what didn't happen and when.
And I only worry, I mean, but it shows, remember, I want to use it to show that Alyasha's view of devils is the best one.
I mean, he doesn't believe there are any, and he can't believe in this magical idea that the devil actually told Yvonne some important fact that Yvonne himself couldn't have known and didn't know.
If you have any other, I mean, I buy his interpretation, but if you have any other, or if you, with your interpretation, find any place where Dostoevsky's telling us, cooling us in on this, he won't just say outright, but somehow the conversation, you've got half of it.
He's showing us the devil didn't say any such thing because we were there and we heard the conversation.
And you'd think you would see some hint that Yvonne has gone crazy and reorganized the time.
But you don't see any hint.
You just hear Yvonne say this wrong thing.
Well, nothing to get hung up on.
Good, thanks.
Everybody sign up?
I guess so.
Okay.
Now, I want to go on to the next issue, which is where something complicated that I don't understand very well either.
I'm telling you all the hard things now.
After the encounter with Yvonne and Yvonne's encounter with the devil, Alyasha goes to, says a prayer as he falls asleep at the top of 758.
He took a pillow and lay down on the sofa, and then he says this, and he prayed for Dmitry and Yvonne.
It's interesting how he prayed.
When he prayed, you'll read his prayer, and it wasn't any prayer.
He didn't speak to a personal God.
You can hardly pray to the connectedness of the universe.
And remember, whenever Dostoevsky says God, he means the slanting rays of the sun.
He means the thread.
He means the ocean of connectedness.
He has all kinds of names for this ultimately spiritual world that we're all in.
But when he prays, he says, God in whom Yvonne, this is what he thought, God in whom Yvonne disbelieved.
I'm at the top of 79.
This is a very, everything has a paragraph that's so hard to understand that you don't know what to do.
I have, there's a paragraph in Hiroshima one more I can't understand.
Here's the one in this one I can barely understand.
God in whom Yvonne disbelieved and his truth were gaining mastery over his, Yvonne's heart, which still refused to submit.
We can do that one.
What is that one?
That is the connectedness of everything, which Yvonne denies, denies when in rebellion chapter, denies when he leaves town to let Dmitry kill old Karamatsov.
So the fact that Yvonne is connected to and responsible for the evil in himself and in the world is the God he disbelieves in.
But his truth, that is, God's truth, that is connectedness, was gaining mastery over his, Yvonne's heart.
Yes, the thought floated through Alyasha's mind.
Now, this is a sort of prayer, you notice, but there's no praying.
Yes, if Smerzhikov is dead, no one will believe Ivan's evidence that he will go and testify anyway.
Alyasha smiled softly.
God will conquer, he thought.
That means what?
The connectedness will get through to Yvonne because there is this connectedness and you can't really deny it.
So God will conquer, he thought.
Ivan will either rise up in the light of truth or he'll perish in hate, revenging on himself and on everyone his having served a cause he does not believe in.
Alyasha had it bitterly, and again he prayed for Yvonne.
Now, that's the hardest part.
So the connectedness will conquer.
Ivan will either rise up in the light of truth, meaning recognize his connectedness, take responsibility, humble himself for the lacky side of him and for his connectedness, his very important connectedness in the murder, or he'll perish in hate.
Now it gets really hard, revenging on himself and everyone is having served a cause he does not believe in.
All I can think of there is he dies angry that he served what cause?
The evidence, he served the truth that everything was connected to everything by, well, partly by going crazy, I think, partly by understanding that leaving town when he thought he was washing his hands of everything and showing his total disconnectedness, he caused the murder.
Therefore, he was showing the connectedness.
And this is getting pretty far-fetched.
I don't claim this is a very illuminating way to read it.
But anyway, that's my way of reading it: that he can't get himself out of the connectedness, he can't rebel, he can't be detached, and this will ultimately drive him crazy.
Or else, connectedness will get through to him and he will be transformed.
And as I say, there's one sentence in the book that tells us that, in fact, connectedness got through to him and he was transformed.
I was looking for it, but I didn't find it.
But I remember, remember I told you, it says that Ivan remembered all his life as the most awful, repulsive moment when he went out on the landing and listened to old Karamatsov and thinking, oh boy, now by tomorrow he'll be dead, is presumably what he was thinking.
But anyway, somebody had a hand up.
Yeah.
And expect those lack of side, the warn behind the acceptance.
So he either accepts the connectedness or he accepts the lackey side, but he doesn't.
And he despairs because he can't accept it.
I didn't follow you.
I see.
He's committed to the non-connectedness.
And insofar as the connectedness grabs him, he either accepts it and is transformed, or he denies it, and he denies the, and thereby he is full of anger and somehow destroys himself.
Is that?
Okay, I got it.
Yeah.
I mean, giving it a chance, giving the God the connectedness a chance.
And if it were to work out, then he'd give it the appreciation of his life that he gave us for not having to give himself revenge himself on having long moments because he wasn't actually made to that gospel for his life.
He had a chance, but it didn't work.
He didn't, he was sort of called to admit the connectedness, but he didn't admit the connectedness.
And therefore, he has to, that's the weird part, of avenge, revenge on himself and everyone else having served a cause he does not believe in.
See, somehow he's got to be in the connectedness, and that's what makes him so angry.
He wants to reject his involvement, and he ends up having been deeply involved anyway.
I'm back to my version.
Okay, let's hear your version.
Well, doesn't Enon end up to be going to this text that's connectedness who wants to dance and make some difference than other people.
He goes to the trial and his connectedness to prove that he's valuable to other people and therefore, sort of murderism.
And that counts as revenging on himself, his serving a cause he doesn't believe in.
Maybe.
I still like my version best.
The middle of mine is, but I don't think it's great, but I'm not bowled over by any of these versions either.
But I want to say that he served the cause of connectedness by demonstrating, in effect, his connectedness, by leaving town and washing his hands of everything as if he weren't connected, and lo and behold, that caused the murder.
So he demonstrates his connectedness.
Sort of God, namely the connectedness, uses him to be an example of how much you are responsible for the evil in the world.
But I don't know.
I mean, I stop with that just because I want you to think about it, because I want anybody who's got more to say about it to come.
It's sort of so inscrutable.
And Alyasha says it as if it was just obvious and somehow the book had kind of led up to it.
I mean, the more I say it, the more I like my interpretation.
At least the book did lead up to my interpretation.
Yvonne has just had this shocking conversation in which Smershikov says, you did it, you made this agreement to leave town, and you left town.
And that caused the murder.
It's as if he sort of hired a hitman to do the murder, which isn't as bad as actually murdering somebody yourself.
That's why Alyasha can say to Yvonne, you didn't kill old Karamatsov.
Hiring a hitman to kill somebody, which is what sort of happens between him and Smershikov, that is bad enough to, what you go to prison for life for attempted murder or something for that, I imagine.
So Yvonne has sort of demonstrated the connectedness, even though he doesn't believe in it.
I'm going to stop with that.
I'm sure somebody can do better, but it's the best I can do.
Okay, so now let me go on and see where we are.
I summed it up by saying that would mean that Yvonne is in the world whether he likes it or not, whether he chooses to be or not, and that's his problem.
And that problem is getting through to him because of his implication in his father's murder, which he now understands.
But he resists accepting that kind of interdependence.
Here's my final summary, I see.
Now Yvonne must accept the fundamental truth that all creatures are interrelated and admit his involvement, or else he'll destroy everything in himself and everyone else who questions his self-sufficiency, purity, and perfection, and reminds him of his complicity in the suffering in the world.
That's that.
Okay, now we're going on to a whole new subject, the last subject, the rest of the book.
And that is, and I want you to think about how many issues are left unresolved that we now need to find out how they get resolved.
I listed them where we don't even understand yet what the founding of a church is like.
It's hard to remember the first time reading this, or even the second or third, all the issues that are on the table since the Grand Inquisitor.
But remember, the Grand Inquisitor says we're going to give people one universal church, one ant heap, in which they're all together believing the same thing.
That's what they want.
And the Jesus figure says, or is, you know, the Grand Inquisitor says, the Jesus figure says, every man has to relate to God by himself.
There's no place for intermediate churches and priests and so forth at all.
Now, the question is: is there a third view that would be the Russian Orthodox view?
If there is, we haven't seen it yet.
So, Dostoevsky is going to have to give it to us in those last ten pages.
And then there's the question of immortality.
At the beginning of the book, both Mrs.
Holikov and Feodor are all upset about whether there's an afterlife or not.
And surely, if Dostoevsky is demythologizing, that is, existentializing everything, he ought to be existentializing the afterlife too.
And he is, you'll see, he does it in a way.
And then he's been telling us sort of all about the Karamatsovs, that they're reckless, that they're impulsive, that they're sensual and dangerous and so forth.
And so he hasn't really settled on.
He's told us that, in a way, the Karamatsovs are sort of paradigm human beings.
We're all Karamatsovs, except that somehow these guys have got this whatever it is about the self sort of large in them.
But we don't quite know what it is yet, what it is to be a Karamatsov.
Basically, is it a bad thing or a good thing?
We have to hear about that.
We will in a minute.
And finally, we need a hint, and we've talked about this: how in the world is all this going to change the world so that the star will rise in the east, so that we can get a hint at least what Dostoevsky thinks would be the best thing that could happen to humanity and could happen to humanity, and maybe will happen to humanity.
He's got a sort of good record so far as a prophet because he says we'll see how socialism is going to work.
I mean, the kind of Soviet, a state that treats people.
Never mind.
I'll get to that.
Let's do them one at a time.
So, first, we have to talk about Kolya.
Kolya represents the next generation.
He is the smartest young man.
How is he?
17 or younger?
I forget.
14.
Okay, 14.
And he's, and the angel versus devil battle for him is very important because which way he goes has a lot to do with which way the world is going to go.
And so we will see just what we expect to see: Rakitin and Alyasha fighting for his soul.
They're talking about all sorts of things on 639.
And Kolya is giving all sorts of atheist kind of answers and socialist kind of answers.
And talking about there's no, if there were a little two-thirds down, if there were no God, he would have to be invented.
Kolya began to blush.
He suddenly felt that Alyasha might think he was trying to show off.
And I must confess I can't stand such discussions, he said with a final air.
It's possible for one who doesn't believe in God to love mankind, don't you think so?
Voltaire didn't believe in God and he loved mankind.
I'm at it again, he thought.
Alyasha answers very sensibly: Voltaire believed in God, though not very much.
That isn't the correct connectedness and so forth, I think.
And I don't think he loved mankind very much either.
So believing in the connectedness and loving your fellow human beings comes to the same thing.
You can't believe, love your fellow human beings and not believe in God, and you can't believe in God and not love your fellow human beings because God just is the loving connectedness of everything.
Now, I want to ask the Russian consultant, again, Alex, I hope you're listening.
I worry about the bottom of 639.
Either Dostoevsky's making a mistake or the translator's making a mistake.
Because it's right for Rakitin and Kolya to talk about whether you love mankind or not.
But you see, that's the wrong way.
Alyasha shouldn't think about that.
That's like loving humanity.
And remember, if you love humanity, that's not like loving your neighbor, particular people in your vicinity.
And it's the wrong thing to love humanity.
Yvonne says he loves humanity.
He just doesn't like any particular people.
They're all so inferior and awful.
So it's all very well for Kolya to talk about whether Voltaire loves mankind or not, but it it ought to be at the he-he ought to, Alyasha ought to say, I don't think he loved any particular people very much.
And and he and he and he doesn't love God either.
But I don't know I don't know what's happening there, I'm just curious.
But the point is, anyway, you can't if you have the right relation to God, you have a loving relation to your neighbor.
It's not news.
I mean, it's a part of the Christian story that Dostoevsky's been saying over and over.
But then after he says another page of stupid things, and it says in the middle that he's a socialist, he says, I'm in the middle of 640.
I'm an incurable socialist, he announced suddenly.
A socialist laughed Alyasha.
When have you had time to become one?
And you're only 13.
I thought you were, yeah, he's 13, it turns out.
And how has he come to be a socialist and have these views about Voltaire, about whom he knows nothing and so forth?
Well, of course, from Rakitin, who's, if he can get him into being a socialist, and materialists, an atheist, is making a big step against the star rising in the East.
So it turns out on 641 at the top, it happens I've often talked to Rakitin, the divinity student, and then they're talking about some Russian political philosopher, and I don't know anything about it.
It doesn't matter what, which particular thing.
It's just that it's some socialist thing.
Now, where am I?
So Dostoevsky thinks that the kind of socialism that Kolya believes in, is going to end up in bloodshed and destruction because natural human beings, remember, are not are vicious and selfish and so forth.
You can't make a state out of them.
They won't form a community.
They won't really cooperate.
And so he's predicting the destruction of the Soviet Union, in effect.
If the Russians will try, if the Russians try this kind of move, it's not going to work.
You can't have, from Dostoevsky's point of view, a state.
You can only have Christian socialism.
You can't have secular state socialism.
And of course it's the devil that makes that that's causing all this.
Just to mention the devil, so Dostoevsky keeps you tuned in in the middle of 644.
Alyasha says the devil has taken the form of vanity and entered in the whole generation.
It's the devil.
And he sees the effect of Rakitin.
And then, backing up a little, how does he win Kolya over?
I mean, he lets Kolya make a fool of himself, and he shows Kolya that what he's saying doesn't make any sense.
But that's not going to get Kolya away from Rakitin and tuned into Alyasha.
Well, it happens very fast on 643, and it's a funny repeat of what happened with Grushenka two-thirds of the way down on 643.
Kolya says, I'm mean in lots of ways, Karamatsov.
And he says, no, you have a good nature, but it's been distorted, and I understand now why you have had such an influence on the sensitive boy.
That's Alyusha.
Alyasha answered warmly.
You say that to me, cried Kolya.
Would you believe it?
I thought, I've thought several times since I've been here that you despise me.
If only you knew how much I prized your opinion.
It sounds familiar, doesn't it?
Exactly what happened with Grushenko.
These people, it's typical Dostoevsky, are insecure and humiliated and misinterpret everybody's gestures toward them as further humiliation.
And only somebody who's already completely secure in their love of themselves and of others can sort of break through that.
How many did you read in high school, the Notes from Underground?
How many read Notes from Underground?
Only one or two.
Because that's all about this.
I mean, the underground guy tries to help this woman who feels so despised, the prostitute, but she misinterprets all of his gestures as further insults.
And that's a very despairing story because there's nobody there who has the security of Alyasha.
They're both insecure, and they just, they're in hell together.
But in this case, it turns out okay because Alyasha has already got the love funneled to him from Markle to Zosima to him.
And now, I think, did I take two pages?
No.
Okay, now we have to turn to Ilusha.
These are all, you don't know yet, but the sort of all those questions I raised are going to be taken up, but they're not taken up until Ilusha dies.
We have to get all the pieces.
So Ilusha is this nice boy who is dying of TV, and the boys are all his buddies, and he was full of anger and hatred because his father was humiliated by Dmitry, but now he's becoming, like Markle, warm and loving and open because he's also got brain fever.
And he feels this very bad for having done this nasty trick to a dog of putting a pin in the food and then throwing the food to the dog and so forth on 618.
And they are trying to, well, they're all moved by him and his love.
And they also are going out trying to find the dog, or claim to find the dog, so he can die happy.
But that's a subplot we don't have to worry about.
What we have to worry about is what happens actually when he dies.
Now that goes way to the end of the book, A88.
All the things happen very fast.
He dies, full of love and happy, and he tells everybody how much he loves them.
And then, so poor little Ilusha, he died.
And the boys were all around him.
And now comes one move you've got to see.
When he died, there was no smell of decay from the corpse, the bottom of A88.
I say that because you ought to know what that means.
Books, I've seen books and chapters where smart people, presumably, write about the brothers Karamatsov, trying to figure out what it means that Zosima's body rots and stinks and Alyusha's body is perfectly preserved and doesn't have any odor of decay at all.
And they think, well, there must be something better about Alyusha than there is about Zosima.
I wonder what it is.
And they write articles and presumably get PhDs.
But what's wrong?
What's the right way to think about it?
You're all better off than these people.
Yes.
No, that's not the right way to think about it.
Try again.
Yeah.
It's what?
He's innocent.
Yeah, he's innocent, but that's not the point.
Yes.
That his body was washed after he died.
Dostoevsky goes out of his way to tell you it was a cold autumn day and it was snowing.
What about flowers?
Were there flowers?
Yes, there were.
His body was covered with flowers.
So, and I bet somewhere, I just didn't have time to reread it, that the windows were open.
I have the memory that the windows were open.
If you know where it is, tell me about it.
But notice.
So what's the moral?
Remember with Zosima, there were no flowers.
The body was not washed.
It was a warm autumn evening and the windows were closed.
Here we've got a body that's been washed, that there are lots of flowers.
It's a cold autumn evening, and I'm pretty sure the windows are open.
Now, what does it show that Kolya's body didn't decompose?
Nothing.
Absolutely nothing.
It just shows that the laws of physics go on, and if you're expecting miracles and significance that go against the laws of physics and chemistry, you're looking in the wrong place, according to Dostoevsky.
I mean, sure, Ilyusha is pure, but it's not manifest by the fact that his body doesn't decompose, and it doesn't count against Zosima, but his does.
It's a neat move that Dostoevsky's just pulling on you, and all of you fell for it.
I fell for it, too.
But now we are all one step ahead of all those other people who are still battling over it.
Somebody put a hand up over here?
Okay, well, so now that's even that's not the big issue yet.
I just have to get these issues off the table one at a time.
So let's see.
It's only natural, everything is natural.
That's that.
He dies in the cold autumn.
I have 890.
That must be where it says it's cold.
There was a slight frost, it says, at the bottom of 890.
And the room was full of flowers, he says, on 888.
There were flowers in his hands, and the coffin at the bottom of 888, inside and out, was decked with flowers and so forth and so forth.
So now we settled that.
And both of the deaths create a miracle.
Zosima's death sends Alyasha to Grushenka, and the love in Alyasha, and it comes from Zosima, transforms, through Alyasha, transforms Grushenka.
Now, Ilusha also produces a miracle, but it's a different kind of miracle.
It's the miracle of the founding of a church.
That's one of the things that we need to find out about.
And that's the first of them.
What the issue is now, we're going to find out what is an existentialized church community.
It looked pretty much what Dostoevsky thinks must have been the original Christian community before it got mixed up with Greek thinking.
So here's what happens.
Alicia's death creates the church, answers the question from the Grand Inquisitor, and now, and what is the middle ground between the two?
And how does that happen?
Well, here's what happens.
The boys found a church with Alyasha uses the death of Elusia to found a church.
And that happens, and it's sort of almost funny that Dostoevsky again hits you over the head with it.
It's one of my favorite of telling you what he's doing.
First, I'll show you that he's doing it.
Then I'll show you where he shows you that he's doing it.
So let's look at 894 at the bottom.
Let's make a compact here at Elusia's Stone.
There was this rock that Alicia liked, and they're meeting around the rock.
Alicia's funeral was over.
He's dead.
Now the boys are all there.
And now Alyasha makes a big speech.
Let's make a compact here at Alicia's Stone.
And then skipping down.
A compact is a kind of religious commitment.
You can have bad compacts.
You can make compacts with the devil.
I think you can only make compacts sort of in the dimension of the sacred.
But this is going to be a good compact.
Now 10 lines down in 895.
And we will remember him, boys, all our lives.
And even if we're occupied with important things, even if we obtain honor or fall into misfortune, still let us remember how good it was once here when we were all together, united by good and kind feelings.
So he's telling them that this is a childhood memory, that this is some important event that they will always remember, whose meaning can't be taken back by any other events, misfortunes or successes.
And that's exactly what it's like a baptism.
It puts them into this special, religious, and, in a certain sense, eternal dimension.
Why do I say it's eternal?
Because it's a moment that isn't up for grabs, for reinterpretation, any other moment.
It's the instant, in Kierkegaard language.
Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard share the idea that they are these special moments which determine your way of looking at things for your whole life.
Now, he says it on the middle of 895.
He's already shown it with the baptism and the nuts from the old German doctor, but now he says it in general.
You must know that there is nothing higher and stronger and more wholesome and good for life in the future than some good memory, especially a memory of childhood, of home.
People talk to you a great deal about your education, but some good sacred memory preserved from childhood is perhaps the best education.
If a man carries many such memories with him into life, he is safe to the end of his days.
Well, that's pretty important.
That's telling you that there is this special kind of memory which is outside of time and it's eternal.
And remember, the existential word for what is the fancy Greek word for eternal, which is outside of time.
This isn't outside of time.
But this marks the whole time of your life.
The past was, you didn't have it yet, and you were lost, and afterwards you have it, and you have it for good.
And the word for it is, anybody know, forever.
Forever is sort of existentialized eternity.
And now you get this happening on 896.
We're very near the end.
Dostoevsky is throwing in everything he knows.
Two-thirds of the way down.
You're all dear to me, boys, from this day forth.
I have a place in my heart for you all.
And I beg you to keep a place in your heart for me.
Well, and who has united us in this good, in this kind, good feeling, which we shall remember and intend to remember all our lives?
Who, if not Elusha, the good boy, the dear boy, precious to us forever?
Let us never forget him.
May his memory live forever in our hearts.
Yes, yes, forever, forever, the boys cried in their ringing voices.
Now, you've got so many things happening at once.
They've been unified together by Elusha, and that's a kind of community, a kind of sacred community.
They don't just each one remember that this nice thing happened with Elusha.
They each remember that they were all together in it.
That they not only had this common love, but they noticed that they had the common love.
And that was part of what was special about it.
That's what they will remember.
They will remember that at the death of Elusha, they all were there and they all loved each other.
And that's the middle kind of church.
Remember, the Zosima says, where two or more are gathered in my name, that's a world of living love.
They've created a separate forever bond.
They've sort of latched onto the connectedness of everything in their own particular lives forever over the death of Alusha.
And that means, notice that it wouldn't be enough to say if two are united in my name.
I mean, that might be the answer to Kierkegaard, who thinks you have to each one relate alone to God, the extreme Protestant story.
And it might be the answer to the Roman Catholics that everybody has to be in Christendom.
But it takes more than two, because two you could get by a defining commitment.
But Dostoevsky doesn't defining commitments.
It's not, I mean, when you've got a defining commitment, it's only for two.
You can't break into the love of the prince and of the lad and the princess or whatever your love is.
You can't.
I mean, another example is Lear and Cordelia, where in how many read King Lear and School?
They form a little world like birds in a cage, and nothing affects them, and they can listen to what's going on in court.
But there's just the two of them.
It's the two or more that's important.
That's why it's like a church.
That is, it could be two, but it's open to a group.
And in this case, it's open to a group of boys.
And now comes the very funniest thing in the book.
If Dostievsky is going to hit you over the head, but he's just founded a church?
Well, you might suspect is something like that is going on because they're doing it at Iraq.
Those of you who are the Christians who read the Bible know that the church was founded when Jesus gave Peter the power to save people, and he did it at a rock.
But that's not the funny part.
The funny part is elsewhere.
I hope I haven't lost it.
I couldn't.
I could tell you, but I want you to see it in print.
Okay, I'll find it.
The bottom of some page.
The question is: maybe you'll find it before me.
How many boys are there?
Why would we care?
Why would Dostoevsky tell us how many boys?
Here they are at the bottom of 887.
Again, you have to be a Christian to get it.
At the bottom, they had all been expecting him and were glad he had come at last.
There were about 12 of them.
Bong.
How in the world Dostoevsky can do that sort of thing?
There were 12 apostles at the rock when Peter founded the church.
And he's telling you, here's the existentialized version of it, and don't, I'm not going to let you miss it.
Okay, so there they are at Alicia's Stone.
I'm just catching up.
There's a group sharing a special moment, and they chant.
I read that already.
It's a kind of chant that they have where they say forever, and then they go back to saying forever.
And the boys cried in their ringing voices.
Now, we have to see what is the relation of the forever to eternity.
Well, I've said it's already the eternity in time that Kierkegaard talks about.
It's something that's going to be meaningful for your whole life.
But that's not immortality.
Now we want to know about the afterlife.
This one is really tough.
I mean, how is Dostoevsky going to existentialize the afterlife?
After all, nobody knows what happens after you die.
And Dostoevsky doesn't know either.
And he's not going to just be able to, you know, give you a direct answer and say, well, you do live forever in another world.
And he's not going to be able to say, well, you don't, because there's no place for that in physics and chemistry.
He doesn't care about physics and chemistry.
Whatever goes on after you die is not going to be settled by knowing about your neurons.
So, well, he does a weird thing.
I can't say that I'm absolutely convinced, but I'm trying to convince you that his problem is so hard that you don't know what to say.
Well, here's what he says at the top of 897.
And the boy, and then it made the boy's memory, I'm about five lines, dear boy's memory live forever, Alyasha added again and again.
Forever, the boys chimed in again.
This is the sort of church chant part.
Karamatsov cried Kolya.
Can it be true, as they teach us in church, that we shall all rise again from the dead and live and see each other again, all Ilusha too?
So there's Kolya doing the right thing.
He's sort of pushing Alyasha to give him the answer to this question that's tormented, you know, as I say, everybody in the book, really, but particularly old Taramatsov and Madame Holokov.
Well, what is the answer?
Well, it's a weird answer.
Certainly we shall all rise again.
Certainly we shall see each other.
And she'll tell each other with joy and gladness all that happened.
Alyasha answered, half laughing, half enthusiastic.
Now, I don't quite know what to say about that.
I mean, surely he's not telling them that he knows for sure that they're all going to die.
When they die, they're going to see each other again.
It's Assimus Shore.
He tells the woman whose son has died that your son is sitting up with God looking at you and don't leave your husband because your son would be unhappy and all that early on in the book.
Sir, but there isn't any heaven in that sense or any God in that sense in Dostoevsky.
So what's, well, I think what he says, what he's saying is that why do you need to know?
I've told you everything that we know that I can tell you about eternity and immortality.
Namely, that this memory is basic and it'll save you and you'll never lose it and you'll always be together in it and so forth.
And that's the enthusiastic.
And then sort of laughing because he's saying in a way, well, I told you all that we could possibly know and what more do you want?
And he's sort of shrugging off the question.
And what happens next is that he tells them, let's go eat pancakes.
He laughs half, oh, how wonderful it will be, cried Kolya.
Well, now we are finished talking and we could go to the funeral dinner.
Don't be disturbed at our eating pancakes.
It's an old custom and there's something nice in it, laughed Alyasha.
Let's go.
So in a certain way, this very serious question, which he understands is a very serious question.
He doesn't really have a serious answer.
He goes as far as he can, and then he just sort of says, I've told you enough that you can lead a meaningful life and you can found a church and so forth.
And that's it.
So now where am I?
I'm very near the end.
Let's see those questions.
Have I answered all the questions I told you we had to answer?
The founding of a church, yes.
What kind of community that is, and how you get it.
The answer to immortality, yes.
Insofar as he can answer it at all, he answers it.
Well, we still have two more to go.
What's the meaning of being a Karamatsov?
And that's a weird and wonderful tour, of course, which he doesn't, which is easy to see and understand.
All through, remember, we're all Karamatsovs.
Karamatsovs are the sort of paradigm human beings.
Then they've all got a self with a dark side and a bright side.
And now, what's going to become of the Karamatsov?
On 248, all through the book, people give their opinion about what it is to be.
Starting on 248, 248?
248.
Oh, I'm not on 248.
There we are.
At the bottom of 248, the first view you get is the dim view, namely that we are contradictory selves with good and bad impulses, and it's a primitive force, about 10 lines from the bottom.
It's the primitive force of the Karamatsovs, as Father Piasi said the other day, a crude.
This is not too complimentary about us all, Karamatsovs, a crude, unbridled, earthly force.
Does the Spirit of God move above that force?
Even that I don't know.
I only know I'm a Karamatsov.
He's talking to Lisa.
And he's admitting, humblingly admitting, his lackey, primitive, what does he call it, lots of bad things, crude, earthy side.
But that's not the last word on the Karamatsov.
There's kick way back now.
The whole issue comes back on page 810 at court.
In the courtroom, the lawyer is explaining, and he's giving you Rakitin's view of what it is to be a Karamatsov.
The middle of the second paragraph.
Because he was, they're talking about Dmitri.
And remember, he's the broadest Karamatsov.
When we saw him come into the book, he had all those contradictions.
And he said the self is too broad.
He has it narrower.
And now, but the broadness is just what's at stake.
I mean, the Karamatsov self is broad.
It reaches all the way from the earthly to the heavenly, from the bad to the good, from the sensual to the spiritual.
So because he was of the broad Karamatsov character, that's just what I'm leading up to, capable of combining the most incongruous contradictions.
Yep, the self is contradictory.
And capable of the greatest heights and the greatest depths.
Remember, he goes headfirst into the pit and singing a song to the Madonna.
Remember the brilliant remark made by a young observer who was seeing the Karamatsov family at close quarters, Mr.
Rakitin.
Now, you can expect Rakitin to be accurate, but not sympathetic.
He says the sense of their own degradation is as essential to these reckless, unbridled natures as the sense of their generosity, unquote.
And that's true, the lawyer says.
They need continually this unnatural mixture, two extremes at the same moment, or they are miserable and dissatisfied with their existence, and their existence is incomplete.
They are wide, wide as Mother Russia.
They include everything and put up with everything.
Well, that's a big extreme statement.
So now it's not so much that the Keren Matsovs are bad and crude or everything.
They're just too broad.
They combine everything.
And what's left out of this whole story is something like how do they, could they get the contradictions together so as to make one unified, happy self?
And the answer is not on their own, not just quad natural human beings, but of course through agape love.
They get transformed so that Dmitry isn't anymore considered base and sensual, but rather impulsive, but positive.
What was once, what's really going on is really kind of interesting and subtle.
What Dostoevsky is saying is, and I was trying to set it up at the beginning of the lecture with talking about the impulsiveness you have to have if you're going to express your love, that what looks like the dark, earthy, primitive, sensual, crude side of the self, is the same aspect of the self that gives it the impulsiveness and the recklessness to do the best things that people do, like jump on the railroad tracks on top of somebody else and hold them down while the train goes over.
I mean, that kind of connected impulsiveness is part of the Keren Matsov force.
And so, in the end, and remember that when you name the two parts of the self, you already set up how you're going to view the self.
So, if you think the two parts are noble and lackey, you're not going to be able to get them together.
If you think that they're just plain, which is Ivan, if you think that they're Sodom and Madonna, you're not going to get them together.
But you can get them together if you think of them as, or if you think of them as the sensual and spiritual, even that doesn't work.
But you've got to think of them as the earthy, and that's partly the impulsive, but also the sensual.
But the earthly and the heavenly, those don't need to be opposed.
But finally, in somebody like Dmitri, they come together.
Presumably, Alyasha hasn't made it yet, but they will come together.
It's not clear with Zosim that occurs to me.
I think he's got rid too much of the sensual and the impulsive.
He's got the love, but the ideal Karamatsov is recklessly doing good, loving people.
588 is what I say as keyport.
That's one of the places where we hear the word reckless.
Remember, I read it at the very beginning today, where he feels, Dmitri feels that he has to do something to help everybody suffering.
At the end of the paragraph, he wanted to do all this at once, regardless of obstacles, with the recklessness of the Karamatsa's.
So, as I'm talking, I'm trying to gradually, what the book does, work you around from a negative view of the Taramatsov, Father Piases.
It's a boob force, it's a very dangerous thing, that it can be a positive thing, that the sensual side can be the impulsive side and the loving side, and then you get a positive view of the Karamatsa.
And that's the saving thing.
The earthly sensual can be combined with the heavenly spiritual if you experience agape love.
That's the Dostoevsky view.
And that is in a certain sense the end of the book.
But it's done in a weird and wonderful way.
Okay, we're now, he's done it in the last paragraph.
But I want to make sure that I convinced you that everyone of that, he's done all the jobs I listed.
He has to do.
Okay, he's now telling us the meaning of being a Karamatsov.
That it's a positive good thing.
We're all Karamatsavs, and when we get ourselves together in the right way, we will be loving, impulsive, sensual, spiritual, and so forth.
And now, what do the boys say in the last paragraph?
They say, and all our, yeah, and all our lives hand in hand, hooray for Karamatsa.
That's in a certain way the most important line in the book: that there is a way that the self, contradictory as it is, can, by this love that flows into the world and connectedness, become something positive.
So, hooray for Karamatsov, Kalya cried once more.
And once more, the boys took up the cry: Hooray for Karamatsov.
Now, you might well think that that's a good ending.
The brothers Karamatsov, we've gone from bad to worse, but the translation is wrong.
In the Russian, I've checked it, there is that last sentence, hooray for Karamatsov, isn't there.
Now, why isn't it there?
Well, there's one thing I haven't answered yet.
How is the Christianity going to go out and save the world?
How is the star going to rise in the East?
It's not going to be by Hooray for Karamatsov.
The last line is really, and the boys took up his cry.
That is, the last thing in the book has to be the boys charging out into the world, now completely strong because they formed this church, now transformed into good Karamatsovs through this love.
And that's the beginning of, I think you're supposed to think, each of them is going to go their own way, and each of these boys is going to found a church around some other loving person, some other martyr, some other death or something, and the world is going to become colonized by more and more colonies of these kind of communities.
And then Dostoevsky sort of dream, someday those communities will just be everywhere and take over the earth, and then that will be heaven on earth here and now, as Markle says.
I mean, that's the sort of wild vision that's behind it all.
And that's it for the book.
We did it.
Yep, we did it.
Anybody, there's time, five minutes, for anybody to have a last word here if you want to.
Anybody?
Okay, well, go home and write good papers and uh and and and read read the assignment for Tuesday if you possibly can.
We're going to switch to Nietzsche.