But I have to go back to the one Karamatsov that I haven't talked about.
And he's not really a Karamatsov.
He's at most half a Karamatsov.
And nobody ever calls him a Karamatsov.
And that is Smerzhikov.
But Smerzhikov is an important character in the book.
So we have to get him lined up with all the other Karamatsovs.
That is, he is the illegitimate son of old Karamatsov by way of some sort of bag lady street person that he just, I don't know, on a bet, he just fathered a child with her.
And the important thing is to understand what kind of character this guy is and how he got that way.
So starting, he turns out to be arrogant and despises everyone.
At the top of 140, we're going to start.
He was a young man, about 24, remarkably unsociable and self-contained.
Not that he was shy or bashful.
On the contrary, he was conceited and seemed to despise everyone.
Can you already tell which of the other brothers of the real Karamatsov three brothers he's most like?
Ivan, absolutely.
Turns out he also is the same age as Ivan, 24 years old.
Dostoevsky is obviously going out of his way to identify in some way Smershikov and Ivan.
And as you get further into the book, you will see that that turns out to be very important.
And now comes the most amazing thing, also on page 140.
I don't know how many of you could even remember this, because it's hard to remember things that are so weird.
I didn't even notice it for years.
Now I think it's absolutely amazing genius to come up with such a thing.
Do you remember what Smershikov likes to do as a child when he was little?
What?
Hang cats, right?
So there it is, the middle of the page.
In his childhood, not the middle of the page, about 10 lines down.
In his childhood, he liked to hang cats and bury them with great ceremony.
He used to dress up in a sheet as though it were a surplice and sing and wave some object over the dead cat as though it were a censer.
That's all Catholic mass costume and behavior.
All he did, all he did on the slide with the greatest secrecy.
So it took me a long time to even have any clue as to why that was in there.
Then some smart student said, and I think it's right, that it's a kind of parody of the two factors of the self.
That there is the dark side of Smerchikov that hangs the cats and the good side of Smeryakov that says mass over them.
It's a very perverted, peculiar form of two factors, but it is a kind of minimal self that he's got.
But it turns out that he's only got this minimal self for a while, and then it gets wiped out because he's an interesting case of a negative childhood memory.
He's got a memory that, in effect, tells him that he's not got a self at all.
And after that, you never hear anything more of him having anything either negative and dark or sort of religious at all.
And we have to follow that briefly.
So we're still in 140.
What happened then, in the middle of the page, Gregory used to say to all this he did on the slide.
All this he did on the slide with the greatest secrecy.
Gregory caught him once and beat him.
He shrank into a corner and so forth.
Now, what Gregory says is important.
He doesn't care for you or me, the beast, Gregory used to say to Marfa.
He doesn't care for anyone.
Then, speaking directly to the boy, he asks, Are you a human being?
That's like, do you have a self?
You're not a human being.
You grew from the mildew in the bathhouse.
That's what you are.
And now you can see it becomes a negative childhood memory.
Smerzhikov, it appears afterwards, could never forgive Gregory those words.
And if you follow what happens with Smershikov, you see that it turns out that he doesn't have any lofty impulses or any lackey impulses.
He just doesn't have any impulses at all.
You see it on page 142, where he does have one thing he likes to do, and it is so minimal that you could hardly call it lofty or lackey.
The middle of the page.
He came back to us from Moscow, well-dressed in a clean coat and clean linen.
Remember, that's the impeccable side of Yvonne being copied.
He brushed his clothes most scrupulously twice a day and was very fond of cleaning his smart taff boots with a special English polish so that they shone like mirrors.
That's the thing he's most fond of.
Not people, not men, not women, not food, not anything else.
But he was a cook, but you'll see in a minute that he didn't seem to be interested in what he ate, what he cooked.
He turned out to be a first-rate cook.
Theodore Karamaza paid him a salary, and he used it on clothes, pomade, perfume, and such.
But he seemed to have as much contempt for the female sex, as for men.
He was discreet, almost unapproachable with them.
So he's not interested in men.
He's not interested in women.
He's not interested in anything.
And that's very important about him.
Again, he lacks the sensual side and he lacks the spiritual side, the earthy and the heavenly, however you want to say.
He lacks just a second the two factors.
So he doesn't even flee taking a stand on the factors.
He doesn't even have a kind of despair which he's hiding.
He's really not a human being.
He's a sort of a kind of zombie when you get right down to it.
And as I say, nobody ever calls him a Karamatsov because he doesn't have the self-problem that all Karamatsovs have.
But then this leads to a funny problem.
If he doesn't care about anything, how does he get motivated to do anything besides polish his boots, which he seems to care?
Well, that's a very interesting problem for Dostoevsky.
And keep your eye open.
It's very important for the quote of the book.
Where does Mary Juko get his desires and his goals and his sort of model for how to act, which sort of replaces him having any really any desires at all?
Ah, Beatrice, what?
Yeah?
Didn't he could have a great deal of contempt for the other four we need?
Which is a very bad sign, of course.
You know, Russia's the okay, well, he has a contempt.
Remember, he has a disdain and a contempt for everybody.
He has a negative impulse.
But how is there anybody in the book that he admires and respects?
You don't know yet, probably.
There is, and it's going to turn out to be extremely important.
You can guess who it would be.
He's impeccably dressing.
He's having this disdain for everybody.
He's so sort of wrapped up in himself that he doesn't relate to anybody.
Doesn't that begin to remind you of somebody was sort of the grossest version of somebody?
Of Yvonne, yeah.
He's like a parody of Yvonne.
And that, just bear that in mind and watch it develop.
It develops pretty quickly later.
Well, maybe halfway on in the book.
So, by the way, halfway on in the book, I want to tell you what to do for next time.
Next time, we're going to do the Grand Inquisitor.
So bring the Grand Inquisitor page.
And if you don't have it, it's that white one down there.
Pick it up when you leave or print it.
And be sure to read 279 to 302.
Whether you ever, if unfortunately for you, you haven't got that far, what did I say?
279 to 302?
That's the Grand Inquisitor.
It's a separate thing.
You can skip to it without losing your understanding of the plot and without anything being given away.
But if you don't read it for sure by next Tuesday, you would just not, you might as well not come because you won't understand anything.
As I said about today, which I'm going to start talking about now, if you haven't read the part on rebellion, you might as well go out and enjoy the fresh air.
But we're going to do a rebellion now for the rest of the time.
So we're going to talk about Yvonne.
Remember, Yvonne wants to be perfect.
And to get, which, of course, that aspect of Yvonne that Smerzhikov doesn't really understand, except maybe in the parody of the very perfectly polished boots, that Yvonne wants to be perfect by getting rid of everything base, earthy, sensual in himself and become completely refined, completely pure, and completely self-sufficient.
So he doesn't want to get close to anybody, but he does have this attraction for Katerina, his existential double.
But what he says to Alyasha is interesting.
He says that he only can get close to somebody when they're about to leave, or he's about to leave, on 259, 258.
At the bottom paragraph, I want to get to know you once and for all, he says to Alyasha, and I want you to know me, and then we will say goodbye.
I believe it's always best to get to know people just before leaving them.
In other words, don't get involved.
There are really people like that.
You may know some people like that.
I know a few who can only really get close to somebody and intimate with somebody when they're sure that they're about to leave.
That's in the film Breathless, that's part of what's going on.
But that's typical of Yvonne.
But while he's with Alyasha, anyway, and knowing that it's okay because they're all going to get separated and they won't get involved with each other, he does decide to tell Alyasha everything basic and important to him.
On 265, the middle of the page, he says, I am trying to explain as quickly as possible my essential nature, that is, what manner of man I am, what I believe in, for what I hope.
That's it, isn't it?
And that's what he then proceeds to do.
That's what the rebellion story is all about.
And he's going to tell Alyacha his stand towards life, and it's really despair.
I mean, but it's right out in the open, it's despair.
Because it's all about when and why he's going to commit suicide, though he never says it in so many words.
It's clear that that's what he's going to talk about.
So, but first he has to sort of clear some things out of the way, which he does.
So, on 259, at the beginning of the conversation, he makes clear that it's not going to be what, no, I've jumped too fast to 259, just a second.
No, that's fine.
Look at, the important thing, this is where he threatens suicide and explains what he's going to do.
The middle of 259.
Do you know, I've been sitting here thinking to myself that if I didn't believe in life, if I lost faith in the woman I love, which is sort of funny because he says he loves Flatarina, but everybody else says he only loves himself and he doesn't love anybody.
And you could, if you keep your eyes open, you'll find those phrases.
You can underline them because they're sort of scattered around in the book, and I didn't find them.
But I thought, I mean, it's whatever it is to love somebody for Ivan, it's not what anybody else recognizes as loving them.
I lost faith in the woman I love, lost faith in the order of things, as if he ever had any.
We're convinced in the fact that everything is a disorderly, damnable, and perhaps devil-ridden chaos, more like what he thinks.
If I were struck by every horror of man's disillusionment, still I would want to live.
Having once tasted of the cup, the cup of life, that is, this is all sorted in code.
Having once tasted of the cup, I would not turn away from it, that means commit suicide, till I had drained it.
At 30, though, I shall be sure to leave the cup, even if I've not emptied it, and turn away where I don't know.
Well, it gets a little clearer why he's going to turn away, and that it means dying.
But till I'm 30, I know that my youth will triumph over everything, every disillusion, every disgust with life.
I've asked myself many times whether there is in the world any despair that could overcome this frantic search for thirst for life, and I've come to the conclusion that there isn't, that is till I'm 30.
Some dribbling, consumptive moralists and poets especially call that thirst for life base.
It's a feature of the Karamatsovs, to be sure, the thirst for life, regardless of everything.
And you probably have it too.
Okay, so he's saying, you know, he can't help loving the sticky green leaves.
He can't help, I suppose, finding Katerina sexually or erotically attractive in some way.
But all of that, he thinks, is not essential to who he is, and he'll outgrow it.
That's that half of the self isn't the real Yvonne.
The real Yvonne would just go on living a life free of all the sensuality and all the impulses and desires and lower immediacy after he outgrew them, since they weren't important anyway.
But the trouble is that there's something else wrong with the world which prevents him from wanting to stay alive after 30.
As soon as the sort of impulse grip of the world wears off, it's clear that he's going to throw away the cup, but we don't know why yet.
We'll find out in a minute.
So in 268, what is on 268?
Oh, he's talking about how he can't love people at close quarters, which contradicts the Katarina thing, among other things.
The middle.
One can love one's neighbors in the abstract, and even at a distance, but at close quarters, it's almost impossible.
Remember, I said when he's not, he's a lover of humanity in general, but he doesn't like any human beings in particular.
Now, we're ready to.
And it's Fedor who says he doesn't love anybody.
So Ivan is attached to the world and the people and the leaves and the spring and all that.
But really deeply, he's not involved.
He doesn't love anything.
He always is protecting himself from getting involved in anything.
And he will get rid of the sensual and the involved as soon as possible.
And he has to do it.
Now, that's all background.
Now comes the fun part.
And I remember I told you, think about this argument now that he's going to give and see if you're convinced or not and why you are or aren't.
He's going to tell Alyasha what he firmly, deeply believes.
It starts on 265.
The first thing he does is sort of sensibly get God out of the story, not because he says that he doesn't believe in God.
It's just that what he's going to talk about is sort of his existential stance, that is how he relates to life, and not some metaphysical question about whether there's a God or not.
And he thinks that, and it's sort of like Pascal, that we can't know whether there's a God or not.
I think I told you, Pascal says in the Pensées, I don't think I put it in the handout, we can prove the existence of God, and we can prove the non-existence of God.
And therefore, it doesn't do any good to try to think about it.
So he says at the bottom of 265, I have a Euclidean earthly mind, and so how can I solve problems that are not of this world?
And I'd advise you never to think about it either, Alyasha, especially about God, whether he exists or not.
All such questions are utterly inappropriate for a mind created for three dimensions.
So all this is to say, don't get involved in this sort of Platonic, Greek, abstract, philosophical way of thinking.
That's not what matters.
What matters is what your attitude is toward living your life in this world.
So he says, I accept God and I'm glad to.
I accept his wisdom, and it's completely beyond our knowledge.
But then comes what, well, what is his stat?
What is important?
His importance is how he relates to the world.
And about 12 lines down, he says on 266, yet I would, yet, would you believe it in the final result?
I don't accept this world of gods.
So it's this creation, this world, that Yvonne wants to reject.
And he's going to, and that's what it means for him to throw away the cup and get out of this world and, and in effect, commit suicide, as soon as he can get disconnected from the sensuous attractions of things, which aren't really him anyway.
So he's going to prove now to Alyasha that if you're a decent person, then you wait a minute, let's see.
Okay, that any decent moral person is obliged to leave the world as soon as possible.
That as soon as the Karamatsov sensuous force weakens so that he can tear himself away from the world, that is when he's 30, then he will just have to get out of the world because there's something basically wrong with the world that any decent, impeccable moral person like Yvonne would have to reject.
And why does he think that?
Well, his reasoning is a little bit complicated, not very.
The argument is the world is such a corrupt and evil place that no moral person should accept living in it.
And that's what he's going to, and he makes a pretty clear case for this.
It's very convincing.
You should ask yourself whether you're convinced, and then ask yourself if you are convinced, then why shouldn't you commit suicide when you're 30 also?
That is, is there something wrong with this argument?
Or has he really convinced you?
So how does he do it?
Well, how does he make his argument?
Well, he collects a dossier of instances of horrible child abuse.
That's what he's talking about on 270.
He says about a third of the way down, I like to collect certain facts.
Would you believe I even copy anecdotes of a certain sort from newspapers and books?
I've already got a fine collection.
A fine isn't quite the right word.
The next time he describes it, he says it's nice.
And now, that sounds like a subtle difference, but when you get there, you'll see why the right thing to say is that it's nice.
But what that means right now, I can't explain yet.
So he has a dossier, but he also of these child abuses, which would seem to be bad enough that one ought to leave the world.
And he describes these awful things that people have done to children.
And then, but he, there are two possible objections he has to answer.
And one is maybe these sufferers deserve all this suffering.
They've been bad, and they've done bad things or had bad impulses.
And the second is, well, in the world of the other, in the other world, afterlife, it'll all be made up.
The people who did the bad things will burn forever in hell, and the children who suffered these bad things will sing the praises of God forever in eternity.
What about that?
Well, he's got two interesting answers to that.
It's not too hard.
He says the children are innocent.
It's a Greek Orthodox view, I've been told, that children are innocent up to the age of seven, which I think it may be, maybe Roman Catholic too, or at least French Catholic.
But it doesn't matter for this argument.
At some age, children, obviously, from a very early age, children do annoying and nasty things.
St.
Augustine is very good on this.
He wants to prove that there's original sin, and he wants to say that little babies who aren't aware at all of good and evil and so forth are already evil, but they just don't know it.
And his example is interesting.
He says, you have two siblings or twins, maybe, I don't remember.
One of whom has already drunk as much of his mother's milk as he could possibly hold.
He still gets jealous and cries if the mother offers her breast to the sibling.
And if that's true, and it probably is, it shows that what it's supposed to show is children do things like get selfish and jealous and possessive and so forth, but until they're seven, they don't know what they're doing.
But after a while, they know that you shouldn't lie and shouldn't be greedy and so forth.
But the children that Yvonne collects are children who are under the age of knowing, so they're innocent.
They're always, this is Yvonne getting it wrong.
He says they're always sweet and lovable.
Augustine is right.
They're not always sweet and lovable, but they're at least not guilty in a way that they should be tortured the way they are.
And now, though, he says on the middle, no, the bottom, the third of 268, but in the first place, children can be loved even at close quarters, even when they're dirty, even when they're ugly.
And that is, they're not sinful.
We've just said that.
Now, he also says that the grown-ups can suffer.
That's all right.
But the children shouldn't.
At the top of 274, at the top paragraph, I say nothing of the suffering of grown-ups.
They have eaten the apple, damn them.
That is, they know good and evil.
And the devil take them all.
But these little ones, and then poor Alyasha is really, really suffering from all these gory details.
I'm making you suffer, Alyasha.
I'll stop if you like.
No, never mind.
I want to suffer too, muttered Alyasha.
And so now Yvonne has got his case against, I mean, there's no reason, just it's an outrage that these children should suffer who haven't, who are innocent.
And what about this other world where everything will be all right?
Well, Yvonne's got this interesting argument that punishing the child abusers isn't going to make things all right.
It's certainly going to increase the amount of suffering in the universe, but that's not what you want to do.
You want to get somehow fix the suffering of the children.
But they've already suffered.
And you can't take back the fact that they were locked up in the outhouse or beaten by their parents or dogs turned on them by the Turks or whatever it was.
I've forgotten all these gory details.
There's no way to comfort them for that, even if you rewarded them from then on.
So even a higher harmony won't help, he says on 277, the middle of the page.
I renounce the higher harmony.
It's not worth the tears of one tortured child who beat himself on the breast with his little fist and prayed in the stinking outhouse with his tears to dear find God.
It's not worth it because those tears are unatoned for.
They must be atoned for, or there can be no harmony.
But how?
How are you going to atone for them?
Is it possible?
And then by being avenged, no.
And there's no way.
So at the bottom, he says, I don't want harmony from love of humanity.
I don't want it.
See, harmony would sort of try to cover up the unforgivable suffering by saying, ah, that they're happy now.
But that's not going to do it.
I would rather be left with unavenged suffering.
I would rather remain with my at the top of 278.
I'd rather remain with my unavenged suffering and unsatisfied indignation.
It's too high a price to pay for harmony.
It's beyond our means to pay it.
So what follows from that?
Well, it follows from that that any decent person should leave the world.
Let's go.
It's all happening on 277 and 278.
By the way, anybody want to say anything?
I mean, I think there's plenty to say in a minute, but not yet.
But if there is something that I'm missing or you want to say it, just don't get hypnotized.
Go ahead.
But I'll keep talking until you find what you want to say.
On 277, I just read the part about harmony at the bottom, and 278 at the top.
And then now comes the punchline at the top of 278.
And so I give back my entrance ticket.
And if I'm an honest man, I give it back as soon as possible.
You realize that's the story, that I stop drinking from the cup of life as soon as I stop being sensuously hooked on people and things.
And as soon as he can do it, he's got to get out of this world.
I give back my entrance ticket, and if I'm an honest man, I give it back as soon as possible.
And that I'm doing it.
And that I am doing.
It's not God that I don't accept Alyasha.
I respectfully return the ticket to him.
And that's interesting.
He's saying that the world is so outrageously bad that no decent moral person would accept to live in it.
And he pushes it then to the extreme.
But that's rebellion, murmured Alyasha, looking down.
Rebellion?
I'm sorry you call it that, said Yvonne.
One can hardly live in rebellion, and I want to live.
Well, he wants to live, but he has to give up living because the world is such a terrible place that it would be wrong to accept to live on those terms.
And the argument is very interesting the way Dostoevsky sets it up here.
I mean, the test would be whether this argument was convincing was to be whether Alyasha is convinced, because he is the most sensitive, the most sort of upbeat, the most always joyful person.
So will he buy this depressing argument from Yvonne?
And let's find out on 278.
I challenge you, answer.
Imagine that you were creating, this is Yvonne talking, a fabric of human destiny with the object of making men happy in the end.
Imagine that you were doing this, that it's essential and inevitable to torture to death one tiny creature, that child beating its breast with its fist, for instance, in order to found that edifice on its unavenged tears.
Would you consent to be the architect on those conditions?
Tell me, tell the truth.
And then, poor Alyasha, he's absolutely convinced.
No, I wouldn't consent, said Alyasha.
So it looks like Yvonne has made his point.
And the question is: let me see.
Yeah, it looks like Yvonne has made his point.
Are you convinced?
You're the Alyasha ones who just read it.
Has he convinced you that if you're a decent person, you should get out of this world as soon as possible?
And if he hasn't convinced you, sort of, what's the really philosophical question isn't whether you're convinced, but what's wrong with his argument if you're not convinced?
Yeah.
He's saying everyone in the world is bad, including man?
Yes.
He's saying, but that's a very interesting way to put it.
I have to digest what you said.
The answer is yes and no.
So let me give you the yes now, and I'll give you the no now and the yes later.
The no is it doesn't matter whether they're all as bad, including him.
As soon as it's a world in which there are tortured children, it's a bad world because, I mean, nobody's revenging the tortured children, and even if they did sort of revenge on the person who did the torturing, the children are already tortured.
And in a world in which God has set it up so the world works like that, that's a world that he doesn't want to have anything to do with.
He wouldn't make a world like that.
Now, whether everybody is a child torturer, that's a very strange, strong claim.
But in the end, Yvonne makes it, but not yet.
And how come he makes it is very interesting.
But it's enough for his argument if you just have one, remember, one child tortured by one person, and you shouldn't accept the world.
So it's clear he doesn't have to argue that there's anything but this one outrage, unavenged, unavengeable outrage, that then Haliasha won't accept that world, and you shouldn't either, he says.
And I think he's right.
One shouldn't.
But then there must be something wrong with the question somehow, and we've got to figure out what it is.
So Dostoevsky certainly wants you to finally understand something wrong about what Yvonne is saying.
So let's put it this way.
So the question is: should each of us give back our ticket?
There seems to be, that is, should each of us get out of this world as soon as possible?
Because it's like saying if you were in a play, a spectator at a play, or if you were being wooed by a fraternity or a sorority, and you discovered that they were immoral, prejudiced, and the movie was sadistic and violent and so forth, you should walk out.
You should give back your ticket.
You shouldn't join that fraternity or sorority, or if you've joined, you should always, you just didn't know enough.
When you find out how prejudiced they are, for instance, you should leave.
And he's saying, and if that's the way it is in the world, if you find yourself in a world which has values that you can't accept, you can just get out.
Yes, so first you and then you, yeah.
And that's how the old fraternity around, you know.
But there's lack of death, I think, you know, oh.
There's no place to go.
Okay.
Yeah.
Well.
I think I can just have it.
You're giving the freedom to choose how you want to live your life.
But any other kind of you're kind of being empowered.
Well, well, let's let's see.
I see what you're saying, but he would have to say something.
He would say, like, but there's no way to face it, I mean, except by leaving, because here's this situation.
You don't control it, but if you don't want to be part of a world where it happens, it's like, that's why I say it's like the fraternity in the movie.
No matter whether there's someplace else to go or not, you don't want to be in this situation.
And if it's the whole world that's like this, then maybe just consider as a possibility that the only way to deal with it is to get out of the world, otherwise you become kind of an accomplice in it.
That's what he's saying.
Something good.
Well, it's all part of the same world, I think.
That's the point.
If you could leave this world for second life, say, in which in that virtual world, nobody tortured children, that would be nice.
But you can't leave this world just by going into some book.
Ah, okay.
Aha.
You have now.
Can you hear her?
Why not be a good person and change the way the world is, try to fix the evil in the world?
She jumped way ahead of the story.
But you're absolutely on the right track.
But we have to get there step by step.
We'll get there before the end of the hour.
We'll come back to your point.
Yes?
I don't think we should leave the world because some people think it's okay to torture children.
It's like, I'll go to winter words.
I'll go to the body.
Okay, you're both sort of half there.
You've bought too much of Yvonne's story, but you haven't bought all of it, which is good.
But there's something about, well, let's hold this.
Both of you are right, that there ought to be a way to go to other parts of the world, so to speak, and do good deeds in them.
And Yvonne is telling you something like, but there's no way to either you have to fix the world as a whole or reject the world as a whole.
Something like that is his version.
And we have to see why that's wrong.
Yeah.
Once you think about it as a person creating their own world, well, he's saying, and that's the work, and you guys are challenging it in interesting ways.
There's only one big world, and we're all in it.
And since we can't make a world of our own, because we're really part of this world, and since we can't fix it, the only thing to do is to leave.
And you're all questioning that, and rightly so.
But you haven't questioned it at the most basic level.
Yeah.
Is it possible that he's fundamentally wrong that God created the world so that you don't have to be impossible?
Like, it's not that people, I think somewhere in there, you said that Russians are just immediately fond of doing things.
Maybe that's not so much true, but that they haven't, God doesn'ten to create people like all of them.
Well, that's probably okay.
I mean, okay in the sense that it doesn't matter.
I'll get you in a minute.
Okay.
It doesn't matter whether God created it that way or God created it good, but then people fell and became sinful and evil.
It's now a sinful and evil person and a world.
And it's a kind of attack on God, but you could cancel God out of it.
The way he sets it up is: are you going to be part of a system, if it's a play or a fraternity or a culture or a society or a town, whatever, but the biggest system that's bad, don't you have, isn't it your obligation to get out of it?
I'm going to listen to two more questions and then I'll do it my way.
Yeah.
All those really bad things that can happen, if he doesn't say any of the good things that happen to the world.
And you get the world as supposed to only these like bad people who drive to torture phone.
Yeah, but his argument is it's it's bad.
If there's a world from the point of view of the children, so to speak, if it's a world in which one child is tortured in order to make it the kind of world it is, that's already grounds for rejecting it.
It's got to be for him a world in which no innocent victims suffer, or it's a world that you shouldn't accept.
Yeah.
During the first 30 years of his right, he's poor anything.
You got it.
I mean, that's where you have to start.
Not that the other people were wrong, but you're questioning the really fundamental thing that's wrong is that it's from where he's making the argument.
It isn't the argument that's wrong, but it's the idea that he somehow is related to the world the way you're related to a play for which you bought a ticket or a fraternity that you've gone to their initiation party or something.
You're not related to the world that way.
You are born and raised in the world, and you're part of the world, and you can't step back and take a completely detached attitude as if you were free and independent of the world, and whether you want to choose it or not.
You are inextricably enmeshed in the world from the moment you were born.
That's Dostoevsky's argument.
Let me put it this way: I mean, the interesting, brilliant move in this chapter is that you try to figure out what's wrong with the argument, and what's really wrong is the point of view from which the argument is being made.
Yeah.
Yes.
It's from the point of view of the eternal and the infinite.
It's sort of from God's point of view or the philosopher's point of view, or to put it now and bring it down to earth more, but it's taking up the detached point of view instead of the involved point of view.
So the whole argument is made from the point of view of a detached mind who is deciding whether it wants to be part of this, have this body and be in this world.
And the answer is supposed to be, but you're not in a detached mind.
You're stuck with this body in this world.
So you better get a different argument.
And that's when the other people come in.
You just started it a step earlier, which is good.
And Beatrice wants to say something.
Okay, then let me catch up where we are, because you really have worked it out.
Let's see now, where are we?
Okay, what's wrong with Yvonne's argument?
The answer is it's a philosophical argument.
It presumes that Yvonne is related to the world like a spectator at a play.
If the play is stupid or vulgar, you can just walk out.
But that's not how you are in the world.
You are involved.
He's not in a position to accept or reject it.
He's not an innocent bystander.
He's not an eyewitness to the world.
He's involved, and now comes an amazing next move, and he's guilty.
And moreover, and this is just a tour de force of Dostoevsky.
You don't have to do it this way, but he's going to do it this way.
What if he turns out to be an example of child abuse?
That would be really amazing.
But that would be the most dramatic form to show that he's part of the problem, that he can't step outside the problem, so to speak, and reject the world.
Well, how in the world would anybody think that Yvonne, impeccable Yvonne, is involved in the world by way of being guilty?
Well, I'll tell you the story.
It's so sort of sprinkled around subtly by Dostoevsky.
It's just incredible.
But to begin with, why is Yvonne so worried about the suffering of these children?
Is that just something out of nowhere?
Let me read you about the way he describes the suffering of the children.
I guess I didn't write it down.
Every once in a while I find one of these places where I didn't get the copy from the old text.
There's a place where he says that the children suffer for their father's sins.
Let's see if we can find it.
Right around here.
That's one of the examples that he gives.
Can you find it?
Skipped it.
Too bad.
Oh, there they are.
At the bottom, it's about the bottom of 268.
Okay, at the bottom, about five lines from the bottom.
If they suffer horribly on earth, they must suffer for their father's sins.
They must be punished for their fathers who have eaten the apple.
But so forth and so forth.
The innocent must not suffer for another's sins, and especially not those innocents.
Are you beginning to see any relation between Yvonne's complaint and Yvonne's life?
He thinks he suffered for his father's sins.
He's identifying with these tortured children.
That's the first move.
That's why he's sort of making a case for them.
I have to write in here.
Okay.
And that's why he's that's already shows that he's not a disinterested spectator.
He doesn't just stand off nowhere and reject the world.
But on the basis of his unhappy suffering as a child, he is interested in this problem of child abuse.
And that already shows how deeply connected he is to how he raises the question.
No, I don't think he recognizes yet that he's in despair.
He will.
But no, right now, it's just showing you that he's motivated to have this problem by this childhood, which is just part of the argument that he's in, as she was saying, that he's in the world from the start, from being a little kid already.
Yeah.
That has to be that he went when it happened when the answer that he raised.
I see.
Smerzyakov did some sinful thing you're saying, and Yvonne has his own parallel.
I don't think that's going to get us the way we want to get.
We'll get there, but by a different track.
You don't need Smerzyakov.
That's too clever by half, as I did.
You know, Smerchikov is like Yvonne, and therefore you can read things about Smerchakikov and the cats back to Yvonne.
You don't need it.
Dostoevsky has spit up in a much more amazing way.
And that's when you start to realize that Yvonne is, I won't tell you yet.
I'll just read you passages and see if you can see what Dostoevsky's smuggling in here now.
I have to read one of these horror stories at the bottom of 272 because that really gives it away.
He says, a well-educated, cultured man and his wife beat their child with a birch rod.
A girl of seven, notice she, I guess she's just below seven, you'd have to say, or maybe it's only at the end of when you're seven that you get over being innocent.
I have an account of it and so forth.
He likes the birch twigs because it stings more and he begins stinging his daughter.
Now look at this.
I know for a fact that there are people who at every blow are worked up to sensuality, to literal sensuality, which increases progressively at every blow they inflict.
Now, that's ambiguous.
Does he know that because he's read about it?
Or does he know that there are such people?
I think that's all you can conclude from that.
But now, now Dostoevsky throws the punchline at you on 273.
And I have to sort of explain it, but first I'll just let's read it.
He's going on now about a girl of five and how they badly treated her, and at the end of that paragraph, the crucial clue.
In every man, of course, a demon lies hidden, the demon of rage, the demon of lustful heat, at the screams of the tortured victim.
What is strange about that?
He knows that in every man.
Yeah, he's got to have that in himself if he knows that in every man.
I don't know about you, but maybe I'm just fooling myself, but I do not think I enjoy the screams of tortured victims.
I can't even see the country, no country for old men, because I know how violent it's going to be.
I'm squeamish about it.
But I don't know about you all, but I doubt if you all think that you feel the screams of the tortured victims.
But Yvonne knows that everybody does.
That means he knows that he does.
And now you look back at his, why is he collecting these anecdotes that are, as he says, nice, you see, not fine, nice.
He's getting off on them.
He's lusting over them.
He's got his form of sexual excitement.
He is the problem.
I mean, he is a sadist, in fact.
Now, it's too much to get it out of that one sentence.
But I'll show you, you can find it all over the book once you see it, that Yvonne is a sadist.
Yeah.
So into all this big person because he's trying to purify himself.
No, no, no.
I think you've got it upside down.
Put it this way.
It's because he's into these sorts of things that he feels in some level a kind of horror at himself, that aspect of himself, and at the world because of that.
And in effect, he's going to sort of kill himself and stamp out this sadist child molester that he is.
But he's not very conscious of that.
He doesn't seem to see any connection between the fact that he's collecting these fine anecdotes and that he's part of the problem.
He thinks that he's, you know, he can give back the ticket.
He's not a sadist.
There are all these bad people in the world.
He's been asked to join this world, this fraternity, or this movie, or this play, and he's not going to join it.
He's too impeccable.
So he's really sort of lying to himself.
It's just that it comes out indirectly that he admits that in every man.
I mean, Dostoevsky has done it just brilliantly.
He's got Yvonne telling you that he's lusting at the screens of the tortured victims without realizing that he's telling you something special about himself.
He thinks he's just telling you a general characteristic of human beings.
But the main thing is he's giving away what?
That he's not impeccable, that he hasn't got a ticket that he can give back.
He is the problem of torturing children.
And that is just interesting.
And now, if you think that I made this up, you've got to, there's something that happens way late in the book, but it doesn't affect the plot, so I can tell you.
And it's just funny, if you can call it funny, that it's amazing that finally we find the whole story.
And remember that I left you with the puzzle, really, of how Lisa is the existential double of Yvonne.
Now we've discovered that maybe, let's just say maybe, did I say, yeah, oh, of Alyasha?
Ooh, thank you.
You're looking worried.
Okay, now let me think a minute.
Yes, I have not the right to say that.
You'll see why I mixed it up, because Yvonne is relevant here.
But the question remains, and I shouldn't have brought it in, how Alyasha is related to Lisa.
The question we want to talk about right now is how Yvonne is related to Lisa.
And that's the clue.
So let me read it on 265.
He says, Now Lisa's talking, you know, when I read about that child, and it was a child which they crucified, and then they sat and ate pineapple jam while the child suffered for hours and finally died.
They hammered nails into him, the usual horror story.
And then she says, I cried all night.
I kept thinking of how the little thing cried and moaned.
A child of four understands, you know.
And all the while the thought of pineapple jam haunted me.
In the morning, I wrote a letter to a certain person begging him to come and see me.
He came and I told him all about the child and the pineapple jam, all about it, all.
And he said that it was nice.
And now, who did she invite?
It turns out it was Yvonne.
It's no secret that it was Yvonne.
On the next page, what?
I was on 675.
On 676, he says, she never says it's Yvonne, but Alyasha knows it's Yvonne, and everybody knows it's Yvonne, if you're reading the book.
And what happens?
Then, well, let's see if I can.
It's all very interesting.
So Alyasha says, did you send him the letter?
Yes.
Simply to ask about the child?
No.
But he came and I asked him about it, and he answered and laughed and got up and went away.
That person behaved honorably, Alyasha murmured.
That means what she really wanted to be was tortured by Yvonne, that he saw that and he left.
And she says, and did he despise me?
Did he laugh at me?
No, Alyasha says, perhaps he believes in pineapple jam himself.
He's very ill now, Lisa.
Yes, he does believe it, said Lisa with flashing eyes.
He doesn't despise anyone, Alyasha went on, only he doesn't believe and so forth.
He doesn't believe in people, of course.
He does despise them.
Then he does despise me, me, you too.
Good.
She says, when he went out laughing, I felt that it was nice to be despised.
The child with fingers cut off is nice, and to be despised is nice.
Well, she's a raving masochist, and she knows that the one person she can call who will despise her and perhaps rape her, we just don't know what, but generally beat her up, whatever.
And Yvonne comes and at least does come and despise her.
And she, and so now we know that she knows, and Alyasha knows, that Yvonne is a saddest, and she's a masochist.
And then it just can't resist.
It's like the cats in a way.
More weird, dusty, susty stuff happens on 67.
As soon as Alyasha had gone, this is the last paragraph, Lisa unbolted the door, opened it a little, put her finger in the crack, and slammed the door with all her might on her, pinching her finger.
I hope more than pinching, if the Russian probably ought to say squashing.
Ten seconds later, releasing her finger, she walked slowly to her chair.
She sat up straight in it and looked intensely at the blackened finger and at the blood oozing out under the nail.
Her lips were quivering, and she kept whispering to herself, I am a wretch, wretch, wretch, wretch.
So she wants to be punished.
I mean, if just they're both in this suffering mode, but they're both in the wrong sort of suffering mode.
He's the saddest, sort of getting thinking it's fine and getting his kicks out of reading about tortured children, and she's a tortured child, torturing herself.
And then you know that, so Yvonne, in spite of his claim to be pure and lofty and noble, is really got a base side, as base or baser even, than most people.
He's just too refined to actually torture anyone or to beat up Lisa, or right now too refined even to kill himself.
But he has his nice collection of newspaper clippings.
And here's another little variation on it.
Thart has a view about what it is to be a saddest, and it doesn't mean actually beating up people and torturing them.
Just treating people as objects in which you were the observer and free, and they are the object turned into an object by you is a kind of very refined sadistic attitude.
How many know no exit where that comes in?
You recognize the no exit story.
So Thart says that just the desire to be a free and vulnerable detached observer is sadistic.
And that means, of course, that not only does Yvonne have his nice collection of newspaper clippings, but he has his job writing for the newspaper as the eyewitness, the detached observer.
So, at all the levels, from really sort of dirty sadism to kind of very refined sadism, he's a sadist.
Later, you'll find Yvonne asking about the tortures in hell with great eagerness and interest.
Because in the end, I guess every sadist must be a masochist, and the masochist must be a sadist somehow.
I don't really know how to work it out.
So, Yvonne is really interested in the punishments that people get, and of course, interested in the punishments that the children get.
So, now what?
We're almost there, because it now turns out that the way the book works, it shows you that you aren't in the position to give back the ticket.
Yvonne, the sadist, who is relishing the torturing of these children, can't be giving back the ticket to the world saying, I don't want to be in a world in which people torture children, because he's totally hooked on the world in which people torture children.
So, now the conclusion is his whole argument is wrong, because it looks like his relation to the world is like to a fraternity or a movie or a play, but not because they're just local and there's more to the world, but because he thinks you can just leave the world, the way you can leave the fraternity or the play where you're not responsible for what is vulgar and sadistic and stupid and prejudiced that might be going on there.
It's clear that he is doing just the kind of thing that he wants to condemn.
So, he can't, as the righteous person, leave the world condemning the suffering of the children when he really enjoys the suffering of children.
That's Dostoevsky's argument.
So now, I can't tell you much more about this because it's a plot thing, but I'll tell you a little: that Yvonne gets more and more general, and it turns out that being an eyewitness is a very dangerous thing to be.
And it turns out that Yvonne takes responsibility for much of the evil in the book, finally.
And it turns out, too, that I was reading the notes for the brothers Karamatsov.
Dostoevsky calls Yvonne the educated one before he has a name for him and the murderer.
And that's to remember that the guy, the one who wants to play the angel, plays the beast.
It's all part of the same dark story.
So, what's the right thing to think?
Well, first, Yvonne is not a spectator.
He's not an eyewitness.
He's a participant.
He's part of the problem.
He is guilty.
And now the question is, and so we can't give back the ticket.
So now comes the people over in this corner who asked and already had good ideas about what to do.
There are two things.
I mean, one is to discover Yvonne's argument is wrong.
And the other one is to worry about, well, what are you supposed to do when you're enmeshed in a world in which there is evil in suffering innocent children, even if you're not sadistic?
That's just Yvonne's problem.
What are you supposed to do about living in that sort of world?
So now we go to the person who has the most extreme opposite view of Yvonne from Yvonne's.
Do you recognize that?
Have you got far enough?
I don't know.
Who worries about the guilt of, who worries about being guilty for all the suffering?
Well, maybe you haven't got to 184, though you should be getting there quickly.
But it's Zosima.
Zosima is the absolute opposite of Yvonne's story.
Instead of claiming, like Yvonne, that he has no guilt, that he rejects the world because everybody else is guilty, Father Zosima claims that he's guilty for all the evil in the world.
184.
You should be...
How far?
Yes, you should be there.
So let's look at it.
184.
Zosima's making this big speech about guilt at the second sentence or third sentence of the second paragraph, 184.
Because we have come here and shut ourselves within these walls, we are no holier than those that are outside.
On the contrary, for the very fact of coming here, each of us has confessed to himself that he is worse than others, worse than all the men on earth.
And skipping a little, when he realizes that he's not only worse than others, but he's responsible to all men for all and everything, for all human sins, national and individual, only then can the aim of our seclusion be attained.
For know, dear ones, that every one of us is undoubtedly responsible for all men and everything on earth, not merely through the general sinfulness of creation, but each one personally for all mankind and every individual man.
Now, that's a very strange speech.
Took me a long time to sort of free myself from it because the critics all say, isn't that interesting?
Wonderful.
What an amazing character Father Zosima is.
He feels responsible for all the evil in the world.
We're guilty for it individually and personally, for all of it everywhere.
But that's just crazy.
I mean, you can't, and I can't, feel guilty for the...
the thirsty people in the desert or the, I don't know, some Chinese family that's malfunctioning and so forth.
We can't even feel guilty for all the families in Berkeley that are malfunctioning.
I mean, it's just impossible to do that.
And this story that Zosima's telling, which he's telling so well and so moving, and he's such a nice man, you wonder, what does Dostoevsky think about that?
Well, Dostoevsky doesn't ever sort of say that he thinks this is a crazy view, but he shows you that that's not the right view.
And that you get this crazy view if you withdraw into the monastery.
That is really what they're guilty of.
Zosima says we're all guilty because we come here.
But when they come there and withdraw from the world, they can't really deal with all the evil in the world.
Their guilt is that they can feel guilty about everything, but it doesn't make any sense because they're not really guilty in any sensible way.
And if they're staying in the monastery, they can't do anything about it.
So I think we're supposed to think that that is equally wrong.
It's as wrong as Yvonne thinking that you should get out of the world and give back your ticket.
There's a way in which Zosima gets out of the world and goes into the monastery, which is wrong.
Yvonne does it being very righteous, saying, you know, any decent person should get out of the world and I'm leaving.
Zosima has an opposite view.
He gets out of the world and feels very guilty for doing it and guilty for all the evil in the world, but he doesn't do anything about it.
That's what you all see, is that can't be the right attitude.
He assumes responsibility for all the evil in the world, but and he wants, he feels that he's, he doesn't ask how he can forgive all the bad people.
He asks, who could forgive all those bad people, Yvonne asks at one point.
He asks everybody to forgive him.
But it's all in this everybody stuff.
It's not neighbors.
It's not the actual people who have actual problems.
He does sort of treat people who come to the monastery like a kind of therapist.
He does something.
But he certainly doesn't deal with or have any sort of sensible relation to all the suffering in the world.
Just to say that he feels guilty of it, he wants the whole world to forgive him, just isn't going to get anywhere.
So let me see now.
So on 261, I say that he's got just the opposite of Yvonne's view.
Let's see what his view is on 261.
Ah, yeah, oh, yeah.
On 261, he says, when talking about Dimitri, Am I my brother's keeper?
Yvonne asks irritably.
Well, you see, in a way, Zosima thinks that he's everybody's keeper.
Everybody's his brother.
And that's just unrealistic and has no, isn't a way you can sensibly live.
And it turns out that, of course, Yvonne says, just what you expect him to say, that he's nobody's keeper.
He doesn't feel responsible for anything.
He's going to leave.
He's not involved.
And the funny thing is, you begin to see Smerzhyakov as a copy of Yvonne on 255 when talking about Dmitri about two-thirds down, Smerdhyakov says, how should I know about Dmitry?
I'm not his keeper, answered Smerdyakov, so forth.
So again, Smerzhikov is copying Yvonne, and they're taking this, we're not responsible for any of the evil in the world story.
And Zosima is taking the opposite view.
I'm responsible, me, Zosima, for all the evil in the world.
And I think the answer is supposed to be that Zosima's wrong view comes from stepping out of the world.
It's not the suicide kind of giving up, but he sort of gives back his ticket when he goes into the monastery.
And so that he isn't in any particular situation.
It's not a case of philosophical detachment like Yvonne.
It's sort of monastery detachment.
But they both detach themselves from the everyday, evolved, real world.
And that's, and then either they take total responsibility or no responsibility.
And either view is untenable.
So philosophy, for monks turn out to be almost as bad as philosophers.
I say almost because Zosima does treat people who come to the monastery for help, but that's he's got a tiny bit of involvement.
Yeah.
The problem would be why Sosima enters the monastery?
He does it because he realizes that he's still.
Well, the trouble is he's happy to believe that he's guilty about everything.
His mistake is, okay, he enters the monastery because he realizes he's guilty.
I see what you mean.
Yvonne does.
But the trouble is, his way of realizing that he's guilty is so general that it's hardly like, you know, he's not, it's like loving your neighbor, but no particular person.
He feels guilty about all the evil, but no particular evil.
And that's, in the real world, there are really people who are evil, and they are really involved, and they have to realize it and do something about it.
And Zosima, of course, has an evil past or a bad past.
But I'm going to talk about that right now.
But the crucial thing is, if you ask me, how do I know that Dostoevsky thinks that it's because Zosima is in the monastery, that he's withdrawn from the world, that that's why he has this wrong, weird, useless view about being guilty of all evils.
If you take him literally, it's just crazy that he's personally responsible for every bad thing that happens, and he has to be forgiven for it.
I mean, to say one thing, the evidence that this is a wrong way of life that comes from being in the monastery comes early on, on 84.
I can't believe it.
No, let's look and see why I said 84.
Yeah, it's that early.
So you all know.
What does Osama say to Alyasha about the monastery?
He has to leave.
That's what it says at the bottom of the middle of 84.
When it's God's will to call me, leave the monastery, go away for good.
See, the monastery is not a place he could even come back to in his old age.
It's just wrong.
So Alyasha started.
What is it?
This is not the place, your place for the time.
I bless you for great service in the world.
You will have to bear all.
Christ be with you.
What that means, we don't know yet, but Christ has to be existentialized, and he is.
Was he on my list?
I think it was.
Yeah, the incarnation is on the list.
There is somebody in the book who is Christ in an existentialized form.
You have to figure out where that is.
So he says, Christ be with you.
Don't abandon him, and he will not abandon you.
You will see great sorrow, and in that sorrow you will be happy.
Remember my words.
Okay, now, yes.
Interesting.
And I suppose, but I'm going to take up a different part of what you said.
Because the next thing that comes up is that Christ is the one who should take on all the sorrows of the world.
Let's go there.
That's exactly where we're supposed to be.
You're amazingly tuned in.
So Alyasha makes the move that he shouldn't make.
He's now been so upset and confused by Yvonne that he asks whether somebody shouldn't, so to speak, take on the guilt and be able to give forgiveness.
But it can't be the people in the monastery.
And we can add that it would be blasphemous.
He doesn't say that here.
He's just asking, who has the right to forgive, who has suffered for all of this, and doesn't blame anybody.
And Yvonne asks, is there anyone who has the right to forgive everybody?
And Alyasha makes the mistake of saying, yes, of course there is.
It's Jesus.
Because Dostoevsky, believe it or not, doesn't like that doctrine.
The doctrine that Jesus can take on all the sins and forgive them.
Of course, you can see why.
He would say, well, those babies are still suffering.
It's all very well for Jesus to be guiltless and suffer on the cross.
And he may take on the guilt of original sin, but he certainly doesn't solve the problem of the children.
So this is happening on 278.
Dostoevsky's got his own views about how to take on suffering.
And you get them much later in the book, and they get existentialized.
But it isn't the Jesus figure who takes on the suffering.
He's got them separated.
But I can't talk about that yet.
But I can talk about 278.
Let's read it.
About rebellion and so forth.
And here, this is where Alyasha sort of panics and says, well, remember, Yvonne says, can you accept the idea of living in a world with the unatoned blood of a little victim and accepting it would remain happy for you?
And you could accept it and remain happy?
No, I can't admit it, said Alyasha suddenly with flashing eyes.
But Yvonne, you asked just now, is there a person in the world who has the right to forgive and can forgive?
But there is a being, and he can forgive everything, all and for all, because he gave his innocent blood for all and everything.
See, that's right where he is.
You have forgotten him, and on him is built the edifice.
And it is to him that they cry aloud.
Thou art just, O Lord, and thy ways are revealed.
And now Yvonne has sort of set a trap for Alyasha because he says, Ah, the one without sin and his blood.
No, I've not forgotten him.
On the contrary, I've been wondering how you didn't bring him up before.
For usually, all arguments on your side put him in the foreground.
You know, Alyasha, don't laugh.
I wrote a poem about a year ago.
If you can waste another 10 minutes, I'll tell it to you.
Well, that poem, which isn't a poem in rhyme, it's a kind of philosophical treatise.
Well, I don't know what it is.
It's the Grand Inquisitor story, anyway.
That's what he's talking about.
And it's funny, I never noticed it before.
Give me 10 minutes.
The Grand Inquisitor story takes hours, and it's very complicated.
But the way Dostoevsky segues to it is by way of the question of Jesus as the completely innocent Savior.
Dostoevsky doesn't believe in innocent Saviors.
I will have to say more about that next time.
But I've got a little bit of this time.
So, anybody want to say anything more?
The Grand Inquisitor story is, I don't know how many have had the Grand Inquisitor story in school somewhere.
Sometimes people used to read it out of context.
You just outside of the book.
When you read it outside of the book, did it come out in the class that it was for Jesus or for the Grand Inquisitor or against both of them?
You don't remember.
Well, most people, when they used to read it, when you read it all in isolation, it looks like, maybe, if you're not careful, that it's on the side of Jesus, not the Grand Inquisitor.
But if Yvonne is telling it, and then you know the context of it, and you know that he's going to, he's written this somehow to attack the perfect, the view of Jesus as perfect and as able to forgive everybody.
So we have to see how that works.
But in the meantime, I can prepare you for it because I don't want to waste a minute because we're running out of time all the time.
So let's see.
Okay, let me give you the background quick.
So you should, you can, before you get into the Grand Inquisitor story, you've got to know the structure of it.
The structure of it is what philosophers call an antinome.
I'll write that on the board next time.
Antinome is when there are two positions, each of them wrong, and each of them sees how wrong the other one is and uses that as evidence that they're right.
So that I'll give you an example, all this to get it out of the way, sort of, so we can plunge right in.
And antinomy, Kant has these antinomies.
So I have to write antinomy on the board if I'm going to keep saying this new mysterious word.
Where is it?
Oh, yeah, A-N-T-I.
I mean, the word never appears.
It's a word Kant uses, but it's the structure of an antinome.
And the structure, let me give you a Kant antinomy first.
Suppose the antinomy is, is this time eternal, or is there a moment when time begins?
And you say, well, let's say the time is eternal.
Yeah, but how could that be?
Eternal sort of isn't an amount of time.
So, or let's try a different one.
Are things infinitely divisible into tinier and tinier, or are there atoms?
And if you say, well, they're infinitely divisible, well, then you would get to something infinitely small.
But how can you get to something infinitely small?
There is no, infinity isn't a size.
So maybe there must be atoms.
Yeah, but then if there are atoms, you could always chop them up more.
So how could there be atoms?
So you go back and forth.
And now let's try it with time.
So if time has a beginning, that doesn't feel right.
What would be there before?
And how could it start?
Well, then maybe time goes on eternally, forever.
But this sort of forever isn't an amount.
So let me sum up.
If you don't like my examples, forget them.
Because the point is, you'll see in the Grand Inquisitor two views, each of them wrong.
Each of them arguing for their truth by showing how wrong the other is.
And the only way to get out of an antinome is to prove that there's a third possibility.
So Pont says the whole world is only a matter of appearances.
If you think that space and time are real, you get into these puzzles.
But if you think that they're all appearances, then you don't.
So I won't tell you yet.
I'll tell you next time what the third position is.
But let's at least one more minute settle what are the two positions.
You recognize the Grand Inquisitor is, of course, the Roman Catholic Church, but in an extreme kind of caricature.
What could be the other position?
Not the one that solves, not the third one, but the second position.
What is Jesus' view?
Well, if you look at it, you discover that the Grand Inquisitor begins after there, just in 1500, around in the 1500s, where there has been, where's my, well, help me find the Grand Inquisitor quick, in a hurry, so I can read you the first few sentences.
79.
279?
Okay, 279.
So it starts out in the 16th century, in the 1500s, that is.
In North Germany, there's been a terrible heresy.
That's a bottom 280.
What is this heresy that takes place in North Germany at the end of the 1500s?
Protestantism, exactly, the Reformation.
So Jesus is the Protestant, and it's like Kierkegaard.
It's extremely like Kierkegaard.
Dostoevsky is such a genius.
I'll read you passages from Kierkegaard that Jostovsky invented Kierkegaard.
And so it's the Catholic, Greek-influenced church against sort of the super-existentialist Protestant view.
And then you have to figure out what is the third view, because those two views are each so extreme that they shoot each other down.
But anyway, we will do all that in detail.
And you read the Grand Inquisitor over the weekend.