The subject for today is the existentializing, that is, finding that in our human experience, that is what is grasped in the early church and in a kind of magical way as crucifixion and resurrection.
Those are big deal Christian symbols or whatever you want to call them, and they've certainly got to be explained.
I think Dostoevsky's very good in general, on this very good period, in describing two kinds of crucifixion and resurrection.
You'll see, one of them is Dimitri and one of them is Yvonne, and he tells you so in his usual.
Uh-oh, I haven't turned this on.
Oh, I wouldn't be here.
So he wouldn't be hearing it if you hadn't.
Good point.
Okay, so we do the crucifixion.
He does really good contrast of two kinds of crucifixion: one kind that leads to a new life and resurrection, and one kind that leads to just plain madness and death.
What I don't think he does so well, and therefore I'm going to sort of condense it a lot, is explain why it's necessary for somebody to suffer for everybody, which is part of the Christian idea of the crucifixion of Jesus to somehow do something to make up for everybody's suffering.
I think that's a hopeless task to try to find an existential meaning for that.
But Dostoevsky bravely takes it on, and Dmitry supposedly sees it.
I'll mention it as we go, but if you haven't really been convinced or even understood what Dmitry is up to, don't worry about it.
So here we go.
So there is a kind of suffering with joy and a kind of suffering which is self-torture or self-torment.
That's a good translation, I'm told, by my Russian consultants.
Our translation, and almost all the translations, have other terms.
One of them is strains.
That doesn't sound right.
Another one is lacerations.
That sounds a little better.
We've got lacerations in the drawing room chapter, for instance.
But neither one of them seemed to me to convey very well that when somebody is suffering this something or other, it's because they are wallowing in their suffering and exaggerating their suffering and taking pride in their suffering.
And that's, so I may call it torment instead of lacerations, as I talk, if I think about it, because I think that helps convey what's going on.
Now, another thing is important just to tell you, one of the interesting things that Dostoevsky does in many places, and I haven't really followed them out, I think they make possible paper topics too, is that Dostoevsky takes objections that people have to Christianity and doesn't say they're wrong, says there is such a bad kind of strain in Christianity, all right, but it's a mistaken way of Christianity's own self-understanding, and there's another right understanding.
One quick way to tell you about that, I didn't write it in my notes, but you can, the contrast between Father Ferrapont and Zosima would do.
I mean, you can go along and say Christianity is full of a kind of asceticism that denies the body and hates the body and hates the sensual and hates the world and so forth.
And Dostoevsky is not going to say there isn't any such kind of Christianity.
He says, yes, there is.
Here's an example.
It's quite repulsive and mad, but there's another kind of Christianity totally opposed to that and different.
And that's Zosima look at that.
That brings joy.
So if Nietzsche says, as he does, about Christianity that it's sick and masochistic, you'll see such quotes.
Nietzsche is not exactly wrong.
If you go to the big art galleries in Europe where you see lots of medieval paintings, you see lots of paintings of saints cut in half and burnt and full of arrows like porcupines and bleeding all over.
And that's a sick side of Christianity, the suffering of the martyrs, as if that was the most important message.
And so Dostoevsky doesn't deny the Nietzschean claim.
He just wants to say that's fine, but that's not what we're talking about.
We're talking about a kind of suffering which leads, which is which is life-affirming and leads to joyful life and connectedness.
The kind of the suffering that the bad kind leads to isolation and death.
So that now we're going to just follow that kind, the various kinds of suffering for the rest of the lecture today and see how each of them works out in the in Dostoevsky's existentialized version.
Oh, I forgot to pass down out, Beatrice.
We need to sign people up.
It's having an effect.
I am happy to see people I've never seen before in my life in the audience.
So you're all supposed to sign up because if you don't, we'll hold it against you if you're on a borderline, and if you do, it'll count for you.
This is my own, I think this is unfortunate, but it's my only way to make sure that I've got enough people to talk to that I can learn something and you can learn something.
Yeah.
Okay.
How many people didn't get who were here last time didn't get a chance to sign it?
Well, sign it and put and put parentheses last time also if you want to.
That's next time I'll pass around two of them.
But I think it almost worked.
No, you're the only one who said anyway that they didn't get it.
Okay, here we go now.
So just to keep your eyes on it, so there's the kind of crucifixion.
Being nailed to the cross, crucifixion is the way Jesus suffered.
So the kind of saving suffering that Jesus represents is always referred to as the cross in here.
Crucifixion literally means the nailed to a cross.
How many have seen the Passion movie?
It was just hottest thing when I taught this last time.
Well, it's still around, sort of.
You can always get the DVD if you want to see the the sick side of Christianity, the goriness of the suffering, as if that was the point.
I haven't seen them.
I'm protesting against the movie because I I think Dostoevsky would.
But if you want to see the suffering as the main point of the crucifixion with just a hint of resurrection at the end, then this is the movie to see.
I gather, reading about it and talking about it.
Since I haven't seen it, I'm not exactly an authority on it.
Okay, so let's see.
So we've got crucifixion, which is a redeeming kind of suffering and leads to resurrection.
That means Jesus doesn't die, but he goes to heaven, he arises from the cross, is resurrected, that means lifted up after he's crucified.
I tell you all this for some Christians, this will seem absolutely obvious and boring, but to other people I gather talking to people in office hours and so forth.
If it isn't your tradition, all this needs to be explained, and I'm trying to explain it.
So there is the kind of redeeming suffering which leads to the resurrection of being reborn, being in the language of the book, becoming a new man, becoming transformed.
That's what happens to Dmitry and leads to a joyful new life.
It happens to Dmitry, and of course, therefore, in a minimal, in a quick way, it also happens to Grushenka, as you'll see.
Now, there is a kind of suffering, that's masochistic and self-tormenting.
It also calls itself being crucified.
Ivan is talking about being crucified a lot.
And it leads to dying, and instead of, and rather than being reborn and resurrected, it always leads to spiritual death, and sometimes it leads to physical death.
Zosima, already way back on page 50, distinguishes the two kinds.
Here they are on page 50.
He's talking about peasant kind of suffering.
And he says at the bottom paragraph, there's a silent and long-suffering sorrow to be met with among the peasantry.
It withdraws into itself and is still.
But there is a grief that breaks out from the minute it bursts into tears and finds vent in wailing.
And from, yeah, this is particularly common among the women and so forth.
And in this kind of lamentation at the bottom is a laceration of the heart.
That's again the tormenting.
Such grief does not desire consolation.
This is a kind of grief that is sort of wallowing in its grief, feeling bad, feeling that there's such an outrage that they want to constantly cry out against it.
It feeds its bottom of 50 on the sense of its hopelessness.
Lamentations spring from the constant craving to reopen the wound.
See, that's why they say lacerations.
There is a wound.
So one of them is the grief, you get rid of the, you finally get out of the grief, but in the other one, you just stay in the grief.
So one of them leads only to more suffering, and the other leads to joy.
That's on 52, at the end of the top paragraph.
What he says to the mother of the child who dies, Know that your little one is surely before the throne of God, is rejoicing and happy and praying to God for you, and weep not, but rejoice.
Notice that Zosima is perfectly happy to talk in the totally magical or symbolic or whatever terms of institutional Christianity.
But Alyasha, when he's asked about the afterlife way at the end of the book, won't say anything like that.
You'll see when we get there, he says, it's come along, it's time to eat pancakes.
But he's not going to promise things and describe things that go beyond the existential experiences that people actually have.
So at the bottom of 52, Zosima says to the woman, Consolation is not what you need.
Weep and be not consoled, but weep.
Only every time that you weep, be sure to remember your little son is one of the angels of God, and he looks down on you and sees your rejoice and rejoices at your tears.
And then, now comes the, this is the opposite of wallowing in your suffering.
And he says, a long time while yet you will keep that great mother's grief, but it will turn, and now comes into something like joy.
But it will turn in the end into quiet joy, and your bitter tears will be only tears of sorrow.
The bitter tears are the self-torturing period, tears, will be only tears of sorrow that purify the heart and deliver it from sin.
Whereas the other one is sort of protesting against death and the world and suffering, and it doesn't get purified.
And that's okay, so there it is already in the Zosima, but it gets spelled out a lot more later.
I wasn't going to read it, and I don't have it even, but I could say it sort of the epigraph from the book that I passed out to you.
You, none of you have it, I imagine, with you.
Some of you have other translations, though.
And you have the epigraph, don't you?
Yeah, will you read it?
I mean, because the epigraph from the whole book really says what I just said, but I realized just now that you don't have it.
Let's hear it.
You got it?
It's only one sentence, isn't it, from the Gospel of John?
No, not the whole introduction.
The Gospel of John says, well, if a grain of wheat falls on the ground, let me try it.
If a grain of wheat falls on the ground, it abideth alone.
But if something, what, if it, but if it dies?
If it dies, yeah, if it dies, it brings forth much fruit.
So that means there's a way of suffering and falling on the ground and dying to what?
Well, in the jargon of Christianity, the old Adam in you, the selfish, isolated what everybody is.
If you die to that, namely get rid of that, then you'll become a giving, joyful person.
That epigraph is exactly about this issue.
I don't know why Dostoevsky thinks that that issue, of all the many issues of the Incarnation and of Confession, and you'll see later, of eternity and so forth, why that issue is the one that gets an epigraph.
But the fact that it does is something to think about.
Maybe if you understand it, you write a paper about it and tell me about it.
So now we go on, and there is Dmitry the one who's going to be the one who falls on the ground and dies and suffers, that does it the right way, and is resurrected into a new being and to a joyful life.
And it starts already, of course, still with Zosima, who, as you remember, maybe it seems like years ago, bows down to Dmitry and explains later why he did it.
He bows down on 81, where at the bottom, Zosima rose from his seat and moved toward Dmitry and sank on his knees before him and deliberately bowed down at Dmitri's feet till his forehead touched the floor.
And why did he do that?
Well, we're told way back on 323, Dostoevsky expects you to have an amazing memory of what's going on.
He says to somebody, I don't, to Alyasha, in the middle of the page, I bowed down yesterday to the great suffering in store for him.
But not just the suffering, presumably, but the suffering and how he handles it, which is what's important, because there's great suffering in store for Ivan, too.
But it's the way Dmitry suffers that's important.
Grushenka understands that.
Again, you have to sort of keep so many things in mind.
Way on 590, when Dmitry sort of says that he's going to suffer the right way, because he feels guilt, whether or not he killed old Karamatsov, we're not going to tell you yet.
Dostoevsky doesn't tell you.
Whether or not he did, he certainly desired to.
And that's enough, remember, in the whole Christian way of thinking.
You are guilty for your desires, not just for what you do.
So Dmitry assumes the guilt of the death of Karamatsov.
He keeps saying he didn't do it.
Well, that's for you to wait and see.
But he certainly feels that he was ready to suffer for it.
He says two-thirds of the way down.
I accept the torture of accusation and my public shame.
I want to suffer, for by suffering I shall be purified.
Perhaps I shall be purified, gentlemen.
And listen for the last time.
I'm not guilty for my father's blood.
I accept my punishment not because I killed him, but because I meant to kill him.
But so Dmitri, I didn't do what I was going to do.
I mean, that's what he says on the next page.
Grushenka sort of repeats the Zotsoma gesture.
Whenever Dmitri is about to suffer the right way, somebody needs to confirm it.
So two-thirds of the way down, Grushenka made a deep bow to Dmitry.
And that's enough to confirm what he's doing.
And she, too, and this is interesting and important, has amazing, I haven't written down the page number.
I can't believe it.
It's true.
I wonder where it is.
And she becomes a new woman in the same way that he has become a new man.
Maybe, have you no idea.
That's really annoying.
I doubt if any of you are so versed in this that you could find it.
There's a place where we're told that Grushenka has been sick for a while and almost died of sickness, and now she's recovered.
What?
650.
That sounds like about the right place.
How do you do that?
You'd win an award if you did it.
Let's see.
Yes.
Terrific.
Thank you, Beatrice.
That's wonderful.
I would have felt really unhappy if I didn't have that.
Okay, so now Grushenka, as, of course, existential double, must also go through suffering and be purified.
And she does it in one paragraph, whereas Dmitry goes on doing it for chapters after chapter.
So now we skip from where she bows to him to 650, the second paragraph.
Three days after Dmitry's arrest, Grushenka was taken very ill and was ill for nearly five weeks.
She was unconscious and so forth.
Now, that's her kind of suffering.
She's sick, physically sick, but that's always in Dostoevsky, not the point.
The point is what that sickness means.
What that sickness means to us and Dostoevsky and to her is that she's going through some terrible suffering.
That's what's happening to her and what's happening to Dmitry, but she's going through it somehow in the right way.
She was very much changed, thinner and a little sallow, and so forth.
But to Alyasha, her face was even more attractive than before, and he liked to meet her eyes when he visited her.
Why is that important?
Why does Dostoevsky throw that in?
Just to see if you're all with it.
You should all know by now.
Yeah.
That's right.
He was afraid to look at her and look down because he was so attracted by her.
But now he's got this agape love, which protects him completely from the Eros kind of uh desire he had for her, and therefore he can look at her and does.
And now what about her?
Well, she's an example, as I say in one paragraph, of what suffering can do for you.
A look of firmness and purpose had developed in her face.
There were signs of a spiritual transformation in her.
Well, as you can always be count on Dostoevsky to tell you what's going on, and you just have to keep your eyes open.
Okay, we're getting an example of that, spiritual transformation from suffering.
A steady, steadfast, fine, and humble determination.
There was a small vertical line between her brows, which gave her charming face, a look of concentrated thought.
There was scarcely a trace of her former frivolity.
She's not going to sort of play men off against each other and try to seduce Alyasha by jumping on his lap and so forth.
The new Grushenka doesn't do things like that.
The new Grushenka is full of love, but she's full of agape love.
Right now, it's all turned on Dimitri.
So now we're ready to go on and discuss Dimitri as crucified and resurrected.
Yeah, Beatrice.
They're transformed, but still they are very much in touch with Petita.
They quarrel, they're jealous, tried out to be a little bit of a powerful.
Yeah, it's true.
It takes a while to be transformed.
I think Dostoevsky's just being realistic and not sort of Pollyanna-ish.
I mean, you get being reborn, I think, is like falling in love.
It can happen instantly, and it does sometimes, and then people write songs and operas about it and so forth.
And sometimes it takes a long time.
And you just get more and more into the being, the unconditional commitment.
Remember, I said that about Kierkegaard, the instant, which isn't really an instant.
It's that period in which you get transformed and you become another.
And it's a good point, Beatrice, and it doesn't happen instantly with Grushenka.
It does, I think, with Dmitry.
He stops being a living contradiction and becomes a savior of all of humanity.
It's a little hard to understand why he thinks all of humanity needs saving and why he thinks he can save it.
That's Dostoevsky trying hard to existentialize what Jesus was doing.
In Dmitry, I don't understand it, but he'll tell you again and again that's what he's doing.
You'll see.
I mean, there's no doubt that Dmitry is the, there are two Jesus figures.
Dostoevsky has taken two very important Christian ideas apart.
One of them is the incarnation, that the whole meaning of the world as connected love gets embodied in, sort of breaks into the life of a human being, and that human being becomes the bearer of the news of the transformation of the world through love to everybody.
That's Markle.
It's Markle, it's the love channel through Markle, that's on the back of your chart, that is saving everyone in the book, because Markle is the Jesus figure as incarnation of God becoming flesh.
But then there's the God that gets crucified, that suffers for everyone.
That's Jesus too in going through being crucified.
And that's the role that Dimitri plays.
That's why they all bow to him.
That's why he's the paradigm case of suffering.
Only I don't understand how he thinks his suffering is going to help the starving children and so forth, the people, all those unhappy human beings he dreams about.
And he's ready.
He says he's going to go and suffer for everyone.
I think it's a wonderful topic if you don't just repeat Dostoevsky or just repeat traditional Christianity.
If you existentialize how it needs to be that somebody suffers for everyone, how you go about suffering for everyone, and how suffering for everyone somehow fixes things that were bad before.
If you could explain that to me, that would be an A, and I would thank you every time I give the course.
I should thank a student already named Pamela Minkler, who 20 years ago or so told me what I'm telling you in the following.
I had no idea that suffering and crucifixion was part of the book.
I don't know how I could have missed it.
Now that I point it out to you, Dostoevsky is just hitting you over the head again and again, but I didn't notice.
And she said, there's this whole aspect of the book, the meaning of suffering, the right way to suffer, the wrong way to suffer, and you're just missing it.
And she's right.
And so I dedicate this lecture to her.
Now I'll dedicate one to whoever could tell me what, now that I've now that she's explained, that that's what's going on, I still don't understand what it means.
That is what the existential activity is, the way.
The way I can understand Markle, I mean, what he's doing and how he's channeling this love and how that love could save everybody in the world eventually, though it starts just in his living room.
That makes sense.
I mean, I don't know whether I think it's going to happen or whether it's even plausible, but I can understand it.
Okay, I wasn't going to go off on this sort of tangent, but it always bothers me that there is an aspect of the book that I can't understand because Dostoevsky gets everything so clear and so right.
Anyway, so let's go on.
Maybe something will just turn up, or maybe one of you will raise your hand like Pamela did once and fix it.
Okay, let's see.
So now we're going to do Dimitri as the crucified one, namely Jesus or the Dimitri, I think you understand, is to Jesus as Markle is to Jesus.
They're the existential meaning of these important symbols.
Okay, so he's going to turn suffering into joy.
He's going to become a new man.
And Dostoevsky's going to just tell you, clear as day, that that's what he's existentializing.
And Dimitri thinks that going to prison in Siberia is a kind of crucifixion and will lead to a kind of re of resurrection.
And I I'm not going to go into the detailed quotes.
They are you can look at them yourself.
They are scattered around.
I mean, I would look at them.
I haven't written them down because I decided I wasn't going to look at them.
Now I raise you.
Beatrice, where's the place where Dimitri is telling us that he's going to go to Siberia because he's crucified, in effect?
And he keeps using that language.
And there's going to be a hymn arising when he does, a hymn of joy from underground in Siberia.
It's probably somewhere in the Dimitri section, one would think.
If anybody has it, would yes, it goes with the dream about the babe.
Where's that?
Somebody, somebody else to what?
587.
Let's try it.
No, but it's close.
Yes, yes.
Back to 590, though.
That's probably it's right in there somewhere.
657.
Yeah, that didn't quite do it.
Let's try that.
He's going to go to Siberia.
But, yeah, but I mean, that's not the middle of the page, 657, okay.
He suddenly began talking of the babe.
Yeah, that's the hungry child he dreams about.
And he's going to go to Siberia and so forth.
And he's crying and so forth.
That's not the one I had in mind, but that's the right one.
But he spells it out more.
He's going to be in Siberia with those prisoners, and we're all going to begin a hymn of praise and joy in our suffering because we take our suffering the right way.
Now that I've started on this, I have to find it.
I wasn't going to talk about it.
What?
Somebody yell if you find it.
Sooner or later, we'll find it, even if we have to read the whole book to do it.
Oh, let's hope, because I'm getting unhappy that I can't find it.
684, middle of the page.
Yes, that's good.
You got it.
Who gave me this?
Ah, thanks.
Okay, let's look at it.
On 684, he says, Alyasha, these last two months I found in myself a new man.
A new man has arisen in me.
Christ arises from the cross.
That's the phrase.
That's the clue, one of the clues.
And then he says, I go for all.
This is the part I don't understand, two-thirds of the way down.
I go for all because someone must go for all.
I didn't kill Father, but I've got to go.
Never mind that.
I can understand that because he feels guilty for his desires.
Oh, yes, we'll be in chains and there'll be no freedom, but he'll have joy and at the bottom, and we men underground will sing from the bowels of the earth a hymn to God with whom is joy, hail to God and his joy, and so forth.
Okay, yes, that's what I wasn't going to read, but it's the right thing to read because that's the becoming a new man and being arising.
Jesus is buried because he dies on the cross, and then he is resurrected.
That means he arises afterward, and that's the symbol that Dostoevsky is trying to explain here.
I can understand that there could be a kind of suffering, and that that suffering can be purifying, and that it can lead to joy.
That's not the problem.
The problem is how one person can do it for everybody.
See, again, think about it.
Marco can do it for everybody, because agape love is contagious, and it gets passed on by laying on of hands from person to person, and then at the very end of the book, you'll see before next time it gets passed on to the boys by Alyasha.
But how how can this kind of suffering be contagious so that somehow Dimitri can I just there's just no way to understand.
I can't.
There's some piece I must be missing.
Anyway, back to this.
I've got to stop obsessing about that.
So he regards his imprisonment in Siberia as a crucifixion and a resurrection.
That's what we've just discovered.
And now the question is, can he hold on to that realization that there is a way of suffering that will bring joy to him and somehow to everybody?
I'll make this much generalization.
There's a kind of suffering that will bring joy to him, and he is a kind of paradigm example of it.
And anybody who could see it in him can copy it in him.
That may be the answer.
Yeah, that's a kind, not a very exciting answer, but I think the picture is supposed to be he suffers, he does it the right way, he loves God in his suffering, he experiences joy, he starts this hymn, so all the other prisoners see it.
That's understandable, and they become joyful instead of grumpy, and grumpy is an understatement, you know, vicious and angry and full of hate for being stuck in Siberia.
They get spiritually transformed, and then you have to make a little leap, but it's not absolutely unintelligible.
Other people imitate them, and other people imitate those people, and that's sort of a chain of suffering the right way, like the onion chain, only it's a little less convincing than passing on agape love, but you couldn't at least pass on an image of the right way to suffer.
And that's what the crucifixion has to be: that Jesus on the cross going through terrible suffering is not, it's interesting.
Dostoevsky has one reading of the Bible, but you had there are two on the cross.
Oh, that is fantastic.
What Dostoevsky does, it's a fact that in the Bible, three books of the Bible, Mark, Luke, and Matthew, have Jesus despairing on the cross and saying, God, why hast thou forsaken me?
And one, John, which is Dostoevsky's favorite, has Jesus affirming on the cross that he's done his job and he's not, he doesn't feel that he's been deserted by God.
He just says it is finished.
Well, but what happens is, I mean, I don't even know if Dostoevsky knows he's doing this, but what you get is both of those endings.
One of them is Yvonne, the one that suffers on the cross and despairs and dies in misery, almost.
I mean, Yvonne, we don't really, we're told that Yvonne looks like he's going to die.
We are never told that he dies.
But he's off to be, he looks like he's about to die.
What's the despairing result of being crucified, that is, of suffering, when you don't, and not accepting it, just as he doesn't accept it in the rebellion chapter.
And then we get another crucifixion where the person does accept it and is transformed spiritually by it and becomes an example for everybody in the world who can be transformed by suffering.
That's the ending of the Gospel of John crucifixion, and that's the one that Demetrius lived on.
That is interesting.
That's terrific.
I don't know if Dostoevsky knows or not that he's doing it, but I'll show you a place where he certainly knows that Yvonne is the one who is despairing on the cross.
We haven't got there yet.
Yeah.
Suffering supposed to be formed.
Yeah, yeah, I left that out because that is really incomprehensible.
That's what kept me from understanding anything.
Because that picture, the picture of what's called vicarious suffering, that Jesus is suffering, can somehow suffer for other people's suffering and make up for it somehow.
I didn't talk about it because I don't think that I understood because I don't understand it.
But the way that Dostoevsky talks about it, thanks to whoever found the page, that page where it looks like one must suffer for all, he takes that Christian view that somebody can suffer, just somebody can suffer, I'll go next, somebody can suffer for everybody and turns it from there's a debt to be paid for Adam's fall.
This is the Christian view, and somehow somebody's got to be punished, and Jesus takes on the punishment and suffering for all of humanity.
That's the official Christian view.
Dostoevsky can't understand that, doesn't even buy that.
But he has to buy something else that does the same job existentially.
That's too much bookkeeping in heaven for Dostoevsky.
And when he does, then we get the thing I just said.
There is somebody in the book who suffers exactly the right way, and everybody sees that and appreciates it.
Zostamus dies bows because he knows what's going to happen.
Grushenka bows because she sees it happening.
We all get to see it happening too as he goes off becoming a happy, spiritually transformed new man.
Now, Chuck.
Becomplete people.
Do you think he's about very good?
Yeah, that's okay.
The ones he suffers an example, you mean they can see it and they can do it.
That's what I meant by this kind of contagion of exemplar.
Yeah, but that's not what he's talking about.
That doesn't get the faith.
It isn't as if Demetrius takes on the suffering for all of humanity and pays some kind of debt that all of humanity owes for having fallen.
Dostoevsky just thinks that's too magical for him to handle.
You want to say something?
Okay, let her start.
Yeah.
I think another example of that is, you know, bringing his cold down his food.
Well, wait, let's wait till next time.
But I already say this to you.
Think about it.
I don't think Alyosha takes on the suffering.
I don't think he has to suffer.
What?
Ilusha.
Ilusha takes on the suffering.
Ilusha suffers and is transformed.
But keep your eyes open when you read the end of the book.
I'd have to go back and look.
You keep your eyes open.
Is Ilusha suffering does that transform Ilusha?
My hunch is no.
He's an innocent sufferer, and he's and he doesn't show how you can be.
I don't think he's spiritually transformed.
I think he just suffers without getting angry at God or anybody, and he dies contented, and that's it.
I mean, the question is: how much of the suffering showing that if you suffer, you get spiritually transformed and get a new kind of joy happens in the life of Ilusha?
I just don't remember.
Something transforms everything around him.
I think their love of Ilusha transforms everyone around him.
I don't think that he transforms them.
So keep your eye open.
You want to say something first, and then, yeah.
It could have been that book.
You can write that book.
I don't think that's in here.
Dimitri has gotten over the dark side already when he turns his lust for Grushenka into love of Grushenka.
And I don't know where.
And he gets this agape love.
Where does he get it from?
Because he has it before he goes, before the trial, even.
The muckro sort of orgy seal, whatever, that big party, happens before the trial, right?
And so, and he's already got it, the love of Grushenka.
And they both have turned, accepted the bad side, remember?
She says we're good and bad, good and bad.
But that's not the issue about Siberia.
The issue about Siberia is that bad things happen to people.
People they love die, and they have to go to, and people go to prison, innocent, and so forth.
How do you deal with that kind of suffering, I think?
And Dimitri deals with that kind of suffering by accepting it as an appropriate punishment for his desire to kill his father, and that's okay.
And then he goes ahead and accepts it as somehow somebody has to go for all, and my suffering is somehow going to be sort of the model for all suffering.
That's getting to be a little strange.
And then that is going to somehow make it possible for everybody to suffer the right way, because they have an example.
That's, I think, what's going on.
I'm not going to tell you more, but I think it's great to have this conversation because when you read it, you can try to see for yourselves what's going on there.
And if you figure it out more than I've just, if you only figure out what I just said, don't write a paper because you are, one, it isn't all that smart.
And two, I already said it.
But if you can really make more sense of it, then you should definitely, definitely write it up.
I saw another hand.
Yeah.
Because we were showing throwing stones and yes.
But I, you know, here, good that you said that.
She says, couldn't Alicia have been transformed because he's throwing stones and now he's being loving with everybody?
Absolutely.
But now the question is, what transformed him?
And I want to say not his suffering, his TB, or I think is what he's dying of, but that Alyasha loved him and affirmed him in spite of the fact that he bit Alyasha's finger to the bone and gave an example to all the boys that no matter how sort of resentful and unpleasant Alicia had become, that you could affirm him anyway, and then he became nicer, and they became nicer.
I think that's supposed to be the story.
So it's the agape love chain, the onion chain.
Alicia, is Alicia in my chart of the onion chain?
He should be.
Yeah?
Okay.
Okay, yeah.
So maybe this is his chance.
Who?
Alicia?
Dimitri.
Dimitri?
A way of saying this is something that I should do.
Well, fine.
And if he just stopped with that, that would be fine.
Here's what I can do to make up for my past bad things with what's her name, the girl, Dimitri Yvonne's girlfriend?
Katerina.
Okay, anyway, the bad way I treated her and the bad way I treated other women and my bad desire to kill my father.
I'm going to accept all this suffering as appropriate punishment to expiate all that.
Yes, he does that.
And maybe that's a model, I keep wanting to say.
But it's only this extreme Christian view.
Once he does it, nobody else has to suffer because Jesus did it for everybody.
There's some sense in which Dimitri doesn't do it for everybody.
They've all got to suffer their own suffering.
That's what I'm...
But he does show them the way to do it.
That's what you're saying, I think.
You don't look happy with my words in your mouth.
Okay, then let me go on.
By the way, I suddenly realized this is an immensely important moment.
This is an illustration.
I'm thinking, why are we having this interesting discussion today?
And why are we learning things as I talk?
That's because there's about 30% more students in front of me than there are contributing to the discussion than before.
And that's because I stopped letting people just go off and listen to podcasts.
I feel that I've been vindicated.
Thank you for coming.
It makes a big difference.
Okay, now let's go on because we do have lots to cover.
Now comes Rakitin.
So there's going to be, Rakitin doesn't, of course, want Dmitry to get away with this marvelous example of the right way to suffer crucifixion and be resurrected.
And what does he do?
Well, he comes in in his, well, there's one funny thing you have to see at Dostoevsky playing these little tricks.
Dimitri has been talking a lot to Rakitin lately.
And as Alyasha comes in to visit Rakitin, Rakitin is in prison now.
He's trying to figure out whether he should let them send him to Siberia or escape and go to America, whether America is worse or less bad than Siberia, and all those interesting but not big deal for us issues.
But here's the funny thing.
Alyasha comes to see him on 78 and see if you can figure out what's happening here.
It's just a trivial thing, but I love it.
As Alyasha entered the room, set aside for interviews, he came upon Rakitin, who was just saying goodbye to Dmitry.
They were both talking loudly.
Dimitri was laughing while Rakitin seemed to be grumbling.
Rakitin did not like meeting Alyasha, especially of late.
He scarcely spoke to him and bowed to him stiffly.
Seeing Alyasha enter now, he frowned and looked away as though he were entirely absorbed in buttoning his big warm fur-trimmed coat.
And what's going on there?
That Dostoevsky is sort of hitting you over the head with and having fun with.
Well, that's a kind of sort of archetypical, very characteristic encounter between the devil and the angel.
The angel has just come in and driven out the devil.
The coat thing is what's interesting.
Alyasha comes in over there, and Rakitin goes, that's putting on his coat.
You could see it in any painting.
And now, so the devil's been sort of scared away by the angel.
And then what happens?
Well, now the next thing is that Dimitri, it turns out Dimitri's been, that Rakhitin has been trying to corrupt Dimitri, who's not all that bright.
It's not his job to be bright.
Ivan is the bright one.
He's telling him about the discovery of neurons.
This is just amazing.
Somebody, I forget who, who came up and talked to me about neurons at the end of about three lectures back.
When I was talking about, do you, okay, when I was talking about how that Dostoevsky is trying to show that the Christian stuff doesn't, gets existentialized and then doesn't conflict with laws of physics and chemistry.
That's one of the rules of the book.
And now, wow, this guy has discovered neurons in Paris.
And as soon as that happens, Rakitin draws the conclusion that that just shows that we're material beings, just like animals, and what we do is caused by the firing of the neurons in our brain.
And so the whole issue of spiritual suffering and transformation and resurrection is just sort of thrown out the window.
And that's what Rakitin's been telling Dimitri.
And at the bottom of 680, poor Dimitri is trying to explain to Alyasha why this means that he shouldn't, that God is dead, that we're all just material things, and we'll just all have to become natural about it.
At the bottom of 680, imagine inside, in the nerves, in the head, that these nerves, they're in the brain, damn them.
They're sort of little tails, and the tails begin to quiver, and then you see, and so forth and so forth.
And then a lot more details about it.
And at the end of that paragraph on 681, Rakitin explained it to me yesterday, and it bowled me over.
It's wonderful, Alyasha, this science.
A new man arising.
That I understand, and yet I'm sorry to lose God.
That's a great thing.
So there are two views of what it is for a new man to be arising.
Dimitri's been meaning, by sacrifice, by suffering, you can become spiritually transformed and joyful.
And he calls that, that's the resurrection.
Now, the new man arising from the devil's point of view, Rakitin, is the new man is a completely chemical, physical organism, totally explainable by science.
And all this fancy existentialist talk just turns out to be irrelevant.
And that's why Dimitri says, I'm sorry to lose God.
He understands that somehow or other, according to Rakitin, the neuron story undermines the existential story.
But Alyasha, and how does Alyasha answer it?
I don't want to get ahead of where I was supposed to be.
680, okay, that's right.
Okay, and now, what does Dostoevsky think about this?
And then what does Alyasha do about this?
Well, what Dostoevsky thinks about it, he doesn't tell you, because this isn't a philosophy paper, that you can tell what he thinks about it from what happens.
But I'll tell you what he thinks.
He thinks that, of course, there has to be some causal basis for seeing and thinking and suffering and having transformation experiences.
But you can't, that doesn't mean that those experiences aren't real.
It's just, it's as if you could say, well, you're not really seeing in the light in the room.
That's really radiation hitting your retina and stimulating the visual cortex.
Well, of course lights hitting waves are coming into the retina, and of course they're stimulating the visual cortex, but that doesn't mean that you're not conscious and you're not seeing.
That's the causal basis of this phenomenon.
And so it's the causal basis of the suffering phenomena and the freedom to do evil and to repent and so forth.
And now, how does Alyasha handle it?
Well, it's funny.
He simply ignores Dimitri.
All he says about, when he says that, I'm sorry, I'm losing God.
And Alyasha says, he says, and yet I'm sorry to lose God.
And Alyasha says, well, that's a good thing anyway, said Alyasha.
And he goes on, I'm sorry to lose God.
It's chemistry, Alyasha.
Chemistry.
There's no help for it.
Rakitin dislikes God.
Boy, does he dislike him?
And he goes on and on.
And then Alyasha just completely ignores him.
And then he says, Dmitry pulled out his piece of paper from his pocket and he says, and it has some philosophical jargon in it.
He doesn't understand it.
And Alyasha says, I don't understand it.
But, and now he's giving sort of Marxist things about how the environment determines people and so forth.
But finally, he just lets him go on like that.
He doesn't try to answer him.
And at the bottom of 683, he says, he just sort of breaks in and he says at the bottom, Dmitri, I can't stay long, Alyasha said.
Tomorrow will be a great and awful day for you.
The judgment of God will be accomplished.
I'm amazed at you.
You walk about here talking, and I don't know what.
Namely, neurons and Marxism is what he's talking.
And he just changes the subject.
Let's see.
And then what happens with Dmitry?
He went up to Alyasha and embraced him.
His eyes glowed.
Rakitin wouldn't understand, he began in a sort of exaltation, but you'll understand it, and that's why I was thirsting for you.
And then he tells him again, was it 684 that we were reading before?
Because we're back now to the top of the page, Alyasha, these two months I found a new man in me, a new man has risen up in me, and so forth.
Alyasha just changes the subject from the causal neuron level and the causal material conditions, that's the sort of Marxist level, to the existential issue for the person who's having the experiences.
That's the existential phenomenological level where the courses I teach are, and Dostoevsky is.
And that's just how he goes back to Dimitri talking just like a Christian on 684, and that just gets rid of Rakitin and the Rakitin problem.
And it goes back to the other new man, the new man that arises from the suffering.
And that's what he talks about on 684.
And he's just driving the point home when he says that a new man has arisen in me.
I mean, if you hear that sort of with Christian resonance, that it says, I've been resurrected.
I am the resurrection.
That's what Dimitri is saying.
Okay, for Dimitri.
Now, we've got a lot to cover.
So I'm going on.
We still have time to do some more.
And now we're going to do Yvonne.
Yvonne is a masochistic.
I got, my title is nice.
Yvonne's masochistic martyrdom as a parody of crucifixion.
That's what we're going to get next.
But now, oh, I forgot.
No, I didn't forget because I wrote it down.
I can't resist these little touches that Dostoevsky puts in.
They're just too much for, let me like, what did I just give you one?
I can't remember already.
What was it?
Yeah, okay.
Here's a, now, here, before we switch to Yvonne, I'm sorry, I put it a little ahead of your Yvonne if you're taking notes.
Here's the last word, in a funny way, on Dimitri as a crucified one.
No, we've had the last word, sorry, of Dimitri as a crucified one.
The question is now we're switching to Yvonne as the crucified one.
He's going to be crucified the wrong way.
He's going to suffer the wrong way.
That is set up early in the book, just like the way Dimitri's suffering is set up early in the book by Zosima.
But this one is set up in the weirdest way.
Here's what I'm going to read you in the middle of 301.
They've just had their conversation about lots of about life and so forth.
And now Yvonne's...
This is right after the Grand Inquisitor story, right after Alyasha, the Grand Inquisitor, kisses the, sorry, Jesus kisses the Grand Inquisitor, but that's not what we're talking about.
So here's 301.
Yvonne turned suddenly and went his way without looking back.
It was just as Dimitri had left, left Alyasha the day before, though the parting had been very different.
And now comes the funniest thing.
The strange resemblance flashed like an arrow through Alyasha's mind in the distress and dejection of that moment.
He waited a little looking after his brother.
He noticed that Yvonne swayed as he walked and that his right shoulder was lower than his left.
What in the world is going on there?
And why does he notice that?
What does that mean?
I'm not going to tell you.
Somebody you've got to figure it out.
Yeah.
Yes, exactly.
He's carrying a cross.
He's Jesus crucified, Yvonne, too.
And it reminds him of Dimitri.
In that crazy paragraph, he's pulling together both Dimitri and Yvonne as carrying the cross, which is part of the crucifixion, which is part of the suffering story.
It just goes by.
I mean, nobody's going to see that.
But Dostoevsky sees that, because he knows what's going to happen, is he's going to put them together 500 pages later.
Okay, so now they're put together, and we're switching to Yvonne.
Yvonne is carrying some sort of cross.
That's why he walks that way.
And he's going to do it.
He's going to confess.
It's now, what's he going to do at the trial?
He's going to confess that he's really the murderer.
And he says at the bottom of 755, lest we haven't got it from that funny par the thing where he's carrying it around, tomorrow the cross, but not the gallows.
By that he means tomorrow he's going to take on himself the suffering of, and he's going to confess that it's his fault that old Taramasov died.
Don't believe anything I say in the sense of the plot.
The plot is so amazingly convoluted and strange that everybody gets blamed for the murder, but somebody actually has to do it, but I'm not going to tell you who until next time.
So anyway, okay, so he said now on 755, we get his view.
Well, we just did that of confession.
Now I've got to read something.
Yvonne's suffering, like Demetri's, comes from being responsible for the selfish impulses in him and his own evil desires.
But Yvonne's response is not to face the dark side of himself and ask forgiveness and take on a public punishment and punish himself and thereby that, but no, that period.
But Yvonne differently wants to punish himself and thereby show that he's better than everyone else.
That's the basic trouble with Yvonne, and probably Father Farah, and maybe all the masochistic martyrs from Dostoevsky's point of view, or some of them anyway, they were showing off, so to speak, by showing that they were how well they could suffer.
You get it when Yvonne, again, Dostoevsky playing funny tricks.
Yvonne, instead of explaining it about himself, because he doesn't see that his suffering is self-indulgent, self-tormenting, prideful kind of suffering.
But he sees it in Katerina.
And this is what he says in the middle of 2:14.
He's describing Katerina, and to her, he says, Your life, Katerina, will be spent in painful brooding over your own feelings and your own heroism and your own suffering.
And in the end, that suffering will be softened and will pass into contemplation of the fulfillment of a bold and proud design.
See, he's turning the very words of Zosima about how suffering will be transformed.
But here, suffering is getting transformed into something prideful.
Yes, proud it certainly is, and desperate in any case, despairing, of course, but a triumph for you.
And the consciousness of it will at last be a source of complete satisfaction and will make you resigned to everything else.
I mean, it's a kind of weird parody of Zosima's view about how suffering will finally make you mellow and make you, even in the end, joyful.
But it's a proud kind of suffering, and, of course, it doesn't do that.
And Yvonne, but that prepares us for Yvonne, who is an example of the proud kind of suffering.
Instead of a infirming his involvement with the rest of humanity and accepting his punishment so as to be united with the rest of his fellow men, like the mysterious visitor does, Yvonne goes to confess to justify himself.
I mean, this is all, once you see it, obvious, but I didn't see it for years, so I assume you haven't seen it either in the swamp, all this book.
So he's jealous of Dimitri, that Dimitri could suffer the right way.
And he says, 758, I hate the monster.
I hate that monster.
I don't want to save the monster.
Let him rot in Siberia.
He's begun singing a hymn.
Oh, tomorrow I'll go and stand before them and spit in their faces.
That is, he's going to go on, he's going to confess, he's going to justify himself.
I thought there was a quote that said he was going to justify himself.
I haven't committed it quite.
Maybe we'll find it yet.
He surely is.
And we'll find out in just a minute.
In fact, right now, 757, the devil tells him what he's really up to.
And it's at the top paragraph, big paragraph.
No, the second big paragraph.
757.
Skip the first line.
The devil says, you are going from pride, he says.
Yvonne is reporting what the devil says.
You'll stand up and say, it was I killed him, and why do you writhe with horror?
You are lying.
I despise your opinion.
I despise your horror.
That's why he spits in their faces.
He said that about me.
That is, the devil said it about Yvonne.
And do you know you are longing for praise, the devil said.
Quote, the devil says, he is a criminal, a murderer, but what nobility?
He wanted to save his brother and he confessed.
So that's certainly the wrong way to confess and take on suffering, so that you do something that everybody admires and you show that you're better than everybody else.
That's how he's doing it.
And he's jealous of Dimitri because he sees that that's not at all what Dimitri's doing.
How are we doing?
Oh, good, good.
Just right.
This is on 877, the bottom.
He talks about some hymn.
She went on.
Katerina is now reporting on what Dimitri says.
Some cross he has to bear.
The cross symbols are just hitting you over the head.
At first, he was carrying the cross, now he's talking about it.
The cross he has to bear, some duty.
I remember Yvonne told me a great deal about it.
And if you knew how he talked, Katerina cried suddenly with feelings she could not repress.
If you only knew how he loved that wretched man, that's Dimitri, at the moment and how he hated him at the same time.
And that's, of course, because he sees that Dimitri is suffering the right way and he admires it, but on the other hand, he hates it because he can't do it.
He's doing just the opposite.
So now that's clear, I think.
And the kind of confession that he's going to make is only going to separate him more and more from human beings and isolate him more and more, not unite them.
I think I said this, but I'm not sure, so I'll go back and look.
I hate the monster 750.
Yeah, okay.
So his self-inflicted pain is motivated by pride.
So he's jealous of Dimitri, who does it another way.
They are suffering for the same crime, and they illustrate crucifixion, but in opposite ways.
They illustrate real suffering and self-torment out of pride.
Dimitri can turn suffering into a new life of joy by confessing and asking forgiveness and taking on sacrificial suffering, and Yvonne only creates more suffering.
So that's the two.
You won't really, I don't know whether I want to skip ahead or not.
I think I will because I want you to see the end of it.
So what's going to happen when Dimitri is, sorry, when Yvonne confesses?
Okay, so let's see if I have jumped there.
I'm not sure I can jump around it.
Yeah, what I'm doing is skipping the, trying to do this before I get to the part on the devil.
So what happens at the trial I want to talk about?
Yeah, it's all over the place.
I know where it is.
It's just I don't know how to get to it.
Who said what page?
Seven?
Probably.
That may be some of it.
I've got a different place, but let's see what you find.
Oh, yes, of course, but you jumped ahead.
That's exactly where it is.
But let me just lead to it.
So, Yvonne goes into the trial, and he's suffering.
Yes, 794.
What is 794?
I'm trying to say that he's dying instead of being reborn.
Oh, no, I see.
Yeah, well, let's just jump to 794.
Although, there's a place where it looks like he's dying.
Oh, here we are.
Okay, now, having said all that, what happens when Yvonne finally gets a chance to confess?
Is he going to spit at everybody's face and tell them how much better he is?
Yes, but it's killing him to do it, literally, killing him to do it.
At the bottom of 792, Yvonne walked up very slowly, looking at no one and with his head bowed as though plunged in gloomy thought.
He was irreproachably dressed, but his face made a painful impression on me at least.
That's the narrator, who oddly enough comes back in.
The narrator's been gone for about 500 pages, but it doesn't mean anything.
It's just Dostoevsky doing what he wants to say.
But he wants to say, and he wants to say it as a sort of objective fact from the outside, that Yvonne is dying.
He was irreproachably dressed, but his face made a painful impression on me at least.
There was an earthy look in it, a look like a dying man.
So there he is going to the crucifixion where you do die, but he's dying in the wrong way because he's not going to be reborn.
But it's a kind of crucifixion.
This is where the 294, the 794 comes in.
Yvonne's been talking about being crucified a lot, just like Dimitri.
But Dostoevsky playing his little game, in case you haven't realized that Yvonne is one of the kinds of Jesus on the cross, namely the kind of Jesus on the cross who despairs.
You get at the bottom of 794.
He's talking and he's raving because he's crazy, and he says at the end of the paragraph, Have you any water?
Give me a drink for Christ's sake.
He suddenly clutched his head.
Well, those of you who know the Bible know that Jesus on the cross says, Give me a drink.
And then, oddly enough, saying for Christ's sake, that's just an incredibly crazy thing.
Yvonne never talks that way, but just to hit you over the head, Dostoevsky is saying, Look, I'm staging the crucifixion as it's done wrong, and that's and Yvonne is it.
And I don't remember now, somebody who knows the Bible well, does Jesus ask for a drink in all the Gospels or just in the three where he despairs and not in the Gospel of John?
Somebody look it up and tell me next time.
Okay, here's the question: I would like in my new insight to think that the giving, asking for water and getting vinegar seen in the crucifixion goes with the despairing crucifixion where Jesus says, Why has God forsaken him?
And that that isn't in the Gospel of John, where everything goes very well.
I don't think he gets, asks for water and gets vinegar.
Please, somebody, will you tell me?
He does it in all four.
Okay, well, there goes that brilliant move.
Dostoevsky does it differently.
That's all I can say.
Dostoevsky puts it with the wrong kind of crucifixion and puts it with Yvonne.
And Dostoevsky is, you know, dividing up these existential insights in his own way.
Okay, now we've still got time to do one more thing, and we need every minute.
Then now we're ready for a new thing, and I'll set it up, but I won't start it.
And that's Yvonne's encounter with the devil.
Starting on his way home from talking to Smershakov, which I'm not going to talk about, but which you can look up, Yvonne encounters a drunken peasant singing a remarkably relevant song, 718.
It's so remarkable that I'm amazed Dostoevsky does it because it's not in keeping with his kind of very realistic kind of world.
But when he hears, Ivan suddenly came upon a drunken peasant, 718, about eight lines down.
He was wearing a coarse coat, and so would zigzag, grumbling, swearing to himself, and suddenly he began singing in a husky, drunken voice, Ah, Vanka's gone to Petersburg.
I won't wait till he comes back.
Can you tell what that means?
Partly it's a plot thing, and you can't tell fully what it means.
But who is Vanka?
Yvonne, remember, way back.
Nobody calls him Vanka except his father occasionally.
But that's his nickname, so to speak.
And what did he do the night of the murder?
He left town, right?
And something happened, namely, the killing happened before he got back.
So Vanka's gone to Petersburg.
He didn't go to Petersburg.
He went to some neighboring town.
I won't wait till he comes back.
That is incredible.
That song is the story of Yvonne's, at least part of his implication in the crime.
Remember, Tatipu posted, he left town on the assumption that if he did, Dmitry would kill old Karamatsov.
And that's why he feels guilty of being the murderer.
And he can't stand being guilty.
So let's go on.
Skipping a line.
Yvonne felt an intense hatred for him, the peasant, before he had thought about him at all, suddenly realized his presence and felt an irresistible impulse to knock him down.
Well, what that means is that whenever anybody reminds Yvonne of his dark side, he wants to get rid of it and of them.
So now he wants to get rid of the peasant, who is in effect accusing him of at least accessory to the murder.
And he hits him, and the peasant stumbles against Yvonne.
Yvonne gives him a big push, he knocks him down, and at the end of that paragraph, Yvonne, he will freeze to death, thought Yvonne.
And he went on his way to Smerzhikov.
So now it turns out that Yvonne is sort of implicated in another sort of murder.
He doesn't try to save the peasant.
He just lets him die.
He says he'll die, and that's it.
Now, when he's coming back from Smershikov, he hits the peasant, he comes across the peasant on 732, and an amazing thing happens.
He feels pity for him, and he saves him on 732.
Where is it?
He's left Smerzhikov at the middle of 732, and now he suddenly, Yvonne feels that he's going to confess honestly.
The snowstorm was still raging.
He walked the first steps, and then he said, he's staggering at something physical, he thought with a grin.
Something like joy was springing up in his heart.
He was almost ready now to confess in the right way and be like Dmitri.
He was conscious of unbounded resolution.
He would make an end to the wavering that so tortured him of late, this torment.
His determination was taken, and it will all be changed.
That is his life, he thought.
At that moment, he stumbled against something and almost fell down, stopped short.
He saw at his feet the peasant he knocked down, still lying unconscious.
Snow had almost covered his face.
And look what happens.
Yvonne lifted him up in his arms.
Yvonne, who is so distant and who doesn't care, and this sort of drunk-smelling peasant, he picks him up in his arms and he saves his life.
And that is incredible that he looks like Yvonne is really on the way to being a good human being.
And he's admitting his involvement with the world.
He's trying to do something to make the world a better place.
And he's about, to do that, and he needs to go and confess.
And then he says, top of 733, the last thing I'm going to read, just as he reached his own house, he stopped short, asking himself suddenly if he'd not better go at once to the prosecutor and tell him everything.
He decided the question quickly.
Everything together tomorrow, he whispered to himself.
And strange to say, almost all his gladness and self-satisfaction passed in an instant.
What happened?
Well, it's a subtle Dostoevsky point.
But Dostoevsky believes that when you do these Christian good deeds of agape love and of sacrificial suffering for the right way, you have to do them impulsively, recklessly, without reflection.
Because if you start to reflect, if he starts to ask, well, when is the right time to go and confess?
And should I really do it?
Or shouldn't I do it?
As soon as you start to deliberate, you fall back into the selfish, rational kind of human being that people normally are.
And so, Yvonne, the only way to accept responsibility for everybody and suffer rightly is to do it spontaneously, emotionally, impulsively, without reflection.
This is the sort of anti-Plato, anti-Socrates.
The best things people do in their life, they do without thinking at all.
They do without reflection.
I'll tell you more about that in a minute.
And the connectedness isn't rational and goes against our selfish nature.
And we can only go against our selfish nature when we are sort of carried away impulsively and not rational.
As soon as Yvonne loses his spontaneous resolution, then his conflict between pride and guilt returns in the form of a confrontation with the devil.
That's how far I wanted to get.
But I've got three more minutes.
I'll start next time with the confrontation with the devil.
Which starts on 7, I'll start on 749, but you need to finish the book.
But I just want to tell you that this idea that people, this is sort of to protect you from what you learn in college, you learn to be rational, critical, reflective.
Don't stick into lower immediacy, do mediation.
You get it from Socrates, and it comes down to us.
But the best thing people do, Dostoevsky thinks, they don't do my thinking and calculating.
They do them impulsively.
They have to.
And I'm going to end with just the story.
You know, probably a lot of you do about the guy in New York in the New York subway when a guy fell on the tracks in front of the subway train.
Any of you know that fact?
You know about it.
Well, when this guy, about a 30-year-old guy, had some, I don't know what, epileptic fit or something, and fell on the tracks and the subway train was coming, somebody standing on the platform with his kids gave his kids to somebody, said, keep these, and jumped on the subway tracks on top of the guy who had fallen down, held him down, and the subway train went over them and nobody was hurt.
And he became a hero and he was written up in all the papers in New York and interviewed.
And when he was interviewed, they asked him, sort of, why did you do it?
What were you thinking?
And he said, I didn't have time to think.
I wasn't thinking at all.
It just had to be done.
Somebody had to do it.
And they called on me, and I did it with a perfectly Dostoevsky thing.
I mean, that's a much more amazing hero or saint.
Neither one of those is quite right.
A much more amazing human thing to do than stopping to figure out what to do.
Because, of course, in that case, the guy would have been dead.
Okay, that's it.