We have want to look at the answers to the Grand Inquisitor.
All we've got so far is the antinomies.
And we know that the two alternatives, the Protestant and the Catholic, the Grand Inquisitor, the Catholic, and Jesus, the Protestant, are equally bad.
One of them has a view that human beings are hopeless, slavish, and awful, and the other one has the view that human beings are totally free and capable of completely austere dedication, like Kierkegaard.
And the Russian Orthodox Zosima's view, we really don't know yet.
So we're going to run through them now and look for the third view.
You should have been looking for it, and I hope some of you know it.
And well, of course, the chart helps, but the chart is pretty cryptic.
So, anyway, we will do the third view.
Some of the third view is in the sayings of Father Zosima.
That's where, in his letter, Dostoevsky says there is this oblique answer to the Grand Inquisitor.
But the crucial, two of the most crucial ones, there are so many of them, all of these existentializing moves, that two of the crucial answers to the specific antinomies of the Grand Inquisitor are over the issue of confession and miracle.
And I don't know whether you're going to get to miracle today, but I'm going to try.
That's why I sent around a message that you should all read through the passage on miracle so that if we get there, you'll know what's happening and how exciting it is.
I have a feeling we may not, because it turns out I have to leave about 10 minutes early today and rush out of here.
But let's go and see where we end up.
So let's look first at what I think is, as I say, the least interesting of them, but we've got to start where we start.
Do people need material satisfaction in order to lead good lives and be moral?
And how much material satisfaction?
On one side of the antinomy, you get the extreme ascetic view attributed to Jesus, and on the other side, we get the sort of, we indulge people because we know they're weak and we want to make them happy, a view of the Grand Inquisitor.
So the first is to see evidence outside of the dialectic, that is the give and take of the antinomies, independent evidence that Dostoevsky rejects the Jesus story and rejects the Grand Inquisitor story.
We have to see that before we can see the positive thing he's proposing.
Well, the way to find out is to ask yourself questions like this: Is there anybody in the book who is the kind of religious person that the Grand Inquisitor says Jesus wants?
The kind that can give up bread and simply live on mushrooms and locusts and berries.
Anybody know who that is, or if there is such a one?
Yeah.
Have we done this already?
No?
Okay.
I suddenly thought, gee, maybe we've already discussed.
Okay, yes, Father Farrapont on 190 is the sort of reductio to craziness of the Jesus view.
He says at the top, yes, I can give up their bread, not needing it, and live on mushrooms and berries.
They can't give up their bread.
They are in bondage to the devil.
The unclean deny that there is need for such fasting.
Haughty and unclean is their judgment.
And then, and you wonder, well, maybe he's right.
Well, then at the bottom, you hear him tell this story about this devil, which he could see through, and he saw the devil hiding behind the door, a big one, tail a yard long, and he slammed the door on the tail, and the devil squealed, and he made the sign of the cross over him, and he died on the spot.
And what do you think?
I think it shows that he's completely insane.
And I think that's the general view that people have.
Some think he's sort of holy, and that is H-O-L, well, wholly insane.
I think he's holy, I guess, with a W, totally insane.
There's not a sign that he understands, that he makes any sense, and he's the big enemy of Father Zosima, and you would expect sort of the enemy, we aren't going to be likely to like the enemy of Father Zosima.
But then, is there any evidence that it's okay not only to eat bread and not to sort of starve yourself, but it's even okay to eat goodies?
I mean, what's the equivalent of, I mean, what I think of as the equivalent of hot fudge sundaes and banana splits in this book, something that people really like, and it isn't good for them, but they can't resist it.
Yes, cherry jam.
Don't ask me why, but cherry jam is the thing that both Father Zosima and Alyasha will die for.
About a third of the way down on 258, Ivan asks Alyasha, do you want soup?
And he says, Yeah, and he says, and cherry jam, they have it here.
And then Alyasha says, Let me have jam too.
I still like it.
So he gets his cherry jam.
And more important, Zosima, I had it marked here.
I don't see it now.
Zosima also gets cherry jam.
The ladies bring it to him.
Where is that?
I don't know yet.
I lost it just a second.
Hmm.
Anybody know?
I have it written here.
It's 383.
This just shows you what we're looking at is Dostoevsky obviously thinks that fasting is not necessary except on special occasions and that you can indulge yourself in good things as long as you don't get addicted to them.
We'll get to that.
But at the bottom of 382, they are complaining about the Zosima.
He was not strict in fasting, allowed himself sweet things, ate cherry jam with his tea.
That's interesting, and it's important.
That is, he's clearly a spiritual, moral, pure, joyful person.
It is.
And spiritual, moral, pure, joyful person, Father Ferrapant.
Farrapont certainly is not.
He's always in a grumpy mood.
He's always denouncing everybody.
He always says he's better than everybody.
So it looks like score one for against, score against the Jesus view that you should be an ascetic like Ferrapont.
And now we have to talk about the other side.
We've got evidence now that people need bread and they need even goodies.
But there's also evidence that they need bread.
I mean, I should have done it in the other order.
Put it in your notes in the right order.
We want to see, one, that they need bread and shouldn't be starving themselves.
And two, they even can have hot-fudge Sundays.
And that's all right.
So let's, here's the evidence that they need food and just plain old food and shouldn't be fasting all the time.
Where is it?
The bottom of 332.
Friends and teachers, I've heard more than once, and of late one may hear it more often, that the priests and above all the village priests are complaining on all sides of their miserable income and their humiliating lot.
They state and so forth that because of the smallness of their means, if Lutherans and heretics come, you know, these dangerous Lutherans are prowling around on the periphery of the Russian Orthodox Church.
If the Lutherans and heretics come and lead the flock astray, they let them because they have so little to live on.
May the Lord increase their sustenance.
It's so precious to them, for their complaint is just.
Their sustenance is their food.
And Zosima is saying, the priests say they're too hungry to go around doing their priest's job.
And Zosima says it's true.
We've got to get them more food.
How we're going to get them more food, we're not ready to say yet.
But he thinks the monks' complaint is just.
And now you get the cherry jam, that they ought to also have goodies.
But what they shouldn't do is cultivate their appetites beyond what they are and need to be, and get addicted just to trying to increase their desires and satisfy them.
I call that the Berkeley approach.
The Berkeley approach of learning to love all sorts of delicious and pleasant and wonderful things and being able to increase your desires for things you never even knew you wanted.
That's what people do around here.
That's what the Grand Inquisitor is very much against.
The bottom of 359.
The world has proclaimed the reign of freedom, especially of late.
What do you see in this freedom?
Nothing but slavery and self-destruction.
Because the world says, wherever it says world, you say Berkeley.
You have desires and so satisfy them, for you have the same rights as the most rich and powerful.
Don't be afraid of satisfying them and even multiply your desires.
That's the modern doctrine of the world.
They think that in that they see freedom, which is, but it's not really freedom.
And what's the middle ground?
Well, it's sort of implied in there, to begin with.
You eat enough food to be able to lead a comfortable life and do the job that you are called to do.
And you can even have some goodies, but you don't get addicted to satisfying all your desires.
You cut off your superfluous and unnecessary desires, except maybe for cherry jam.
I mean, it's a kind of nice, I mean, it sounds sort of inconsistent, but it's just a kind of flexible, sensible view.
I mean, you don't have to cut off all your unnecessary desires, but only if you don't, but you can't let them get enslave you.
If you become addicted to smoking, for instance, then you've gone too far.
And if you became addicted to cherry jam, that wouldn't be good either.
But if you can enjoy them, this is all talked about on 360 at the about 20 lines from the bottom.
For how can a man shake off his habits?
What can become of him if he's in bondage to the habit of satisfying the innumerable desires he's created for himself?
And then below that, next paragraph, the monastic way is very different.
Obedient, fasting, and prayer are laughed at.
Yet only through them lies the way to real true freedom.
I cut off my superfluous and unnecessary desires.
So a little skipping to the bottom, which is most capable, see, who's most capable of conceiving a great idea and serving it?
The rich man in his isolation, or the man who has freed himself from the tyranny of material things and habits.
So that's a sensible view.
It's so sensible that it's not very exciting.
I mean, it's more fun if you, as you'll see, you get far-out views like Dostoevsky's views about confession and miracles.
But we have to follow this.
And what does Osima think you should do?
Would there be a necessary amount of bread without a planned economy?
Remember the issue.
I mean, suppose all you need to do is get bread for people.
Maybe there's not enough bread to go around, unless you plan from each according to his ability to each according to his need and have a kind of Soviet communism, which he's sort of predicting.
Without that, there won't be enough bread.
Well, Dasima's view is sort of interesting, but I don't know whether it works.
He thinks you don't need one big planned economy.
What you need is lots of, in effect, hippie communes.
People who live together and share things and love each other and eat a reasonable amount that don't cultivate their desires and aren't selfish.
And they, thousands, hundreds of thousands of kibbutzes or hippie communes or whatever you want to call them, they will be the sort of economic backbone, and then everything will be all right.
This was sort of in the 60s when I was teaching that here.
This was much more relevant because the hippies were going off to Oregon and Washington and setting up such communes in which they would share everything and all love each other.
And it looks like an argument against Dostoevsky that, as far as I know, they've all failed.
I don't, maybe you know more about it than I do.
Yeah.
What?
Well, a cooperative is different.
The students don't own all their goods in common, do they?
Their clothes and their oh, okay.
But anyway, and if it works, they're good.
And I gather it works still.
There are still kibbutzes in Israel.
Anybody know?
That's what I think.
But it's not, let me just say, Dostoevsky, I think, would have to admit that it's not working well enough to be the general form of the economy and to solve everybody's problems.
Now, that's not just me saying that.
That wouldn't be interesting.
Dostoevsky thinks it's not going to work.
That's what's interesting.
He's really criticizing Zosima on this one.
Zosima thinks there should be this local communes and everybody will just love each other and help each other.
He says it in terms of the priests on 334, those priests who don't have enough food.
What are you going to do about that?
And he says to the priests, 12 lines from the bottom, you will penetrate their hearts with these simple tales.
He says, tell them the Bible stories.
Give one hour a week to it, in spite of your poverty, only a short hour.
And you will see for yourself that our people are gracious and grateful and that we will pay you a hundredfold, mindful of the kindness of their priests and the moving words they have heard from him.
They will, of their own accord, help him in the fields and in his house and treat him with more respect, and so will increase his worldly well-being.
So, in a way, everybody's sort of helping, and so maybe the Amish have this too.
I mean, it's something that it's an interesting proposal.
And what's really surprising and interesting to me is that Dostoevsky doesn't buy it.
You might think, if you say to Dostoevsky, if you say to Zosima, this is too idealistic, people are innately selfish, they won't want to share the fruit of their hard labor and their clothes and their books and so forth.
Most of these communes didn't last.
And what would that be?
Would that be an objection to Dostoevsky?
Well, interestingly enough, no.
He differs from Zosima on this one.
He thinks people are really selfish and that it basically you're not going to be able to set up this kind of shared commune-like world.
You don't get it said clearly until 347.
It's very important to Dostoevsky's view that ordinary human beings are Hobbesian.
Hobbes is a philosopher who's famous for saying life is nasty, brutish, and short, and that everybody tries to get as much possessions as possible and then has to sort of guard their possessions against everybody else.
And that's why we have government.
So Dostoevsky has a similar view.
He says at the bottom of 346, well, it's presented sort of backwards.
So let me do it on 347.
Here he's telling you what's wrong.
This is the mysterious visitor, who we'll hear more about, who comes to talk to who Zosima knows a lot about.
The mysterious visitor knows a lot about human nature.
Here's what he says.
The second sentence in the first big paragraph, 1347.
For everyone strives to keep his individuality.
Everyone wants to secure the greatest possible fullness of life for himself.
But in the meantime, all his efforts result in attaining, well, not in attaining fullness of life, but self-destruction.
For instead of self-realization, he ends by arriving in complete solitude.
All mankind in our age is split up into units.
Man keeps apart, each in his own groove.
Each one holds aloof, skipping a little.
He ends up repelled by others.
And this is the Hobbesian thing.
He heaps up riches by himself and thinks how strong I am now and how secure.
And in his madness, he does not understand that the more he heaps up, the more he sinks into self-destructive impotence.
Namely, he can't really defend himself and his possessions against everybody else who wants to get his possessions to add to their possessions.
Now, what's going on?
I mean, it's odd when you find a kind of conflict between Zosima and Dostoevsky.
Of course, you could say Dostoevsky doesn't agree with the mysterious visitor, but he does.
I mean, I can't sort of quote you any line, but keep your eyes open.
The story is this: it's another existentialized.
The original sin, when existentialized, is that people are naturally selfish and insecure.
And if you just take people the way they naturally are, you can't build a commune and a successful state on the basis of them.
And original sin just is the way everybody is selfish, basically, and insecure.
And what do you do then?
Well, in some way, which is way later in the book, you have to understand how people can be transformed by existentialized Christian love so that they stop being selfish and insecure.
We may get there today.
It happens to Grushenka.
He told you to be sure and read for today.
Maybe we should just mention.
I mean, Grushenka is.
How many read the passage I told you to read for today in the email?
Okay, thanks to you all and congratulations, but not enough that I want to skip ahead to Grushenka.
But you may understand what I'm saying.
But anyway, the idea is that Dostoevsky's idea, Dezova is living in this too protected way in his monastery, not really, and there they share lots of things, and they're very special people, and they all love each other, and they all experience Christian love.
It's a proof that you could have these kind of successful communes, but only if they're Christian communes.
Where Christian doesn't mean anymore just belonging to some Christian church.
It means being in the culture in which there is a certain kind of love and having been exposed to it and, so to speak, caught it in a way that we haven't explained yet.
So, and that's on the bottom of 346.
The mysterious visitor is saying, and what do you have to do to get rid of these terribly selfish, upset people?
Well, he says you have to have a psychological transformation.
He says it's a spiritual, psychological process.
Now, just for a moment, word about vocabulary.
The right thing to say is certainly spiritual.
And it was okay in Dostoevsky's time, I gather, to equate psychological with spiritual some of the time.
Now, I mean, that doesn't, to say it's a psychological process now means it's something natural that happens because of the way, I don't know, the neurons are, or the DNA is, or your brain is, or how you're socialized.
And Dostoevsky thinks that it's a spiritual change.
I mean, it's a kind of being reborn.
And it's not something you can account for in a scientific way.
And he's very strange about this because he really understands that.
He's against psychology.
Because of their attempt to make a kind of rational understanding of human beings, they don't understand the contradictions in human beings.
They don't understand the possibility of transformation.
And the way his hate, really hate of psychologists and psychology comes out is in the trial.
The forensic psychologists are all trying to understand who killed old Karamatsov, that's no big secret, and why.
And they are making absolute fools of themselves.
But that's just because they don't understand spiritual transformation.
And Dostoevsky thinks because psychology has to do with the soul, so to speak, in the satsika in Greek, it ought to cover the spiritual thing.
But if you, it's better to read him just understanding that what he really is interested in is these existential transformations.
And that's got to do with selfishness and sinfulness and how it can be overcome by love.
And we'll just call it spiritual.
So it's a spiritual process to transform the world.
We're at the bottom of 346.
To transform the world, to recreate it afresh, men must turn into another path psychologically.
I cross it out and say existentially or spiritually, just confusing.
Until you have become really, in fact, a brother to everyone, brotherhood will not come to pass.
No sort of scientific teaching, see, so psychology was not considered scientific teaching then, like it is now.
No sort of scientific teaching, no kind of common interest will ever teach men to share property and privileges with equal consideration.
Everyone will think his share too small.
They'll always be envying and so forth.
And now we're getting into that other passage I read.
They will be sinful.
Only his transformation can make it all right.
Now I have to choose.
So given the way human nature is, the free market won't work.
The planned state won't leave people free.
The communes will fail until something very radical happens to all of humanity, which, believe it or not, Dostoevsky's got a big vision.
We will hear about what it is and how it's going to happen.
But in the meantime, he's anticipating the failure of state communism and the meltdown of the free market and so all on it all on his own.
So, but now we're on to this interesting thing, which is very hard to understand until you crack the code, which is Yvonne's story about whether the state should become a church or the church should become a state and what in the world that means.
Remember, he's written an article to that effect, and all the monks are very confused trying to interpret it, and I was confused for years trying to interpret it.
But I've now given you all the clues you need to understand it.
The Grand Inquisitor proposes a kind of secular socialism, and therefore the church plays no role in it.
The church becomes the state, it becomes, say, Soviet Russia.
That's one possibility.
Then the church stops, disappears, and the secular gets the job of distributing the wealth and keeping people from grabbing things from each other.
The church can't be formed, transformed into a state, however, because the people will stay as nasty as ever.
It's the mistaken idea, the way it's set up in here, of the Catholic Church, who doesn't understand the need for transformation, to think that if you just, the way it's set up here, collect all the stuff from everybody and redistribute it, everything will be all right.
But that's just the Roman Catholic way, not the right way.
Now, this is on 72.
I've been saying all this.
Now, what happens if the church gets turned into a state, it just stops being spiritual and religious and takes on the planned economy business.
So, what would it be for the state to become a church would be for everybody in the state to become genuinely religious?
So, this is talked about on 72, second paragraph.
They're discussing Yvonne's paper.
You are completely misunderstanding it, said Father Pius sternly.
You must understand that the church is not to be transformed into the state.
That's Rome and its dreams.
See, there's the imp.
Dostoevsky is always giving you these guidelines lest you're lost.
I mean, that's the Grand Inquisitor.
That's the third temptation of the devil.
On the contrary, the state is to be transformed into the church, will ascend and become a church over the whole world.
That's what I've been telling you, which is the complete opposite of Rome, never mind that other thing, which I don't know what it is, of Rome, and your interpretation, the other guy that Pius is talking to.
And it is only the glorious destiny ordained to the Orthodox Church.
The phrase that I've been using, and which you'll hear again a few times, the star will arise in the east, means the Russian Orthodox Church will save the world.
And that means that in this sort of code, the state will become a church.
That is, the people will be transformed, and then they will have their religion.
Now, again, Dostoevsky is so easy to understand in a way.
You will, if this is what, if this is really the explanation of what Ivan is talking about, Dostoevsky is going to tell you right out and hit you over the head with it.
On page 73, four lines down, we have a little thing attributed to Peter Muazov.
Muazov, and usually when Dostoevsky tells you the true view, he puts it in the mouth of somebody who doesn't believe it and doesn't understand it.
We'll see that happening again today if we get to the miracle.
But so here you get Muazov, who is the Western European secular guy in the book.
He'd be a bad guy if he did anything, but he's just a kind of observer.
So he doesn't play any important role.
But now, Dostoevsky is going to put into the mouth of the bad guy his belief, which he's going to sort of defend and explain in the book, that for human beings to survive, the state must become a church.
So here it is, four lines down on 73.
We are not particularly afraid, he said.
Muazov was talking to some sort of CIA guy or FBI guy, a secret agent in the West.
We're not particularly afraid, said he, of all these socialists, anarchists, infidels, and revolutionaries.
Those are all secular religious groups.
We keep watch on them and know all their doings.
But there are a few peculiar men among them who believe in God and are Christians, but at the same time socialists.
Those are the people we're most afraid of.
Well, that's Dostoevsky.
The people they're most afraid of are the people who think that there must be, that people must be changed, transformed in order to form a state, and that they know how to do it, because Christianity knows how to do it.
Okay, now I think I should stop for a minute because I think I want to make sure I have done the whole story about bread.
Yeah, okay.
Anybody want to say anything?
I mean, it's so consistent and original and fascinating, but you really can't test it.
You really can't test it till you have to get to the end of the book, and then you have to ask yourself, well, has he showed you how it's going to work and convinced you that the star is going to rise in the East or not?
So I think you can't really, I can't really expect you to have an opinion, but happily someone does.
Go ahead.
That's what?
That it's, in a way, socialist.
What?
Dostoevsky is a socialist.
Yeah.
He's a Christian socialist.
No, I never said that.
Somebody else might have said that.
I think maybe the introduction, the forward or something says that.
He may have been a monarchist too, but I don't know what he thought the monarch was supposed to do.
His basic view is to be a Christian socialist.
That is, you've got to believe that the monarchy, I don't believe he could hold that because the theme can't transform people.
Only Christian love can transform people.
Let me just review.
And people are innately sinful and selfish.
That's original sin.
And you can't build a state on people who are so insecure and greedy.
So you've got to have a Christian socialism.
And he may think, you know, like in England or someplace, that there ought to be a nice place for the monarch to be the kind of high example of the Christian life or something, but he can't, he can't, he has to be a Christian socialist, given what I've, all the stuff I've said.
If anything in the book contradicts this, please come to my office hours and tell me or send me an email.
And if you find out even that he was a monarchist, just give me the reference and I'll okay.
Yeah.
Wouldn't you like to see the instance of related arts orthodox by law enarchists?
Well, I don't know what to say to you guys because I don't really know, or I must admit, care much about what he really believed.
I wanted to sort of talk about the Dostoevsky that comes out of reading this book.
And there's nothing in this book which pretends to, or claims to explain all the possible socialist and anti-socialist view about how to distribute material goods, and nothing about monarchists.
When the star arises in the East, I don't think the monarch is going to have anything to do with it.
So I don't know.
It's a great subject for both of you to try to figure out how he could be a conservative Marxist and be busy writing this book.
This book sounds like it comes from the time that he got in trouble and almost shot, not the view he ended up with.
But don't worry about it.
We're trying to figure out what, remember back to the first lecture, what is the kind of revealing experience that Dostoevsky's got, out of which all of his views come, and which he's trying to get you to experience in the book.
And I don't care whether he actually had that experience or that view, but the way the book works, in fact, we're very close.
You are now within 20 pages, if you did the assignment, what I told you to read, with the central religious experience of the book.
You get to read it over vacation.
Because even if we get to the miracle today, which I don't know yet, it's right after the miracle that he understands sort of the deep religious truth about the universe.
But we're not going to talk about that yet.
And I really am worried now.
Both of you really help try to figure out what's going on here.
Because I'm absolutely sure that I'm telling you what the book says, and I don't feel that you're going to find anything that contradicts what I'm saying, but I don't understand yet how to deal with what you guys say.
So let's see now.
Where am I?
Turn too many pages, maybe.
Yes.
Okay, here we are.
Now, what about community and church?
We get them out of the way in three minutes, which is a good thing.
But remember the issue: should must people relate to God as a single isolated individual?
Sort of Protestantism, Luther pushed to the absolute limit, the thing that Kierkegaard, that Jesus says in the Grand Inquisitor, and Kierkegaard really believes?
Or is it necessary to convert everyone to Christendom, Roman Catholic Christendom, one universal antepe, as the Grand Inquisitor calls it, because people can only believe in whatever they think is true, and they can only believe in the kind of truth which is objective truth, universal, and shared.
I mean, Kierkegaard, you know, just takes that head on and says the truth is subjectivity, meaning everybody has their own unconditional commitment, which is their own truth.
But the Grand Inquisitor says, no, the truth is objectivity, and there must be, and there's some right answer, or even if there isn't, it doesn't matter.
We're going to give everybody the impression there's some right answer.
And what does Kierkegaard?
I mean, what does Dostoevsky think?
Well, it's very simple what Dostoevsky thinks.
Not very exciting.
But, you know, I mean, what he thinks is that a single individual can't be a believing Christian, and that Christianity isn't going to be some universal church.
Sort of contradicting what I'm saying in a way, because when the star arises from the east and the world is saved, why isn't that a well, it might be a universal church, but what makes it work is the individual loving of people's neighbors by their neighbors, not because the church has the truth and everybody believes the truth or has to believe it.
So here's what you need to have.
Dostoevsky's kind of religion, about four lines from the top of three, four lines from the top of 370.
And if this is all Zosima, but I think we're supposed to believe it.
Most of what Zosima says.
You believe whatever Zosima says until it's proved otherwise.
And sometimes it is, sometimes it isn't.
And that's only natural, because being in the monastery, he's got it sort of right and sort of wrong.
And if two of you are gathered together, then there is a whole world, a world of living love.
Embrace each other tenderly and praise God.
If only in you two, his truth has been fulfilled.
So that's consistent.
I mean, if the Christian message is love of the kind, which we're going to hear more and more about as the book goes on, it's love of one person for another.
It's what used to be translated charity and faith, hope, and charity, but now charity's gotten sort of used up, so people say faith, hope, and love.
But I mean, as long as you can't love just by yourself, and it's not love if you can't love everybody, you can't love humanity.
That's what Yvonne thinks he can do.
But you have to love your neighbor, and then there is a church.
So when there's two or more people gathered together, that is a Christian community, according to Dostoevsky's account.
Now that's so simple and straightforward, I don't have anything more to say about it.
At the end of the book, so many things happen in about the last ten pages of the book.
You will see the creation of a Christian community.
Dostoevsky has a workout idea about what a Christian community is and how you create one.
But until then, I don't think there's anything more I can say about it.
I doubt if there's anything you can say about it, though you're welcome to say something.
Okay, well, then we get to the great good one, which we're certainly going to do before I rush out of here.
And that's confession.
Now, remember the view again.
Christ's view in the Grand Inquisitor is that you have to settle any moral issues alone with God.
God isn't going to give you any rules.
God isn't going to give you any help.
God isn't going to get you out of your anguish.
It's the teleological suspension of the ethical.
There's something higher than the ethical, and it's unintelligible, and there's nobody going to help you deal with it.
You're going to be in anguish.
It's all Kierkegaard.
The Inquisitor's view is that people need moral guidelines.
They need people to hear their confessions and forgive them when they do something wrong and tell them what they should have done.
And so now we're going to expect a complicated sort of answer.
Or maybe you're not expecting it, but you're going to get a complicated answer.
Because this is the first place, and one of the only places, I think, where Dostoevsky diverges from the Russian Orthodox Church.
I mean, remember, the Russian Orthodox Church is the answer to the antinomies.
And so it ought to come out that somehow the relation of what he says to the Russian Orthodox Church ought to be pretty similar.
But on confession, he just thinks the church is wrong.
And after all, he's got his own brilliant view about all of these existentialized notions.
And when he existentializes confession, which is what he's about to do, he has his ideas about what it really is when it isn't magical.
And he thinks just somebody going and confessing to somebody else who has the power to absolve them and says you're forgiven, that that's magic.
And we're not going to have that kind of magic.
So out with the Russian Orthodox view of confession.
Because even for the Russian Orthodox, as for the Catholic, the Roman Catholics, confession is private and secret between the person and the sinner, you or me, and the person they're confessing to, the priest.
And moreover, it's secret so that nobody needs to know what you confess.
That's all just wrong, psychologically or existentially, let's say, spiritually.
So we have to go on.
So get rid of that.
So the question is, what should the Russian Orthodox Church do?
Well, that's the second stage would be to look at Zosima.
Because normally, Zosima gets it right.
Again, not always, but in this case, what Zosima does is obviously what confession should be.
But you don't have to believe me.
Gostevsky is going to hit you over the head with it when the time comes.
But it starts on 179.
Here's what Zosima does.
As a rule, every evening, the middle of 179, as a rule, every evening after service, the monks walked into Father Zosima's cell and confessed aloud, see, not private, their sins of the day, their sinful thoughts and temptations, their disagreements.
Some confessed kneeling.
The elder absolved, reconciled, exhorted, imposed penance, blessed and dismissed them.
It was against this general confession that the opponents of elders protested, maintaining that it profaned the sacrament of confession.
Well, it does.
I mean, the sacrament of confession, the way the church, both Roman and Russian, interpreted it, it's not supposed to be a public, it's not supposed to be an encounter group.
I mean, when I first came to Berkeley, there were these encounter groups where everybody had confessed everything in front of everybody else, and everybody forgave them, and everybody felt better.
But that's not what the church wants, and that's not even that's not what Dostoevsky wants either, because if you do it without love, it's not going to work, he thinks.
But then what does Dostoevsky want?
Well, he wants something like what Zosim is doing, but he wants it to have an existential basis.
I mean, it looks like Zosima just arbitrarily does this.
Zosima gives no explanation directly of what he is up to when he calls them in and absolves them and so forth.
But, and now we get to the really interesting part.
Dostoevsky is going to give you, and it'll take probably the rest of the time, an example of a real existential confession.
And that's the mysterious visitor.
That's what happens on 344.
And starting on 344 is, and Zosima is telling it.
So in a sense, Zosima is really giving you the story behind what he's doing when he calls everybody into the room.
He knows, I think, what he's doing.
But he tells it indirectly.
But it's the, as he says in his letter, Dostoevsky, it's the indirect answer to the Grand Inquisitor story that you either should be confessing secretly to God, or you should be.
Did I get the other side, confessing to everyone?
No.
What's the other half of the antinomy of confession?
Help.
Where's my?
I need a chart.
Who has my chart?
Whoever was giving out the chart, what's the third view on confession?
No, no, that's what the Grand Inquisitor says Jesus wants.
That's Kierkegaard.
I said a lot about that, but I didn't say what the opposed view of confession would be.
I see what you're saying.
That's why I didn't is because it's so confusing.
The Kierkegaard won.
Ah, no, I see.
Oh, now I see.
Remember when the Grand Inquisitor says there shouldn't be any tittle-tattle between men about what should only be with God?
Yeah, the funny antinomy works.
Everybody thinks confession is private.
Kierkegaard thinks it's so private that you can't even share your confession with a single other human being, and that it's a bad thing that in the Roman Catholic Church, human beings confess to me or other human beings about what they should keep secret and confess to God about.
So that's the antinomy.
And the resolution is it's not a private thing, it can't be a private thing.
That's the common mistaken assumption between the disagreement about whether it's confession to nobody but God or confession to somebody who represents God and keeps quiet about it.
Now, that's okay.
Here we go now.
And the mysterious visitor is going to explain what confession is, what spiritual/slash psychological role it plays, and how it has to be done.
And so we're ready to go.
So the mysterious visitor story starts on 344, and it starts with the mysterious visitor saying these stories about how everybody lives in isolation.
And the background story now is the mysterious visitor has committed a murder.
He murdered his girlfriend out of jealousy.
And he got away with it because they arrested the wrong person.
And then before they had a chance to find out it was the wrong person, that person died in prison.
And the Grand Inquisitor was always a respected member of society, and nobody suspects him at all.
So now that should remind you of two Woody Allen movies.
I mean, it helps a lot.
If I had time, we could have shown one.
Has any, let me get better, close the door.
A riot is about to take place out there.
So, yeah, close the door.
Go ahead.
Stand up.
We're going to close the door, please.
No, I think we'll open the door.
And it's not going to chop it.
We're all in here.
Well, come in and close.
I've got a solution for you.
Come in and close the door.
Seriously.
Then whoever's chasing you will protect you.
Okay?
Okay, well, we're going on.
We offer you asylum if you want it.
Okay, whatever it is.
It ended peacefully.
Okay, now where were we?
Oh, yeah.
Two movies.
How many, a while back, Woody Allen movie sort of come and go.
That's good.
Good.
He closed the door.
Now that one's closed, too.
Peace and quiet.
Okay, so have you seen Crimes and misdemeanors?
Good, good, good.
Okay, the latest one is Matchpoint.
Have you seen Match Point?
So, Woody Allen's got two movies that are exactly the same.
I was sort of annoyed at Match Point.
I think Crimes and Misdemeanors is better.
But those movies are aimed at taking back the mysterious visitor.
And Woody Allen knows his Dostoevsky, and he's always sort of trying to take it back.
What happens, but notice it starts the same.
Somebody who's a pillar of the community commits a murder and gets away with it.
And there's going to be nobody ever going to find out about it.
And then, remember, the second thing in Crimes and Misdemeanor is he starts feeling so guilty that he can't go on.
And it's like crime and punishment at that point.
He has to confess, he feels.
And then time passes and he gets his wits back together again, and he doesn't confess, and he lives happily ever after.
That is the anti-Dostoevsky view.
The Dostoevsky view is he has to confess.
And now the question is: who's right?
And I can at least tell you Dostoevsky's story.
I really don't know who's right.
I'm inclined to think that Dostoevsky is right.
People can't commit murders and just feel okay about it.
But I'm not sure.
Anyway, Dostoevsky seems to be sure.
So let's go on.
So what happens now?
Here he is.
He's gotten away with this murder.
He's a happily married man and has children.
And then the trouble starts at the bottom of 351.
The children came.
How dare I love them, teach and educate them?
How can I talk to them of virtue?
I've shed blood.
They were fine children.
He longed to caress them, but I can't look at their innocent faces.
I'm unworthy.
And this is the thing.
You're getting the picture.
What's really happening?
He's isolated because he can't share with anybody the intimacy because what he essentially is, namely a murderer, is what he can't tell them.
It's there, it's like Hiroshima Monomur.
She's leading this totally secret life from her own husband and family and so forth, that she's really brooding over the love, still loves the German in her night of resignation way.
And she's in trouble and in despair.
And he's in trouble and in despair.
At the bottom of 351, at last he began to be bitterly and ominously haunted by the blood of his murdered victim, by the young life that he'd destroyed, by the blood that cried out for vengeance.
He began to have awful dreams that being a man of strength, he bore his suffering a long time, thinking, I shall atone for everything by this secret agony.
Well, that's the Kierkegaard Jesus one.
You atone before God with your secret agony.
That didn't work.
He was respected for benevolence.
He's like the doctor in Crimes and Misdemeanors.
And then, about 15 lines down, we leave Woody Allen and go on to Dostoevsky.
An idea which he had at first regarded as impossible and unthinkable, though at last it got such a hold on his heart that he couldn't shake it off.
He dreamed of rising up, going out and confessing before all men that he had committed murder.
For three years, this dream pursued him, haunted him in different forms.
At last he believed with his whole heart that if he confessed his crime, he would heal his soul and would be at peace forever.
But the belief filled his heart with terror, for how could he carry it out?
And then we get a bit of example of how people influence each other's lives, which is a whole theme in the brothers.
And Dostima, without knowing it, and for reasons that we don't know yet, threw away his gun instead of fighting a duel.
And that convinced the mysterious visitor.
Looking at you, I made up my mind.
I looked at him.
Is it possible that such an incident could give rise to such a decision?
And then he says, Yes, I've been going on for three years thinking about it, and you sort of crystallize it.
And so remember his problem.
He's in isolation because he can't tell the truth about himself.
So he can't have any intimacy.
So he's in despair.
And now there's a solution.
Tell everybody.
And so he says in the next page, in the big paragraph in the middle, I know it will be heaven for me, heaven the moment I confess.
14 years I've been in hell.
Well, incidentally, what's being demagicalized and existentialized?
And you're being hit over the head with it.
Confession and heaven and hell.
Yes, he's going to say this over and over, lest you might miss it.
14 years I've been in hell.
I want to suffer.
I will take my punishment and begin to live.
You can pass through the world doing wrong, but there's no turning back.
Now I dare not love my neighbor or even my own children.
So he's going to do it.
And again, Dostievski hits you over the head again in an interesting way.
He wants to say, this is in the Bible.
And he says, the mysterious visitor takes this book, or the Grand Inquisitor does, I don't remember.
I took the book, opened it in another place.
Yeah, this grand, it's awesome, and showed him the epistle to the Hebrews.
He read, It's a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.
That's the sort of magical expression.
Then we're getting the psychological, spiritual reality or the existential reality.
And so he does it at the bottom of 355.
There was a big party.
Everyone in town went to it.
After dinner, he walked into the middle of the room with a paper in his hand, a formal declaration to the chief of his department who was present.
The declaration he read aloud to the whole assembly.
It contained a full account of the crime in every detail.
I cut myself off as a monster.
God has visited me.
He said in conclusion, I want to suffer for my sin.
And then he brought out and laid on the table all the things he'd been keeping for 14 years that he thought would prove his crime.
Well, then strange things happen.
But you got it already, I hope.
The basic point is: confession is necessary because if you've done something wrong, you're isolated.
This is sort of the extremist version, and you're the most extremely isolated.
That if you've just, I don't know, stolen something, that's a secret too, that you keep, and if it was important enough for you to do it, then it's a part of you that keeps you from getting in a full intimate relationship with people you care about.
It's a secret.
You can't tell anybody.
So, what kind of confession do you need?
Will it help to talk to a priest who's sworn to secrecy about this and shouldn't even testify in a trial, even if you tell him you're a murderer?
Certainly not.
That won't get you back in touch with your wife and your kids.
And will it help to secretly, you know, before God, suffer for what you've done?
Well, that won't help either.
The way Dostoevsky sets it up, which is very interesting, is that crimes isolate you, and confession reunites you.
See, that's what's happening in his cell when the priests all come in and they all tell their nasty thoughts and the bad things they've done and what things they may have stolen and so forth.
And then he doesn't have to absolve them.
I mean, or he doesn't absolve them in any magical way.
He tells them, okay, now we all know your secret and we know you're sorry, and we're all part of it.
We're back together again.
That's the idea.
Anybody?
Okay, so now, but then comes the weirdness that would be in the movie that Woody Allen didn't make.
How are you going to end it?
Well, it turns out nobody believes that the Grand Inquisitor is guilty.
Sorry.
Nobody believes that Michael, the mysterious visitor, is guilty.
And that's because he's been behaving like such a good father and good member of the community all this time.
They can't believe that he would ever kill his lover, his girlfriend.
And the question to ask is: would he, the man that he is at the time he's confessing?
Would he be the kind of guy to kill his girlfriend?
Certainly not.
It's the puzzle of people on death row, after 15 years on death row, reading the Bible and feeling terrible about what they've done, are now different people, and then they're going to put them in the electric chair or not.
I suppose the Christians, I think that this person has been reborn, and the people who are picketing and saying no capital punishment are Christians, and the secular people are saying he's the same guy he always was, and he's a murderer, never mind whether he's transformed or not.
And so Dostoevsky raises the question, and he sort of dodges it by having the mysterious visitor.
The mysterious visitor is happy because he's now recognized for what he is, namely a good man who would never kill anybody.
And that's all Dostoevsky needs.
So he gets him off the stage.
He dies in a hurry in prison.
So at the bottom of 356, he says, second sense, the nature of his illness I can't explain.
They said it was an ailment of the heart.
Dostoevsky loves to make these relations between the sort of physical body and the emotions that you have.
It's an illness of the emotions.
But it became known that the doctors had been induced by his wife to look into his mental condition and had come to the conclusion that it was a case of insanity.
Well, Dostoevsky thinks, like, psychologists don't understand anything, doctors don't understand anything because they're looking for the physical causes of spiritual things, and there aren't any.
They operate on two different levels.
You can't mix them up.
So, anyway, so and so he dies in the middle of 357.
He says, God has had pity on me and is calling me to Him.
I know that I'm dying, but I feel joy and peace for the first time after so many years.
There's been heaven in my heart.
There's where heaven is.
From the moment I did what I had to do, now I dare to love my children and to kiss them.
And so now we've got the whole story.
That's what confession is.
And so many things are happening at once.
Dostoevsky is just amazed at how many things he's juggling at once.
Not only does the Zosima change the life of the mysterious visitor radically.
not fighting in the duel, but the mysterious visitor changes the life of Zosima radically, because it's the mysterious visitor's transformation from hell to heaven, in effect, that makes Zosima decide to go into the monastery.
So the end of the chapter is, but I held my tongue, namely about the truth of the murder, and very shortly after I left the town, and five months later, by God's grace, I entered upon the safe and blessed path, following the unseen finger that had guided me so clearly to it.
Now, I used to think the unseen finger that guided him to the monastery was the mysterious visitor.
But it isn't, because it says, but I remember in my prayers to this day the servant of God, Michael Michiel, who suffered so greatly.
So that's not the unseen finger.
So who guided him into the monastery?
It's this mystery.
What movie is it?
Is it Sundance Kid?
No, I don't think so.
There's a movie with the same people in it, where there's somebody watching over Redford the Kid all the time, but you only see through the car, windshield, and so forth what this person is seeing.
Do you remember that?
Anyway, never mind.
But it's, yeah.
What's a childhood memory?
Yeah, but not.
Yes, you know that.
Right.
Never mind, I talk about the movie.
I mean, I was just suddenly struck by this funny fact that there's an unseen, literally an unseen finger pointing the way in that movie.
But what is the unseen finger?
That we don't know yet.
Beatrice is right.
It must be a childhood memory.
Have anybody read far enough to know what childhood memory that could be?
You shouldn't think.
Well, you do.
I mean, if they've read, if they've read far enough.
Yeah, but I don't know how many people are keeping up, but you should know whose finger led him, pointed him to the monastery.
Do you know?
His brother, his brother.
We haven't talked at all about his brother.
We have to have a whole lecture on his brother.
His brother, very important existentializing.
A really interesting, complicated existentializing is going on there.
But let's see.
So now let's get this straight.
I want to just catch up.
350.
I want to see that I've read all the passages that are important.
Yeah, that's right.
Ah, yeah, there's one.
I knew some little thing was missing.
Again, I mean, I'm just showing you, and you have to learn to do it, that Dostoevsky, if he feels that he hasn't said it enough yet, will be saying again and again what he thinks is important to existentialize.
This one, you go way back to 357, and remember I said that Dostoevsky said that the answers to the antinomies of the Grand Inquisitor are in the sayings of Zosima.
And so we should see that the sayings of Zosima is, and it's that, that's where he's talking about the mysterious visitor.
Ah, 371 is what I want.
No?
Ah, 371, yes.
I mean, just summing it up, what repeating it.
Fathers and teachers, I ask, what is hell?
Maybe Dostoevsky isn't sure we've got it yet.
I maintain that it is the suffering of being unable to love.
Once an infinite exist once in infinite existence, immeasurable in time and space, a spiritual creature was given on this coming to ear was given on his coming to earth the power of saying, I am and I love.
This again, hell is the suffering of being unable to love.
That's just the other side of saying heaven is being able to love.
And there is going to be somebody, namely obviously a Savior, who comes to earth and tells people about love and shows people how to do it.
You might ask yourself who that is, but I'm not going to say yet.
So let me see.
He gets back in the community.
Okay, so we've done that.
Now I have to think about whether to start the miracle.
I think that's a crazy idea since I have to leave anyway.
But I guess I'll spend a minute setting it up so we can just jump into it next time.
Remember that the miracle is going to be the tough one.
Because a miracle, one would think, would go against the laws of physics and chemistry.
That's what a miracle is, you would think.
And yet the existentializing says we don't want Christianity to go around committing themselves to things that are going to get them in trouble with science.
Science is going to take over the material world.
You better have a story about miracles that is in the world of the spirit, to talk like Pierre Guard.
How can that be?
Well, we're going to find out.
So the next, now, and what's the antinomy?
The question is to keep in mind, we're going to get a demonstration of the answer to the question: can people live without miracles when the situation in their life is extremely desperate?
On 290.
Not 15 lines from the bottom.
Is the nature of men such that they can reject miracles in the great moments of their life, the moments of their deepest, most agonizing spiritual difficulties, cling only to the free verdict of the heart?
What do you think?
What does Dostoevsky think?
What does Sosima think?
Let's just say, what does Dostoevsky think?
Can people, who expects them to, without any miracles, cling to the free verdict of the heart?
Jesus in the Grand Inquisitor story.
Always, you've got to be free.
You take responsibility.
God isn't going to help you.
Your priest isn't going to help you.
And of course, the other side says, no, of course, in the middle of the page, there's this weak and unruly bunch of men, and they can't, in crises in their life, get along without miracles.
Otherwise, they'll lose their faith.
Now, it's very, very interesting what Dostoevsky does with this.
I will just tell you two more places than I'm going to run.
Well, no, I think I'll stop.
But the issue of the miracle is that Father Zosima's body decomposes and begins to smell bad prematurely.
And the question is, how does that affect Alyasha?
That's one question.
That's going to be the test of whether a very religious person in a very big crisis, the death of his elder, can get along without miracles.
And you will have to keep your eyes open for that.
The second question, then that I just want to keep your eyes open for, is how is the death and this isn't the crucial laws of physics and chemistry story, but it's relevant.
How is the the decomposition of Zosima's cor corpse a miracle?
That is a kind of anti-miracle showing that he's a bad guy?
Is normally the fact that elders' bodies stay a lot longer before they begin to smell bad show that they perform miracles than Zosima doesn't?
Or is Zosima's smelling bad just a perfectly normal following of the laws of physics and chemistry?
Dostoevsky gives you scattered around in ways which he never collects the answer to that question.
You should expect which answer are you going to get?
What do you think?
Which way is it?
Is it an anti-miracle?
Is generally the non-decomposition of elders a positive miracle?
Or is this something that you can explain by the laws of nature?
Remember, it's not a normal.
He's decomposing much sooner than he one would normally expect.
I'll give you this puzzle.
Okay, that's an after vacation.
So you've got lots of interesting questions.
Does Alyasha need a miracle?
Does he get a miracle?
Want miracle?
And did the b and how do you explain the premature decomposition of Zosima?
Yeah.
Wait, what?
Ah, good question.
Let me look.
You have to get through all you you're almost there when you read what you're supposed to read for today, because all you have to do is get to the uh you get to four nineteen.
That's what you have to get to before that.
So read to four nineteen for sure after the lecture, right after vacation.