Okay, now I'm ready to talk about Hiroshima Monomur, which is, I hope you enjoyed it, if that's the right word, sort of taken up by it, overwhelmed by it.
It's so hard and so deep and so dense and so utterly Kierkegaardian.
I trust you did see that.
We'll see as we discuss it.
It's so Kierkegaardian that I feel pretty sure that Marguerite Duras must have read Fear and Trembling.
Why not?
Everybody reads Fear and Trembling.
She's a French intellectual.
But if anybody happens to ever come across anything which tells them that she's read it, I would love to know.
Be sure and tell me.
I sort of hope she hasn't read it, because I'd rather think that if anybody thinks about these issues, they come to this conclusion because this is the way the phenomenon goes, and that the fact that it's exact in agreement with Fear and Trembling should be sort of evidence for fear and trembling rather than evidence for the influence of fear and trembling.
But it would be nice just to know.
Okay, let's start.
It starts in a way the sort of cleverness and deepness of which only becomes evident much, much later in the movie.
In fact, it starts purposely, completely misleading you about what's going on.
First, there's this ambiguous picture of the lovers, and according to the scenario, they're supposed to be covered by dust from the atomic bomb and perspiration from making love.
I mean, I don't know if that comes across.
It doesn't come across to me particularly, but if it does, then so much the better.
But their voices come across clearly.
Obviously, it's not what they're saying to each other.
You could hardly want to carry on such a flat and detached conversation while making love, but it's what they're thinking, I presume.
And what they're thinking is, and now we get to the text.
I'll read a lot from the text because how else can you tell what's going on?
In the movie, it goes by so fast.
So it begins.
This is the very beginning, two sentences.
And those two sentences are going to come back again and again, literally or sort of in the background, till the very last words of the movie.
He says, you saw nothing in Hiroshima, nothing.
And she says, I saw everything, everything.
And then they go through all kinds of variations on that, which I won't go through all of, but at least a few more.
So she says, listen, I know, I know everything.
And he says, nothing.
You know nothing.
And then more important, because the issue in the movie is about forgetting, she says, listen to me.
Like you, I know what it is to forget.
No, you don't know what it is to forget.
Like you, I have a memory.
I know what it is to forget.
No, you don't have a memory.
Like you, I tried with all my might not to forget.
Like you, I forgot.
Like you, I wanted to have an inconsolable memory, a memory of shadows and stone.
And he doesn't say, no, not like me, but he could, because he denies everything, she says, during that first theme.
And how do you naturally take that first theme?
Anybody want to say?
I mean, I think everybody must have the same reaction when they see it.
They're supposed to.
Who's right about, did she understand it?
Did she see it?
Or not?
Well, here, let me give you another clue to how I think you're supposed to understand it, which I skipped because it was sort of an obvious one.
She says, I've always wept over the fate of Hiroshima.
Always.
He, no, what would you have to cry about?
Now, what does that say?
Here's this tourist from France in bed with this Japanese man in Hiroshima, and she's telling him she always wept over the fate of Hiroshima.
And he's saying, What would you have cried about?
So, what's going on?
It's sort of obvious.
I'm not trying to be subtle, but you're supposed to have an immediate reaction to it.
Somebody say, That's what she feels.
Well, no, more extreme than that.
He's telling her she can't understand anything.
She hasn't seen anything.
She's had nothing to weep about.
What right does he have to tell her that?
What does he mean?
She wasn't there.
He's been through one of the greatest disasters maybe in the history of the world.
I don't know how many thousand people killed in a few, in a minute or two.
Anyway, in a huge disaster, which it turns out later his family was at, meaning his mother, his father, his siblings, his wife, if he had one, and his kids, if he had one, was some.
Interestingly enough, we don't know, and he doesn't bother to tell her how many there were or where they were killed or anything like that.
But he's been through this great big disaster, and she's coming as a tourist making a movie, and she's saying, I've seen it all.
And he says, no, you haven't seen anything.
And she says, I've understood it all.
And he says, no, you haven't understood anything.
And it gets clearest when she said, I really wept over all what happened to you guys in Hiroshima.
And he says, why were you crying about?
Compared, of course, to what he's been through.
The disaster was so terrible that uh uh she's bound to misunderstand it, n bound not to be able to grasp it.
And s he I just want to go through the place where he says that he's lost everybody, but he says it so fast that you hardly notice.
And that's important.
It's as if he hardly notices.
He says, Is that where I want to be?
Wait a minute, I'm sure I am where I want to be.
I'm 28.
You guys he lost.
Oh, yeah, okay, that's what I want.
Okay, I'm 28.
I'll give you the pages in the scenarios I read things, so in case you want to go back and read them, you can.
She says, you were here at Hiroshima?
He laughing.
No, of course I wasn't.
She, that's true.
How stupid of me.
But my family, he says, but my family was at Hiroshima.
I was off fighting the war.
And she, a stroke of luck, eh?
And he, weighing the pros and cons, after some hesitation, yes.
Meaning that, it turns out, he wanted to die having lost everybody, and but he didn't.
Exactly similar thing, let's admit it now, that happened to her.
But of course, he doesn't know that.
For him, at this point, still, she's just a French movie actress that happens to be there.
So and it's true that if he had lost all those and she had lost nothing, she wouldn't have been able to understand.
But it turns out she had an exactly equal world-destroying disaster.
Although they didn't blow up all of Nefu Never, from her point of view, everything she cared about in her world and made her life meaningful was destroyed when her German lover was killed.
And just as everything presumably that he cared about was destroyed when Hiroshima was totally wiped off the face of the earth.
And you have trouble realizing that, although not much trouble after you see the movie a few times and begin to collect your wits.
But the translation in a certain place does everything it can to confuse you.
It's hardly to be called a translation.
On page 13, the final words of the introducer, whoever that is, I don't think we're ever told who it is.
Somebody who's writing a synopsis anyway says, in this translation, it says, at the end, they name places, names that are not names.
And this is really French fancy talk, what John Searle, my colleague, calls frog fog.
I mean, it's all very, they name places, names that are not names, and then goes on.
It is as though through them, all of Hiroshima was in love with all of Never.
She says to him, Hiroshima, that's your name.
That has nothing to do with what happens at the end.
By the end of today, you will see.
But already, it has nothing to do with what it says in the French.
It's not a translation.
It's a sort of a hallucination.
The translation says the disaster of the woman head-shaved in Never and the disaster of Hiroshima correspond exactly, which is the right thing to say.
I don't know where the translation got this, but you're meant to see that she has seen and understood and experienced exactly what he has understood and experienced insofar as, and only insofar as, they both experienced world-destroying disasters.
Now, they certainly haven't had the same experience in the sense of how they came out of it, what kind of people they became afterward.
That's the whole movie.
But they started out in the same place.
And then now we need a kind of story about world-destroying disasters and about worlds.
I misunderstood this movie for about the first ten years, and it led many, many gullible undergraduates to confusion, I imagine, if they were sensitive.
Because I thought, well, let's start.
What is the first level of reaction to world-destroying disaster?
Well, it's nature.
And nature, which is the vegetation around the town, doesn't have much of a problem.
It comes back.
In fact, it comes back even more healthy and happy than it was before on page 19.
On the 15th day, Hiroshima was blanketed with flowers.
There were cornflowers and blah, blah, blah, lots of flowers.
And they rose again from the ashes with extraordinary vigor, quite unheard of for flowers till then.
By the way, that's a kind of mystery to me.
They're loose ends.
Nobody has a totally complete interpretation.
I would have thought the flowers ought to come back just the way they left.
I mean, oblivious to this kind of world-destroying event.
Flowers don't have worlds and they don't have world-destroying events.
And why they got sort of pepped up by it, I don't know.
But yeah, I wonder.
I mean, perhaps, maybe that's a true story.
I mean, if it was a true story, that would explain it.
Maybe they do get sort of radiated into a better form of life.
And the fish, too, it turns out, get radiated into a better form of life.
That was on 19.
On 24, he says that the fish regularly came back rich with gray and blue, depending on the hour and so forth.
And so the fish were back in plenty and the vegetation.
Then he says new vegetation will arise from the sand and so forth.
But it's nature anyway.
Nature unperturbed, to say the least, and that's all I need to make the point I want by the disaster.
Yeah.
Yes, that's true too.
But they had to throw away the first batches of fish.
But finally, the fish kept coming, and after the radioactive ones were thrown away, apparently there was plenty of fish.
The problem really is that the question we're going to keep asking yourself in the back of your mind, and what about the town or the city or the city of Hiroshima?
Is it also like nature?
Well, I certainly thought so.
That's my 10-year mistake, or maybe more.
I didn't count how long I was wrong because I didn't know I was wrong.
And because you get sort of fooled by the fact that they have this conversation about how Hiroshima is brighter and more busy than ever, and she loves cities that are bright all night and active all night.
And I thought, aha, well, nature and objects like cities, they just bounce back.
And for some odd reason, they bounce back even more peppy than they were before.
But so we don't know yet if Hiroshima really is part of like the vegetables.
And what is it?
It's all about lower natures in Kierkegaard language.
You recognize Fear and Trembling talk in What I'm Saying, I hope, on 72, where he says about two-thirds of the way down, deeper natures never forget themselves and become something other than they were, so the night will remember everything, but lower natures forget themselves and become something new.
Thus, the butterfly has altogether forgotten that it was a caterpillar.
Perhaps it can so completely forget in turn that it was a butterfly that can become a fish.
I mean, I have the wild idea that Kierkegaard thinks too, like Marguerite Durvas, somehow, that nature gets better and better.
Caterpillars become butterflies.
And I don't know about butterflies becoming fishes, but the fact that she goes right from vegetables to fishes.
I mean, these are tiny signs, maybe, that this book is in the back of her mind.
I don't know, and we don't care.
What we care about is that the lower natures just forget what's going on and just keep doing their thing.
And that's the first thing.
But people aren't part of nature.
And so we get to the next level: the mediated beings like us.
And the person who most sort of mediates and meditates and thinks about all this, who is that?
I mean, you guys must have been sort of hit over the head by the movie.
I understand, but not so completely.
Who?
I couldn't hear you.
The girl, the French woman.
Yes, the French woman, of course, she's constantly talking about what happened and what Hiroshima is like and what she understands and what she sees and what she felt.
And the Japanese man is just silent.
He never talks about what happened before or what's happening then.
It's just not something that he mediates and reflects.
He doesn't reflect on it.
Whatever he does, it's something different.
We'll get to that.
But she's reflecting on it all the time.
And there is now in her a kind of struggle between the part of her that wants to remember, we've got to think about her disaster now.
The part of her that wants to remember her disaster, the death of her German lover, resists the part of her that's a part of nature, which would, in general, just forget and go on.
Now, this is a Marguerite Diracim.
It has nothing to do anywhere in Kierkegaard, but it's nice.
What you get in her is a kind of attempt to be in eternity, which is her madness, and to get out of nature, which is out of temporality, that low, immediate temporality, just sort of one thing after another.
So, something that Kierkegaard wouldn't mention that is interesting to the movie is that she says on page 98 that her hair grows back.
Then she says that she got over her madness in the spring, that she suddenly says she has children, sort of knocks them over because she hasn't really mentioned that she's even got a husband or anything, or a wife.
And she constantly is resisting all this sort of natural change that's trying to drag her down into lower immediacy.
So on 23, this is happening.
She says, she says to him, like you, I have a memory.
I know what it is to forget.
He says, no, you don't have a memory.
We won't know for a long time why he says that, because she seems to be totally obsessed with this memory.
She dreams about the German.
That moment that goes by so fast when she sees the Japanese man's hand on the bed and she sees instead the hand of the dying German lover, or, of course, the whole time when she thinks that the French guy is her German lover because he's gotten her drunk and taken over the role of that.
So she's constantly remembering.
And he says, no, you don't have a memory.
And we have to see whether he has.
We don't know that.
So she, like you, I too have tried with all my might not to forget.
Like you, I forgot.
Like you, I wanted to have an inconsolable memory, a memory of shadows and stones.
See the photograph by the light of the bicycle on the stone at that point.
She says, for my part, I struggled with all my might every day against the horror of no longer understanding at all the reason for remembering.
Like you, I forgot.
Well, she's telling him a whole lot of things of the Japanese soldier, which in fact turn out to be false, every bit of them.
But she doesn't know any better.
She's just projecting on him correctly what she's been doing.
And what she's been doing is trying to preserve eternity in time in her way to preserve this ideal love and to keep, if it means going mad, she'll go mad, and she did for a while to stay in eternity.
But then when spring came, more of nature, then the sun came and it got warm in the cellar, and she came out of eternity.
But she's still using all of her energy to preserve the memory of the German lover.
This gets clearer and clearer, but it's clear already.
She wants to be in mediation.
She wants to be in some kind of ideal memory of the meaning, of the meaning of the love that she had and lost.
And she wants that memory in stone.
So when I say madness and eternity, I'll just give you the pages.
So she says, she was in eternity, and she says, I don't remember how, after they put her in the cellar, she says, I don't remember anymore how long.
He says, how long?
She says, eternity.
And that's really what it was like for her.
She was like crazy.
She says, what pain, what pain in my heart?
It's unbelievable.
Oh, and yeah, that's more pain.
This is interesting.
Subplot.
She's suffering not only because she lost the German, but because everybody is happy, because it's the end of the war in France.
And she's the only one unhappy because her lover is dead, and moreover, he was a German, and now she's having her hair cut, and her father's being humiliated.
Everything bad is happening.
And she's so miserable, and everybody else is so happy, and this makes her bitter.
And this, so she spits in the face of her mother.
Do you remember what the Japanese man says about that?
It's one of those moments when you know that he also went through this kind of thing.
She says, I can't just turn to it, I don't think, but she says, and I was they were all happy, and I was in pain, and he says, and your mother comes to you, and you spit in your mother's face.
And she says, yes, of course, of course, you would know.
And he says, it was a beautiful day in France when they dropped the bomb on Hiroshima, and everybody in France was celebrating when Hiroshima was killed.
Everything is parallel.
That's what the right translation of the beginning of the comment says.
Yeah.
I know what you're talking about, about her time.
Okay, good.
I mean that she, it's going to get clearer, but I'll try to be clear as I can at this point.
She wants to preserve the memory of this perfect love, remembers the moment when she cries, it was my first love, and he slaps her.
I mean, she is so into this, feeling sorry for herself and feeling that this was this perfect story.
And remember, she's never told anybody the story, not even her own husband.
She's into preserving this special thing about her.
If it weren't for this special thing about her, she'd just be like the fishes, and that she would just go, as it looks like maybe he has, just forgotten the whole thing.
And she's not going to forget it.
And so being in eternity is the wrong way to do it, because that means living the way she was living in the cellar, just sort of staring at the cat and licking the wall and just sort of out of touch with reality.
But when after a while she got so she could live in the world and still be in something like eternity.
So he says, and then one day, my love, you come out of eternity.
And she says, yes, it takes a long time.
They told me it took a very long time.
And then she says, but finally she did.
She said the winter was over.
And then, but she says, it's terrible.
I'm beginning to remember you less and less.
You see, every time she gets out of eternity, out of that sort of totally hypnotized state, she starts remembering, and time starts making her start forgetting him.
And she starts telling her story again to him.
That's when she's drinking in the bar.
By the way, you remember the name of the bar?
I mean, every detail in this movie is so perfect.
I mean, that's the Casablanca.
And what about the two lovers in Casablanca?
You've also seen Casablanca.
What are they?
Well, they're nights of resignation.
Of course, she has to go off with her lover, who her husband, I guess he is, who's the resistance person, and he has to stay where he is in his bar in Casablanca.
And though they love each other, and finally, after all kinds of trouble, get together, they just have to remember, they have to just have the memory of it.
So there were two nights of faith.
And what's happening in this movie is, of course, somebody, did I say two nights of faith, sorry, two nights of resignation, because they're not sitting around waiting to ever get back together again.
They've made this.
Doesn't he say something about it being a beautiful memory?
I wonder if he does.
We'd have to look.
But anyway, she certainly does.
Yeah.
We'll always have Paris.
Well, that's it.
That's the phrase, though, isn't it?
That's the same thing.
They've got a shared memory of the...
That's perfect.
Of that one day they were together in Paris when they got their signals crossed and missed each other.
I forget why.
But that moment is in eternity.
It's out of time.
It's perfect.
And it's what they've got.
Yeah, Beatrice, do you want to say something more?
That's perfect to bring that up.
Grief.
Well, she is in something, but it isn't grief because, how will I?
Well, depends on what you mean by grief, of course.
She's suffering sorrow and misery and so forth.
If you mean by grief, what I was trying to put on the board with my MIT diagram, where grief means the way you interiorize the person you love so that you can love another person, then she wasn't in grief because her basic problem in the movie is she can't love him, though she wants to, and though she sort of does, because, I mean, just we're jumping ahead, but it doesn't hurt to remind you.
She's in the state, if this is her, of trying to keep the ideal memory of that relationship.
And that's not grief.
Well, her big problem is she's so lonely and she's so longs for him, and she's so sorry that she'll never see him again because he's dead.
And if grief, I want to say, is something more this way, which is that you interiorize the person and are open to another.
I can't say more about it yet because I'm not ready to bring it into the story.
Yeah, but go ahead, I can listen anyway.
Okay, that's true, but she's in a kind of eternity anyway, she says.
That is, she's what you can say is she's in something that is neither lower immediacy for sure, and she's not in higher immediacy either, for sure.
And she has various versions, I think, of mediation, whether she's reflecting on it, whether she's able to think about it, or whether she's in this sort of dazed state where it's all she does is sort of live in agony.
But whatever they are, they don't produce a situation in which she can't get into the right relation to the Japanese man.
We have to talk more about that, and that's what the whole movie is about.
And so let's go on with that.
So finally, she manages to have some kind of eternity in time without being mad.
That's where we are.
And that's when she leaves the room.
But there's something about her that she takes, so to speak, with her, namely, some sense of not being in the world, but being outside the world, outside of time, or trying hard to be, and more or less tricky.
I mean, trying very hard and maybe succeeding and maybe failing, it isn't clear until the end of the movie, to be outside of time and finitude and always living in terms of the love of the German soldier.
That's how it should be for her.
But, of course, it's hard to do, particularly if nature is constantly sort of undermining what you're doing.
But let's go on, and you'll see it's clearer.
So, what is she then?
After she comes out of eternity and into being the kind of person she is, and she's a person who is serene and joyful and at the same time, always sad.
And she's got what Kierkegaard calls comfort in sorrow.
And you can see it in Fear and Trembling, it's all over the place, but I'll just read you one place on 74.
In infinite resignation, there is peace and repose and consolation in pain.
And you see a picture of her in the book here, still from the movie, which is just perfect, which shows her looking extremely sad and yet beautiful and calm and so forth.
And Marguerite Duras has a sense of this.
I want to show you that.
Let me see.
When the author describes what she wants her to look like and do, oh, yeah, here's the picture, but holding it up won't help.
It's the picture.
You see her when she's looking at the Japanese man sleeping.
And she looks so sad and so loving and so much in a kind of repose and so tortured all at the same time.
It's really very remarkable.
But let me go back to something I can convey.
Okay, so it's when Marguerite Dura writes about her, then you get a clue as to what she thinks is going on.
But I've lost where it is.
Oh, I think it's way back in the beginning where we're describing these people.
Yeah.
What happened in Nversre, her native city, in that region called Nievre, where she was brought up?
What happened to her to make her the way she is?
Now, how is she?
So free and yet so haunted, so honest and yet so dishonest, so equivocal and yet so clear, so predisposed to chance love affairs, so cowardly when faced with love.
Well, that's a tremendously good description of her, and she's tremendously good to have brought it to the screen.
But let's go over them one by one.
In what way is she free and haunted?
Well, take the case of her wandering around the hotel room, drinking her tea and feeling happy after they'd been making love and I think after they took a shower, and then all of a sudden, free and sort of serene as she is, what happens to her?
What haunts her?
Remember, she sees the hand of the German lover.
I mean, there's always the German lover sort of there just on the margin of whatever she's doing.
And now, the easier one is so honest and yet so dishonest.
I'm not going to tell you that one.
What's the dishonesty?
She hasn't told her husband and kids, or let's just stick to her husband, that she's not at all acting like the person she really is.
She isn't letting anyone get intimate with her, and she isn't letting anyone see what really matters to her.
So she can be sort of trivially honest about her affairs and about her life and everything.
She just sort of bluntly tells the Japanese man that she likes men, that she's had lots of affairs, that her husband doesn't know, and so forth.
And it doesn't, it just, all those kind of trivial honesties are possible because basically she's just living a kind of lie.
And so equivocal and yet so clear is the same thing.
Somehow you can see everything that she's thinking, particularly when she's constantly sort of telling him that she's leaving him.
She's very clear about it, and yet she's always sort of not doing it and taking it back and showing how much she longs to stay with him.
And so she's trying to be clear, but there's something always happening that's sort of messing up the clarity.
Now let's go back and see.
So that's because she's what?
What was, I don't have to ask you.
She's a knight of infinite resignation.
Of course.
I mean, let me, how many understood that when you saw the movie?
I'm just curious for future good.
Good.
I just don't want to think that I'm showing, I mean, that I have to make a speech before the movie.
You're good for you all.
Yes, of course.
She's a knight of resignation.
A beautiful example.
And that's what's why it's so great to have it in this course, because it all seems pretty hard to get when Kierkegaard's telling you in his poetic, philosophical way, but you can see it when you see her.
She's a knight of resignation, she's got infinite sadness.
Why infinite sadness?
And why infinite resignation?
Well, that means that it's bigger than any of the things in the world.
None of the situations in the world are what's making her sad.
Everything about her existence is defined as sad.
That's what makes it infinite.
Everything that would ever come into her world is already sad.
It's just her way of being that I'm trying to say is sad.
That's what makes her infinite resignation and infinite sorrow.
Anybody can be sorrow about some specific thing or other, but she's made this movement of resignation where she's given up the German lover in the finite and temporal altogether.
And she had better because he's dead.
But I mean, she has done it.
She has given him up altogether.
And that has changed her world so that everything is colored by that.
And that's, of course, why she can't get together with the Japanese man.
The infinite sadness, the infinite resignation has put her into a situation in which, if she does get involved with the Japanese man, I mean, besides just sexually involved, but really admits that she loves him, and they both agree they're going to stay together.
Then we get stuff that starts happening at the end of the movie, which I'm not ready quite to go to yet.
Her world starts falling apart because she's defined in terms of the relation, the love and lost.
She loved and lost her first love, that foreign German soldier, et cetera.
That's her story.
And there wouldn't be any her if she didn't have that story.
So let's go back and trace the story.
So when she lost the lover, she wanted to be dead too.
That's one way to see it.
And that's the moment in which she's getting so sorry for herself, so deep into her sorrow, that he snaps her out of it.
But it gives her this kind of ease and detachment that I already just read you, I think.
There's another one, I don't think so.
No, it gives her that business of being haunted and yet at ease and so forth that we talked about.
It also, another place Kierkegaard said, the knight says, the Knights of Resignation are bold.
She is also bold.
She's bold because she's invulnerable.
She can say anything and do anything.
Nothing can really touch her emotionally.
That's both her success and her problem.
It's a success because she holds on to the most meaningful thing in her life, her first love.
But it's a problem because then she can't have any real intimacy.
So she's totally lonely.
And she has all these sexual encounters because she's so lonely.
But what she really wants is to be with a person, really with somebody.
She says at one point when she's falling and really getting involved with him, how great it is to be with somebody sometime.
But in most of the time, she's alone because she's keeping all of her real feelings to herself.
So, for instance, on 68, that's where she says it.
She says, all of a sudden, she says in the middle of the page, oh, how good it is to be with someone sometime.
And that's because she's for a moment feeling close to him.
I mean, it's very complicated because she's constantly sort of risking falling in love with him, getting involved with him, getting back into the finite and temporal, really, you know, revealing herself instead of hiding herself.
And she's both terribly tempted to this because the Kierkegaard jargon, you'll be in despair unless you get the finite and temporal in your life, and she hasn't got it.
There's nothing finite and temporal in her life that has crucial meaning for her.
The only thing that has crucial meaning for her is her first love of the German soldier.
And that can only keep its crucial meaning for her, the way she set it up, as long as nothing in this world has crucial meaning for her.
So she's in that, that's her interesting, and that's just for Kierkegaard, pure Kierkegaard, that's the situation of the night of resignation, and we just have to follow it out.
So let's follow it out.
For instance, I don't remember where it is in the movie, but I saw it once and wrote it down here: that there's a point where she reaches out to caress the Japanese man when they're in bed together, and instead of a caress, her hand turns into a fist.
Anybody remember that?
That went by so fast?
I didn't see it this round.
But it's just a neat, and again, the details are amazing.
I mean, that's her fighting off this involvement that she's also getting being dragged into.
Okay, so the Japanese man understands what the problem is, and his job is to get her out of this narrative, out of this story, out of this identity.
And so there they go to the Casablanca, oddly enough, or interestingly enough, and he gets her to tell her story.
And to put it in a kind of slogan, which I like when I could think of them, he wants to get the story out of her, into the public, because that's the way of getting her out of her story.
Because it's only when it's a special secret story that could never be told, then it's hers.
But if it becomes a story that she can tell, and then it's something that somebody else could have experienced too, then it's not really hers anymore, and she'd be free of it.
That's what he's trying to do.
Yeah, Beatrice.
Has she left the ethical?
Oh, definitely, definitely she's outside the ethical.
She remembers she says she's dubious of the ethics of others.
She's outside the ethical because the only authority that has any claim on her is the love of the German.
And if the love of the German would require her, for instance, to kill the Japanese man, she'd have to kill the Japanese man.
It just doesn't happen that way, the way nobody set up the plot that way.
But she would kill to keep that pure love of the Japanese man because that's what gives her life meaning.
That's the only thing that's crucial.
Yeah.
And you try, and the therapist tries to get it out of you and get you to say it and see it and reflect on it as something that you can get rid of because it doesn't sort of permeate you and your world so completely that you live in it like the goldfish in the water.
Yeah, and that's what he that's the Japanese is trying to give her a very intense one evening of therapy with lots of beer.
And it works.
I mean, the interesting thing is he gets her to tell the story.
And that has, I mean, and he thought, he thinks now he's done it.
Now he's freed her.
He can have her and they can go off together.
You're just supposed to bracket the fact that they're both happily married.
That's not, I mean, it just doesn't interest Marguerite Durat at all because there is this big metaphysical or whatever you want to call it, theological issue on the table.
And he would have, he thought he succeeded.
And he did succeed.
He succeeded in getting her to sort of objectify, reflect on, and mediate even more than it was before her story.
And then to say one more sentence, and now we'll soon see in a minute how he totally backfires.
I mean, the fact that he did that was the end for him.
Go ahead.
Even though she's probably reflecting on it, and she's always started just a moment.
She can.
That's right.
It's something, it's what you're raising.
I can see as I answer you, you're raising interesting questions that are making me say puzzling things.
I mean, there's so many kinds of mediation.
It's as if she is constantly reflecting on it and keeping it in front of her as a kind of ideal and a kind of picture.
But that's still inner.
To be really mediated, it would have to be made public and put in public language, and that's just what she doesn't want because then it would lose its totally private, specific thing.
So it's sort of half-mediated with her.
I mean, that's, and the Japanese man is trying to make it totally public and universal and intelligible, and she wants to resist that.
Yeah, that's right.
That means that, well, that's tied up with something very interesting and important, what you're saying.
Let me see if I can.
It's so subtle and complicated that I don't understand it too well, and I don't know how to begin to say it.
Let me think a minute.
They've got some secret in common, and that's what you're asking about.
And if he were being pulled into her secret, that wouldn't be the right thing to be happening.
So he's happy that he's the only one who knows.
See, I'm trying to get, he's happy because they share.
I mean, you could bring it back to the you never saw anything.
Yes, I saw everything.
He now sees that they share what they saw in Hiroshima.
They saw world disaster.
And they understood what they understood in Hiroshima.
They understood world disaster.
And what was the third thing?
Oh, and they left, well, I don't know, leptover.
No, that's her thing.
At least those two things.
So he sees that he has this deep connection with her and always had it.
But now he sees that it gives him some kind of special right to her that her husband doesn't have, that nobody else has, because he's the only one who ever understood her.
That's the important thing.
And what's really important, I'm going to say it earlier than I wanted to say it, but it's so relevant now.
What is it that gives him this special access to her that nobody else has?
Yeah.
You're on the right track.
I don't think it's something I put in the she needs in the truth.
Because they both need that these limits of their life where she puts any principles on his person.
Yeah, you're on the right, exactly on the right track.
But you have to put it a little further to make it.
Why is he, at one point he sits up in bed and he looks at her when she says something about Never in some way, and she says, why do you care about Nevers?
And he says, I have come to understand that it was in Never that you became the person you are and so forth.
What's happening is he's the only one who can understand her, or maybe the only, maybe there are others, but in this case, he's the only one who's around who's succeeded in ever understanding her.
Because, and now comes the crucial thing, he had an identical disaster.
So he's understanding her through his experience of the disaster.
That's why he knows that she spit into her mother's face.
That's why he knows that she would want to get out of it if she could, and he's trying to help her get out of it, and he sees how she's trapped in it.
But the basic thing to remember is that he relates to her through his experience of the total destruction of everything that was important in his life and of Hiroshima.
And only because he's experienced that can he get to her.
Yeah.
Well, how come he can love her since she's stuck?
Why isn't he stuck?
Is that what you're saying?
Well, that's a terrific question.
It's got a one-sentence answer, but I'm not going to tell it.
Somebody, somebody, what's the answer?
I mean, we have to jump.
You're jumping way ahead, but we'll.
What is he?
Of course, he's a knight of faith.
He's got an entirely different relation to the disaster.
He did not turn the disaster into an ideal thing and get stuck on it.
And we're so close to getting the whole answer that I think we should just go on.
What did he do?
Well, he did it.
He turned it into something.
We don't know much about it yet.
It became a part of him such that he could get access to her and the world through it.
I mean, that's what that's.
He did this.
He's a knight of resignation.
He's a knight of faith.
They both had the disaster, but his relation to the disaster becomes his way of being open to other people in the world.
And her way of taking the disaster makes her totally self-sufficient and closed to other people in the world.
And that's because she's a knight of resignation.
And in other words, she's a knight of resignation, and he's a knight of faith.
Yeah.
Good, good, good.
All you guys are onto something.
Yeah.
You're half on it.
You need another piece, but you got it right.
Being an architect is very important, and it fits exactly with what he should be doing.
But it's not a thing about himself.
We need a new character on the scene.
We've talked about him.
We've talked about her.
Who else?
Not the German.
We never see the German.
There's only one other important character.
If I'm being a strange way to put it, it's Hiroshima.
Who said that?
In spite of my saying it in a crazy way, who said it?
You said it?
Somebody else, too.
Two people said it.
Somebody up here.
Anyway, yes, the third character on the scene is Hiroshima.
Because Hiroshima, he's Hiroshima, you know.
So you've got to figure this out.
When she says he's Hiroshima, she's right.
What is it about Hiroshima that's interesting?
Well, this is the thing I missed for 10 years.
I thought, well, Hiroshima bounced back with total energy and lots of lights, just as if it was lower immediacy.
And only people could be mediated and become higher immediacy.
But that's wrong.
And now let's talk about it while we're at it.
And don't let me forget the architect point.
But let's see.
Tell me things about Hiroshima.
What is the name of the hotel in Hiroshima?
The new Hiroshima.
That's interesting.
I mean, they could have named it the Hiroshima Hilton.
They could have just, you know, built it.
That would be to be like the fish.
I mean, they would just build a new hotel and give it a new name.
Or they could have just left the rubble of the hotel, the way they did leave the rubble, was one building.
What I'm asking is: what is the relation of the people of Hiroshima to the disaster?
And the answer's got to be: they don't forget it, and yet they never think about it.
You notice that he doesn't tell her which parents and relatives and wives and kids were killed.
He doesn't say, Come over here, I'll show you where our house used to be.
He doesn't think about the disaster at all.
But what everything he does think about, he thinks about in terms of the disaster.
Now we're back to the architect.
What's the role of an architect in Hiroshima?
It's to build the new Hiroshima, which is, in other words, to not get stuck in the disaster and live in the rubble.
That's what she's doing in the darkness of Nevair, but to build a new Hiroshima, which remembers that it was the old, that it was destroyed.
What else is there that reminds it that it was destroyed?
Well, there's that one destroyed building that they keep, a sort of cathedral-like.
And the museum, absolutely.
He doesn't go to the museum, but they've got a museum.
And they make peace movies there.
And at one point, he says, I think it's interesting, I couldn't find it in here, but I've heard it in the movie.
He says something, and he says, We don't joke about peace in Hiroshima, meaning this is a very, this is not just very serious, this is an absolutely serious issue to them, war and peace.
And they're always there making these peace movies.
And we're now, you with your architect, what else is he?
A politician.
And why is that something that is, again, related to the city and related in how he deals with things?
All right?
Well, he wants to, I couldn't hear you very well, but anyway, I think I heard you.
He wants to, the politicians are changing the world.
He's trying to change the world so that there won't be another disaster.
It isn't as if they've just forgotten the disaster.
But they don't think about the disaster.
They think about making a better world.
They think about making new buildings and a new hotel and so forth and so forth.
So what's interesting is that his whole way of life depends on having been devastated by the Hiroshima disaster.
To be a politician, to learn French, because they're about, I don't know really why.
He says because to read about the French Revolution.
Why not?
I don't know.
But anyway, to be a politician, to learn French, to be an architect, to fall in love with this woman who had a similar disaster.
Everything that we know about him, I mean, we don't know about his family and kids, but everything we know about him happens to him because his world was destroyed when Hiroshima was destroyed.
And he has taken it over so much.
I keep wanting to stress this.
This is the thing Kierkegaard doesn't understand.
This is what it is to get a new Isaac.
He has taken over the disaster in such a way as to forget it in the sense that he never thinks about it and to remember it in the sense that everything he thinks about, he thinks about in terms of it.
It's a very, very interesting move he makes.
And he makes it just right.
And the city makes it just right.
Okay, how do we do it?
Well, I think we've got to go on.
So let me go see.
We're not far behind where I want to be.
So let's contrast Hiroshima with Never for a minute.
I mean, Hiroshima is lively and thriving, but always also remembering, whereas Never is like she is.
Remember, he calls her Never at the end of the last line of the movie, just like she calls.
She sees that he's Hiroshima.
She sees that he's something she can't have, that he's been in the disaster and he's more alive and more in the finite and temporal than ever.
He sees that she's Never and he can't have her because what?
Because Never is frozen in the past.
If you could make the movie in black and white and color, Never would be in black and white, and Hiroshima really cries out to be in color.
If I were making the movie, maybe I'd have her in black and white and him in color.
You're lucky I'm not making the movie.
But that's the feeling you get.
And that's important.
And her memory of the German countryside is all sort of romantic and beautiful and so forth.
I don't think I have anything to say about that.
Well, it's all she's turning it, it's part of the ideal of this first love, hiding in the woods with this lover and so forth.
And okay, let's go on.
I'll get back to Hiroshima.
Well, how does his therapy backfire?
She tells him his story, her story.
And instead of getting it out of her, so to speak, so she can now get some distance from it, instead of sort of wallowing in her suffering, what happens is she gets convinced that she's been unfaithful to the German.
And that's the end for him.
That is, she's betrayed the one thing that gives meaning to her life by just turning it, as she keeps saying, turning it into a three-penny story, turning it into a song.
She means just turning it into something trivial that could have happened to anybody, not sort of a world-defining and world-destroying experience.
This is on 73.
To the German, she's talking, You are not quite dead.
I told our story.
I was unfaithful to you tonight with this stranger.
You see, it was a story that could be told.
For 14 years, I haven't found the taste of impossible love again since Nevair.
Look how I'm forgetting you.
Look at me.
That is, she's tempted now to turn him into an object or a memory, but a memory that she could now leave behind or do something else with and go on with the Japanese.
But she can't, she has no understanding of getting a new Isaac.
She has no understanding of this puzzling, amazing thing that people can do, which is really impossible irrationally.
Go through grief, make the first defining thing a part of themselves, so that everything they do, they do in terms of it, and remain open to a new finite temporal defining thing.
She can't do that.
And because she can't do that, she bounces back and forth between thinking that she's got to be true to the German or her life will lose all of its meaning, and thinking that she wants to get involved with the finite temporal Japanese man, really, with a profound intimacy and love.
And she can't do it.
And so she's telling, she's saying, Look to the German, I'm betraying you, I'm forgetting you.
And now comes this interesting move.
I didn't understand this for a long time.
Why?
What does she finally do to preserve the meaning of the love of the German, of her first love?
Because not being a knight of faith, she can't turn it into interiorize it the way the Japanese man did, so that she could forget it and remember it.
She can't make that complicated move.
She doesn't really understand forgetting, as he says.
So she can't do that.
So what does she have to do?
And I didn't really realize it until I'll read you the scene where it happens.
He says, she's giving him up, the German.
Three penny story, I bequeath you to oblivion.
Three penny story, you will disappear just as he will, and so forth.
And she sees that if she betrays the German from her point of view, in order to go with the Japanese, she'll betray the Japanese too, because everything will just go down to being lower nature.
She says, the Japanese man at the end, very near, right at the end, she buries her head in her hands there in the hotel room, clenches her fist, closes her eyes, and moans a moan of utter sadness.
The light of the city is in her eyes.
That is, she's looking at him.
He's the light of the city, really.
But she doesn't really see it.
Never mind the light of the city.
That's me putting in too much.
A moan of utter sadness.
And what is the utter sadness?
Well, that's despair, the moan of utter sadness.
She sees that she cannot keep the meaning in her life unless she gives up the finite and temporal.
Because otherwise, in her world, all she would do was go from lover to lover, betraying the German because she loves the Japanese, and then betraying the Japanese when the next person comes along.
She says to the Japanese man, I'll forget you.
I'm forgetting you already.
Look how I'm forgetting you.
Look at me.
And then she calls to him, this is the directions from afar, lost in wonder.
She succeeded in drowning him in universal oblivion, and it's a source of amazement to her.
She wipes out the Japanese man in order to preserve the meaning of her life.
And the way I would like to put it is, when he gets her to see the whole situation and makes her see that she's either got to give up the German from her point of view and go with him, the Japanese man, or else remain faithful to the German, what she understands when she sees it is that she's got to sacrifice her life to preserve the meaning of the German.
That's what she's doing.
When she says to the Japanese man, I'm forgetting you, she means you don't count, only the Japanese man counts.
I'm sacrificing the temporal, finite, everyday, intimate meaning of my life, here and now, to preserve the meaning, the only thing that really matters in my life, the love of the German.
And that's what happens.
That's why they can't get together in the end.
Now, I jumped way ahead.
So I want to go back, but I want to see if I've lost you all or whether there's somebody you want to say something.
Go ahead.
If she fears that she'll go back to the gifts, but then is it depending on the person because the Japanese bad?
That's right.
It is.
Yes.
He wasn't able.
Exactly.
You're on the right track.
Being able to be a knight of faith or not is a kind of grace.
It's a kind of thing you can't do by your willpower.
You can be a knight of resignation by your willpower, and she's got the strength to think it and do it, as Kierkegaard would put it.
But he's got something else.
He's got, if you put it in Kierkegaard terms, faith in the absurd.
That is, he is able to go through grief, which seems an impossible frame of mind and make something that seems impossible happen.
What seems impossible is that you could remain true to the person you've defined yourself in terms of and still define yourself in terms of somebody else.
That looks impossible.
It's only possible if you'll give up this kind of memory for this incorporated kind of memory.
And you can only do this in the sort of space or field or something that even the impossible is possible.
That is the field of faith.
That is a certain kind of trust and vulnerability that the Japanese man obviously has.
If that's any help, yes, you have to be a different kind of person.
That's right, Greg.
But before you say anything, he said something very interesting.
I want to follow up on it, which is the following.
He knows that.
This has got to do with this, the Y-shaped chart.
She's a knight of resignation, which means that at the moment when she became, made the movements of resignation here, she went up here and became a knight of resignation and took all her energy into her defenses and into idealizing and keeping remembering and telling herself this story.
Whereas he, when he was in a disaster and made the movement of resignation, got up here to be a knight of faith and did what we saw over there.
But now, how could we, now his question is, what could save her?
Well, only what could save her would have to be that her whole personality would be destroyed.
The whole kind of person she was, namely the kind that actually, you know, has to have faith in the person their first love or their life will become meaningless and they're holding on to it and they've got the willpower and the strength to do it.
She's that kind of person.
And the interesting thing is, and that's why I thought what he's saying is interesting to what we're saying, she understands that.
And in her way, let me see if I can find it.
I know what I want to say.
I just would like to find the quotes because the quotes are so interesting.
What she has to do is she has to, she begs him to destroy her, you know, and to change her into his image.
First, it's one of these little reversals.
The first time she says it, you destroy me.
This is 25.
You're so good for me, you destroy me, you're good for me.
You're great, how wonderful, you're great.
That's just a kind of sexual story about how he just completely blows her mind and gives her satisfaction and so forth.
But that's not what she gets to later, where it gets reversed into something else, which I have to find.
By the way, architecture and politics, just in case anybody wants to find it, is on page 34.
I just found it in passing.
Now, we get into a lot of destroy me talk pretty soon, and that's what I want to find.
Okay, I'm getting there.
It's toward the end of it, where you expect it, where she finally sees that she's in this trap, where she finally sees that she's in despair, because she can't be a knight of faith unless she gives up completely the kind of person she is, not only the German as somebody she remembers in front of her, but her whole attitude for preserving the meaning.
And then she says toward the end, and now it means something different: you were made to the size of my body, who are you?
You destroy me.
I was hungry for infidelity, and you destroy me.
You're so good for me.
That's not it quite.
That's still, that's ambiguous, what's going on there.
I want there's a crucial place, and oh, I don't know if I'll be able to find it.
You might help me.
No, you don't have a thing in front of you.
You can't help me.
Okay, then I have to find it.
It says, Destroy me and change me into your likeness.
That's what I'm looking for.
Where then the men that destroy means, get rid of me as a knight of resignation, turn me into a knight of faith, is what she wants to say.
And I just don't know where it is, and I'm amazed I can't find it.
Oh boy, Beatrice is going to find it.
Hell, I hope so.
You destroy me.
You're so good for me.
Ah, yeah, you're right.
It was right.
That's the page I was on, but I didn't have it underlined.
It's in the middle of page 77, which is very important.
Take me, deform me to your likeness.
That's what I was looking for.
So she understands that the only way she could get from being a knight of resignation to being a knight of faith is if he could even more blow her mind than he's done already with the sort of therapy that he was trying to give her.
He would have to just get her to stop understanding anything the way she understands it, seeing anything the way she sees it.
He'd have to get her to believe that even the impossible is possible, or believe isn't even right, to experience the world in faith, in the Kierkegaardian kind of faith, namely that there's some other possibility which you can't really think, which isn't lower immediacy and isn't eternalizing kind of mediation either.
Okay, now, yeah, go ahead.
Yes, good question.
I think the answer is exactly like fear and trembling.
Does Johannes de Salentio understand that there are knights of resignation?
I mean, knights of faith?
Sure, he keeps talking about them all the time.
But does he understand what they're doing and how they're doing it?
No, he keeps saying, I can't understand them at all.
All he can say is it's incomprehensible.
They live as if the sword is hanging over the head of the beloved, and then they have no defenses as if it's the surest thing of all.
They know that they're going to kill Isaac, and yet Abraham knows he's going to kill Isaac, and yet he lives as if he's always going to have Isaac.
So when he doesn't have Isaac, he's not even surprised.
And so, in other words, so it looks like Knights of Resignation can understand that Knights of Faith are doing something very special that they can't do, but they can't really make any sense out of it because it's not rational.
It's paradoxical and impossible.
The movie is written exactly from the same perspective, namely her perspective, as the night, as Jeremy Pembling is from the DeSilentio's perspective.
We never really understand the Japanese perspective.
And because it only comes by, just in a second, in this way, she noticed by little things that he happens to be an architect, that he happens to be a politician, that he knows French, that he understood her.
That's the most important thing.
As soon as he saw her start to talk about Novere, those are all things that make us aware that he's a knight of faith and something that you could see, but the Knights of Resignation don't know how he's doing that.
Wait, somebody had a hand up here.
Yeah.
Market despair is not when the German dies, but when she meets the Japanese and discovers that the whole world, the whole life that she had lived before then was threatening to fall apart once again.
No, you were half there, then you blew it.
The first half, yes, there's something very important.
Despair happens when she meets the Japanese.
But the despair that happens is she understands that the kind of life she's got is going to be condemned to despair.
If she stays with the Japanese man, she's going to not have fulfillment of what's temporal and finite, and she needs that.
If she goes with the Japanese man, she's going to betray the German, and therefore she will also betray the Japanese man, and she won't have anything eternal in her life, and she needs that.
She can't get the eternal and the temporal and finite together.
And when she didn't really understand that, when the German died, that's your important point.
She just thought it was suffering, misery, sorrow, grief.
How could such a bad thing happen to me?
I lost my first love.
But that's not despair.
That's just misery.
And despair is when you see that the very structure of your life makes it impossible for you to be happy.
And you never were happy, and you never could be happy.
And even if the German hadn't died, you wouldn't really be happy.
And then she sees that.
And that's the thing that this forces her to see.
I saw another hand up.
Yeah.
Yes, that's right.
She would never, in Kierkegaard jargon, I'm not getting ahead of the Kierkegaard story.
You'll hear about despair in the last Kierkegaard lecture.
She would have been in lower immediacy, but she would have been in despair without knowing it.
And what that means in Kierkegaard, we have to explain.
It's very interesting.
It's brilliant in Kierkegaard.
Just ask yourself, put it on hold.
How can Kierkegaard say to all of you and me, no matter how happy you think you are, no matter how well your life is going, no matter what hopes you have, you're all in despair.
How can he tell you that?
What kind of craziness is that?
Well, he's got a very, very interesting argument that goes to prove that.
So she's in despair until the moment that she sees that she has to be a knight of faith or she's going to stay in despair.
And she chooses to stay in despair.
She doesn't choose it.
Given the life she's got, she can't get out of it.
And he, he's not in despair.
He's managed to get together the finite and the temporal and keep the meaning and keep the memory all together.
Yeah.
Become a knight of faith.
That's the knight of verse.
Of what?
Of resignation.
So it would just have to be contingent on herself.
No, no, no.
You see, even that wouldn't do it.
I mean, it wouldn't be enough to throw her into resignation.
It wouldn't even be enough for getting her to be a knight of faith, which is what you're talking about, to get her to see that her current way of life is despair, because she can't get the eternal and the temporal together because he's got to also destroy her, whatever that means.
That this mysterious thing.
He's got to really, I mean, it's hard to know what it would be to do it.
If he couldn't do it, it looks like nobody could do it.
But she understands that unless her whole way of life is just wiped out, she won't be able to get out of it and get into faith.
What she knows is that it's a paradox.
It can't be thought.
It can't be understood.
And she can't do it because she's only able to do what can be thought and understood and sort of rationally done.
So another hand.
Yeah.
He, oh, that's wonderful what you're saying.
Only you don't know how wonderful it is.
But follow it up.
Ask yourself: well, okay, so he got a new opportunity to rebuild the new Hiroshima and do it out of his experience of the destruction.
And now what about her?
Sh we don't know what her opportunity was, but we know what her job is.
What is her job?
Actress in what?
In a piece film and in only piece films.
And now that's I can't tell you what she should have done.
I'm only to tell you half.
Notice what's so characteristic of her that she's doing that.
What is it to be an actress in peace films?
Is it being like politicians or architects sort of building a new world?
It could be maybe.
But yeah.
She's reenacting and reenacting the disaster.
She comes to Hiroshima and she does just what a night of resignation should do, keep alive and keep the memory.
He's not interested.
I never thought of putting it this way.
It's just a crowd getting in his way, that movie and that parade.
And he doesn't care a bit because his relation to Hiroshima is so much deeper.
But she has she's now your question is still there.
I don't know how to answer it.
What she could have done instead to turn her love of the German into something interior to her, out of which she could understand the world and know what to do for the finite and temporal way.
Certainly she did it exactly right for a night of resignation and exactly wrong if she for a night of faith, but that's what you'd expect.
That's all I can say about it.
I've only got three more minutes, and there's something.
Oh, yeah, I'll take your question, and then I have to do my sort of summary.
Yeah, should not also move on.
So, isn't that a resignation?
Yes, doesn't want to move on.
The night of resignation has the following idea: if I move on, I will forget the German, and the German, the love of the German, my first love of that wonderful person, was the best thing, the most meaningful thing, not only in my life, it defined me in my life.
It's what made my life worth living.
So, I can't move on.
That's her problem.
Now, I wanted just to take the time to remind you, because it was just a complete, now you can go back to the beginning and ask what they meant when they said their little speeches which I read at the beginning.
When he says, You see nothing when you come to Hiroshima, and she says, I've seen everything when I came to Hiroshima.
He means you haven't seen the way Hiroshima can be reborn from the rubble into a new and happy city, taking over, paradoxically, taking over the old and turning it into some positive way of life.
She hasn't seen that.
And she says, I've seen everything.
Well, she's seen the museum four times.
She's seen the disaster.
She's seen how many people were killed and all that.
But she's not understood at all the new Hiroshima.
And the same thing he says, she says, I understood everything.
She says, I understood everything.
He says, No, you didn't understand anything.
Well, this is what she didn't understand.
She didn't understand how these people in Hiroshima could, and he anyway, could take the disaster and take it over in a positive way.
And finally, the only thing that sort of gives it away and makes it look touristic is she says, I've always wept for Hiroshima.
And he said, what could you wept about?
That's sort of a mistake, because they both weep about the same thing, namely world disaster.
But what's important is, and how neat she's done it, what a great play it is.
It turns out that he, see, from his point of view, he hasn't seen anything.
And she hasn't understood anything because she's not a knight of faith.
And that's the end of it.
Okay, we did it.
We did it.