The idea that you could be so involved in something that that was seen to be the most important and most satisfying thing in your life, and you're going to keep it forever.
And at the same time, you know from past experience that you've had that experience lots of times, and eventually these things stop being exciting and you and some new thing grabs you.
Now, question.
Kierkegaard defines commitments to infem.
Something that's like some or not something that's ephemeral, but something that is undistinguished and something that is not fine.
That's right.
The Kierkegaard ones are eternal.
You can't lose them.
I had a discussion about that in office hours, and it was very interesting.
By the way, I wrote down here to tell everybody that my office hours for Philosophy 7 are 2 to 3 on Wednesday.
Very few people show up for that.
Let me write it down again.
Then we'll come back to your question.
But this came up in office.
I take it, you know that it's 303 Moses.
So now, yeah, it came up, and I went back and looked at the Kierkegaard.
I don't know, I had the dim memory that it so much defines you that you can't give it up.
The issue was: can you freely give up an unconditional commitment?
I think the answer is clearly for Kierkegaard.
And again, I want to say, pay attention to the phenomenon.
If you're in Kierkegaard, which is doing the phenomenon of romantic love, you have the power to resist getting into it.
You can stay away from the other person, you can look at all their faults, you can feel all your inferiorities or whatever.
But if you let yourself be bound, that's a phrase from Heidegger that I like, if you let yourself be bound once you are into that relation, he says explicitly that you can't pull yourself out of it.
It's twined about every ligament of your consciousness.
It defines who you are, and you would just be a kind of zombie if you gave it up.
That's the real extreme romantic love, knights and ladies phenomenon.
But now, now, not yet.
So, but I want to say, stick to the phenomenon.
This is in office hours.
Before we went to look at the Kierkegaard, I said, it looks to me like the way romantic love has been described, you are not free, and the way it experienced.
You're not free to just say, I'm going to stop loving this person.
This is just such a mess, it's ruining my life, and I'm just going to just call all to this right now.
It isn't like that.
The other person looks like the most important person in your life, and everything else looks like it's important only relative to that.
And you just can't say it, just quit it.
And while we're on the phenomenon, I mentioned it.
I mean, romantic love is very different than infatuation.
Nietzsche's on to infatuation.
He likes the idea that you could be totally overwhelmed in some relation to somebody, but it's in terms of the excitement of it, not letting it define you, but letting it be what is right now the most important and satisfying thing for you.
Knowing and feeling that it's for good and knowing that it isn't, because if you felt that before lots of times and it never turned out to be good, those are two different phenomena.
And if you stick to trying in your papers too, to stick to describing the experience, then you will be able to understand the books.
I mean, very few courses and very few articles do that.
I mean, I don't claim I invented that.
Heidegger's the one who, my guru in the background, who says you should always start paying attention to the phenomenon, then pay attention to the text, and then you will understand the text.
So, have I answered you or just made a speech?
I'm not sure, because I didn't really let you finish.
I was filling in the what?
A little bit, but it's just sort of one thing if it in positions that we were talking about about how it has to be like you know the blind egoism's experience of completely immigration.
I saw that sort of defining way for the thronger thought completely inspired, finding the commitment.
And I thought, well, maybe because one of the characteristics of the defining commitment is it has to be something that's vulnerable.
So, what if it?
I think you have a good flying meeting.
I think I could something by having a defining commitment to something, it's not real defining commitment, to something that isn't, you know, vulnerable.
Like a defining commitment, eating the sneeze will be defined and maybe something.
So, like a defining commitment to in more concepts, like defining the measurement, you know, like romance love.
So, you throw yourself completely out into the idea of romance and love.
But how do you interpret that games?
Wow, that's interesting.
That's really interesting.
What you've done is reinvent Plato on love.
None of you read the symposium, have you, or have you?
Plato's written this terrific dialogue about love, and in effect, says that loving any particular person is a crazy thing to do.
It's a petty thing to do, it's a stupid thing to do, they're vulnerable and they get old and they're only attractive in some aspects and not in other aspects.
He has all a list of reasons why you wouldn't want to have, make a single individual the important thing in your life, but you make love with a capital L the most important thing in your life.
That's what the symposium is about.
How you get, but now Nietzsche's going to hate that, that's sure, but we have to figure out why.
Why is it that it somehow tries to avoid suffering?
You won't be ever losing it the way you could lose the romantic love object or the infatuation object.
That's what Plato thinks is good about it.
You love the loving the loving love and loving the lovable in abstract is perfectly safe.
But I think you have to attach it to your individual instances.
AID lose and those individual instances.
And then you move on to the next thing.
So while we're maintaining the overall concept.
Yeah, well, now you're certainly not Plato anymore because you've got these overall, you stick with these instances and the overall.
But now I don't understand what the overall is doing for you.
I mean, brief habits is a series of instances.
Well, it says they're all instances of romantic love, for instance, no, or of loving some music or something.
So there does it add anything?
I mean, Nietzsche says, too, they're all instances of brief habits.
That's his concept under which all of them fall.
I don't see that it makes any difference to your particular commitment to whether it falls under some concept or not.
You're not committed to the concept.
And that's all sort of tied up with Kierkegaard.
Nietzsche would agree that you've got to satisfy the finite and the temporal.
And once you're doing that, it's bound to be risky.
And bringing it under a concept which is secure either gets rid of the importance of the finite and the temporal, and where are you then?
You're in the night of resignation.
You're in love with the principle and nobody, and not the person in particular, and it's safe but unfulfilling.
Or you really are in love with or infatuated by the person involved, in which case it's going to be, in one case, changeable, in the other case, risky.
But Nietzsche doesn't think you should be sort of trying to defend yourself against the fact that it's changeable.
You should just enjoy it as a necessary way.
If what you like is the exciting and the wonderful and the surprising, then of course it's going to finally, you're going to lose it.
But that's all right, because there'll be something else wonderful and exciting and surprising.
So I guess if we need to talk about it more, it'll have to be in office hours because I'm not getting what you're trying to do.
But I know from your questions that there's something important behind what you're saying.
I just don't know what it is.
Okay?
Anything else?
Well, then let's go on where we are.
That is, I wrote down here to sum up last time, I want to talk about 127 and 129.
I don't remember why.
Whoa, I don't see anything on them.
Maybe that's because, I mean, I'm in here.
Let's hope so.
Yes.
Okay, now I know where I am.
Connecting up with last time.
Not with the talk about grief habits last time, which is fine to connect up with, but connecting up with the last talk, last, I guess maybe it was time before last.
I'm not sure I remember.
When did we talk about life being willed to power and the most important thing?
I think that was time before last, right?
Okay, well, I'm coming back to it because it's going to be the important issue again today.
Nietzsche transvaluates values, he transvaluates them toward being the most alive, flourishing, constantly expanding and outgrowing and overcoming.
That's what is worth doing.
That's what, it isn't as if that's what you ought to do.
Nietzsche doesn't believe in any oughts.
Where would they come from?
And why would you get, and you'd be stuck in them.
But what you, this, this kind of higher thing where you never get stuck is not a thing you ought to do, it's something you can't help doing as a living being.
And then comes the question: well, why doesn't everybody do it?
Well, everybody does, but some people are strong and do it well and frequently, or and so forth.
And some people are sick and weak and degenerate, and they haven't gotten much overcoming and will to power.
And those weak people, you're supposed to ignore them or walk all over them if you need to, because they just don't matter from a nature point of view.
The powerful ones are the ones who are worth having.
He would get rid of all the weak, decadent, sick ones if he could.
And now that's sort of that's that's why am I saying that?
Well, just to remind you where we are.
Now, on 127 in Twilight, which I haven't read, I think, because I didn't expect you to have it with you.
Now we're at the bottom of 127, summing up what I've just been saying.
What is good?
All that heightens the feeling of power, the will to power, power itself in man.
What is bad?
All that proceeds from weakness.
What is happiness?
The feeling that power increases, that a resistance is overcome.
That's pretty clear.
But let's go on.
He's against notice.
And I don't remember again how much I said about this, because what I say in office hours blends in my mind with what I say here.
But I want to say, of course, it follows from this that he's against the value of peace and contentment and serenity and such.
Those are sort of stagnation.
That's sort of resting.
Contentment is being satisfied with where you are.
That means you must be a declining part of life because life, when it's flourishing, is never satisfied.
Then this is what he says at the top of 128.
Not contentment, but more power.
Not peace at all, but war.
Not virtue, but proficiency.
That is, mastery, really, I think would be better there.
Virtue in the Renaissance style, virtue, which meant free, oh, well, that's free of moralistic acid.
That's weird, Nietzsche talk.
Never mind.
But the virtue, virtue is a funny word.
It used to mean masculinity and strength.
Then it got switched around and it's what women had.
And now it's sort of a kind of general term for sort of good characteristics of people.
We don't need to talk about that.
I want to make another speech about peace.
I think I did already, but when you're reading Nietzsche, it keeps coming up.
It's so important that Nietzsche sees that you could question, and he does, the idea that what people really want is peace.
But yet in the prayers, I mean, the very last word, I think, of the Mass, the Catholic Mass, is, Dona nobis pachem, give us peace.
Why should that be the last word?
Why not say, give us excitement, give us power, and so forth.
And I learned a prayer, some Jewish prayer I can't remember very well when I was young, and it ended also peace.
And somewhere there's this prayer begins, give us peace, thy most precious gift.
I think that's probably the Jewish prayer I learned.
But whatever it is, what's so precious about peace, Nietzsche wants to say.
And I think that that's a very important thing to say.
A little better than peace, I think, would be at least a kind of tense equilibrium.
That's Pascal's proposal, that we live in the extremes of wretchedness and greatness and stretching, filling all the intervening space.
But if we follow Jesus, we manage to live there in a way that isn't breaking us up.
He was, after all, God and man, and didn't crack him up.
That's the Pascal version.
And then in Kierkegaard, you get another version of it where the remember that the last line of the thing on despair that I passed out is that self is, I think, in equilibrium, if I remember that right, is transparently grounded in the power that posited it.
Never mind all that talk.
It's the equilibrium I want to mention this time.
So for Kierkegaard, you manage to get an equilibrium between the two sides of the self.
And that's sort of a, but it's a kind of tense kind.
You didn't read it, I don't think, but he talks about how when you're a knight of faith, you're constantly swimming over 20,000 fathoms, meaning it's a sort of risky way of life in which you put all your eggs in one basket and it's all vulnerable, but you have to live it as if it was the surest thing of all.
Those are all ways of not, well, you could put it either way, those are ways of not making just plain contentment and that kind of peace the top thing.
But from Nietzsche's point of view, they would all be ways of trying to make an equilibrium where what you really want, if you want power, and that's what you can't help wanting, being alive, you want a self that's in a constant struggle.
Now, I was going to talk about that.
And I'm going to jump to this because I got to this in a different angle than I thought I was going to.
Let me say one more thing about it, though, first.
Some missing.
Well, maybe it isn't what I was going to say, but I mean, this is Nietzsche, you must remember, transvaluating all our values.
I mean, he's going to not only make life the highest value, but he's going to take peace, which looked like that was the highest value, and turn it into the worst.
Oh, now I remember I was going to say, somewhere he says, that happiness, like contentment at the top of 128, is not anything that any really powerful, alive person wants.
He says there's some aphorism somewhere that says happiness, only the Englishman wants that.
That's a strange thing to say.
We read that, don't we somewhere?
You saw it in there.
But anyway, it's supposed to be, but it sounds like a crazy thing to say that people don't want contentment and happiness.
But the point is, that would be a place to stop.
And, you know, here I am contented and happy.
Now I can just rest.
But if you're alive and powerful, you don't ever rest that way.
Only you can rest again.
You know, you've got to go sleep and relax a while in order to go on overcoming everything.
In the end, the goal is constant overcoming.
Okay, Beatrice, yeah.
Is what?
What does power mean?
Well, that's a good deep philosophical question.
I wonder, let's go back to what I was just quoting.
What is good?
The feeling of power, power itself.
What is happiness?
The feeling that power increases.
I see what you mean.
Power is just an undefined variable in all that.
So what is power?
Well, I don't know if I think it helps to say power is constant overcoming.
That is, power is what enables you to form grief habits and then go on and do something else, form another.
What is the full expression of power would be to be able to create new worlds, new eyes, new suns.
You remember S-U-N and all.
That's what the Free Spirit does.
And I think all I can say, I'm not sure, I may be saying something very intelligent and I may not, but all I can say now is: if you want to find out what power is, and you're told that the Free Spirit is the extreme form of the will to power and has more power, and you ask, well, what is the Free Spirit doing with all this power?
Well, the Free Spirit isn't just going on from one infatuation in the world to another infatuation in the world.
The Free Spirit is going on from inventing one whole world, one whole way of seeing things, to another whole way of seeing things, and in which the previous way, and this is important, is experienced as having been outgrown.
It isn't just sort of arbitrary.
First, you see things this way and then that way and then that way and that way, but you see things better and better.
And what does that mean?
I think that means for Nietzsche, you see more the richness, the complexity, and finally the excitement and wonder of whatever it is worlds that you're getting into from that.
So that's, I'm glad you asked.
I'm not sure that's a good answer, but at least I'm not embarrassed by it now.
When I listen to myself, if I do, I may discover that I should have said something else.
If so, I'll tell you, unless anybody else already knows some other thing.
I mean, again, that's what did I just do, by the way?
I tried to get back to the phenomenon again.
What you want with power is not a definition of power, but examples of power, of the minimal but still good kind of power, like infatuations and brief habits, and the maximum, namely, like artists, I didn't mention that, but artists create whole worlds.
Like, we'll go back to Picasso's power to paint everything blue and then to paint everything cubes, and presumably he has new eyes each time and sees everything blue and sees everything cubes.
That's the phenomenon that Nietzsche is calling power.
Never mind what it's called.
The point is to see that that's what he really thinks he can make the highest value by saying that's what all being is.
Finally, he generalizes not just living things, but everything is will to power.
And it's either a will to power that's really doing a great job, or it's wet, weak, and decadent.
Now, okay?
Now, but I've gotten to myself into a place where I want to change the order of the lecture altogether.
Maybe not.
Maybe I can connect.
So now, well, I'm going to talk about how the free spirit relates to their own passions, which is, because that's sort of, you can consider that the sensuous side or the dark side, the finite and the temporal, the body, all that gets put on one side of the self by various people.
You can call that the earthy side if you like it.
You can call it the dark side if you don't like it.
But there's something about being embodied in the world, which we want to know what the free spirit does with that.
Or here's another way to put it, connecting up with the way I got into this.
If contentment and peace and equilibrium are not what we should aim at as the way ourselves, as we relate ourselves to ourselves, to talk like Kierkegaard, what should we aim at when we relate ourselves to ourselves?
That's what I want to talk about.
There are lots of different stories, and we've had several of them.
I'm constantly rewriting this.
It's probably going to get me in trouble.
But I want to start with where I was going to end up.
That is, so you'll see what the question means.
So, in Plato, how does the self relate itself to itself?
Remember the Greek method, the relate itself to itself by a negative relation, which means repress half.
And in the case of Plato and the Greeks that we're caring about, it means repress the temporal, finite, embodied half.
But what I'm talking about here is just repression.
The self relates itself to itself by denying half the self and claiming it's only essentially the mind.
That's now what's the next one?
Well, the next one we've also had, this is a kind of review.
There's the Christian way of dealing with the sensuous, embodied, and earthy side.
And what is that?
Well, definitely not repression.
I mean, that's what happens if you do that.
You come out like Yvonne and eventually go crazy.
So, Zosima tells Mrs.
Holokoff what to do.
Remember, it's you have to look at the dark side and face it honestly and integrate it into what you're doing and in effect sublimate it.
That is, turn it into something positive.
And that's the Christian proposal.
And how do you sublimate it?
Well, I think you need agape.
Somebody has to love you with agape love in order to enable you to do it.
Zosima doesn't say that.
I think that's because he's too close to it.
He just does it.
And what you'll get out of that is purity, joy, harmony, something like that, which is still a kind of peace, but it's a very, it's not a contentment kind of peace.
It's a much more intense kind of peace.
So remember that there's two kinds of purity involved.
This turns out to be a kind of review, which is a good idea at this near the end of the course.
The purity of Plato is you just deny the impurities.
That's the, you sort of take yourself to the dry cleaners version of cleanliness and purity.
But then the Christian version in Zosima, the good Christian version, Kierkegaard thinks there's, Nietzsche thinks there's a bad Christian version, which leads the, I don't know whether I'm going to get back to it today now or not, but I'll say there's a bad Christian version which could be put with the Plato version, which wants to get rid of the part of the self that it doesn't like.
And that goes from the Bible saying if your eye offends you, cast it out, to Christian, almost saints and so forth, who take it so literally that they castrate themselves.
This is what Origen, a famous church father, did.
That's like repression on a ferocious scale.
And interestingly enough, he's therefore disqualified from being a saint.
You're not supposed to actually get rid of these sensuous impulses.
You're supposed to purify them, not in the sense of getting all the dirt out, like dry cleaning, but remember, again, transform it, sublimate it, turn the impulsive side into impulsiveness to do the good.
But if you got all the energy that goes into these impulses, you have to be able to transform it into positive energy.
And Dmitri does it through his love of Grushenka.
And she can return the love because she's been loved by Alyosha.
We know that story.
So now the interesting question for today: well, what has Nietzsche got to say about this?
As usual, you can expect Nietzsche, being the absolutely original and brilliant character that he is, having taken on the most hard job he possibly can to invent new values for his culture now that God is dead, that's a pretty big job.
He's going to have to have a new story, a totally new story, about how the self gets related to itself.
And that's going to be by command.
The self has to be able to command itself.
Now, that was supposed to be the end, but in fact, I jumped ahead.
Now let's see what that means.
So your passions are, to begin with, chaotic.
If they're just chaotic, it makes you weak.
So you've got to be able to sort of bring them into some kind of order.
One way is to get rid of the bad ones.
That's the Greek and wrong Christian way.
One way is to sublimate the dangerous.
That's the Christian way.
But then there's something else you can do.
Now I have to find the pages from the other end, so to speak, where I am, and see what I want to read.
Oh, back up one.
Just on 53.
I just want to, I'm sticking with the Christian for one more moment.
The beginning of the aphorism 3 of Twilight on page 53 is: the spiritualization of sensuality is called love.
It's a great triumph over Christianity.
But you've got to be careful.
I mean, that means, I've got to explain this, otherwise what I've been saying will confuse you.
There's two stories.
I've been saying it, but I haven't done it right yet.
Christianity has in it a good version and a bad version of how the self should relate itself to itself.
The bad version is to get rid of what's bad.
That's at the bottom of 52.
The church combats the passions with excision in every sense of the word.
Its practice is the cure is castration.
That's he's thinking of origin.
It was at all times laid emphasis of its discipline on extrapolation of sensuality, of pride, lust, power, avarice, and so forth.
That the attack of passions at their roots means an attack on life at its roots.
The practice of a Christian is hostile to life.
Well, that's the Farrapont Christian to take the extreme, or the Yvonne Christian to take the most.
Well, Yvonne isn't a Christian, so never mind.
So it's in Dostoevsky, I guess Ferrapont may be the only one who's living on locusts and starving himself and in general trying to get rid of the earth side of himself.
But then there's the other side of Christianity, and it's that's going to confuse you all.
Here, he's still talking against that kind of Christianity when he says on three, the spiritualization of sensuality is called love, it is a great triumph over Christianity.
Well, that you've got to read that.
That's Dostoevsky Christianity, is a big triumph over Ferrapont Christianity.
The Christianity that says get rid of your dark side is very bad news and it's decadent and life-destroying.
But there is another kind of Christianity which says that through agape love, you can take your sensuality and make something positive out of it.
That's not what he's saying here.
He's still attacking what he thinks is the bad Christianity.
But we'll get to the good Christianity before long.
I can't quite jump to it yet because it will only confuse things if I do.
But we're looking for, don't lose track.
I'm losing track, sort of, trying to reinvent as I go.
Don't lose track that we're trying to get now a focus on what Nietzsche thinks, which is, and I just keep reviewing, he doesn't like the castration kind of Christianity, and he doesn't like, oh, he likes, but not, it's not for him, the spiritualizing by way of love, the Dostoevsky kind of Christianity.
He's got something else to propose.
So it's not, neither the extirpation nor the sublimation is how a free spirit relates to his or her passions.
You shouldn't get rid of your dark side.
You shouldn't become, you shouldn't purify it by loving and looking at it until it becomes loving and harmonious.
Now comes what should you do?
You organize your passions so that the chaos of your passions, which would destroy you if you were just sort of running off in all directions of lower immediacy, like a child for everything you desired, you constrain the passions, but not by repressing them, but by preserving them all in a dynamic and unstable unity.
That's what makes you powerful and creative.
That's the new idea.
You want to be a self which preserves and even strengthens, but also controls all the most evil and destructive passions.
Not get rid of them.
They give you energy.
They give you originality.
They're a part of life.
So now we have to read that.
I think that's a fascinating story that Nietzsche has come up with, a new notion.
Where are we going to find it?
About eight lines down on 54 in Twilight.
We adopt the same attitude toward the enemy within.
One is, now he's going to talk about what he wants to be.
One is fruitful at the cost of being rich in contradictions.
One remains young only on condition that the soul does not relax.
Again, no peace, no contentment, no equilibrium.
Does not long for peace.
That's the bad guy.
Nothing is growing more alien to us than that desideratum of former times, peace of soul.
The Christian deserves erotum.
Nothing arouses less envy in us than the moral cow and the fat contentment of the good conscience.
That's the ones he insults is the English ones.
And so forth.
But he's got to spell that out a lot more.
So we're going to spell it out a lot more.
And now I'm going to find out where to spell it out.
It's sort of scattered all over.
I wish I could give you a reading of it.
I'm just going to pick it out where I can find it.
It's all on your list.
And a lot of them you've read, but some of them you haven't because I spent the morning trying to find every reference I could to this idea.
Remember the idea now?
Control of chaos.
Bringing under your control all the evil as well as the good, all the sensual as well as the purely spiritual.
That's what he's going to try to tell you about.
So you want to establish something.
Okay, here they are.
No, that's not it yet.
Okay, try this one.
76 in what?
Twilight?
Maybe.
I haven't, that's not what I'm looking for now, but it may well be what I was looking for, will be looking for sooner or later.
76 in Twilight?
Page 76?
Aphorism 6.
On 76.
Gee, no, maybe I missed that one.
I think that's very hopeful.
What are you see there?
I've been tracking the eye to report locations to let anything cost bread.
Learning to defer judgment with that given control.
I don't see it yet about control.
I see.
I'm learning to see.
Oh, I see where you are.
The middle of aphorism 6.
As I understand it, is almost what is called in unphilosophical language strong willpower.
Yeah, that sounds hopeful.
The essence of it is precisely not to will the ability, not to will, the ability to defer decisions.
Okay, let's skip a little.
No, I mean, there's nothing wrong with this, but I see why I didn't mark it.
Because that is, I want to say, what's interesting about the Nietzsche version is that he wants to preserve what's dangerous, what's evil, what's destructive, and not purify it and sublimate it and not surely not repress it, but control it, make it part of your life.
I'll get clearer about that as I go.
Now I'm looking for page 237, and maybe I thought I should be looking.
No, not on 237.
Okay.
Well, I don't know what in the world I have in mind.
One more possibility, but I don't think it's.
But there is, in will to power, you have to add it.
I didn't have time to add it to the handout, but I'll just read it to you because it's relevant here.
Domination of the passions is not their weakening or extirpation.
The greater the dominating power of the will, the more freedom may the passions be allowed.
The great man is great owing to the free play and scope of his desires and to the yet greater power that knows how to press these magnificent monsters into service.
That's the line.
So everybody's got monstrous side of them, crazy desires and impulses and so forth.
And the point is not to deny them and get rid of them or even transform them, but be strong enough to have them under control.
That's the monsters that you press.
What is it again?
The kind of you have to know how to press the magnificent monsters into service.
That's good nature.
So certainly such a person wouldn't have peace.
They wouldn't even have equilibrium.
They would be constantly sort of struggling to keep it all together.
And the idea that the more powerful desires, even the destructive ones, that they can keep under control and make some positive use of, the better.
Yeah.
No, well, it shouldn't.
That's my fault.
I mean, it shouldn't be integrated.
That's the word I don't want to say.
You keep the dark side.
You don't, what did you say?
You do something to it.
You don't transform it.
Okay, let me, okay, let me try.
Let's try a phenomenon or two.
Suppose you are a generally aggressive person, and your first impulse, whenever anything isn't going the way it is, is to hit somebody or something.
Now, one way to do is to try to get rid of that.
Another one would be to try to transform it into something else, but you could just try to use it on appropriate occasions in the sense that go in for martial arts or join the army.
Do something where you can make a virtue.
of what if you're say a professor would certainly be a vice if you go around hitting students or something but if you're if you're in the army you can go around hitting the enemy so so the idea is find a way that you can actually manage to uh keep that impulse but be under control you can't go around hitting everybody your your children and your wife however that this there's something right about this impulse to to strike out and try to annihilate people and things you don't like don't get rid of that impulse just bring it to bear as best you can on the situations when it's appropriate and then in another situation some other dark impulse may be appropriate let's say you want to impress people and so I mean you're you're you're egoistic and you want them all to think how great you are okay well there's opportunities for that to become an actor perhaps maybe a professor I'm not sure but in any case there again don't get rid of this impulse to impress people but try to control it so that it doesn't come out on the wrong occasions of course, that's risky you if you really sort of knock it out so much that you control it and it's so peaceful that you know it'll never come out on the wrong occasions, you weakened it too much.
You may just have to hit somebody sometimes, risk hitting people who you really wish you hadn't hit, or trying to impress people that you really wish you had just listened to.
Okay, I see a hand up here.
Go ahead.
Okay, well, I see that.
I mean, I don't know.
She's asking, yeah, what about people who really have pathological impulses?
Well, they're weak and self-destructive people because this isn't increasing their power and constantly giving them more and more of a grip and able to open up new worlds.
This is just going off in all directions.
He certainly thinks that's a bad idea.
And that means they haven't got control of their impulses.
The trick is to have these impulses and get control of them instead of getting rid of them.
And the more you can get control of them without weakening them, the better.
But if you go too far in her direction, and instead of weakening them, you just let them ride run you, that's going too far in the other direction.
And how do you do it right?
Well, you just have to have a feel for it.
If you're a healthy free spirit type, you'll know how to do it.
And if you aren't, you're sick and decadent, and nature will just think you're good riddance if you just fall apart.
Okay, yeah.
I think it's appropriate to act on when the masses will have an opinion, but of course the free spirit won't go with the masses' opinion.
The only person who decides when it's appropriate, finally, is the free spirit.
And the only way to determine, and what makes it appropriate, not whether it makes people happy and like you or something like that.
Again, it's appropriate if it gives you creativity, if it gives you new ways of seeing things and new ways of doing things, then you're doing it right.
And the important thing is there isn't any general standard of how it's appropriate.
I mean, you're right about that.
The general standard of what's appropriate is exactly what Nietzsche thinks is dangerous.
It levels down and represses and takes away the importance of this seemingly evil, but if properly directed, powerful impulse guide.
Okay, I'm going to go on because there are quotes that help a lot, because they're all looking not very, not sort of aha, and isn't that interesting, so I must have to do it better.
Let's see.
Well, here's one about being like a tree on 331 of gay science.
It's only a metaphor, but maybe it will help.
It's on 331, we incomprehensible ones.
Have we ever complained because we are misunderstood and so forth?
No, no, that we haven't.
We've, and so forth.
We keep growing and changing and so forth.
That's not what I want to read right now.
We push, I'll start at the very bottom of the 331.
We push our roots ever more powerfully into the depths, into evil.
That's the crucial part.
While at the same time, we embrace the heavens ever more lovingly, more broadly, imbibing their light ever more thirstily with all our twigs and branches.
Now that's really interesting.
You see how that's related to Dmitry and the brothers?
Dimitri's got this problem about the evil, going into the pit of Sodom, but heels up and head first, and at the same time, beginning a prayer or a song.
I think it's a prayer to the Madonna.
And Dimitri thinks that's too broad.
He wants to get rid of that.
And Dostoevsky thinks that Dmitry will get rid of it finally when he gets enough agape love for Maliasha and Grushenka.
He won't have that problem anymore.
The self won't be too broad and stretch between contradictions.
He'll get the two aspects in harmony.
But Dostoevsky thinks that no, now let's go on.
It's not getting them into harmony.
It's getting more and more into the heavens.
That's the Madonna stuff.
And the evil.
That's the Sodom stuff.
And like a tree we grow.
This is hard to understand.
This is all of life.
Not in one place only, but everywhere.
Not in one direction, but upward and outward and inward and downward.
That's the evil side.
Our energy is at work simultaneously in the trunk, the branches, the roots.
We are no longer free to do only one particular thing to be one particular thing.
Okay, that's another way to do it, to say it.
And I've got others scattered around.
Things are not totally uncontrolled, but we get the positive force of all our impulses.
This means dealing openly with the more unsavory aspects of ourselves and find room for them by establishing this hierarchy of control.
That is, sort of, some of your impulses are used to control other impulses.
You've got to, and it's you that have to organize that.
And the free spirit is able to organize that.
That's how he relates himself or she relates herself to themselves.
Yeah.
That's right.
We sort of don't cut them off.
That's this extirpation, castration, platonic, you know, negative R2, get rid of half of the self.
You don't do that.
You keep the roots that are going down, and you even sort of promote the roots that are going down, but you don't let them pull you down.
Instead, they hold you up.
You convert all this into a kind of impulses that you control enough so that they come out in situations where they are appropriate in some way and not in other situations.
But you don't get rid of them.
That's again how different from what?
No, no.
Look at Dimitri.
You want to say to Dimitri, you don't want to say to Dimitri in Dostoevsky, well, keep the sodom side, the kinky sex and the nasty way he's been relating to women.
Just keep it, but only do it on appropriate occasions.
That's not quite right.
It's something like, how are we going to do it now?
I've got myself into this.
I can't think of the appropriate occasion that or the way of life where you could control these impulses, not get rid of them, but make them give up their energy to you, help you in some way to be a strong person.
Well, you got in health here?
We need to have experience with developers?
That's right.
Not only do you need to experience them and face them, and then you never will actually act on them, but they will gradually go away and become other impulses.
That's the sublimation thing, impulses toward rushing recklessly to help people out and so forth.
That's the Dostoevsky picture.
In Nietzsche, they stay evil.
They stay deep.
They stay down in your unconscious where you've got all kinds of strange and weird impulses.
And if you're enough of an artist and enough of a free free spirit, these impulses still give you energy.
I can't really explain in some detail how, but that's the picture.
Somehow they'll be there, not denied.
If I keep going, who knows?
I might get it better.
So let's try.
Let's see.
Okay, well, that's the best I can do.
So for Nietzsche, you don't, a free spirit is not like a Dostoevsky and saint.
A free spirit is like an artist who manages to make something positive out of their, even out of their pinky ways of looking at things.
There's an artist named Balthus.
He's a famous, good artist who only seems to be interested in painting very young adolescent girls, but he paints them very well, and his paintings are in major museums.
And that sort of kinky side of him presumably takes the place of his actually molesting the girls.
But he's not denied that impulse.
He's controlled it and found a way to make it a positive source of creativity.
That's the best I can do.
So I'm going to go on because there's another thing I want to cover.
I don't know whether I'll get, but I want to make sure.
And if anybody wants to say anything more about this, I think that it's very interesting and challenging.
And I went around trying to find more quotes.
I'm sure there are more quotes.
If anybody comes across or knows any more where Nietzsche explains this more, I asked Hans Slug, who's our Nietzsche guy, and he feels too that there's more in Will to Power, for instance, which you don't have, but I could only find one.
Anyway, there's a picture there that Nietzsche's trying to work out of a, let me just sum up, of a view of the way the self relates to itself, which is not extirpation of half the self, and it's not turning it into something else by sublimation.
It's control and making it work for you.
That's all I can do with it.
But think of your own examples.
Come and tell me in office hours.
I'm going on.
I want to talk about Christianity and Jesus because I said before that Jesus would be for Nietzsche a free thinker, or almost a free thinker.
And now I owe you an explanation of that.
It's really fascinating and very relevant to the Course.
So there's, again, Nietzsche's so complicated.
There is Jesus the Redeemer, as he calls him, which I think he picks that name because I take it the Redeemer is the one who suffers on the cross for everybody and thereby pays off the debt that was caused by original sin.
The thing that I think Dostoevsky can't understand and can't existentialize, and neither can I, and neither can Nietzsche.
Nietzsche is very much against that understanding.
But I'm not even going to read the part where Nietzsche is sort of railing against that understanding.
I want to read the part where, in more general terms, he's against the Redeemer.
On 150, now I'm in the Antichrist from now on.
So at the bottom of 152, Aphorism 29, he says, What I'm concerned with is the psychological type of the Redeemer.
And then he goes on saying how much he's against that.
And he, well, that's the general heading.
I don't want to read the next thing I thought I wanted to read, because I think it's too confusing.
But what, now we want to find out more about this story about Jesus.
So he's asked the question: well, is he really this Redeemer, this suffering servant and so forth?
And he thinks he's not.
He says on page 154, number 31, I've anticipated my answer to the problem.
I mean, the problem is: how are we supposed to understand Jesus?
Is he the Redeemer or is He something else?
It's presupposition is the type of the Red Redeemer has been preserved to us only in a distorted form.
So he's going to say, well, Jesus is doing something very interesting and important, except it was so world-transforming that nobody could understand it.
So we've got this kind of very confused account of it in the letters of Paul and in the Gospel.
That's what he's going to say.
So now the bottom of 154, about eight lines down.
That strange and sick world to which the Gospels introduce us, a world like that of the Russian novel, in which the refuse of society, neurosis, and childlike idiocy seem to make a rendezvous.
That's why people think he's read Dostoevsky The Idiot, must, in any case, have coarsened the type.
The first disciples in particular had to translate a being immersed entirely in symbols and incomprehensibility into their own crudity in order to understand anything at all.
For them, such a type could not exist until it had been reduced to more familiar terms.
You recognize that.
You should be used to it.
The first stage of Christianity, Nietzsche thinks, turns out Dostoevsky also thinks, with Marko, is so revolutionary, so new world-defining, that the disciples can't understand it.
And neither can Jesus.
He doesn't say that, but it's implied nobody can understand it.
But Jesus can only describe it in incomprehensible parables and so forth.
And because there's no familiar form, that's why it has to go into the monastery.
But that's Dostoevsky.
And then we get to the real Jesus.
That's what I wanted to be sure and get to today.
That's Nietzsche trying to see what Jesus must have been like, even though the disciples couldn't understand what he was doing, and even he couldn't explain what he was doing.
So, and then it looks like Jesus is a free spirit on 156.
That's about ten lines from the bottom.
One could, with some freedom of expression, call Jesus a free spirit.
And now, why would that be?
Well, he cares nothing for what is fixed.
The word killeth.
Everything fixed, killeth.
That is, he's making him into somebody who believes in constant overcoming and doesn't want to get stuck with a universal, fixed, ethical law.
And he doesn't like the law.
He thinks he's fulfilled and surpassed the law.
So the concept of the expression life in the only form he knows it is opposed to any kind of word, formula, law, faith, dogma.
He speaks only of the inmost thing, life.
All this about eternal life.
Now, but Nietzsche thinks that when he said eternal, he didn't mean eternal the way Plato would have meant it or even the people who talked about childhood memories like Dostoevsky or Kierkegaard.
None of them.
He speaks about, because he talks about eternal life.
And everything, the whole of reality, the whole of nature, language possesses for him the value of a sign, a metaphor.
On this point, we must be absolutely no mistake, and so forth.
I can skip for a while.
He's sort of affirming everything.
So, skipping down to where it says denial in the italics on the next page in the middle of that.
Denial is precisely what is totally impossible for anyone.
Dialectics are likewise lacking.
The idea is lacking.
The idea is lacking that a faith, a truth, could be proved by reasons.
His proofs are inner lights, inner feelings of pleasure and self-affirmation, nothing but proofs of potency.
So, he's feeling his own power, according to Nietzsche, making him up.
And now, the other important thing is that he understands that we're in paradise here and now.
So, that's in 33, aphorism 33 and 157.
Blessedness is not promised, it's not tied to any conditions, it's the only reality.
The rest is signs for speaking of it.
And then he doesn't fight back when people do bad things to him.
And in the end, it turns out that it sounds pretty much like Dostoevsky what he's done.
He says, He settled, and I'm now on page 158, the second sentence in the first full paragraph.
He's settled his account with the whole Jewish penance and reconciliation doctrine.
He knows that it's through the practice of one's life that one feels divine, blessed, evangelic at all times, child of God.
It's not penance, not prayer for forgiveness, which leads to God.
Evangelical practice alone leads to God.
It is God.
So God is sort of experiencing the glad tidings, and the glad tidings is that we're all in heaven here and now.
That's the last paragraph.
The profound instinct of how one could have to live in order to feel oneself in heaven, to feel oneself eternal, while in every other condition, one by no means feels oneself in heaven.
This alone is the psychological reality of redemption.
That's the positive, right kind of redeemer.
A new way of living, not a new belief.
And it's sort of like the ocean of love.
It's the next, about 10 lines down on 159.
In a word, in the word son, S-O-N is expressed the entry into the collective feeling of the transfiguration of all things.
I mean, this is the world being totally transformed by love.
In the word Father, this feeling is the feeling of perfection and eternity.
And he says, I'm ashamed of what the church has made of this symbolism.
Well, he's trying to make it, Nietzsche is trying to make it, some kind of shared feeling of power and life, I take it.
And the glad tidings are that you should live this way.
On 35, aphorism 35, 159, the bringer of glad tidings died as he lived, as he taught, not to redeem mankind.
That's the everything sacrificed on the cross.
That's the Dimitri thing.
I'm suffering for everybody.
But to demonstrate how one ought to live.
That's the incarnation side.
What he's bequeathed to mankind is his practice, his bearing before the judges, before the guards, before the accusers, his bearing on the cross, and so forth.
And that's all something that Nietzsche seems to admire.
So we've got to ask the question now, pretty soon.
So, well, why isn't Jesus, if he understands that we're in heaven here and now, if he understands that the law is a bad thing, that you have to completely invent yourself, if he turns out to be giving us a whole new set of values and opening up a new world, why isn't he just a free spirit?
What's wrong with him?
Nietzsche never says what's wrong with him, but you ought to be able to figure it out.
Let me see if I need to read anything else.
Now, I think, yeah, I think that's it.
But now, what is it that he's got wrong, according to?
If you were finishing what Nietzsche is thinking, because he says he's almost a free spirit.
He's the last, let's get remember, he's the last of the Christian free spirits because the disciples misunderstood him, thought he was talking about in another world where in heaven there would be bliss and another eternity, where he's really talking about the kind of power you can have.
It won't be agape love, of course, the kind of aliveness and power you can have right now in this world if you get outside the law, if you would start inventing new things.
That's what he really came to tell people.
But there's something that he's got wrong.
Yeah, that's good.
That's good.
You're right on.
Exactly.
That's the trouble.
Nietzsche doesn't say it as if it's his trouble, but he does say that there is, he doesn't resist the top of 160.
He doesn't defend his rights.
He takes no steps to avert the worst.
And so forth.
He turns the other cheek, he says at another point.
Of course, that's the Christian words for it.
And so he says at the end of that, not to defend yourself, not to grow angry, not to make responsible, but not to resist even the evil man to love him.
He says that as if he likes it, but he obviously wouldn't like it, as you say.
And that's one of the things that he's got against, would have against it.
The other that he never, I'm sure he somewhere does what I'm going to say, but I don't know where it is.
If anybody finds it, let me know.
What would he think of Jesus's compassion for the weak and the crippled and the blind and in general, what Nietzsche would call thick and decadent people who haven't got much will to power and not much life?
What would Jesus think of?
Well, that you shouldn't do anything with them, or if you have to, you can just wipe them out.
I wish I could suddenly open to a quote which says that we have to be tough against all the weakness in us and not just us, he says, underlining.
Do you remember that quote?
I think I'm pretty sure it's in the reading somewhere.
Anyway, that's it.
You'd have to be tough on your any time when you're trying to be weak, when you want to be peaceful and just rest and so forth, when your life energy is running down, you'd have to fight that.
And if there are other people who are weak and energy is running down, you've got to fight that too.
And that's the other thing that I think he thinks Jesus is doing wrong.
But one thing is sure, the only good Christian died on the cross, he says, and that's because the right things that Jesus was doing got forgotten or misunderstood, and the wrong things that he was doing, again, he doesn't say this in anything I'm quoting, but I'm sure he thinks that the wrong things about what he was doing, namely turn the other cheek and compassion for everybody, even the weakest, that's what got to be the main story about the Redeemer.
That's what he's against.
Yeah, Beatrice, good.
Just all horror finally goes out to the poor but to the other people.
They're not really weak in the venue.
They're just good.
Well, insofar, I mean, they're two different things.
When he saves Mary Magdalene and says, let he is guiltless, cast the first stone.
And then that's one side of him that Nietzsche could like, that he is sort of somebody who is being falsely, badly treated, and who, but they're not really, let's assume, not weak themselves.
But I'm talking about all the cripples and the blind and the deaf and so forth that he helps.
He helps everybody.
Nietzsche says himself that there's nobody that he wouldn't help out.
I just read it somewhere.
Well, we know that, that he would help everybody, and we know that Nietzsche doesn't like it.
The quote I would like to find is how we have to be strong and be opposed to everything that's weak, not only in ourselves, but in anybody.
Yeah.
Ah, good.
Yeah, yeah.
Melissa's just reminding me or us that we've got to be careful and not take the Jesus that Yvonne makes up in the Grand Inquisitor story, the extreme Protestant, super demanding Jesus who wants you to be totally free and totally individual and take all of every, you know, all the stuff that you believe without any miracles, believe without any bread, believe without any community, believe without any arguments.
You just commit yourself to Jesus.
That's certainly not Nietzsche's story.
And it's not the church, the early church's story either.
That's something that Yvonne invented.
It would be just sort of Yvonne craziness if it weren't exactly Kierkegaard.
Because Yvonne has invented this extreme Protestantism where the individual is totally free and totally responsible only before God.
It's Luther.
I mean, Kierkegaard is extreme Luther and Yvonne is extreme.
Jesus in the Grand Inquisitor is extreme Yvonne.
Okay, but it's a good thing to keep track.
In fact, it sounds like a good question for the exam.
I think we should remember it.
These various accounts of Christianity is something to try to keep straight and relate.
That's the kind of thing.
I'll stop with that.
But the kind of thing we're going to ask on the exam is how to take some concept like Christianity, I'm not sure we want to use that one, and show how it works in these various books and how they relate to each other.
In a way, that's what I was trying to do today.
Okay.
Mm-hmm.