Okay, we're going to talk about the self, and we're going to give a view of the self that is the Christian view of the self, and it's the view that is sort of covered up for the long time in Christianity by all this Greek philosophy and the gods of the philosophers getting in there.
It's Pascal who first sort of announces the Christian view of the self, the Judeo-Christian, which has been there all along.
But first, let's go back to the Greek view, because it's the Greek view that's been there covering up the Christian view because the Greek gods of the philosopher got mixed into Christianity very early on with Saint Augustine in 300 AD.
Interestingly enough, the Russian Orthodox don't count Augustine as a saint.
I think that's a good idea because he's a big contributor to not messing up this understanding.
So here we go.
In the Platonic tradition, of which Augustine is unfortunately a big example, it was understood that human beings were an unstable combination of body and soul, of time, the body was in time, and eternity, the soul contemplated eternal truth.
And the idea was that to make this unstable combination stable, so you could lead a happy and harmonious life, you had to find out which part was essential and just get rid of the other part.
If your commitment to being involved in the world and getting the most out of having a body gets in the way of your contemplating eternal otherworldly forms, then you've either got to get rid of the otherworldly forms and enjoy having a body, or play down having a body and enjoy the bliss of contemplating eternal truth.
So, and Plato says you have to die to your body if you're a philosopher, so that you can have your head clear, so to speak, to think, to do your philosophy.
And Lucretius, just to give you an example that you're going to need later, you can go either way.
I mean, the body is a combination, each of us is a combination of a soul or mind and a body.
And given that we're this combination, you have two choices.
Since you don't fit well together, and you won't have a harmonious life if you've got these two contradictory impulses, you have to make live a life in which one or the other is essential and play down the other.
So I just gave you the Plato, Augustine, medieval Christian one: you play down the body and you go devote yourself to having a soul.
But there are others, of course, materialists who think opposite.
Lucretius, Roman philosopher, poet, I'm just using him as an example.
I mean, you don't have to know anything about Lucretius whatsoever, but I'll write it on the board so it isn't mysterious.
Okay, well, his idea was that we're just made out of atoms juggling or jiggling around, and that what he wanted to do was get your body in the best possible condition for these atoms jiggling around in a harmonious and pleasant way.
And that didn't mean having orgies.
That would be not a good kind of jiggling around.
It would be too, but it meant eating nice food and talking in pleasant places with pleasant friends.
You could give your own story.
But the idea was to get the most out of the kind of natural material body that you are.
And what did he think about all this Greek, all this Platonic stuff about the truth in the other world that was eternal and so forth?
Well, he thought it was just superstition, and that what you had to do was sort of talk yourself out of it.
And it was just a kind of bad dream that you got in the way of leading a pleasant way of life.
You don't want them.
You don't want these superstitions to guide you.
And they would get in the way of your natural needs and natural pleasures if you didn't get rid of them.
Okay, so that's the story.
And once you realize that you're essentially an eternal soul combined with a temporal body, then, and that you only have to identify yourself with one or the other, you get out of this conflict and this instability, sort of thrashing back and forth, and you tend to lead a happy, harmonious life as long as you live as if you were one or the other of the set of factors.
Now, I want to skip something, but I have to see how far I'm supposed to skip.
And what you're a life, living a life is a kind of voyage from confusion to clarity, from conflict to harmony.
When you live your life right, by the time you get to be old and wise, you have stopped having these contradictory impulses, and you have a harmonious life.
You realize whatever it is you take your true nature to be, and you get rid of whatever you take your unessential desires to be, and you satisfy the essential needs and desires, and you just get rid of the superficial, the wrong needs and desires.
Okay, and that gives you, I said, harmony, happiness, in other words, for it, peace gives you fulfillment.
All this talk about peace being so important, and the prayer you, you know, peace, people say, in lots of Christian and Hebrew prayers and services and so forth.
That's a very Greek idea that what you really want is peace and harmony, and that when you lead a good life in the right way, you'll get it.
You might wonder what could be better than having peace and having had it drummed into you in endless prayers and services.
It's a good question, but you'll find out in a minute.
Because Pascal already, and being the genius that he is, sees that that's not really the right thing for the Judeo-Christians to want.
So he's the first existential thinker, and he has an entirely new and different view.
For him, the self is essentially both soul and body.
And the Hebrews already thought that, or acted that way.
They didn't make a big distinction where you had to decide whether you were serving God or whether you were winning battles, fighting idol worshipers or something.
That was all part of the day's work and in your life.
And certainly, when you get the fact that God becomes man, which is what Pascal is, it looks like having a body is just as important as having a soul.
I mean, if having a body wasn't an important thing, then why in the world would God take on a body?
And of course, if it wasn't important to have a soul, then God would just die, period, when his body died.
Surely there's something going on in the Hebrew Christian account of it, which seems to indicate that the body and the soul are equally essential.
Dante's interesting on this.
Dante understands that the.
See, they may get it wrong about peace, but they certainly get it right about their bodies and souls.
They never lose it.
Even when they take over the Greeks, they take over Aristotle, who likes bodies, over Plato, who thinks we should die to our body.
In fact, Dante thinks bodies are so important that the people who die and go to hell and in the inferno and go to paradise and don't have any bodies couldn't really be there at all.
So they get loner bodies, which are sort of like bodies, until the day, until the final judgment when they'll get their real bodies back.
And only when they get their real bodies back will they really experience the pain of hell or the bliss of paradise.
You just can't be a full human being without your body.
But then, if these are contradictory impulses, and now that's something Dante had no clue about.
That's what I said Pascal thinks.
So he thinks that these two aspects are contradictory, the soul and the body, and says, what a monster then is man, what a novelty, what a chaos, what a contradiction.
And that's the new idea, that the self is a set of contradictory impulses.
The Greeks already knew that.
But those contradictory impulses that are equally essential, and you can't get rid of either one of them.
That's news.
What that means is that you're never going to get happy harmoniousness and peace.
That isn't what you could have, and it isn't what you should have, and you don't want it anyway.
There are better things.
So, what is the best thing?
Well, one funny way to put it, in your Pascal quotes, these quotes I'm quoting are there.
Pascal says that you should live wholly in a way stretched along this tension between these two aspects.
He says, we do not display greatness by going to one extreme or the other, but in touching both at once and filling all the intervening space.
Be as embodied as you can, be as disembodied as you can, be as involved as you can, that's the body part.
Contemplate truth in a disembodied way, as much as you can, that's the other part.
Get them together.
But you can't get them together in a peaceful way.
You'll always be under this kind of tension.
And so, the idea of this harmoniousness and peace, that's a Greek idea.
For Pascal, the most you can do is be constantly alive to what an incredibly wonderful and hard thing it is to be a human self.
And of course, you see that coming out in Kierkegaard, where anguish turns out to be a defining feature of the knight of faith.
He never gets over it.
You don't say to the knight of faith, well, grant him peace, let him sleep well tonight, and so forth.
He never has peace, and he never sleeps well, and that's just, but he's got something else better than peace.
He's got anguish and bliss, which go together.
And that's so there you get, from Pascal's point of view, you can repress and deny part of yourself, or you can live in the tension.
If you try to repress and deny the way the Greeks did, and if you look at it from a Plato point of view, that you should be more, you should be, sort of, bring out the angel in you and repress the devil in you.
Pascal says man is neither simply angel nor simply brute, and the unfortunate thing is that he who would act the angel acts the brute.
So not only is it impossible to be one or the other, but it's even dangerous to try to be just one or the other.
He's very extreme.
It's brilliantly out on a new limb.
I don't know.
Anybody could see so many amazingly, radically new things.
And Dostoevsky is very influenced by Pascal.
I have not read anywhere that he read Pascal, but I know he must have.
Anyway, every Christian would.
So I could begin to ask you questions that you can keep in mind as you read the brothers.
Which brother Karamaza turns out acting the brute?
That is, not in the sense of bashing people around, but the bad guy.
Who turns out to be a bad guy because he wants to be so perfectly good?
Any brother come in there.
And so now let me see.
But if you try to live in this contradictory way, you oscillate between pride and despair, he thinks.
And Jesus is the extremist version of somebody who should oscillate between pride and despair, because he's, after all, God, and that's something to be pretty proud of.
But he's also meek and humble and washing the feet of Mary Magdalene and so forth.
He seems to be somehow and letting people, in effect, walk all over him if they want to.
That's this non, non-what, what's the word for it?
When you let people hurt you, but you don't hurt them back.
That's a Christian notion.
There's an obvious phrase for it.
Non-what?
Non-violence?
It's sort of, it's what?
It's turned the other cheek, but what is that?
And well, anyway, it's it's so Jesus is whatever this is, somebody who, and what are we supposed to think about that?
Well, somehow, Jesus, the God-man, lived at these extremes of misery and greatness, of what, and somehow he's able to do it without falling into pride or despair.
And what we're supposed to do, and here's where Pascal just cops out.
He doesn't have anything interesting to say.
He says, well, since Jesus did it, we should imitate Jesus so we can do it too.
But that doesn't help much.
I mean, we don't understand how he did it, what it was to do it, and how come we can do it.
After all, he was the God-man.
Pascal just hasn't got anything helpful to say.
He got as far as he got.
We're a contradiction.
We've got to live in anguish and bliss, and there's no way to get outside the contradiction.
You've got to be alive in it.
But that's not enough.
So, where do you go from there?
Well, I don't know that anybody said anything interesting about the self between Pascal and Dostoevsky, but I bet they did.
And somebody may send me an email from the podcast world, or you guys may come and tell me in office hours.
But as far as I know, the next move that sort of completes what Pascal did half of is Kierkegaard on this page, where he decides to tell you exactly what the self is and how it should be put together.
This page is from a book you'll see at the bottom of the page one, Kierkegaard's book, The Sickness Unto Death.
And the interesting thing is that, you know, I told you Kierkegaard writes almost all his books under other pseudonyms, like Fear and Trembling is from the point of view of Johannes de Salentio.
So, De Salentio, as I keep telling people in office hours when they come in, believing, I mean, DeSalentio says he loves God, that when he's contemplating God, it fills him with peace and happiness, and so forth and so forth.
And that's true, all right, but he's in despair.
De Salentio hasn't got faith, and he's no knight of faith.
Loving God is Platonic, it's in Dante, but it's not, it's not from Kierkegaard's point of view, it's not Christianity.
And so, don't get confused by that.
But Sickness Unto Death is one of the two books Kierkegaard wrote from the point of view of a Christian.
And he signed, he didn't sign it with his own name because he said it's so hard to be a Christian that he doesn't claim that he can do it.
The best he can do is love God and be blissful in his radiant stuff that resignation can do, that Johannes de Salentio can do.
But we're supposed to believe that the right answer, so to speak, of how to live is in sickness unto death.
The sickness unto death, the title, is the Bible name for despair.
And the book is all about kinds of despair.
And then there is in the middle of the book this very formal definition of the self, which is, as you'll see when we go through it, supposed to be a definition or a description or a formal something of what a self has to be and do in order to be out of despair, out of the sickness.
And he wants to say that all of us are in despair.
We're all in the sickness unto death.
But I'm not sure do I want to start with that or with the self?
Well, having gotten into this in a different way than I intended, I'm going to go through with it.
It was something I had to talk about today.
So it would make it a lot more interesting, I guess, and maybe I should have always done it this way, to try to convince you first that you're all in despair so that you will read this passage with special attention because it's supposed to tell you how to get out of it.
And if you think you aren't in it, if you're having a good time and you're exercising your capacities and either satisfying your body or your mind or in unstable ways, maybe both on and off, then you're not going to be so impressed.
So I better give you Kierkegaard's interesting, I think, maybe even convincing argument that you're all in despair.
And me.
There may be a few people here, I don't claim to be one, who aren't.
The only way to not be in despair, I'll just tell you in advance so that any of you who know that you satisfy these conditions can relax, the only way to be out of despair is to have been in despair, to recognize that you're in despair, and then have been saved from it.
Unless you've gone through all that, you're in despair right now.
Now, how can that be?
Well, look on the page two.
I've decided that is to do the chart, not the chart, but what's below the chart.
Below the chart is the argument that you're all in despair.
So I'm going to read it to you.
The common view overlooks the fact that when compared with illness, despair differs dialectically from what one usually calls sickness.
Dialectically, I don't, I mean, Kierkegaard throws in the word dialectically a lot.
As far as I can see, you could just cross it out.
It doesn't do anything, is the argument.
It's a Hegel term.
And it has, I think you could almost say philosophically, but the best thing is just not to say anything there.
Despair differs from what one usually calls sickness because it's a sickness of the spirit.
And this aspect, dialectical, I'm going to skip it for now.
This aspect, properly understood, brings further thousands under the category of despair.
You are those further thousands and me.
If at any time a physician is convinced that so-and-so is in good health, and then later that person becomes ill, the physician may well be right about his having been well at the time, but he's now sick.
Not so with despair.
Once despair appears, what is apparent is that the person was in despair.
In fact, it's never possible.
Now, let's stop with that.
It's a very funny kind of disease.
It's a disease that has what Kierkegaard calls the dialectic of eternity, but it just, again, it's just eternity in it.
And that means that, remember, if you go living along in time like this, just moment by moment by moment, and then comes the defining moment, and you get a defining commitment, it affects your whole past as not having it, and your whole future is having it.
Well, despair has the same kind of eternal structure.
You're living along moment by moment, and then comes despair.
When you discover that you're in despair, it goes back and tells you you've been in despair all along and you always would be, will be.
Well, what could that be?
Well, that's a very strange claim.
Well, luckily, you see Rishima Monomur.
That helps a lot understanding.
What does that woman realize, little French woman, when she looks into the mirror, remembers that if she loves the Japanese man, she has to forget the German and then her life will become meaningless.
But if she doesn't love the Japanese man, then she can never have fulfillment and intimacy, and she realizes she's trapped.
What's the trap?
She's got a kind of life that just doesn't work.
There is no way to do it, to keep the first love alive and in front of her and to have another love too.
That's so impossible that it isn't even possible for the people who live in the world where impossibilities are possible.
But there are lots of different ways that people's lives may, in the end, turn out not to work.
I'll just give you one other from Kierkegaard's Either or Volume 1.
There he talks about some person who was somehow badly treated when they were a child, abused or beaten up by their siblings or abandoned by their parents or whatever.
And they've defined themselves as that unfortunate person.
And there's nothing they can do to fix it.
And what they need to do is go on and get over it, integrate it somehow, and give themselves a life.
But they don't want to get a new life.
They want to vindicate and get back what they feel they deserve from their childhood.
And they won't be happy unless they get it back.
But of course, it's impossible.
As Kierkegaard would say, they want this impossible fixing up of the past, which they can't have.
And they don't want the openness to the future where they could still be happy, which they do have.
So their life is impossible.
And they're in despair.
But there are all kinds of ways of living.
And the general way of being in despair is to be in the contradiction, which in some way or another you are living in, and you don't realize it.
But now the question is: well, then why am I telling you that you're in despair now?
Well, that's the interesting dismal.
Kierkegaard is so full of funny and wonderful ideas.
Despair is such that once you experience it, you see that the kind of life you are living, you can never be happy.
And that's half the story.
But if it's really what you see is that your life isn't working like the Japanese woman, then you see that you never were happy, that you always were living in such a way that you could find out that the way you're living is a way that you can't live it securely.
And once you fall into despair, then you see that you were in despair all along.
That's what it is.
Let me try one more way to put it because you're not looking as convinced as I thought you should be.
So let's say, I'll try this.
Distinguish despair from being sad.
Suppose something really sad happens, your dog dies or whatever, and you feel really sad about it for a while.
That doesn't mean that you were sad all your life.
Remember, that's the first sentence.
That would be like an illness.
If you discover you're sick, it doesn't mean you've been sick with that disease all your life.
If you discover that something about, you might even discover something about your life that makes you sad, namely that you, I don't know, are dyslexic or something.
But that might be too bad.
But that's not this kind of sadness.
Well, that might just make you sad for a while.
But now, maybe something really awful could happen to you, that you've been training all your life to be a ballet dancer and now you've broken your ankle, you'll never be able to do it again.
That would make you miserable because of how much that was tied up in your life.
But that wouldn't mean that while you were a successful ballet dancer, you were miserable.
It would just mean that you had seen that for the rest of your life, you would never be happy again.
Yeah.
Well, you could say that, but it wouldn't be that, how can we put it?
It isn't, it isn't as if there's something about the way your way of life is impossible.
I mean, you could certainly say that you didn't realize something bad was going to happen, but it was sort of an accident that it happened.
That's why, and you're miserable from then on.
But if you realize that the kind of life you're living doesn't work, now comes the question.
You certainly realize that you're going to be in X, let's say, despair, from now on.
But if you realize that your life isn't working, what about your past?
Do you realize, what do you realize about your past?
And you were always in despair.
Because you always had set things up so that you could never really be happy, satisfied, and fulfilled the way you were living.
And that means, you see, there's nothing now, it's easy to draw the last conclusion with it.
That means what?
That we're all in despair right now.
Because when we were all, you may be lucky enough to get through life without realizing it.
But if you realize that your way of getting the factors and the self together, which we'll talk about next, is not working, then you realize it never did.
And you realize later that you were in despair right now, sitting here, only you didn't know it.
Now, you want to say something?
Well, that anguish, no, the interesting thing about anguish is that it's also, I think, I have to think about it, I think it's also eternal, but it's eternal like the finding commitment is.
Not that you had it all along, but that it's who you are.
And when you didn't have it, you were lost and your life was empty.
And now you've got it, and your life is positive.
So here, anguish starts here, I think.
And anguish says you are in anguish from now on because you see the sword over the head of the beloved, and you see that you've got a higher authority in your life that can make you go against the ethical.
But you don't see that you always have a higher authority in your life that make you go against the ethical because you didn't.
You only got it here.
So you can't project the anguish back.
The answer is to sort of think about the phenomenon.
And the only thing, the only experience that you can project back this way is despair, Kierkegaard thinks.
So let's read it now.
So once it happens, once despair appears, I'm in the middle of the paragraph.
What is apparent is that the person was in despair.
In fact, it's never possible at any time to decide anything about a person who was not saved through having been in despair.
That is, you can be saved if you're in despair and then get the right thing to get out of it, get a savior.
But only then, you can't just be saved before you ever get into it.
For when, whatever, for when whatever causes a person to despair occurs, it is immediately evident that he's been in despair his whole life.
When someone gets a fever, on the other hand, it cannot possibly be said that now it's evident that he's had a fever all his life.
That despair is a characteristic of the spirit.
It's related to the eternal and has something of the eternal in its dialectic, that is, in the way it works.
Okay, I was going to put that later, and we put it here now, because now we're going to find out both how it is at a very abstract level, we're all in despair.
You have to fill it in with your own story about what it is that makes your life not work.
But everybody's life isn't working for the reason that Pascal understands, that we are a contradiction and we've got to get it together.
And there's only one way to get it together, and most of us haven't done it.
But now we have to see how that works.
Yeah.
With what?
The moment you.
Well, when you realize that the way you've set up your life, you can never be happy in the future, and then you realize, and moreover, it follows, if it follows from the way your life is set up, that you can never be happy in the future, then it's always been like that, at least since you got old enough to have a way of life.
Think of the French woman again.
When she gives her sigh or moan, I forget the word, of utter what?
Utter misery?
I have to go back to the script, but she gives a something of something, the script says, which is clearly her expression of despair, as she realizes that her life, the way she set it up, she could never be happy.
She was lucky enough to, if the German had lived, she never would have realized that she was sort of skating on thin ice.
But the way she set up the fact that she's got a defining commitment, and that if that defining commitment dies, she can't deal with it without giving up meaning or intimacy the way she set it up.
Then she realizes that that's the way.
It's always been the way her life has been, that she can't have meaning and intimacy, or at least she's subject to this always possible disaster.
And that's her despair.
And the despair comes, that the experience comes at the moment where she actually sees the disaster and sees that it's not just bad luck or something she can fix or hope that it'll get better, that that's just the way her life has got to be given the way she, the kind of life she has.
Does that help?
Okay.
Now, we're going to read this difficult thing.
I have to start now because I want to read it before you all go away so you can think about it.
Okay, so we're going to read the first paragraph.
And always keep the chart in mind, but I'll tell you when to look at it.
So we're going to understand the human being is spirit, but what is spirit?
Spirit is the self.
Then what is the self?
The self, this is a crucial sentence.
The self is a relation which relates to itself, or that in the relation which is its relating to itself.
The self is not a relation, but the relations relating to itself.
That's a fancy new idea.
And it became, it's now, I mean, all existentialists talk this way.
Heidegger starts his big book, Being in Time, that human, he called it Dasein, which is us, is defined as, what is it now?
We are a being who is defined by for whom our being is an issue for us.
That's his way of putting it.
But whatever, it's the idea is that you have to, in the way you behave, take a stand on what a human self is.
And that's already been in what I said.
I mean, the Greeks did it one way, and the Romans did it another way, and so forth.
But this very abstract thing, that human beings are defined by the way they understand what it is to be a human being.
That's what that complicated sentence says.
The self is not the relation.
to itself, but it's that the relation relates to itself.
That's the tricky part.
See, if you look at the picture now, it's a relation between, we'll read more in a minute, two sets of factors which are listed in those boxes.
But just being a relation between the two of them only gets you R1 in my drawing.
And that is, that's just the relation.
The relation relating itself to itself is R2.
We haven't got to that.
Don't think about that yet.
So we have to have the factors first.
Now we get the factors.
A human being is a synthesis of the infinite and the finite, the temporal and the eternal, the freedom and necessity.
In short, it's a synthesis.
The synthesis is a relation between two terms.
Looked at in this way, a human being is not yet a self.
That's a funny paragraph.
You think that last we just, you know, we've been just told what a self is, and it was a mouthful, but at least we heard it.
But no, no, that wasn't a self.
Why wasn't it a self?
Well, it's because the synthesis didn't take a stand on being a synthesis.
The self didn't relate itself to itself.
Now, and what does all that fancy talk mean?
Well, here we go again.
It's a synthesis of two sets of factors, and you should be very familiar with them by now: the finite, temporal, necessary.
We'll say more about them all.
The infinite, the eternal, and the possible.
But again, I'm not quite ready to tell you all about that, but what does it mean to say that it's a synthesis?
Well, that's very important.
I put on a chart body and soul in a ghostly sort of way with dentes.
Kierkegaard never says that we're a combination of body and soul.
And it's no accident.
He doesn't want to because he thinks that body and soul are a combination.
And I'm putting a big emphasis on that word.
A combination means you could take them apart.
And that's exactly what the Greeks thought they could do.
They could either die to their body or get rid of their superstition about souls because they were a combination of these two sets of factors.
But Kierkegaard says we're a synthesis of the two sets of factors.
That's his way of saying you've got to satisfy both of them.
You've got to live in such a way that you can't dump either.
I mean, it's just his way of saying that we're defined as a contradiction.
It's the Pascal point.
It's the Judeo-Christian point.
Our body is essential.
God sort of wouldn't have had a body if it weren't.
Our soul is essential.
Certainly we wouldn't be worrying about eternity and such if it weren't.
And we're both of them.
If you're just a synthesis, then you haven't even seen the problem yet.
And that's what it is to be R1, to be a human being.
Being a human being isn't a self yet.
Being a human being is sort of a problem that isn't solved yet.
So let's go on.
In a relation between two things, the relation is the third term in the form of a negative unity.
Now, this is probably the hardest paragraph.
And it took me years to sort of crack it.
But once you understand this paragraph, then everything falls into place.
So try hard.
In a relation between two things, two sets of factors, the relation is a third term in the form of a negative unity.
And the two relate to the relation, and in the relation to that relation, I don't know what that means for it.
This is what it is from the point of view of a soul or soul and body to be in relation.
So you see, he does talk about soul and body.
I made it sound like he didn't.
But he doesn't think they're factors.
He thinks, but I see this is a really tricky paragraph.
What this paragraph is about is the Greeks.
And what it says is that there's a way of relating to yourself in a negative way.
You can unify yourself by getting rid of half of yourself.
It's a very abstract and condensed way of saying this long thing I said at the beginning about what it is to have a self.
And one of the ways to try to have a self doesn't work is to try to get rid of one of the back sets of factors, claiming it's not the essential one.
You're only essentially a body, or you're only essentially a soul.
And that would be a negative unity.
That doesn't work.
And we'll hear more about that in a minute.
And then, if, on the other hand, the relation relates itself to itself, then this relation is the positive third, and this is the self.
Okay, that means, if you go over here, if the factors are related to each other just by being combined, you haven't got a self.
You haven't even got spirit and passion.
You're just living along like an organ, like an animal or something, or child.
If you try to get the self together with all your might, that's R2.
And what happens in R2 is that you can't do it.
You can't alone fix the contradiction.
Now, Kierkegaard is going to try to go beyond Pascal.
Pascal got that far.
You sort of are kind of crucified on the extremes of pride and humility and so forth, but he doesn't explain how you can get them together.
So now comes the very next line.
Such a relation which relates itself to itself, and now it is a self, must either have established itself or been established by something else.
Something else?
I was looking for that phrase.
Okay.
Now, how do I want to put this?
Okay, well, it turns out you can't do R2.
We have to explain more about that in a minute.
But what is R3?
Well, that's, now let's go back here.
The self relating to itself by relating to something else.
You see, right?
That's the third little paragraph.
Do you recognize that that is a very abstract form of something that you've been hearing about a lot?
I hope you do.
How is the self relates to itself by relating to something else?
Or in a different translation, by relating to another, which is the same.
What?
Yes, yes, hooray, good.
Several people said it.
Last time I gave this, nobody said it, and I almost went home in despair.
But so there you have it.
The idea is that the only way to get the two factors together in a harmonious, well, harmonious isn't the right thing, get them together in a way where they reinforce each other.
The more of one, the more of the other, instead of contradicting each other, is to get a defining relation.
And I will explain that in a minute, but let's finish reading this.
Skip all the stuff now that goes on in between and go to the end of that big paragraph.
The imbalance in despair is not simply an imbalance, but an imbalance in a relation that relates itself to itself and which is constituted by another.
Skip that for a while.
That's going to come out back later.
That's hard.
Let's go down to the next.
This then is the formula which describes the state of the self when despair is completely eradicated.
In relating to itself and in wanting to be itself, the self is grounded transparently in the power that constituted it.
That is a mouthful.
And if you read it sort of through kind of orthodox Christian eyes, it looks like he's saying, well, the self has to get outside of itself and somehow be grounded in God because there's this power that established it.
But if you read it very carefully, you notice that the power isn't capitalized, that it's a very general notion.
I mean, it could be Jesus for reasons that we get mentioned every once in a while.
It can't be God the Father, because Kierkegaard thinks that once Jesus has come along and says he's God, and he is, I mean, that's always inside Christianity we're talking, then you get your relation to God by having an unconditional commitment to Jesus.
You've got no relation to God the Father at all.
There isn't even any God the Father, it looks like what used to be God the Father is now understood to be simply that all things are possible.
You don't love and pray to that things are possible.
You love and pray to Jesus, who's a finite, embodied God.
And that's the power that constituted it.
But it needn't be Jesus.
I mean, then it would be capital P, or it could be just the God-man.
You could write God-Man.
It could be, of course, we could keep doing this, Dante's relation to Beatrice.
Beatrice posited or established Dante.
Now, how could that be?
Well, Dante became Dante, the greatest love poet of all times, let's suppose.
He thought he was, who wrote the best love poem about his lady that anybody ever wrote.
Beatrice did that.
I mean, she made it possible.
She made it, she drew out of Dante an infinite passion, which defined him as the poet of the lady Beatrice.
In that sense, she really produced Dante.
That's the first half of this.
That is the sense in which the self is grounded transparently now in the power that constituted it.
Well, Dante is grounded in Beatrice, and she made him Dante, gave him the definition.
He was already running around, and everybody was calling him Dante, but he didn't have an individual until he got an unconditional commitment, and that defined him as the poet, lover of Beatrice.
So she did that.
Now, what is it to be transparently ground?
Well, that's Kierkegaard jargon for in everything you do in your life that matters, you reflect, you express this relationship.
So, whatever Dante did, he did it if it was worth doing and important to him, and was the lover of Beatrice.
So, that whenever you get your power that establishes you, that is, draws out of you an unconditional commitment that gives you a definition, you will then express it in everything meaningful you do.
I don't think you wash your hands, I don't think Dante washed his hands as the lover of Beatrice.
I don't think and brushed his teeth if he could do that.
But anything that anybody does that matters, they do as in a way that expresses that this commitment is defining them.
So, now that gives you that whole story, but it doesn't have, I haven't ever really explained very clearly, and I won't really be able to fully, but if you look at the top italics, we can now explain more of the diagram, anyway.
See where we are?
Despair is a sickness of the spirit, of the self, and so it can have three forms.
That's where you've got R1, R2, and R3.
You're unconscious in despair of having a self.
That is, you're in despair, but you don't know you're in despair, and you don't know you've got a self.
And you aren't even in despair, really, because you haven't got any of this feeling of eternity, your life doesn't work.
You keep yourself in a constant state of distraction.
Pascal's word for it is diversion.
Pascal, I think I read it when I read these quotes.
You can do it by playing tennis, or you can do it by gambling.
He has a list, or dancing, or staying alone in your room and doing algebra, like he thinks Descartes was doing, or whatever.
You can, and you can do it also by getting drunk, presumably, and running around with wild women, whatever.
And I'm putting some of these in there because I want you to keep your eyes open.
Which karamatsa is going to be in that state, the state that is in the state of spiritlessness, where he hasn't even understood that he's got a self and a problem.
Okay, that's the first one.
That's the despair of having a despair of having a self, being unconscious of the despair of having a self.
Then there is not wanting in despair to be oneself.
These are all so cryptic, I have to unravel them.
What would it be to, in despair, not want to be oneself?
Yeah.
Are you even fair?
Oh, well, we've talked about it, you know.
I mean, so this person's life is already not working.
They're just not aware it's not working.
They manage to keep themselves sufficiently busy in the stock market and drunk and running around with ladies that they haven't, they're doing it on purpose not to notice that their life isn't working.
And that's possible.
Lots of people do that.
And that would be to be in despair and not notice they're in despair.
How do we know they're in despair if they don't notice it?
It's the same story we told.
You know.
Yeah, I could see you know.
Somebody knows.
So how do we know that everybody's in despair who isn't out of despair?
Yeah.
That's half of it.
But I was going to go with the other half.
We know that once they realize they're in despair, they will realize they always were.
And since they haven't been saved, they will someday realize they're in despair, or maybe they won't.
They might live without noticing.
But if they did, so we're talking about this Karamatsov.
If this Karamatsov ever gets unmuddled enough to be able to realize what state he's in, he'll not only realize that he's in an eternal mess, but that he's been an eternal mess forever.
Okay, yeah, your hand is up.
How does that work?
How can you go about getting saved from despair?
Aha.
Well, you need help from outside.
You need a savior.
The savior, in Dante's case, was Beatrice, who was so attractive, so beautiful, had such beautiful legs and smile and eyes and everything that he became the devoted his life to her.
I mean, it might be some job that is so attractive, might be being a teacher is so attractive that you devote your whole life to it.
Something comes along and is your calling.
So how do you get out of despair?
You answer your calling, so to speak.
You can always refuse to answer your calling because of course once you do, it's all risky.
Okay, yes, Beatrice.
A what?
A cause.
Sure it can.
Yeah, why not?
Anything finite and temporal and therefore risky is a possible object of a defining commitment.
That is, Martin Luther King is an interesting case which keeps coming up.
If you say that Martin Luther King thinks of himself and his cause as justice for the black people somewhere, sometime, the sooner the better or something, that's not enough because it's not really vulnerable.
He can live and die and he will have succeeded in doing his part.
He has to think of it as justice right now for my people in the South, in the United States, in the 19 whatevers.
And then that tells him, and there's the test.
It tells him every day, finitely and temporally, what to do.
When he gets up in the morning, he knows what matters, namely organizing marches, presumably most of the time.
But the point is, it's got to be something that tells you moment to moment what to do.
I'll tell you a whole story that will answer Beatrice's question.
I wasn't going to, but I will.
Go ahead.
I'll tell you in a minute.
Your defining commitment is impossible.
Ah, well, then you have to have faith, and then you will discover that you'll have it anyway.
I mean, that's we're back to the new, you'll always have Isaac.
If you're willing to suffer the anguish, you'll always get the bliss.
And the answer is grief and whole stuff to another.
Go ahead, yeah?
So you're being yourself, or no, no, you will go through anguish, not despair.
I mean, you could be in despair, but that would mean that you would have sort of lost it.
I mean, that is repudiated and forgotten what you got.
But if you've got a defining commitment, you never lose it.
It becomes part of you out of which you see the world, and you get another one.
You always will have a new Isaac because even though it seems impossible, you can be able to be defined in such a way that you can keep your definition and get a new definition.
This is all the story of Hiroshima and the Japanese man.
Oh, no, if they stop with resignation, it's still despair.
Because you, I guess I haven't made it clear.
The only way, I see that there's a basic thing I haven't said, but I was going to get there.
The only way to be out of despair is to get the factors together, keep the picture in front of you, in such a way that the more finite, the more infinite in your life, the more temporal, the more eternal in your life, the more things are fixed and necessary, like a definition, the more they are possible and open.
That's the only way to get out of despair.
That's the first thing to say.
And the only way to do that, what I just said, is to relate to something outside the self.
And how relate?
Well, he doesn't say it, but it's with unconditional commitment.
I write it there.
Now, I'll tell you the story, the story for Beatrice later, but I will.
But right now, I want to say, and how does that happen?
Well, that's very important.
And that's what you're sort of seeing, I haven't said.
How does a defining commitment get the factors together in this positive way?
That's what you need to know, right?
Because then you'll know how to be out of despair if you've got these factors together in a permanent, positive way.
Well, it follows.
That's the brilliance of Kierkegaard.
It just falls out, so to speak, of the definition of what it is, our description, of what it is to have an unconditional commitment, that it is finite and infinite, temporal and eternal, necessary, and possible.
Let's go through it.
The easiest one is the temporal and eternal.
Where did, by the way, I should have read that.
Didn't I ever read?
Yeah, a human being is a synthesis of those things.
I just, okay, so now, a defining commitment, let's start with temporal and eternal, because that's the easiest.
How is it temporal and eternal?
Well, it's going along in time, and it stays in time, but when you get to defining commitment, it is forever.
To talk like Dostoevsky, he's got this good way of, instead of talking about the eternal, to talk about forever.
But anyway, you can get in time a forever relation.
I will read it because I wrote it the way I wanted to write it.
Here's my section: how the factors reinforce each other.
Oh, I want the quote from another book of Kierkegaard's: Only in time do I become eternal.
You're prepared for that now.
That is, it's a special kind of eternal, not the Plato kind where you contemplate something outside of time, outside of involvement, outside of the body.
It's by being completely involved bodily and mentally with another person or in a cause that you become get and time becomes crucial for you and eternal.
So the more time, the more eternal, so to speak.
Now, to explain the finite and infinite is harder because I haven't prepared you for it.
But the sense in which a defining commitment is finite is easy.
It's an unconditional, you love something finite.
That's what I said to Beatrice now.
That's the vulnerable part.
That's why you can't love yourself and you can't love the ethical.
Those aren't finite.
And now what is it?
How do you get the infinite in there?
Well, he's got a very, just as he redefines the eternal in order to fit them together, but it's not a trick, it's an experience.
So there's an experience of the infinite, which is the world.
Now, how is the world infinite?
Well, when you've got a defining relation, everything that you come across that matters is constituted by or gets its meaning from the defining relation.
And not only everything actual, but everything possible, that is, everything you could ever come across that mattered, would get its meaning and significance for you from the relation.
Well, that's a different thing.
That's a new dimension.
That everything that you could ever conceivably come across would have this meaning.
That's because it's part of the way your world is.
It's not just another fact.
Let me see how I wrote it here.
It gives, yeah, an infinite passion for something finite gives you your world and makes you able in all experience to distinguish what is significant and insignificant or you.
So there you get the more finite, that is the more particular and vulnerable and present the person or cause is, the more infinite, namely, the more it defines the limits of your world.
It tells you what can enter your world and under what conditions, so to speak.
Now, the next one is easy again.
And since the commitment defines you, it's like it's got a kind of necessity, like triangles have 180 degrees.
I mean, it's if Dante is the lover of Beatrice, then that's a necessary fact about Dante.
And everything that follows from that fact, like having 180 degrees follows from being a three-sided closed figure, will be necessary about Dante.
That, well, let's not try to list them.
I'm sure there are lots of things.
Anyway, now, oh, yeah, but free.
What about this freedom and possibility?
How does it look on the chart?
I gave you.
Let me just look at it.
What's it called?
Okay, there's necessity and there's possibility or freedom.
That is, and that's easy.
You're free, one, to give up your defining relation and betray it.
That's what Holly Martin does, if we think he has a defining relation to his friend Harry Lyme.
You can eternalize it in a bad sense.
Let's call it, idealize it, and become a knight of resignation.
That's what the French woman does.
You can express it in everything you do.
That's what you're supposed to do.
And that's, and you're free to have those choices.
So it's always, just because it's your definition, it makes it necessary about you doesn't take away your freedom the way triangles are not free to be, I don't know, anything else.
You're a human being, you have a definition, and you're free to deal with it.
And moreover, you have to be free to take a new way of dealing with things all the time.
Martin Luther King is free to call off his peace marches or to do them.
He's free to do them with white kids from the north or not and so forth.
And each time you have to make a decision and you're free.
So there you get it.
The more necessity, the more freedom.
So now we see that if you have a defining commitment, sort of voila, it all falls out.
What was a contradictory self becomes harmonious as an understatement?
A self in which the factors reinforce each other, where you could say of each the more this, the more that.
And so you are out of despair and, so to speak, always out of despair.
Of course, you could be in grief, and you could get stuck in a defining commitment with resignation.
So I should say if you have a defining commitment in faith, you're out of despair.
You have to be a knight of faith, obviously.
Put that in.
Yeah.
Okay, the three forms.
One is not knowing you're in despair.
That just sort of keeping yourself drunk or being an innocent child.
Those are both forms of spiritlessness.
Then there is, and I'm not going to say enough much about this till we get to the brothers, because it goes into it so completely.
That is trying to get rid of one half of yourself or the other.
I wasn't clear about that at all.
And not being able to do it, of course, because you're a synthesis, not a combination.
So you beat your head against the wall, trying to get rid of your sensuality, for instance, so you can be pure intellect, or trying to get to be pure sensuality, and it doesn't work.
Then the third one, I forget how they're listed here, because I don't think I even mentioned the third.
Okay, not what I've done, inauthentic despair, the drunken one.
Not wanting in despair to be oneself, that's how to get rid of, trying to get rid of half.
Then there is wanting in despair to be oneself.
I didn't explain that one.
What would it be?
It would be not trying to get rid of half, but trying to keep both halves and get them together without being related to another.
If you don't, trying to be a self on your own willpower without a defining commitment is another and most interesting, and for Dostoevsky, the most interesting form of despair.
And there's a brother who's a perfect example of it.
Okay, now I think I did that.
Now I'm going to come back with a crazy example.
I don't know whether you're going to consider that it shows that all of Kierkegaard is really like a joke, or whether it's going to show you that defining commitments come in very many different forms.
It's a true story, but I saw a hand up, didn't I?
And ignored somebody.
Where did I see that?
Didn't I ignore somebody?
Yes.
Ah, well, it depends.
I mean, it's a good question.
If you're doing it in a way that is universal, like being for the equality for the black people or for all ethnic minorities or something, that's ethical, but it's not vulnerable.
And if it's, I'm going to save these people here now in Georgia or into the South right now, or I consider my life a failure, that's not ethical because there's no universal principle, save the black people in the South right now.
That's why they're different.
Okay, okay, now here's an amazing story.
A true story, it's hard to believe.
And I know the person well who about it is a fellow graduate student of mine long ago was, wrote a book which was a bestseller.
You can still find it in Moe's, I bet.
It's called An Unknown Woman.
And it's about her life and her despair.
That is, she was a mess, and her relationships were all a mess.
And she finally decided she couldn't live that way anymore.
She had to go and sort it out.
So she got a dog to protect her and went out to Nantucket, this lonely island, in the winter when nobody was around to just think through what she was up to.
And after she thought it all through, she really reached the bottom because she was in despair.
She decided there was no way that her life would ever be anything but a mess.
She was going to commit suicide.
She thought that was a, you know, was worth the trip, so to speak.
She saw the way she had to do it, what she had to do.
And then, when she got ready to commit suicide, she thought, but who will take care of the dog?
And the dog incidentally was named Logos.
That's the Godman.
Independently.
Don't ask me why.
I mean, just the strangest coincidence.
So there was, she couldn't kill herself because of Logos.
And she had, it turns out, defining commitment to the dog.
It didn't turn out you couldn't see Yetix defining.
She just wondered who was going to feed the dog.
But because, and so the dog prevented her from committing suicide, she came back, she got her life together around the dog.
How could you do that?
She became a vegetarian, an anti-vivisectionist, the kind of person who sort of attacks people who wear furs and belts and shoes and whatever.
Everything.
And she built her life around causes, all of whom were related to the dog.
And that was what the book was about.
She didn't know any Kierkegaard, but it's a neat example.
She found another, an other, and not a human being, she wasn't good with human beings, that made, that gave her life a central kind of meaning.
The next part is really sort of sad and pathetic because the dog died.
And she did not make it into being a knight of faith.
She wrote a second book about how upset she was that the dog died, and she sued the veterinarian for malpractice.
And the book was all about that.
And that was a sort of an aberrant form.
Nobody bought that book.
Did not sell millions of copies.
But anyway, if you weren't busy reading Dostoevsky, I would tell you, go read this book, An Unknown Woman.
It's very well written and it's quite remarkable.
Okay, now we've got five more minutes.
We can't just throw them away.
What should we do with them?
Let me see, because there's so many things I've jumped over.
But let's go back and look at the self, we've got the chart, we've got everything that's really important.
So maybe I should let you guys ask questions.
Ah, good.
Question.
Yep.
No, it's the other finite object, be it Beatrice or the dog, that draws out of you unconditional commitment and thereby produces you as the kind of person, as the individual, talk like that you become.
And now here's what I'll talk about, unless somebody has another question.
It's very interesting to ask the question: are people from other cultures, Buddhists say, all in despair?
And it's not clear what Kierkegaard thinks about it, but it's clear what I think about it, so I'll tell you.
I think Kierkegaard, Shatyrka got this far.
He said this whole story about the self is dogmatic.
That's a technical term.
That means it's based on the revelation in the Bible.
It doesn't claim to be able to argue by rational means that should convince everybody that we're a set of factors, that human beings are all, every human being, everywhere, forever, has been a set of factors which are contradictory but can be gotten together by unconditional commitments.
It says that, the way I want to read it, any human being raised in the Christian, the Judeo-Christian West, and maybe Muslims come under that too, I just don't know enough about it.
But Buddhists don't.
Because how did we get to be this kind of self?
I mean, the Greeks weren't the kind of self that had to have the two factors together.
I don't even know if the Greeks were in despair.
I don't think Kierkegaard ever says they were.
They had their thing, they had a harmonious life based on negating half of themselves because the two halves weren't essential.
How did they get to be essential?
Well, now this is sort of weird.
Maybe it's, I mean, my story is, Kierkegaard is saying that it's because of the revelation they became essential.
It's dogmatic.
But what does that mean?
That means that there was this guy, Jesus, who claimed to be the God-man, and people believed he was the God-man.
And I'm not saying whether he was or wasn't.
That depends on what you believe.
But enough people believed he was that they had an infinite passion for him, and that that took over the West.
All the Romans finally became Christians and so forth.
It took a long time for them to get the Greek out of it, though the Middle Ages were still in the dark ages as far as getting Christianity right.
But finally, Pascal and Kierkegaard came along and sort it out.
Now, what really happened?
What really happened is that one of two things, or both.
Jesus, Kierkegaard says, is the paradigm.
That means the most exemplary case.
And he brings in the possibility of unconditional commitment.
And then it turns out that if you have unconditional commitment, you have a new kind of anguish and a new kind of bliss and a new kind of an aliveness, which spreads sort of like a disease.
And it is sort of like a disease through all of Christendom.
It's like a disease in that Christianity is the sickness for which it is the cure.
That means, if you're done, sickness unto death, Christianity produces this despair.
The Greeks and the Buddhists don't have it.
It produces it by giving people the possibility of a higher, Kierkegaard would say, form of life than they had before, and a higher kind of bliss than they had in any other culture or any other religion.
And anybody raised in this culture, it isn't in our DNA, anybody raised in our culture with our language, with our practices, with our books and movies and millions of paintings of the biblical stories and so forth, can't help but have this kind of self.
And once you've got this kind of self, you're going to be in the sickness, namely, of despair, unless you get a defining commitment.
And what sort of flinches it is, I mean, what Jesus showed was that if you do get a defining commitment, then you get this higher kind of life.
And then you get addicted to it.
I mean, the culture got addicted to it.
I mean, who wouldn't want to live in bliss and anguish and get the most finite and the most infinite and the most all the goodies?
So more and more people come to do it.
Now, let me say, just because I've got still four more minutes, there's two ways that Jesus could have done it.
And I don't know which it is, and it's hard to see that it could be, it could sort of be both.
I mean, is Jesus the paradigm?
Because he tells the disciples that they should have a defining relation to him.
That would be an interesting new idea.
He says that they can worship him as if he were God.
And that means that you could have this absolute unconditional, infinite passion for a finite being.
And he tells them that, but does he demonstrate what it is to have an infinite passion?
Well, he says that he things like, you know, it's the high, that he is ready to die for his friend.
And it doesn't say for all his friends or any old friend.
I mean, if you read that, that the friend is a defining commitment, like Augustine and his friends, then Jesus not only asks people to have a defining commitment to him, but he shows what it's like to have a commitment to them or to one of them.
It's not very, it's all pretty murky in the past.
The other thing he could do, which really uses or sort of interests me more, is I used to say, well, if he's really the paradigm, he ought to have an unconditional commitment for some kind of cause or for one person.
And I don't think you could build all that on just something like something, anybody know the Bible well enough, something, something who lays down his life for his friend.
That doesn't seem like an unconditional commitment to me.
So I said, well, maybe Jesus is a freedom fighter.
Maybe he's fighting on the side of the Israelis against the Romans, that that's his cause, that he's risking his life for it.
And everybody sort of laughed at me, and I kind of laughed at myself.
But then it became a kind of fad about 20 years ago, I don't know if it still is, to read the Bible that way.
There are books and books saying, well, look, I'll give you two examples.
When the Romans come to get Jesus, Peter slices off the ear of one of the Romans.
And people say, well, these are supposed to be non-violent people.
What's he doing with the sword?
And why is he slashing off the ear of the Roman?
It's sort of weird.
And then Jesus is weird in when he goes around and says all the time after performing miracles and saying wise things, and don't tell anybody.
As if somehow the Bible has got it into it in a way that it doesn't explain that something secret is going on.
And as if this is kind of code for some meeting they're going to have in which they're going to plot against the Romans.
So anyway, I don't know what it would, you have to think of your own example.
In what way Jesus is the paradigm.
But those are some possibilities.
Okay.
We're going to do one more Kierkegaard next time.