I'm looking for what I had and read last time from Huck Finn because by happy coincidence, since this is about podcasting partly, but as I told you last time, by happy good luck, some podcast listener sent me the quotes from Huck Finn where he is suspending the ethical.
And I read them and it seemed terrific to me.
And then I got another message.
I get email every day from some podcast listener who said there's a problem.
It's not like suspending the ethical.
And I think it's very interesting.
They're both right.
And the issue is over this quote, which I'll just read the basic part of it, where he has the letter that he's going to send to tell Mrs.
Watson where her slave, Jim, is.
And he says, I took it up, I held it, the letter, in my hand.
I was all trembling because I'd got to decide forever betwixt two things, and I knowed it.
I studied a minute, sort of holding my breath, and then I says to myself, all right, I'll go to hell, and tore it up.
It was awful thoughts and awful words, but they were said, and I let them stay said, and I never thought no more about reforming.
Well, that sounds certainly like a case of suspending the ethical, of doing something which he feels he has to do, and yet he knows that it's morally wrong.
And as he says, he knows he's going to go to hell.
He's trembling.
I take that to be the Mark Twain version of anguish that he feels when he has to go against the ethical.
And it's utterly unintelligible what he's doing to him or anybody else because it's absolutely part of the ethical that slaves are property and property.
You don't go around stealing other people's property.
And he's in effect stealing Jim.
Why isn't it?
Does anybody figure out why I would get another podcast email telling me that this is not the right way to explain the suspension of the ethical?
Well, it's an interesting, deep issue.
Somebody writes and says, yeah, but on the name of what?
He doesn't have any unconditional commitment to anybody or anything that is making him do it.
When Kierkegaard writes about the suspension of the ethical, remember, he says that it's the call, Abraham's calling, that makes him go against the ethical.
And I generalize that to say that if you're in love or if you have any kind of unconditional commitment, then the commitment has higher authority than the ethical.
And if it conflicts with the ethical, it trumps the ethical.
But now, what about Huck Finn?
What's his unconditional commitment?
Well, I don't think he has any.
And in that sense, the latest letter from the podcast world is right.
It's not exactly an example of Abraham's kind of suspending the ethical.
Or my examples from when I did it.
Remember, I said, suppose you were homosexual and in love with somebody in 18850 in Copenhagen, then you would have the same problem that what you were doing was, when you tried to say it, you could only say that you were depraved and perverted, and yet you would feel that this is what you were called to do and the best thing you could be doing.
Well, Huck, the answer is something like this: the Huck Finn is a kind of half of it.
It's the sort of bare bones of the story.
That is, if the essence of it is that you feel that you have to go against the ethical, and you feel the anguish of having to go against the ethical, but you feel that it would be even worse if you didn't, you're already suspending the ethical.
And so the Huck Finn is like a very minimal case.
But it's a special case of the general story that something requires you, some higher power over you requires you to go against the ethical.
Then there seem to be at least two kinds.
Maybe there are three or four kinds, and maybe somebody wants to write a paper about it.
The two kinds we've come across now are: you have a defining unconditional commitment that requires you to go, could require you to go against the ethical and does sometimes do it, or you just have some, I don't know, innate sense of decency or something, I don't know what Huck has, which requires you to go against the ethical.
And in both cases, the crucial thing is you can't justify what you're doing.
If you try to describe what you're doing, you have to say it's bad.
Huck says that this is bad, and he's going to hell for it.
And he's serious about it.
He's trembling.
He knows it's an awful thing that he's done.
And that was, so just let me finish.
So that's the crucial thing, that you have to go against the ethical, and you can't justify what you're doing.
And if you try to justify what you're doing, you can only justify it in terms of what is the shared, intelligible understanding of what's right and wrong and good.
And by the shared understanding of what's right and wrong and good, when you can't justify it, because you have to say, I'm a slave protector, which is a terrible thing to be, apparently.
Or you have to say, I'm a murderer, which is what Abraham has to say.
Or you could have to say, I'm going to break my engagement to Regina, which is what Kierkegaard has to say.
All of which are, when described from the point of view of the ethical, and that's the only way they can be described, are bad.
Okay, now, question.
Yeah.
Kierkegaard likens faith to being a non-conditional method to God.
So we're.
I was hoping I could get by the whole semester this year and nobody would ask me that question.
But I can't make any sense out of the role of God in the way Kierkegaard is telling the story, and I don't think Kierkegaard does either.
Because what happens is that God just stands for whatever calling it is that requires you to go against the ethical because it's higher than the ethical.
And God isn't some other authority, some supreme being, which sends Abraham a method, a message, and you go against the ethical.
And it isn't as if everybody understands that when God asks for something to be done as a sacrifice, it's okay.
Nobody thinks it's okay for Abraham to go out and murder Isaac.
Even Abraham doesn't think it's okay.
But God stands for the fact that there is some authority, some higher calling, which is requiring Abraham to do it.
But in the Abraham story, you can't make any sense of it when you try to translate it because in the Abraham story, it was Yahweh.
It was God, the supreme, it wasn't even the supreme being yet.
That's sort of too Greek.
It was Jehovah who was commanding it.
And Kierkegaard just can't turn that into the story that he wants it to be.
So he just puts it in.
But he doesn't say much about it because, as I've told you before, when he does talk about God in another book where he's talking about what he thinks the right way to think about Christianity is, he doesn't think God is a supreme object or being.
He says God is that all things are possible, and that all things are possible is God.
And having faith isn't believing that there is this kind of supreme being.
Having faith is acting as if all things are possible, acting in the field of the shining of this power.
And you'll see, but this won't mean anything to you quite yet, when he does actually mention some, the sort of creation, the creator, sort of, he mentions it with lowercase.
He talks about the power that posited it.
He doesn't have a creator God in his story.
That help any?
I mean, it says in it.
What it helps is that there's nothing to say.
Don't get tangled up in talking about God the Father or God the Supreme Being or Jehovah in this story.
Don't let the fact that Kierkegaard can't quite map his problems onto Abraham's problems, mess up what you're doing.
Keep your eye on the phenomenon.
That's always the keeping your eye on the phenomenon is thinking, well, some authority says to Abraham, you got to kill Isaac, and that authority is something that nobody else can understand, nobody else can, nor Abraham himself, but he feels he has to do it.
Yeah.
But it seems like the ethical is pulling him in two directions.
But there isn't something tired of the ethical, sort of telling him to stay in Jim.
Rather, something like, well, on the one hand, he's a human being.
And on the other hand...
Well, he thinks you're right, sort of.
I think, let me put it back this way.
The way it works with Huck is that there's something bad going to happen, and he's being called to prevent it, namely giving Huck back.
That's another way of putting the difference.
When it's the love of the homosexual story, or the love of Regina story, or imagine Martin Luther King not being a non-violent person, but knowing he's got to kill some people to get the peace march going.
I mean, those are all things that you're called for the sake of something that is for you good, though you can't explain how or why, to do something which is ethically bad.
It turns out that what happens with Huck is to avoid something ethically bad, namely, well, no, no, no, I guess I haven't got inside of it.
Maybe you aren't inside of it either.
Let me try again.
The good thing is to return a runaway slave.
And he thinks that that's a bad thing.
And he's therefore acting.
He's doing something which is bad by the current ethics, helping a runaway slave, and something he feels he has to do.
I've lost it.
Tell me again.
Yes.
Well, okay, now I see why I lost it.
But that can't be quite right because that's very important, what you're saying, because it's wrong.
But that's important to be wrong, because then you can get clear of what's right.
It can't be in the ethical sphere because the ethical sphere is what people agree on is the good, intelligible thing to do.
His conscience can't be, so to speak, calling him from Berkeley now, telling him, don't turn in slaves.
There aren't any real people, black people aren't slaves.
From the point of view of Huck, that's the important thing.
The ethical is that you should turn in runaway slaves.
And his conscience, and this is the helpful way you put it, because it's misleading, is your conscience is supposed to tell you ethical things.
But in the way Kierkegaard has set it up, your conscience tells you what counts as good according to what everybody agrees on in the culture.
So his conscience tells him, turn in that runaway slave.
And so now we're left, but then why doesn't he do it?
And that's your interesting point.
We don't really know.
I mean, looking at it from where we are, we have to say something like, well, his natural understanding of the value of all human beings or something.
And maybe that's right.
But one thing you have to say is he can't put it that way.
His conscience can't say, but Jim is another human being.
You can't just treat him like a slave.
His conscience says Jim is a piece of property and you're stealing him.
And so his conscience says, give him back.
That's why he's trembling when he doesn't give him back.
Okay?
Yeah.
Well, good.
I think, I mean, there's a whole literature based on one sentence.
Come back to the raft huck, honey.
Do you know any of you know that?
I mean, and then they try to actually make a kind of homosexual attraction between the two of them and interpret it as, then it's easy.
Then his love of Jim trumps the ethical, and he's really suspending the ethical.
But he can't say, I love Jim, and Mark Twain can't say it either.
And maybe that's the way to read it.
Okay, did you do this on your own, or have you read this literature of Come Back to the Raft Huck Honey?
No.
Okay, it was a big thing when I was a graduate student.
I don't know whether anybody pays any attention to that way of reading the Huck Finn or not.
Has anybody read the sort of homosexual reading of Huck Finn?
Okay, well, I don't think we need to.
But if you do, if you do, then you at least have a reason that trumps the ethical, that is something that they can't say to eat themselves or understand, but has authority, and that's nice for the symmetry.
Yeah.
At the very end of the book, when Huck ultimately says, not the fact that Levin is, oh, you're right.
You know, slaves are real people.
He says, Jim, I love you despite the fact that you're hiring.
He says, especially throughout the book and especially after the letter, Huck is saying, I'm doing the anti-I'm doing the anti-ethical.
You say.
He actually overcomes the fact that Jim is a slave, because then you're my friend, despite the overwhelming.
Good.
So he's in just the right place.
So now we can accept the podcast, the first podcast person.
Jim is in the right place.
I mean, sorry.
Huck is in this place where his kind of commitment to Jim is making him do something which he has no vocabulary and no understanding for how to say it.
And because when he says it, he says, I like to even though you're a slave.
And that's not the way it's supposed to.
I mean, that's not the how, what?
That's that's to buy too.
Yeah, that's to buy too much into the ethical of that time and find him.
But anyway, good.
That's interesting.
I mean, there's a great possibility of some paper in there trying to sort this all out if you're on the track of one.
Yeah, yeah, both of you.
First you, yeah.
Of course, we have to ethical, which is kind of like a social register, well, intended to.
I think it's quite right to inject define that when we have humanistic ideals and other ideas we'll have in this thing.
Our intelligibility, our ethics.
Almost transcended the language of a higher calling, something exceeded.
You could also come from a more feminine perspective.
And this would.
A what perspective?
Oh, Berkson, yeah, the philosopher.
Okay, okay.
Yeah, you're right.
We take all our different kinds of feelings and emotions where meaning comes from, and then the tree that we're solving.
And so in this sense, it would be not necessarily a higher calling, but the emotional reaction sense of not only the order of interactions, I have to have some sense of.
And so here, this is kind of a very interesting, interesting.
All the issues are in here.
It really is an interesting topic, paper topic or something.
Now, let's put this in Hegel terms.
In Hegel terms, that would be that he doesn't turn in Jim because he gives him to lower immediacy, his own personal attachment.
And that means, and that would be to be sinning, to be doing evil, you know, bad.
How can he let his feelings about Jim trump what every right 30 thinking person knows you're supposed to do when you've got a runaway slave on your hands?
So that would get rid of the paradox, and it would get rid of the anguish and the trembling.
He would just he well, he would just be saying, Well, I don't care whether I'm damned, I'm going to make an exception of myself because I like it.
And that's that's bad.
I mean, that's that's normal sort of bad.
Okay?
Boy, you know, you can let her go on because she's already in the middle of a thought.
Yeah.
Because, I mean, Jim stays puffed innumerable times.
He yields it from the dead body.
When Jim has an author's need to run away, he comes back and hides like a p-ball for two weeks to stay Jim for like these really rough random villagers.
Like, what the ultimate lesson is the fact that Jim chooses the top.
Interesting.
I don't know what, I mean, there's not enough in my memory of the book to know what to say about how it looks from Jim's point of view.
All I want to say to you is that being sort of doing it from an existential Kierkegaard thing, the right question to ask is, how does it look from Jim's point of view?
How does it look from Huck's point of view?
And not how does it look from our point of view?
And that's what you're trying to do.
And Jim, for all, I mean, he says, come back to the RAF Huck, honey, we're back to that again.
He really likes him.
I don't know what more to say about that.
Yeah.
No, wait, stop.
Thought.
No, no.
You you you left out uh something.
The ethical is the universal in problem one.
That's Kantian sort of thing.
But remember now, we're sort of inside of problem two now, which is Hegelian, where we talked about this last time.
The ethical is whatever the shared norms of intelligibility and good action are.
So the ethical is certainly turn in the slaves.
And there isn't any Kantian ethical about all treat all human beings as means and as ends and not as means.
And it's only when you relativize the ethical like Hegel that you get the paradox like Kierkegaard, which makes Kierkegaard happy.
He likes paradoxes.
Yeah.
An ethical value that's supposed to be above another.
So like the technological aspect, so it's because for the more general sport of most the goodness for everyone for the social scheme at that time, for inclusion conversation.
What I wanted to note is: does Kierkegaard in mind that the conflict can take within the ethical of it?
That it's not so, it's not so clear which ethic value is above which, so that makes sense.
Okay, well, that's that may be Hegel.
That would be the issue about whether you subsume, we're in the tragic hero business at that point, which where Hegel and Kierkegaard will get agree that there is a higher principle for Agamemnon, above whether he should kill his daughter or not.
He has to do his duty as king and commander-in-chief.
But in general, that it's complicated about Hegel, and you guys shouldn't think about Hegel.
But in Hegel, the ethics is in the everyday way people do things.
In German, the word is Zittlichkeit, which is custom.
And like in Pascal's phrase, custom is our nature.
And that's, and it's, and Zittlichkeit is lower immediacy.
And then it gets, as you're saying, sort of spelled out and mediated into actual ethical principles.
And that's higher than just reacting the way one does in the culture.
But even the ethical principles, I think, express whatever is implicit in the customs of those people.
However, now, but we don't want to go back.
I'm going to get the last word on this because I just don't want to get further into it.
Hegel is enough of a philosopher to think that there are better and worse customs.
That's what you're going to say, too.
Yeah, well, Kierkegaard doesn't go into that.
But if he did, now we're back where we started.
It would be one ethical subsuming another ethical.
And that's, and Kierkegaard thinks that there is this from the inside of the customs and of any rational way you could explain the custom.
All of that, which is a complicated ethical thing with levels of ethical principles that are higher and lower, all of that can't capture doing something that goes against the ethical principles, the customs, no matter how.
It isn't, I mean, I don't think I should be talking about this because it isn't going to help any.
It isn't as if it's a question, I'll go back to Kierkegaard's way of thinking about it.
However, you want to think about it, Hegel can only understand what philosophers can understand.
And philosophers can only understand subsuming one ethical principle under another, that there are higher and lower ones.
And the best you can, and Abraham is not acting on a higher principle.
Abraham is acting on something that you can't express except on the lower principle, namely it's murder.
Agamemnon is operating on a higher principle.
And he's not murdering Ephigenia.
Let's just remember that.
He's sacrificing Ephigania because the prophet said to do it, and everybody praises him, and he lives happily ever after on Kierkegaard's version.
There are other Greek versions in which Clytemnestra never forgives him and kills him in the bathtub when he comes home from the Trojan War.
But that's from Kierkegaard's point of view, Agamemnon did it right.
He has a suspension of one ethical by another.
But that's not the teleological suspension of the ethical.
The teleological suspension of the ethical is all levels of the ethical are put aside by something which isn't in the ethical because it isn't anything, or put aside by doing something which, if you did put it in the ethical, would be murder, killing Isaac, but which, because it's done in a way which we're going to go to right soon, in a different way, isn't anti-ethical.
That it isn't because it's a higher ethical either.
It's what's the magic word going to be?
If it isn't lower immediacy and it isn't mediation, higher immediacy.
That's right.
We've got to explain what that is now.
But whatever it is that Abraham's doing, it's higher immediacy, and there's no such thing in Hegel.
There's only just good old-fashioned immediacy.
Now, okay, Chuck.
Why, what can't be defined?
I can't be defined by his commitment to Jim.
Well, that's good.
I mean, you're going to talk me out of what I began with, namely that Huck wasn't a perfect example.
And my podcast informant, the first one, may be right.
If you think that Huck has a commitment to Jim, which he does in some sense, all right, here's the question: Do you think Huck's commitment to Jim is such that Huck defines himself as the lover of Jim, or not homosexual now, but just that Jim is the unconditional thing in Huck's life such that who Huck is is tied up with that?
I was thinking that, I don't know, what do you think?
Okay, well, if you read it his way, if you want to say that Huck is defined by his relation to Jim, so that if he betrays Jim, he betrays himself, and he can't be himself unless he's ready to go against everything rational and ethical for Jim.
Then it works perfectly.
I'm happy.
I want Mark Twain to get it right.
Yeah.
What's that?
This is tied up with the fact that the whole second half of the book is so bad, really.
You know, after this exciting and wonderful beginning, he starts playing these games with Tom Sawyer and Jim, and by the end.
So let's just bracket that, how he behaves at the end.
Yeah.
Don't tell anybody.
I mean, so two things.
When you read Kierkegaard's story about Agamemnon, forget two things.
It was my fault to bring up at all what happened afterward with Clytemnestra.
The main thing is, don't think that what you learned about tragedy in high school, then namely this Aristotelian thing that Aristotle, the sort of book, movie, or play review that Aristotle wrote about Oedipus and how there you have a tragic flaw and you have to recognize this tragic flaw and then everybody has a catharsis.
A lot of you learned all that.
But that's just not how Kierkegaard's thinking about it.
He's thinking about it in a Hegelian model.
He's thinking about it as the kind of suffering required to go from a lower to a higher ethical.
And that's the kind of tragic suffering.
And it leads, you know, you read it.
It's his version.
Then it isn't what happened in the Orestea, and then it isn't what happened according to Homer.
It's just another story.
The only tragedy it fits, I think, is supposedly Antigone, where there are two conflicting ethics.
Bury your brother, support the state, and the tragedy consists in the conflict between.
It's that model.
Yeah.
What happens when two different people...
Who's colliding with it?
Yeah, that's right.
And okay, and what the Hegelian's going to say, and Kierkegaard's completely in agreement with Hegel as far as Greek tragedy, or this Greek tragedy anyway, is concerned.
Well, the tragedy is that there was a higher ethical than the...
It's very lower immediacy for mothers to be totally attached to their daughters and get upset when their daughters are killed.
It's a much higher thing and more mediated when kings and commanders in chief do what they promise to do and lead the army the way they're supposed to lead the army.
And Clytemnestra is just wrong.
Lower, she just should be, she didn't realize she was trumped by higher ethical.
Yeah.
More on the regional pure graphic.
I hope you guys are good.
And I wonder what would happen if I can and two different.
Yes, there would be suffering, but the suffering wouldn't be unintelligible.
Everybody involved would understand that there were these two, I'm just thinking out loud, two ethical claims and what?
I mean, who and within the customs, within the culture, there is an implicit understanding which they all share, which the tragedy makes explicit, that kings trump mothers, and that and there is suffering because it's hard on the Fijian and her mother when the father kills his daughter, but there is an ethical order.
And this is not, here's a way to sum it up.
This is the teleological suspension of one ethical, namely mothers' daughters, for a higher ethical, namely kings, but it's not a teleological suspension of the ethical, where all forms of ethical, universal, intelligible understanding, is being denied by Abraham, who is nobody, nothing in the culture says murder is all right.
Murder just isn't all right.
Here, I'm going to stop, though.
It's been fascinating, but we've got to go back to this because you've got to know a lot more about these things.
One last remark.
Because at the end of what I say, despite what they just suggested that for Activision of Laws, the higher leadership and a conditional commitment.
And I think there's a third way of holding Further Degree, which is that there was a suspension clear, but keep it in mind that he's young, he's a kid, and a lot of ways to teach you the dance of society.
And maybe he could express himself, as John was to say, that, you know, despite the efforts, despite how I understand your role in society and your ability to re-wash the beat, that I can suspend that to a higher.
Oh, you blew it, you blew it.
No, no, no.
That's too universal.
I mean, as soon as he says that, he's intelligible and he's in the ethical commitment to humans.
No, he would have to say, in spite of the fact that slaves are inferior, in spite of the fact that you shouldn't protect their property, I like Jim so much that I'm going to protect him, and I'm bad.
I'm in lower immediacy.
Or he can say, I'm going to protect Jim, and this is dreadful, and I feel terrible for doing it.
I'll never forgive myself for doing it.
However, I'm going to, and I can't understand it, but I have to do it.
Remember, it's unintelligible.
Abraham can't speak.
Remember all that.
There's nothing you said too much to be Abraham or to be Huck if he's suspending the ethical.
Now, I've got to go on, because there's, oh, I can't resist hands.
You've got to help me.
Go ahead.
I don't know.
I've got friends from the ship.
Well, and what you'd be doing was going down to lower immediacy.
You're making an exception of yourself and your friends because you really feel like it, and you're doing something intelligible, namely wrong.
There are two kinds of intelligible.
I haven't said that clearly enough.
There's intelligible as going against the as going with the ethical.
There's intelligible as going against the ethical.
When you go against the ethical, it's intelligible as you sinned, in Kierkegaard language, you did a bad thing.
As long as Huck just understands himself as having done a bad thing, which you could read it that way, he's not suspending the ethical.
He's sinking beneath the ethical.
I've got to draw a picture.
Ah, piece of chalk.
Okay, I have the picture in here.
I need my picture.
A lot of complicated things in what you're saying.
Okay, so you can go along and follow the universal.
That's what most people do all the time.
And now you can, if you're here, you could deviate to lower immediacy.
And the universal is mediation, of course.
And here's lower immediacy.
And now you, and this is temptation.
So what's the temptation?
Once you get used to this vocabulary, you can see that Huck's giving into the temptation, or you with your friends who did bad things and you don't want to turn them in.
The temptation to say, well, I know I should turn them in, but I'm just going to make an exception of myself because I like them a lot and I don't like to hurt people I like.
Then that's temptation and it's sin.
Sin is a funny name for it.
I mean, I would just want to say it's morally wrong.
Nothing is important there except sin sounds too necessarily religious.
So, and then if you go down here, what happens?
What do you have to do to make up for it?
Why is your hand up?
Because you're making an exception of yourself and your friends.
And you're not doing what one ought to do.
That's all.
One oughtn't to defend their friends if their friends have done something against the law, say, stealing something.
You can't just say, well, I won't turn them in and I won't tell anybody because I put my friends first.
That's saying, well, that's lower immediacy.
I mean, that's like a child.
I like my friends, and I don't care what you're supposed to do about your friends.
I'm going to do what I like to do.
And then that's down here.
No, no, wait, no, no, no, sorry.
If I don't talk about this enough, you won't understand a lot of what's going on in the third man next on Thursday.
I got a loose, something's wrong with my jeans or something.
I can't resist hands.
Go ahead.
Wait, I couldn't hear people talking.
Talk loud.
Well, in any, I mean, it's always wrong to go against the ethical.
But if you turn, I mean, if you want to save a child, that's a higher ethical.
I mean, that's that.
So, no, it's not wrong.
It's not wrong to go against.
A good point.
I see.
Yes, I have to say this.
Of course, it's not wrong to go against the ethical for a higher ethical.
But her story is making an exception of herself and her friends.
Most people should turn in their friends when they steal things or damage things or something.
But I happen to care so much for my friends that I'm not going to do it.
That's lower immediacy.
If you say, I'm not going to turn in my friends because what they were doing was trying to collect money for a worthy cause or something like that.
Then you're just, that's okay.
Then you're doing a higher, you've got to, it's okay.
You haven't sinned.
You haven't gone down here.
But now, now I'm going on.
Sorry.
Oh, okay, okay.
Yeah, yeah.
Kierkegaard's got a very interesting view about it.
Very different than, say, Heidegger, who thinks average intelligibility is just conformism.
And the last thing an authentic person would do is give in to the average intelligent ethics.
Kierkegaard and Hegel have this deep idea that you've got to have, remember I said, a way of explaining to yourself and other people what you're doing.
And therefore, you have to have a sense of what's the right thing to do and what's the wrong thing to do.
And there's no, of course, from Kierkegaard's point of view, particularly, but Hegel sort of, anyway, there's no right answer to this.
All you've got is what everybody in the culture generally agrees on is the right way to behave.
That's where the whole problem starts.
If you could step outside and decide what was rational like Kant, or what was natural, or what was, what else have we got?
God's orders.
There are all kinds of ways where you might think that there was some higher thing than what ordinary people just ordinarily think.
But if you don't think that, then you've got nothing to go on but what ordinary people think is right and wrong.
You can sharpen it up.
You can order it in levels.
You can try to iron out the inconsistencies.
But it's, if people are going to be able to think, they've got to have a shared language of what's worthy and not worthy, what's good and bad, and so forth.
Okay, now I'm surely going to be able to go on.
Let me put my chart on the board because Kierkegaard's got this chart in mind.
If there is another way to deviate from the universal, well, what would it be?
It would be going up here, it would be higher immediacy, and that's what you get when you have faith or when you have an unconditional commitment.
And then, and here, you should do what you have to do to get back to the universal.
And that means you're guilty, and you have to repent, and you have to expiate what you did.
Maybe you have to go to prison, maybe you just have to apologize, depending on how dramatic what you did is in breaking away from the universal.
But this is guilt, and this is repent, and this is expiate.
Okay, this is what philosophers can understand, according to Kierkegaard.
And this is all that Hegel can understand: that there is a universal, that's what it's the shared customs that make things intelligible, that people are always tempted to go and make an exception of themselves, that when they do, they have to go back up here, and people will force them to or put them in prison if need be.
But now comes Kierkegaard.
And Kierkegaard says, but there is a way of deviating from the universal, which is to be ethical.
Well, I never finished that thought.
Inside the ethical, you have levels of suspending the ethical.
That is, Agamemnon suspends the father loves daughter, for the ethical king does his job.
But then Kierkegaard has the idea that you could suspend the whole ethical, not just some ethical by some higher ethical.
But here's some place where you suspend the ethical altogether.
Abraham killing Isaac, for instance, but also homosexuals in Denmark and Huck saving Jim.
And what about them?
What is this?
What's the name of it, and what's the phenomena, according to Kierkegaard?
If you've been doing this reading, which is pretty difficult, but not very much, reading it over and over, tell me the name of that arrow.
What's the temptation in that?
If you're up here, say gay in 1850 Copenhagen, what's the temptation?
To go to the universal, to go straight, to get married and have kids and so forth.
That's the temptation.
That is, and his word for this is a trial.
Abraham, what Abraham is going through is a trial.
That doesn't mean that it's something that he's aware of and it's a test, although it is sort of like that.
But think about the phenomena.
What's the phenomena?
Whenever somebody would be gay in a time when all they could say to themselves was, this is perverted, this is depraved, this is disgusting, and so forth, then the big temptation is to go back to the ethical.
And that pull toward the ethical is a trial, and we need some word which Kierkegaard doesn't have, that the ethical, here's lower immediacy, here's the ethical.
Both of them have a kind of pull.
The lower immediacy pulls you away from the universal.
The trial pulls you away from higher immediacy toward the universal.
I'm going to call them, they're both a kind of attraction to deviate.
So the attraction here is to deviate from your calling.
Let's call this the calling.
So here's the attraction to go back to the universal.
The attraction here is to deviate from the universal to making an exception of yourself, to the immediate, and that's the attraction.
And just to show you a place where he talks about it, he talks about being a trial on 137.
I've got to get back to the book.
That is beyond where your reading is, but that's a good definition of a trial at the bottom of 137.
He would have to sacrifice Isaac because it was a trial.
Oh, well, that doesn't explain it.
He uses the word there.
There are other places where I'll come across them when I do my lecture in the normal order.
Well, lots to cover.
Let me go back and see where we are.
Ah, but here's a whole big bunch of things to talk about.
But let's just read one place where, what's the bottom line of all we've been talking about, is that philosophers have only this picture down here.
Therefore, philosophers have no way of distinguish acting on one's calling from sinning.
And that's what you get on 84 in this wonderfully complicated way of saying something which is pretty complicated.
On 84, I'm going to read this because I'll see if you can tell me if you can explain it.
For faith is just this paradox.
You see at the first paragraph on 84, that the single individual is higher than the universal, though in such a way be it noted that the movement is repeated.
That is, that having been in the universal, the particular, you have to keep rewriting it because the translation doesn't know what's going on.
The particular now sets himself apart from the universal.
No, sorry.
Sets himself apart as the individual above the universal.
If that is not faith, then Abraham is done for, and faith has never existed in the world just because it has always existed.
Do you understand that?
See if anybody could decipher that.
Good, yeah?
I think that what it's saying is that if faith is the universal, then it goes rational.
Well, you've got the form of the answer, but what you're saying is dead wrong, unfortunately.
You may have misspoken.
It's not about the universal.
It's about now faith.
If faith has been the deviation from being an individual to being a particular, and then at particular, yeah, you want to say something?
Sure.
Go ahead.
No, go ahead.
And there's extension principles to people.
And so he said, well, it's not a divisional calling.
That's well put.
Well put.
Faith has never existed because it has always existed.
That is, the only thing, the only way to deviate from the universal is toward lower immediacy.
And faith is just like superstition.
Remember I said last time, that's just another form of lower immediacy.
And faith has always existed because lower immediacy has always existed and superstition and so forth.
So there's no place to understand Abraham because all you can say about Abraham is, well, he's going crazy or something.
That's all the table can account for.
That's the story.
You're looking puzzled by your own remarks.
Oh, okay.
I feel like with the faith and the calling, you know, if you look at the two calling.
Yeah.
Right.
The distinction made on the calling itself divided on this other symbolic or okay.
Well, I well, that's that's, I mean, if you want my personal opinion, that's the kind of jargon that you get in English departments.
I don't have any objection to it.
I just want to say that are you from the English department?
That's what happens when you're a podcast.
Now, look, I'm all over the world.
They know that I think that this kind of jargon is, I'm not sure it's nonsense, but what I want to say about it is it misses the phenomenon.
You see, you're going to say that?
I mean, the idea isn't the symmetry here, and yes, this is related to the universal, and this is a kind of semiotic bunch of relations.
This is something that you feel when you've got romantic love, and this is something you feel when you're making an exception of yourself to go in for some desire.
And either that phenomenological distinction is true about our experience, at least in the West, or it isn't.
And it covers it up to talk about it too formally, if you're a phenomenology person like I am.
So let me go on because time is so short.
And I'm now, where am I?
Okay, so now we understand that faith has always existed because it's never existed, because it gets lumped down here with superstition and desire and moods and stuff, and there's no place for something up here because philosophy doesn't have that.
So let me go on the rest of the paragraph.
For if the ethical life is the highest, you see, that's what happens if you cut this piece off.
If the ethical life is the highest and nothing incommensurable is left over in man, except the sense of what is evil, another word for down here.
Now we've got evil.
Well, this sounds still too religious.
You don't need evil, but we'll put it on here anyway.
It's okay.
So, yeah, that is, now they go on.
What's left over is what is evil.
That is, the particular who is to be expressed in the universal.
Then one needs no other categories than those of the Greek philosophers or whatever can be logically deduced from them.
This is something Hegel, who has after all made some study of the Greeks, ought not to kept quiet about.
That is, Hegel can't understand Abraham.
There's no place in Greek philosophy for unconditional commitments and all the important issues and callings due to this picture.
If you throw the Judeo-Christians against the Greeks, then you get this complicated picture.
Now, I want to switch to something else you need to know, and that is about how do you tell whether somebody's suspending the ethical in the higher way, here, suspending the whole ethical and doing their calling, and here, somebody's deviating from the ethical and going in to satisfy their lower immediate impulses.
Well, I'm going to go through a whole bunch of different ones because you have to keep your eye open in the movie to see where, who is deviating in what way.
The whole movie is about deviating from the ethical.
So, here's some examples.
So, there's one way that we need, as Kierkegaard says, some criteria in order to be able to sort out the difference between people acting for lower immediacy or just crazy and people suspending the ethical.
On 106, he talks about needing the criteria in the bottom paragraph.
It's possible on the basis of a paradox to construct certain criteria which even someone not in it can understand.
Now, I'm going to tell you three criteria.
And they're running around in the book.
Maybe I'll define them, and maybe I won't.
So, first, there is one thing you have to see before somebody could possibly be a knight of faith suspending the ethical, is that they're free.
And what would it be?
Otherwise, it would be a compulsion.
I mean, if, as Jack Nicholson in The Shining is out to, having read too much, Kierkegaard is out to kill his son, it's not as if he's doing it freely.
He's just crazy, and he's compelled to do it.
The most perfect example is Peter Laurie in M.
How many of you take out M and watch it if you want to understand the extremist version, a deviation from the ethical.
Peter Laurie in M is an irresistible, he's a man who has an irresistible compulsion to kill little girls.
And whenever he sees a nice little girl going by eating an ice cream cone or something, he tries not to.
He goes to a cafe, he orders brandy, he tries to read the newspaper, but pretty soon he just can't resist that he kills a little girl.
And he feels very sorry for himself because it isn't even as if he's freely choosing to do this.
He just can't resist.
And that kind of compulsion that you can't resist isn't even in this business.
You just see that to see somebody who is definitely not a knight of faith suspending the ethical because they're not doing anything.
They're not free.
At the top of 139, again, I'm sorry, a little outside your reading.
Abraham can refrain at any moment.
He can repent the whole thing as a temptation.
Well, Peter Laurie in M can't refrain at any moment, and he can't think of the whole thing as a temptation because he can't help it.
He just does it.
Now, it's very hard to hear the difference.
You've got to get used to this.
When Luther stands in front of the church in 15-something and defies the whole Catholic Church, who Luther has clearly got an unconditional commitment, and he's clearly going against the whole intelligibility of medieval times, it's no coincidence that Kierkegaard is a Lutheran.
Then Luther famously said, Here I stand, I can do no other.
Now, Peter Laurie also said, I mean, here I go, killing little girls, I can do no other.
But the difference is that the psychopath literally can't do any other because he's got this compulsion.
Whereas Luther doesn't mean I'm compelled to stand up against the Catholic Church.
Boy, I wish I didn't have to do this.
It's very painful to everybody concerned that I can't resist.
No, he means I have to, because of my unconditional commitment, whatever it is, because to be Luther, I have to do it.
But that's the first thing.
The knight of faith suspending the ethical has got to be free.
It's not a compulsion.
Now, then what is it?
Well, Kierkegaard's going to give you two negative criteria and one positive one for how to recognize the...
So if you want to recognize there are two things that if they, if somebody shows these two things, they can't be a knight of faith, suspending the ethical.
What would they be?
Well, the first and most important is, see if I can put it so you can see it, guess it.
Well, it's built into this.
If you're suspending the ethical, you're here.
If you're not suspending the ethical, you're here.
How do you know where you are?
It's sort of in the picture.
Yeah.
You could explain what you were doing and so on.
Yeah, well, yeah, you're on the right track.
Right.
So you've got to go through mediation.
But now, what does it mean in this case?
Well, it means that the knight of, you'll recognize it when I tell it to you this way.
The knight of faith suspending the ethical respects the ethical.
Otherwise, there wouldn't be any problem.
I mean, Abraham's got a problem because he doesn't want to murder Isaac and so forth.
So it's just because the knight of faith does respect the ethical, that the ethical is at trial and is pulling him down here.
And it isn't right to respect the ethical.
It's not a good idea to go around going against the established ethics of the time, which is the only ethics you've got.
So he has total respect for the universal.
Otherwise, Kierkegaard calls that he would be a vagrant genius.
That is, somebody who thinks they're so smart, so special, that they can do anything.
Now, you all, I mean, I don't know if I can get you to thinker.
Who do you know from your reading?
Lots of you, who thinks that he's so smart and so superior that he can just go against the ethical and kill somebody without even feeling bad about it.
Does that sound familiar?
Yes.
Who said that?
You win something.
Okay.
What?
Did I?
Did I say?
Ah, yeah, well, that's right.
There was something to be said for being, according to English guys.
He says, for Koen.
So, yeah, Raskolnikov says that he's the superior person, so he can kill the old pawnbroker because he will do better things with her money than she would do with her money.
So Raskolnikov isn't suspending the ethical.
He's just ignoring the ethical.
Forget it, friend.
What's he doing?
Making an exception of himself.
I'm Raskolnikov.
I can go down here and do what makes me happy and fills my satisfies my desires.
So we look at him and we say, he's not.
And I think I had another list.
Charles Manson is certainly not respecting the ethical.
And it's hard to know about Hitler, but it always comes up.
Isn't Kierkegaard saying that Hitler might be a knight of faith suspending the ethical?
None of you asked me.
Either, I don't know whether that shows you're understanding it better or less.
But anyway, it's true, Kierkegaard, sorry, yeah, it's true, Kierkegaard wouldn't have a problem about Hitler because Hitler doesn't respect the ethical.
I mean, Hitler thinks killing Jews is just fine.
And so that's the first criteria.
If the character in question, look at me, Puck Finn respects the ethical.
That's why he's trembling when he's tearing up the letter.
The gay person in 1850 Copenhagen respects the ethical.
And then they go up here and do what they do anyway.
But they do it in, you know, all in upset.
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
I mean that they think that the ethical is right and that they should obey it and that that's that they'd have no, they know do not remember they're inside their culture.
They aren't in Berkeley.
They think from where they are that it's bad to be homosexual.
They think from where they are that it's bad to protect a runaway slave and so forth.
I mean by that, that they that they see that the ethical has authority over them and then they go against it.
Okay, that's number one.
What's number two?
Well, that's sort of more surprising.
The other thing that you could be sure, if this is a person is, these remember negative criteria that you can see from the outside.
You can see from the outside that Hitler and Raskolnikov are not knights of faith suspending the ethical.
The other thing you can see from the outside is if the person claims to have a new ethics, they're not a knight of faith, the suspender of the ethical.
So he says at the bottom of 106, the true knight of faith, about 10 lines from the bottom, is always in absolute isolation.
There's an in there's a typo there.
There should be an in, at least in my copy.
Still missing an in in your copy here?
I've got an older one.
It's still okay.
The true knight of faith is always in absolute isolation.
The false knight is sectarian.
That is, the false knight has, you know, a new ethics to propose.
Or across from that on the next page, the true knight of faith is a witness, never a teacher.
That is, the true knight of faith will sacrifice for their unconditional commitment that they believe in, but they've got no principles.
They're not saying everybody should love Beatrice.
They're not turning their commitment into a cult or something.
So, if so, that's the second one: that if you see somebody who's, and now we could put Hitler there, that's what's interesting.
If Hitler thinks that he can justify what he's doing by proposing a new ethical, namely that the Aryans are superior to the Jews, the Germans are the superior countries that are going to save the West, some of the Nazi jargon is like that, then you can see that he's still not a knight of faith because he's now not a knight of faith suspending the ethical because he's claiming that he's got a higher, when he kills the Jews, he's claiming he's doing it on the basis of a higher ethical that any intelligent German can understand, that Jews are subhuman and they're bad for the culture, and they're like sort of undermining everything, so you've got to kill them.
So, again, that's not suspending the ethical.
And both of those lead up to the really important criterion.
There's one more.
This one is a tricky one, though, because it's not how you can tell from the outside whether this person is suspending the ethical, but whether they can tell from the inside.
What would that be?
Well, remember what happens to Chuck when he decides to tear up the letter?
Yep.
Yes, that's right.
He's trembling, which is the anguish story.
Yes, if you're feeling anguish, that is, if you're feeling that this is a terrible thing you're doing, and when you try to talk to yourself, you say, I'm a murderer, or I'm a pervert, or I'm a slave protector, or whatever.
And you're trembling, then you know, then that doesn't, I think, prove that, you know, there may be something else wrong with you.
Maybe you've got malaria and you're trembling or something.
But I mean, but if you're trembling because you're contemplating this tension, then you know that you are suspending the ethical.
Now, I've got a whole bunch of quotes that say things like that, so let me get to them.
On 60, no, I don't think, well, anguish, middle of that top paragraph.
The ethical expression for what Abraham did is that he was willing to murder Isaac.
The religious expression is that he was willing to sacrifice Isaac.
But in this contradiction lies the very anguish that can indeed make one sleepless and so forth.
So let's try that.
I'm wondering whether Kierkegaard is being consistent there, whether sacrifice, he's got to assume that sacrifice is not a sort of normal ethical term.
Abraham can't say to Sarah, I'm going to sacrifice Isaac, the way Agamemnon can say to Clytemnestra, I've got to sacrifice Ephijaniah, because it's clear that when you sacrifice Ephijaniah, you do it because you have a higher ethical duty, namely king.
But Abraham isn't sacrificing Isaac to some higher ethical, and that's what's important.
So it turns out that if he says it's a sacrifice, it's still unintelligible because it isn't a kind of tragic sacrifice, which is the only kind of sacrifice that's intelligent.
It isn't as if there's some higher ethical that he's sacrificing Isaac to, that he could explain to himself or anybody else.
Okay, let's look at some more.
On 95, the topic.
I don't see anything about anguish there.
Let me think a minute.
No, that's not going to help any.
So let's go on to 89.
On 89.
Well, that's just important.
That's the main paragraph to mark where it says Abraham can't be mediated, that he can't speak.
That for him, the situation is a temptation, namely a temptation to return to the universal, and so forth.
But I've got to find the one that says anguish is the criterion.
I thought I had marked it.
Oh, I'm reading in the wrong place.
Here we go.
Try again.
106.
Well, about 10 lines down, the tragic hero acts and finds his point of rest in the universal.
That's Agamemnon.
The knight of faith is kept in constant tension.
That's that I'm looking for.
There's a place where he says anguish is the criterion.
Until I find it, I have to keep looking.
102.
Those are all relevant quotes, the clincher quote.
No, there's another one near the bottom of 102, which says, no person who has learned that to exist as the individual is the most terrifying thing of all will be afraid of saying it's the greatest.
Why is it the most terrifying thing of all to be an individual?
Wait a second.
Let me just.
You got that?
Because it might sound like, after all, there are all these people who love other people and who commit themselves to good causes and so forth.
Never mind, good causes.
That makes it ethical.
Commit themselves to a cause that they don't understand, but they feel they have to do it.
Why is that terrifying?
Well, the answer is something like: it doesn't have to be terrifying.
But all it means is that there's a higher authority in your life that may require you to go against the ethical.
But if you've got enough imagination to see that once you've got an unconditional commitment, you could be called any time to go against the ethical, that's already terrifying.
It's the equivalent of seeing the sword hanging over the head of the beloved, which you, when you, that is, you don't have to all the time think that your beloved is about to die, but if you've got any imagination, you realize it could happen anytime, and yet you get more involved.
And Abraham, or anyone suspending the ethical, realizes that they could at any time be called to go against the ethical, and yet they get more, yet they go on doing it.
Yeah, I see a hand way back there.
What is it?
I hope not.
Yeah, Agamemnon does, but why Abraham?
In the Today of Hypton file, I thought important thoughts that James wasn't comfortable.
Good.
Yeah, somebody has to say that, and I'm glad you said that.
But you've got to see that Kierkegaard performed a kind of move on that, where, think of it this way: if God had a way of saying so that everybody could understand it intelligible, I've just, right with skywriting over the Israelis, the Israelites, if I've just commanded Abraham to kill his son, and it's all right, because I just did, then it would look ethical.
And P.S., you always ought to do what I command.
If God had said all that, then it would have become ethical.
But of course, Kierkegaard sees it as if, well, what is this thing about sacrificing Isaac, this command?
It doesn't really, this is where the God gets sort of confusing.
All he has of God in there is there is an unconditional commitment, and there is a calling, and this calling is calling Abraham to go against the ethical.
And he just turns the sacrifice of Isaac into something unintelligible because there's no way, it's not just that there's no way to tell whether Abraham is sacrificing.
There's no way to even express it because there's no way for God to turn it into, according to Kierkegaard, some universal thing like always obey God.
That's what the philosophers will do to it.
That's what Augustine does to it.
Augustine says the Abraham-Isaac story is ethical.
It shows you should always do what God commands you to do.
But Kierkegaard says, that's, wait a minute.
What does this look like?
How can I make sense of it?
Yeah.
Well, you were just where I was sort of about an hour ago.
You're right.
You can't make sense of it.
Just don't let it mess you up.
I mean, don't let your own reading of the Abraham story as God saying to Abraham, I want you to do this because I ask you to do it and you ought to obey me.
Don't turn it into that kind of story.
That makes it intelligible.
That makes it ethical.
Ask yourself how Sarah is going to take it.
If Abraham can say to Sarah, I'm very sorry about this.
You can't imagine how upset I am, but I'm called to do it.
And Sarah understands it and says, I admire you.
You're a really God-obeying person, and this is terrible.
We waited until we were 90 to have this kid, and now you're going to kill our child, but I forgive you or something, then you've made it all intelligible.
But you've got to realize that Abraham could only say to Sarah, I'm setting out to murder Isaac, the way Kierkegaard sets it up.
It doesn't add anything to say, I'm setting out to sacrifice Isaac.
Because the way Kierkegaard sets it up, that's not something intelligible that anybody could do, that a father could go out to kill their son as just as something God commanded.
So just don't worry about it.
Consider all the phenomena, not the Bible story.
Let me see.
I got three more minutes.
I got to see where we are.
I'm looking for the anguish, and I haven't found it yet.
How about 137?
Let's try that.
Ah, there we go.
Two-thirds of the way down.
For distress and anguish are the only justification conceivable, even though they cannot be conceived in general.
Abraham is silent because he cannot speak.
Therein lies the distress and anguish.
For when I speak, when I, for if I speak, if he speaks, he cannot make himself understood.
And then at the bottom, it's a trial.
That is, we're back to that again.
I mean, there is this temptation, this attraction to explain it, but he can't explain it.
Okay, so anguish turns out to be, how did it go?
The only justification.
It's a funny kind of justification.
It just, it's, what do you get for your justification now?
Let's put it together.
You have to be, to be a knight of faith, suspending the ethical, you have to be free, not compelled.
You have to believe it, you have to go through mediation and believe in mediation and understand the value and the authority of the ethical.
And then you have to do this, and you don't feel good about it.
You have to feel anguish and dread about it because it's telling you to go against that.
And you feel the pull to go back.
Then you've got the whole picture.
And you can ask yourself now whether anybody in the movie, Thursday, fulfills the condition of being a knight of faith, and whether anybody in the movie fulfills the condition of living in the ethical.
Those are the categories.
Now, don't think in terms of defining commitments.
There is defining commitment in the movie, but you've got to see it now in the light of the issue of the suspension of the ethical.
Okay.