So, Dostoevsky and Nietzsche have a lot in common.
They share a dislike and a distrust of the whole Greek tradition of rationality, philosophical detachment, theory, and science, any kind of pursuit of objective truth.
They think that it's okay, maybe, I mean, Nietzsche at least thinks it's okay, as science, he's got nothing against science, but as a way of life, to be detached, objective, and so forth, is indecent, degenerate, dangerous, decadent.
They all have sick, they all have words for it, that it's impossible really to get away with it.
People are living things, and life they are necessarily involved in, and the attempt to get out of it is, as Socrates says in the stuff I read last time from the Twilight of the Idols.
It shows that Socrates and the Athenians have become degenerate because they can't just trust their instincts and be involved in the world anymore.
And both of them wrote at a time when the Enlightenment, which is the whole Greek project brought up to date by Descartes and Kant, and with the Enlightenment which promised that somehow, thanks to disinterested critical reflection and reason and objectivity and science, the world would be saved from all kinds of bad things, lower immediacy like dogmatism, superstition, fanaticism, and a new enlightenment, mature human being would arise who was free and rational and in control of nature and society, master of himself and everything else, as Kant said, at last a mature and self-sufficient human being.
And Dostoevsky and Nietzsche both agree that this platonic will to truth, to objectivity, to getting the answer about everything, didn't fulfill its promise.
That instead of giving us all those goodies, it undermined meaning and commitment and made having a fulfilling life more and more difficult and finally impossible in the West.
So that's their shared take on something very wrong with our culture.
And remember, they wrote within a year of each other, the brothers Karamatsov and the Gay Science.
But they differ totally on what you should do about it to resist it or reverse it, this bad change.
Dostoevsky, like Kierkegaard, thinks that Christianity, purified of Plato and the Greek influence, is what can save the culture.
Nietzsche thinks, I said this before, but it's so important to say again: Nietzsche thinks Christianity is part of the problem.
And he would say it's no accident that Augustine, for instance, merged Christianity and Plato.
They had this otherworldly view from the start, and therefore, and this wrong view, and no wonder they put them together.
We have to not only get to the root of Platonism, but to the root of Christianity and philosophy and destroy them all, Nietzsche thinks, if we're going to be able to live, he can't even say meaningful lives, you'll see why, but lives worth living.
And they both see that our culture is undermining the Greek Christian Enlightenment values.
And a new way of looking at things in which God doesn't play any role is on the horizon.
Dostoevsky was very sensitive to what was coming next, and he considered that a disaster, a total, a total destruction of everything.
We'll read the, I'll go back and read the relevant passages from Yvonne.
Nietzsche, which thought that somehow you had to make a virtue of what was coming along.
So, Dostoevsky, to put it finely, Dostoevsky is conservative.
He wants to go back to the way things were when our culture was healthy.
Nietzsche is a radical, in the sense that he wants to destroy the whole culture as it, because it was never, well, it was once, but never since the Homeric Greeks.
It would just been downhill ever since.
And so, depending on whether you yourself believe and cherish this tradition in the West, which seems to be sinking, and want to save it, or whether you find it upsetting, whether you find it hopeless, and when I finish it off, that's whether you're going to be for Dostoevsky or for Nietzsche, finally.
And now, that's enough background.
I think that's just supposed to be a summary.
If anybody has anything to say about it, you can say it, but I thought I sort of said it, but I read a lot of text, and I thought maybe it was better to sum it up.
Okay, now we get on to the exciting part.
Probably the most famous and important thing that Nietzsche ever wrote, and he wrote lots of famous and important things, is The Madman, where he asserts the death of God.
So I don't know now, I have to find out.
How many people have this copy, which is the one I told you to have?
How many people have some other copy?
Correct, great, that's good.
That means I'm going to cite it by page numbers, not by aphorisms.
On the handout, which I'll give you, the assignment, I'll put it in by aphorism so that people who have other, there are other translations.
And so you can't, the aphorisms are not going to always be on the same pages.
But I'm going to give you the pages.
And so we start with page 181.
And I just have to read things because it's so amazing.
So have you heard of that madman who lit a lantern in the bright morning hours and ran into the marketplace and cried incessantly, I seek God, I seek God.
And that's well, let's go on.
As many of those who did not believe in God were standing around just then, he provoked much laughter.
And then they say, has he got lost?
Is he afraid of us?
And they yelled and laughed.
And so let's stop with that.
There's so many puzzles in this that you have to try to figure out.
So it looks like there were people standing around who didn't believe in God.
But on 182, he seems to say the opposite.
Because after he's been trying to convince them that God is dead, he sees that he isn't convincing them at the top of 183.
So here the madman fell silent and looked again at his listeners.
And they too were silent and stared at him in astonishment, skipping a little.
I've come too early, he said then.
My time is not yet.
This tremendous event is still on the way, still wandering.
It's not reached the ears of men.
So he says, one, on one page, that when he tells them that God is dead, they say, okay, ho-hum, we know that already, or joke about it.
And on the next page, he says, the people in the marketplace, meaning the ordinary people, haven't a clue about this business of God being dead.
They don't know what he's talking about.
The news that God is dead hasn't reached them.
So now that's a kind of clue that you better think carefully about what he means by God.
Because what's really going on is the people in the marketplace think they don't believe in God.
They're atheists and scientists and philosophers and whatever.
And maybe ordinary people too who think they don't believe in God, but they do believe in God.
They just don't know they do.
And so that's how the news hasn't reached them yet that God is really dead because they don't even know what God is.
So we have to figure out what God is.
Nietzsche tells us in other places.
The most important place is on page 283.
You've got to read this book in a weird way.
You've just got to sort of put together the story from the pieces that are scattered all over the place, or there are many different stories.
I'm telling you the story always about sort of the death of God in our culture.
And here's, and now, here's the top of 283, we find out the sense in which those people in the marketplace, even the smartest ones, the scientists, let's say, still believe in God, three lines down.
It is still a metaphysical faith upon which our faith in science rests, that even we seekers after knowledge today, we godless anti-metaphysicians, see, they all think they're godless anti-metaphysicians.
You won't find any people who are doing speculations about the supreme being in any of the science labs, at least not scientists, and maybe on the side they might be Christians or philosophers or something.
But even the godless anti-metaphysicians, the materialists, the people who think that the science will eventually prove and control everything, are still, and now look, we godless metaphysicians still take our fire too from the flame lit by a faith that is thousands of years old.
The Christian faith, which was also the faith of Plato, what they combined in.
And the faith is that God is the truth and the truth divine.
So, what does that mean?
Well, it means that as long as you believe that there's some right answer to the way the universe is, that there is something like objective truth, which a lot of you still do believe, although more and more really people don't, and maybe you don't.
But, I mean, what would it be not to believe it?
It would believe, we'll get back to that a lot later, but it would be to believe that there are only interpretations and perspectives.
And there isn't any answer to the structure of the universe.
It's not just the claim that science hasn't got the answer yet or may never get the answer.
It's the claim that the idea that there's some right way of describing things because there's some objective way things really are.
That's the mistake.
That's what he says when he says at the end of that quote I was reading, God himself may or should, what if God should prove to be our most enduring lie?
What would be the enduring lie?
The enduring lie would be that there's some kind of truth and the truth is a good thing and we in our lives and in our science and philosophy and every way pursue it, believe in it because we think there is such a thing and it's valuable.
That's a lie.
And it's that, you see, back to 181, that the people in the marketplace aren't really atheists.
They just think they are.
So those standing about who don't believe in God and laugh really do believe in God and haven't even heard the news.
You probably haven't heard the news either until you read this, that the very notion of objective truth doesn't make any sense.
That it's all, and you'll see later reading more of it, perspectival.
Everybody can have their own perspective, their own interpretation of the structure of things and the meaning of things.
There's no right answer.
And that's because there's no perspective, there's no position from which to take what a philosopher these days, Tom Nagel, calls the view from nowhere.
There's only perspectives and all these contradictory perspectives and interpretations.
And that's the news that's coming, and Nietzsche is the first to know.
And he's way ahead of his time, but it's more and more the case.
I mean, it's changed a lot since I've been teaching.
For instance, if you ask young scientists now, I mean, well, Einstein still believed there was one right answer to the universe, and our minds had been made by God to be adapted to understanding that structure, and that he was making progress, and that was the best thing you could do was to make progress understanding that structure.
Now, there are lots of people, when I say to scientists, my daughter, for instance, who's a chemist, and I sort of say, well, there really are electrons and galaxies, and so she looks a little worried and thinks maybe there's something wrong with me to believe that.
So that's simply like that.
Maybe this is just one big social construction.
I think she really still is a bit old guard and believes finely that there are the things she's studying.
That the more you find the younger scientists, it seems to me, I don't know, how many of you are majoring in science?
Okay, I'm just curious, how many think that science is getting it, is gradually converging and getting it right about the way the world is, independent of us and our investigation?
Woo!
Okay, well, that's what I thought.
I mean, I'm all for, I'm still one of the people in the marketplace who believes in science.
But Nietzsche says, and that word hasn't reached most people yet, that and what word that's on the way, namely, there isn't any objective truth about ethics.
I'm sure more of you believe that than even the science-maybe people.
I mean, is there some right answer to what is the right way to behave?
Well, the Christians think they've got an answer, and the Buddhists think they've got an answer, and Kantians have an answer, and so forth.
And those are all just perspectives, Nietzsche would say.
The idea that there is one right answer about the right way to behave is just, well, I was going to say old-fashioned, but let's be more specific.
It's something that the Greeks and Christians inspired to get everybody to believe.
And now let's go on, because Nietzsche has a theory about why everybody believes it.
Do I say that?
Well, let's see what it says.
At the bottom of 105.
During the last century, science has been promoted partly because it was by means of science that one hoped to understand God's goodness and wisdom best.
This was the main motive of the great Englishman like Newton.
And Einstein was still part of that.
Partly because one believed in the absolute utility of knowledge, and especially the most intimate association of morality, knowledge, and happiness.
This is the, whether it's Aristotle or Kant or probably Hawking, who says at the end of the brief history of time that when we get science done, we'll understand the mind of God.
Presumably, then we'll understand why we're here and so forth.
That's the main motive of a great Frenchman like Voltaire.
Partly because one thought that in science one possessed and loved something unselfish, harmless, self-sufficient, truly innocent, in which man's evil impulses had no part whatever.
The main motive of Spinoza, who felt divine when attaining knowledge, in some owing to three errors.
So Nietzsche doesn't believe any of that, but he's trying to diagnose why people think the truth is a good thing and we should pursue it, because it's going to tell us how to live.
Okay, and it's going to satisfy, but we'll get to that in a little while, but I'll just say ahead.
I mean, it's going to give us a sense of the meaning and order of things.
And who wouldn't want to understand the meaning of all this, the usual question, why we're here and what we should be doing.
But it doesn't, and it can't.
But I want to get there the way Nietzsche gets there.
We'll get back to that in a minute.
But the first thing, we have to go back to 181 because there's, I mean, I'm trying to go through this sort of step by step.
So the second thing that the madman tells them is that second paragraph: the madman jumped into their midst and pierced them with his eyes.
Whither is God, he cried.
I'll tell you, we have killed him, you and I.
All of us are his murderers.
But how did we do that?
How did we drink up the sea?
Who gave us the sponge to wipe away the entire horizon?
And so forth and so forth.
And now there's a new interesting question.
How did we do that?
Well, it's tied up to the will to truth.
Once you've got the will to truth, and if you suppose, as Nietzsche does, that there isn't any truth, then you're eventually going to find out your will to truth is eventually going to get you to find out that there isn't any and undermine itself.
I mean, that sounds a little weird, so I have to explain it more.
So, Christianity, which is what he's talking about in the passage I'm going to read you, overcomes itself.
Science also overcomes itself.
That means that by pursuing the truth relentlessly, they discover that what they believed just isn't so.
And now, here's what he says on 307.
You see what Triumph, middle of the page, you see what Triumphed over the Christian God, Christian morality itself, the concept of truthfulness that was understood ever more rigorously.
The Father Confessor's refinement of the Christian conscience, translated and sublimated into a scientific conscience, into intellectual cleanliness at any price.
What he's saying is that the remember that I've mentioned this before, for the Christians, it's important that people understand their desires because they're either pure and saved or they have to transform their desires if they've got bad desires.
But therefore, they need a science of confession to find out what people's desires are, to get people to recognize what they really desire.
And once they recognize what they really desire, they will discover that what they really desire, they can't have.
But now we have to jump, go on.
So, so far, the Christians have this got more and more through confession, through philosophy and theology, into getting clearer and clearer about what people want.
So, skipping really, interpreting one's own experience now, and against any kind of self-delusion that there is some God, that there is some answer, and the problem is: if they discover that they believe that there is a God, because it would make them happier and be very satisfying and get them out of the sense that there's no guidelines in the universe, if they want to believe it, so much that they do believe it, that would be fine.
But if they also have this will to truth, so that they can sort of see that they're believing it because they want to believe it, not because they've got any evidence for it, then the will to truth will undermine their belief.
So, this is what he says next.
And it sounds, it's sort of funny, if you think of Dostoevsky in the background, about 12 lines from the bottom of 307, interpreting one's own experiences as pious people have long enough interpreted theirs as if everything were providential, a hint, designed and ordained for the sake of the salvation of the soul.
That is all over, underlined now.
That has man's conscience against it.
That is, you can't just interpret everything to make it look like.
Remember, there's always the guiding finger in Dostoevsky.
There's the constant sense that, and the experience, oh, where did I find?
I wonder I lost a quote, I realized.
Maybe I've written it down and it'll show up, I hope.
But if not, I'll just tell you, and then I'll try to find it.
I mean, the idea that the connectedness of everything, that very important experience in the middle of the brothers, Dostoevsky has very funny things to say about that.
I hope I've written them down here, but if not, I'll find them anyway.
I don't know.
It's a quote, I doubt if any of you remember it, where he says people shouldn't believe in little angels, and when they have religious experiences, they should be sure that they're not hungry and upset.
And it sounds like a list of things that was wrong with Alyasha when he had that experience.
And it's part of the, according to him, sort of a Christian duty.
to question yourself when you're having these religious experiences and making sure you're not just having sort of private psychotic experiences.
Now, where?
Does that sound familiar?
Something about the voices of little angels.
Well, I'll bring it in next time if I don't discover it as I go on talking.
So let's go on and we'll see what happens.
Unless I turn the page and find it.
No, there are no little angels on the page.
So I'm going on.
So putting aside now, well, no, I'm still continuing on the idea that because Christianity is committed to getting the truth about one's desires and one's religious experiences, they're finding out more and more that there isn't any basis for this, for that the world is the way they would like it to be.
And so let's go on.
In our culture, and now I'm going to give some background sort of, in our culture, and uniquely in our culture, I think he thinks, we want meaning.
We're in the meaning business.
We are, in a way, addicted to meaning.
Now, you might wonder what other cultures are different, if not meaning.
Well, I could just blurt it out ahead so you could think about it.
Maybe in the Homeric culture, instead of meaning, they've got wonder.
Or Plato and the philosophers that say that philosophy begins in wonder, and Heidegger takes that, my, my guy, very seriously.
But there could be a kind of world in which, instead of meaning, there were all kinds of sort of amazing things were happening, exciting things were happening, mind-blowing things were happening, and that would be more important than some stable meaning order.
And maybe Bali is like that.
I think of Bali as the place where gods are showing up all the time, and every day is a religious holiday, and it isn't a question of pursuing truth and meaning, it's sort of preserving the sacred and feeling the wonder of it.
So anyway, but our culture got into the meaning business.
So let's look at that on page 75.
And it isn't something that human nature just naturally has.
It's something that our culture somehow wandered into about 15 lines from the bottom.
Human nature has been changed by the ever new appearance of these teachers of the purpose of existence.
It now is one additional need, the need for the ever new appearance of such teachers and teachers of a purpose.
Now, I can't tell, and it doesn't matter for us whether he thinks this is true of all human beings all over, even in Bali, which maybe it is, we don't know.
What's only important is really, he thinks in the West anyway, we've gotten so.
We've got to understand the purpose.
So he says, gradually man, I think you should just say Western men and women, and stick with that.
Gradually, Western men and women have become fantastic animals that have a full, they have to fulfill one more condition of existence than any other animal.
Man has to believe to know from time to time why he exists.
His race, no, he really wants to make it about all human beings.
What do I think?
I think you can read it either way.
You can read the myth of any culture as a story about how it came into existence and what the gods were trying to do and so forth.
So let's, I really think he's wrong about that, but let's give him the benefit of the doubt.
So all that is, the human race can't flourish without a periodic trust in life, without faith in reason in life.
And again and again, the human race will decree from time to time there is something at which it is absolutely forbidden henceforth to laugh.
That's an amazingly interesting statement.
The sacred, whatever it is, is certainly that in the culture about which you can't laugh.
And according to him, every culture has something in it that's sacred.
That's probably true.
I mean, if you put it that way, and not that they are asking the question, why is there human existence, but that there is something whose meaning you can't question.
And it's forbidden in the way the culture is set up to laugh at it.
Now, that sort of is fascinating in itself, but it also has a funny relation to Dostoevsky.
Do you realize?
And Kierkegaard.
Because this Nietzsche thing that you're forbidden to laugh at is really the same thing as the eternal in time.
It's that those special moments who are so important to who you are or to the whole culture.
If you want to bring in the God-man as something that happened at a special moment.
I mean, those special moments are taken to be so definitive of what the culture is and who you are that you can't laugh at them.
And that makes me want to remind you how close that is to Dostoevsky.
Just sort of by accident, but he did, but it's not me, it's not that it's false.
He really says the following thing, which I'm now going to find.
Where are we?
728.
Hope I haven't got it.
It's something we've read already, so it shouldn't be me.
Well, I'm not off to a good start.
Now I can't even find a thing about not laughing, which I thought I had in front of me.
Let me catch up where I am.
So the culture is getting more and more addicted to meaning.
And, well, oh, I know.
Why am I making such a fuss?
I mean, we know where it is.
It's in the very last thing, the very last pages, on 896, I would think, where he tells the boys that no matter what happens to them, they won't laugh at how they were at this moment.
That's what I want to find.
Where are we?
We've got to find, what is it?
Oh, at top of 8, it's on 896, but I don't see it.
Oh, I see.
But I assure you, boys, the man often laughs at what's good and kind.
That's only from thoughtlessness.
But I assure you boys that it laughs, he will say it once in his heart.
No, I do wrong to laugh, for that's not a thing to laugh at.
Now, that's funny.
That isn't the quote I had, but it's the same kind of quote.
Does he say it again?
No, maybe he doesn't say it again.
Well, it's a good thing you found that.
Because I didn't even have that marked.
I thought I so I must have someplace else marked, but let me mark that one.
So it's no matter what you boys think, I'm still looking for it.
You will look back on this moment and you won't feel cynical and you won't laugh about this moment.
Surely that's okay.
Well, the quote that whoever, who gave me that quote just now?
Good, thanks.
That does it.
So let's go on.
Okay, there is another quote.
We should get them both.
895.
Together, so forth.
Yes, let him laugh.
Is that the same one?
Or is there another one?
I think.
Yes, yes.
Where are you reading?
That's what I was looking for.
But isn't that the same one I just read?
Not quite.
Oh, yeah, here it is.
That's the one I mark, right?
Dare not to laugh at having been kind and good.
Right.
There is something which that's a sacred memory, as he says.
And since it's a sacred memory, you can't laugh at it.
You can't be cynical about it and so forth.
And so we got, our culture got addicted to meaning as that super, not just little things like these memories, but something even more meaningful, namely the Supreme Being that ordered everything in the super monotheistic way, so that everything got built into it, as he said.
That's very important.
So man becomes this fantastic animal that needs meaning.
And then on 279, of course, by the way, you see where the connections are.
I can't keep them all up in front of you at once.
But if man believes in meaning just because he needs it, because he's become that kind of creature who is a kind of meaning addict and can't live without meaning, and that's why he believes it.
Then, as he gets more and more clear about his beliefs and starts questioning whether the beliefs are justified, he will undermine the very beliefs that crop up this belief in meaning.
That's the idea he's got.
Now, let me find where we are on 279.
And then you get this monotheism, which is certainly not all human beings, but just the West.
But now, skipping about 15 lines down on 217, he's back to talking about the event that God has said.
The event itself is far too great, too distant, too remote from the multitude's capacity for comprehension, even for the tidings of it to be thought of as having arrived as yet.
Well, that's explaining what he said on page 181.
Much less, and now comes the news of what will happen.
Much less may one suppose that many people know as yet what this event really means.
Remember, the people in the marketplace have no clue.
And how much must collapse now that this faith has been undermined, because it was built on this faith, propped up by it, grown into it, the whole of our European morality.
Now, that's really interesting, and there are lots of consequences.
He sees, and I think he's right, that in this Judeo-Christian Greek world, that this monotheism with this one supreme God who created the world, who created it to be good, who gave us the ethics to go with it good, who gave us the kinds of minds to understand the structure of reality and built the structure of reality to fit it.
I think Galileo said, if reality had been like this, then God would have given us a mind that was like that.
I mean, the conviction that God set us up and the universe up so that they meshed.
And that is what's gone.
But if that goes, or that hasn't gone yet, but that's what's going, and if that goes, then everything is going to fall apart.
Because, as I say, we've become meaning junkies.
We've become, we were, in the Middle Ages anyway, at Dante time, say 1300, we had a culture in which everything made sense.
And what we were supposed to do and why we were here and how to find out about the structure of the universe and that there was a structure and that our minds were fixed to find it out.
That all made sense.
And now we can't live without it.
Now people have gotten to the point where, as he says in Twilight on 33, that people simply can't live without meaning.
At the bottom of 33, if we possess the why of life, we can put up with almost any how.
And he says every once in a while, people would be willing to suffer if they could understand why they were here, what they were supposed to do, and all that.
And I think that's right.
And it's very interesting.
I think it's illuminating, or I wouldn't drag this in, but I have these discussions with my son, the Buddhist, in which he tells me that the meaning of everything is to get rid of suffering.
And I tell him, no, no, if suffering is necessary to understand the meaning of everything, then you've got to put up with suffering.
So then in a sort of way, the Buddhist seems to me, in him anyway, to come back and say the real issue is suffering and getting yourself and everything in the universe out of suffering.
And I say, no, the real issue is meaning.
And we have to have meaning.
And if we don't have meaning, we can't stand it.
And we're ready to suffer.
And if necessary, in our lives and in our culture and in our tragedies and so forth to get that meaning.
And now Nietzsche's got a third thing.
Nietzsche thinks suffering is essential, but it isn't to give us meaning.
Meaning we never should have got hooked on, but suffering we shouldn't try to get rid of.
So it's neither a Buddhist nor a Christian view.
And we haven't got it yet.
But he's got his own view, and we'll get there.
So, in our culture, we meaning addicts will be willing to suffer if only we can get meaning.
But on the other hand, we're going to be able to do that.
When religion gets good at finding out the truth about our psychology and science gets clear about psychology, they're going to find out that our craving for meaning and order isn't based on any evidence.
It's just built on all these prophets who promised it until we got addicted to it.
And that's how religion begins to undermine itself.
And that's why he says we have killed God.
Christianity, by being so clear about our desires, undermines our supposed reasons for believing in God by making our motives suspicious.
I mean, that's what the whole confession managed to do: be suspicious of everybody's motives.
Don't just believe every religious experience, like Dostoevsky wants us to believe Alyash's.
Look and see what circumstances led somebody to have that kind of experience.
And that means you undermine the experience.
And that's what he's saying.
So, Christianity undermines its own reasons for believing in God by examining the motives which led it to having that belief.
I think I've already read 307, didn't I?
Yes.
That gets us back to 307.
Okay, now we're going to make another move.
I mean, I could stop.
I mean, I go on and on, and you all sit there.
I think this must be, I hope it is, interesting and original and far out and worth thinking about.
But if somebody wants to sort of say anything, I'm ready to hear it.
Okay, it gets even more fun and weird and deep.
So let's go on.
The next move is that if, and this is where Nietzsche seems absolutely right, if all of our understanding of why we're here and what we're supposed to do is built into this idea that we have been created by a good, single, meaningful God, and then if we stop believing that, everything's going to collapse.
And he's very, very clear about that.
This reign of terror that's going to hit the world.
And this is on 270.
He's very eloquent about it.
That's about halfway down the page.
So they don't know anything about the event.
It hasn't arrived yet.
Much less may one suppose that many people know as yet what this event, that is the realization that God is dead, really means.
And how much must collapse now that this faith has been undermined, because it was built upon this faith, you know, propped up by it, grown into it, the whole of our European morality.
I read that, I think.
But the next sentence: this long plenitude and sequence of breakdown, destruction, ruin, and cataclysm that is now impending, who could guess enough of it today to be compelled to play the teacher and proclaimer of this monstrous logic of terror, the prophet of a gloom and eclipse of the sun whose like has probably never yet occurred on earth.
That's just incredible.
Now, why would it be something that has never before occurred on earth?
Do you understand that?
I mean, why is our culture's collapse a much specialer kind of collapse than any other cultures?
Because what?
Yes, because, and one meaning, we had this monotheistic, complete story of a creator, good God, who made it all meaningful and made us a place in it and made us able to understand it and so forth.
No other culture ever has had such a monolithic view, what Nietzsche calls monotonotheism, but you can like it.
But whether you like it or hate it like he does, the point is it's total.
And therefore, if you believe in thousands of gods, like in Japan or Bali, and a few gods turn out not to exist, it doesn't matter much.
I mean, there's plenty of other sacred places and beings and gods and so forth.
That if you believe that there's one supreme being, and then you stop, and everything gets its meaning in terms of it, and then you stop believing in it, then you get a total collapse like nothing ever before in the history of the universe.
It's something that had probably never yet occurred on Earth.
You have to say probably, because maybe there's some monotheistic religion, you know, it was or asterism or something that collapsed and produced its own local total breakdown.
But for us, this is unique.
And now, what I want you to notice is that he calls it a cataclysm.
Does anybody recognize the surprising that he's using that word?
I mean, it's a perfectly right word.
A cataclysm is like a huge earthquake, I think, though my dictionary, at least in my computer, didn't tell me what a cataclysm was.
But I think it's, and that means that the ground for everything has been shaken totally so that everything falls down.
And that's just a way to say, yes, it was all grounded in God, again, the Supreme Being.
And when you get rid of that, it's like a huge earthquake in which everything falls down.
And the interesting thing is, who else calls it a cataclysm?
It's unlikely that the first dozen times you read the brothers, you would notice that.
I didn't.
But look at this.
On 751, Yvonne, the devil, is telling Yvonne about something Yvonne wrote, and what was it called?
The geological cataclysm.
I mean, it would make one think that maybe Dostoevsky read the brothers, except that the brothers couldn't have been around yet, when he was writing this.
But look what Yvonne says.
Two-thirds of the way down on 751.
As soon as men have all denied God, and I believe that period corresponding to a geological period will come to pass, the old conception of life and the un the old conception of the universe will fall of itself without cannibalism, and what's more, the old morality and everything will begin anew.
Now, never mind that, just for the time being, anyway.
First, they both share, he and Yvonne, this view.
And then remember, I said Dostoevsky is so brilliant that he's invented Nietzsche.
And he's even the same words.
And now, and he makes the next move the same, but I want to go make it in Nietzsche first.
So we are told that it will be a reign of terror like nobody had ever seen before.
Now, what's really strange is so it's a destruction of all the bedrock in which the whole world is based and everything's going to be destroyed.
And what's the title of this section on 279?
The meaning of our cheerfulness.
That's a surprise.
That's right, the title of the section in which this is going to be a reign of terror like nobody ever saw before.
How can that be?
Well, you get it in Yvonne already, because Dostoevsky's inventing Nietzsche.
I just read it.
It's going to turn out to be good news.
And here's what's going to happen, according to Yvonne.
Then something, the old morality is gone and everything will begin anew.
Men will unite to take from life all that it can give, but only for joy and happiness in the present world.
Man will be lifted up with a spirit of divine titanic pride, and the God-man will appear, extending his conquest of nature by his will and his science.
That's interesting.
That's a big difference that I never noticed before.
Of course, Nietzsche's not going to think that science is part of the new man, but he will feel a lofty joy from hour to hour.
And then, of course, on 752, what's more, the new man may well become the God-man, even if he's the only one.
Promoted to his new position.
I didn't quote this, but this is, of course, what Smershikov learned from Yvonne.
He may lightheartedly overstep all the barriers of the old morality, of the old slave man.
There is no law for God, the new God-man.
Where God stands, the place is holy.
Where I stand will become the foremost place.
All things are lawful, and that's it.
So that's the famous Dostoevsky version of it.
And just as for Yvonne, that it's good news, for Dostoevsky, it's good news.
And so now we have to understand why in the world this total collapse of meaning and the end of the culture into a kind of super earthquake would be something to be cheerful about.
Well, there are clues all over.
I mean, the clue, first clue, is that the title of the book is The Gay Science, which in German, maybe it's better to translate it in another translation, the joyful wisdom.
There's some knowledge he's imparting here, and it's a knowledge which would make you cheerful and joyful if you understand what he's telling you.
So we go to 279.
Here we are, back to the meaning of our cheerfulness.
I've read all I need to read from there.
So what's, and it's one more important point.
And it's very clear that whatever he's cheerful about, it isn't because we're going to get some new meaning.
You can't get the old meaning back, and you can't get any new meaning in either.
He thinks that the universe is just plain chaos.
There's nothing that you can say about it.
It's just random events, sort of things bumping into each other, period.
So what's new?
You can't get the old meaning back.
What can you get?
Well, the bottom of 180 is beginning to tell you why you should be joyful.
We've left the land and have embarked.
The land is the solid land that hadn't, that was destroyed by the cataclysm.
We have burned our bridges behind us.
That is, everything that made sense was all interconnected and it all went down at once.
We have gone further and destroyed the land behind us.
That is, we destroyed the very possibility of anything having a ground or a meaning.
Now, little ship, look out.
Beside you is the ocean.
To be sure, it does not always roar, and sometimes it's spread out in reveries of graciousness.
Then hours will come when you realize that it's infinite and there is nothing more awesome than infinity.
Well, that's what I'm not sure I understand those fancy words, but you can see that he's sort of substituting awesome for meaningful.
There is no meaning coming.
But it's exciting to have a new horizon of this sort.
That's what we have to understand now.
And that's, I'm now going to, I'm sort of spelling out the cheerfulness on 280.
Now you ask, what are the consequences of the total cataclysm?
And the answer now is four lines down on 280.
The consequences for ourselves are quite the opposite of what one might expect.
I told you, you'd think, seeing the terror, that it wouldn't be cheerful, but it is.
They are not at all sad and gloomy, but rather like a new and scarcely describable kind of light.
Happiness, relief, exhilaration, encouragement, dawn.
So all kinds of good things are on that list, everything that there's any meaning.
Indeed, we philosophers and free spirits, the name for these people who have understood the cataclysm and are happy about it, when we hear the news that the old God is dead, as if, let's see, indeed, when we're free spirits, feel, when we hear the news that the old God is dead, as if a new dawn shone on us, our heart overflows with gratitude, amazement, premonitions, expectations.
This sounds like Yvonne, except for the science part in Yvonne, that it's, isn't it, everything's going to be terrific.
And then skipping to the end, all the daring of the lover of knowledge is permitted again.
The sea, our sea, lies open again.
Perhaps there has never been such an open sea.
Do you understand why there has never been such an open sea?
It's the same.
It's the total collapse of everything at this point.
I mean, only a monotheistic culture that builds everything into the idea of a creator god, a good creator God, if that collapses, everything collapses.
And that, again, is leaving sort of everything open to new exploration and anybody can do anything.
Everything is lawful.
That's only possible in a culture in which everything is built into this previous order, so that if it collapses, everything goes, and there's no horizon, there's no land, there's no ground, everything's open.
Yeah.
So on Payton's idea of the good, on this single person.
Well, I think he certainly thinks that that gets put pretty quickly with Augustine and the Judeo-Christian God.
They have the same job.
They explain the intelligibility of everything, and the moral order of everything.
And I don't, I mean, he, he's, I read you a passage somewhere where he said Plato and Christianity in the same sentence, but I don't remember which one it was.
But they got fused because they both were totalizing.
Plato's already a mono-something.
He's just not a monotheist because the good isn't a person.
But it's not important whether you're a monotheist.
It's a question of whether you believe that there's one unified, intelligible, making sense to us and guiding us order in the universe or isn't.
Okay, anything else?
I'm glad somebody interrupted me.
Yeah.
Ah, I went over that very fast.
We could go back and look at it, but I can just tell you, that has to do with confession.
I did it in about one sentence.
If Christianity thinks that people's desires define who they are, then it becomes important that people confess their desires to somebody who can see through them, so to speak, because people are very good at fooling themselves and thinking they're doing good deeds when they're really doing something that benefits them and hurts somebody else and so forth.
So then you develop a whole technology of confession to get people to frankly face up to their desires.
And then you see that it's their desire for meaning that makes them interpret all events as having meaning and being significant and so forth.
So that's the idea.
You want to go back to it or do you remember where it is?
I'll read you the sentence.
It's the crucial one.
I don't know.
Let's look at 307.
I think that must be.
Yeah, 307.
See, what triumphed over the Christian God is the concept of truthfulness.
I think I may have skipped the next thing.
That was understood ever more rigorously.
The father confessor's refinement of the Christian conscience.
No, I think I read that.
Anyway, that's what I'm trying to explain.
Sublimated into a scientific conscience, into intellectual cleanliness at any price.
And then interpreting one's own experience as pious people have and so forth, now everything is against it.
And that means that we are involved in Europe's at the very end of there.
I didn't read.
Longest and most courageous self-overcoming.
Self-overcoming is the next thing to talk about.
That's where we are now.
So we become gods.
That's Sivan's reaction, and that's Nietzsche's cheerfulness.
And what is this business of overcoming?
Well, that's a new angle.
In Nietzsche, that's why suffering is important.
What's really satisfying, what really makes life worth living, is constantly overcoming suffering, overcoming sickness, overcoming them not by getting rid of them, by being able to take them on.
I don't know where Nietzsche says this, but somewhere he says, whatever doesn't kill me makes me stronger.
I think, oh, I think that's in the introduction to the gay science.
Let's look.
See, what's interesting about the gay science is that it's all about convalescing.
And from starting on page 32, the whole book is about this business of overcoming.
I find where it's clear.
Oh, yeah, here we are.
Okay.
On 37.
In the end, less what is most important remain unsaid from such abysses, from such severe illness.
See, he had been sick, and then he got well, and now he's feeling very cheerful and powerful and happy, and he's seeing the importance of being sick just for this great experience of being well.
So you get from severe sickness, from the sickness of severe suspicion, one returns newborn.
That's the new man, notice.
It's the same thing that Dostoevsky has already picked up.
Having shed one's skin, more ticklish, more malicious, with a delicate taste for joy, with a tender tongue for all good things, merrier with seconds, innocent joy, more childlike, and so forth.
Nothing about meaning, but everything else.
Or skipping about 15 lines from the bottom of 37.
We convalescents still need art, but it's another kind of art, a mocking, light, fleeting, divinely untroubled, and so forth.
Skipping a little.
We know better afterwards what above all is needed for this.
Cheerfulness.
Any cheerfulness, my friend.
And that's cheerfulness, remember, is why we are cheerful.
We're back today.
So he starts that way at the very beginning.
And I bet in here somewhere is what doesn't kill me, makes me stronger, but I don't think I can flip to it.
And it may be some other place that Nietzsche says that.
Yeah.
If you said it in here, I probably would have underlined it.
So now you're going to tell us about the great health, what you've got.
And now you understand, Nietzsche has such an interesting, complicated picture.
You understand that the culture has been sick.
And the culture has now, once they get rid of God and monotheism, they'll get over this sickness and they'll be convalescent.
And that's good.
That's what he calls the great health.
That's the great overcoming.
It was even worth the culture going through all this bad stuff in order to be able to experience this wonderful thing of being new.
Okay, so on 346, the great health.
Being new, nameless, hard to understand.
We premature births of a yet unproven future, yet for a new goal, also a new means, a new health, stronger, more seasoned, tougher, more audacious, and gayer than any previous health.
I mean, that's the same word as in the gay science.
And let me skip a little.
And so, skipping to the next paragraph: and now, after we've long been on our way in this manner, we argonauts of the ideal, with more daring perhaps than is prudent, and have suffered shipwreck and damage often enough, that we are, to repeat it, healthier than one likes to permit us, dangerously healthy, ever again healthy.
It seems to us as if it was a reward.
It seems to us as if, as a reward, we now confronted an as yet undiscovered country whose boundaries nobody has surveyed yet.
That's again like the ocean with no horizon.
Something beyond all the lands and nooks of the ideal so far.
A world so overrich.
Now, now notice, no meaning, but something else which I'm calling wonder.
A world so rich in what is beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible, and divine that our curiosity as well as our craving to possess it has got beside itself.
Alas, now nothing will save us anymore.
So that's his new substitute for how to live.
You live in this constant getting reborn and having the joy of being reborn.
And that means then that, as I said, sickness is a good thing.
Sickness is necessary because you couldn't get reborn if you didn't sort of die in your old diseases.
This is on way back at the beginning, on page six.
See, he's setting all this up at the beginning with his convalescence.
But I don't find page 30.
All I get is the translator's introduction.
I think I must have made a mistake.
Maybe there is no page.
Well, let's look for aphorism.
No?
Okay, I have to find that.
What else did I have to find that I didn't find that I promised I would find?
Somebody remember?
You remember?
Oh, yeah, the little angels and being hungry.
And you have to be very careful when you're having a religious experience that you're not just having a psychotic breakdown.
Okay, well, I'll find that.
So the sickness is necessary.
I don't know where.
And now we get to the fact that life is constant overcoming.
Finally, he tells you what he thinks the meaning of it all is.
It's a peculiar kind of meaning of it all because it's the meaning of it all doesn't give you any meaning, but it gives you this wonder.
And why is that happening?
And why is that important?
Well, I'm trying to find something, which I okay, so now it's got to do with life is constant overcoming.
So you've got to look now at 290 and 291.
It turns out that there is sort of a basic truth about the universe after all.
Not a meaning, not a structure, not any moral guidelines, but that just being alive means being constantly outgrowing whatever it is you are and think you are and are doing and taking on new identities, new projects, new worlds.
That's what it is to be alive.
So you find at the bottom of 291, the wish to preserve oneself is a symptom of distress, of a limitation of the really fundamental instinct of life, which aims at the expansion of power.
So that's what life is.
Life aims at the expansion of power.
It is constantly overcoming.
At the bottom of the next, on 292, with the big paragraph, the bottom of it, the great and small struggle always resolves around superiority, around growth and expansion, around power, in accordance with the will to power, which is the will of life.
The will to power is that last unfinished book he was writing.
And this is the middle of 292.
This is really his view.
And I wanted to another quote that says that this wonder where it is.
I'll write that down too.
I owe you three now.
Sickness is necessary.
Keep an eye on your religious experiences.
Life is overcoming.
I mean, he says that in the passages I just read you, but there's a place where he says it more directly.
And I don't know where that is.
Okay.
So I've got one more thing to say then.
And nobody else are there any say?
Well, I just have one more piece in this.
So now we've gotten, just let me say again, the fact that everything collapsed is a wonderful thing.
Turns out that our culture is the best culture because it manages to build this amazing monolithic monotheism and collapse it, and therefore has a kind of the biggest amount of overcoming that any culture ever had.
It's going to have to overcome everything that it believed before and start over again, and it'll have a wonderful convalescence, and everything will be wonderful and new and beautiful, just like Yvonne was talking about.
And so what will people do?
Well, there's lots of talk about what people will do, but I just want to read two of them, partly because sometimes I read things because they're related to breathless.
And so this is things that you need to have noticed when you see breathless.
So on 258, you won't know really right now why I'm reading you this, but you will maybe know when you see the movie.
So at the top of 258, surely the faith, he wants to say that you should lead a life of egoism, as he calls it.
After all, if what you're trying to do is sort of overcome yourself and everybody else and your circumstances and increase your power, then you are not going to want to be timid.
You're not going to be turning the other cheek.
I'll say this way ahead of time.
Somebody asked me sort of what he says about Jesus.
Jesus has lots of important affinities with this business of opening up a new world, according to him.
So he likes Jesus.
I think he thinks Jesus only made one mistake.
He was against egoism.
He was for the meek.
Nietzsche has nothing good to say for the meek.
He's all for the strong.
He goes with expansion and life and so forth.
So at the top of 258, surely the faith preached so stubbornly with so much conviction that egoism is reprehensible has on the whole harmed egoism while benefiting, as I shall repeat a hundred times, the herd instincts.
Those are the sort of people that let you walk all over them.
Above all, by depriving egoism of its good conscience and bidding us to find in it the true source of all unhappiness.
Your selfishness is a misfortune of your life that was preached for thousands of years and harmed, as I have said, selfishness and deprived it of much spirit, much cheerfulness, much sensibility, much beauty.
It has made selfishness stupid and ugly and poisoned.
Now, when you see the movie, ask yourself who represents the kind of egoist that he admires.
And now, just one more.
I'm just sort of building a case so that when we're going to see, remember, I'm going to do all the Nietzsche, and then we're going to see Breathless, and then we're going to discuss Breathless, and then there's going to be one final lecture.
But so, lots of things that we're reading.
It's going to help you when you see Breathless.
But if somebody asked me, why do I think that Breathless is a Nietzschean movie?
There are lots of little hints.
But the most important one is a poster on the wall at one point that reads, live dangerously.
And this is what he's talking about on 228.
Ah, I haven't read 228, have I?
Because I'm going to read something I didn't realize.
It's got another one of those overcoming passages which are important, about 10 lines down.
We now need many preparatory, courageous human beings who cannot very well leap out of nothing any more than out of the sand and slime of present-day civilization and metropolitanism.
Human beings who know how to be silent, lonely.
This is not about breathless.
This is about overcoming.
Human beings that know who to be silent.
This is really about Nietzsche, who lived all by himself in a cabin up in the high Alps, where he, and you can understand how you could think very clearly on bright, cold days.
He could think very clearly when it was, and he loved to be walking around in the high Alps and living in his little cabin up there.
And so, and we need people who can be silent, lonely, resolute, and content, and constant in invisible activities.
Human beings who are bent on seeking all things for what in them must be overcome.
See, that's what he thinks he's doing.
Human beings distinguished by, look at that again, cheerfulness.
Cheerfulness is such an among all these terms like bliss and joy and what are other ones, fulfillment, those are all too meaning-laden and too Christian or Greek.
He's got his own sort of strange kind of happiness, which is he calls cheerfulness.
Yeah, I know, I know, I'm about to get there, but thanks.
Yeah, I saw that other quote I wanted to say.
Now I'm saving this one until the last time, time is just running out, but we have time to read it.
So here's the quote, a piece of which appears on the wall in the background in Breathless, about ten lines from the bottom of 228.
More endangered human beings, more fruitful human beings.
How do I begin there?
Okay, I will start with, for believe me, the secret for harvesting from existence the greatest fruitfulness and the greatest enjoyment is to live dangerously underline.
Build your cities on the slopes of Vesuvius, send your ships into uncharted seas, live at war with your peers and yourselves, be robbers and conquerors as long as you cannot be rulers and possessors.
That's sort of the epigraph that you could put over Breathless.
And we can stop with that.
We'll go on and you just do the reading and I will comment on it as we go.