I'm going to start by going back to Breathless because I think I learned something absolutely important, and I hope it's right, and new to me after all these years of teaching Breathless from some people's objections that he really that Michel Poikar is somehow not a Nietzschean free spirit.
And I said, well, of course not.
He's a kind of pop-free spirit.
But he's not even a pop-free spirit.
There's something essential about him, about free spirits, I think, that he laughs.
I was just beginning to get a glimmer of that at the end last time, so I'm going to run quickly through it.
We know he's a positive nihilist, and Patricia's a negative one.
I don't change my mind about that.
But there are degrees of positive nihilism.
And I want to say now, maybe I'll have to give this up under questioning or after thinking about it more, but I think now he's the lowest form of active or positive nihilist.
And he's, and I'll tell you at the end what the highest form is.
And there's a big difference at the end of this little thing on the breathless.
And there's a big difference.
But let's start with him.
Here's what he has of positive, active nihilism.
He has brief habits.
She is his brief habit.
He's ready to risk his life for her, but he's clear that it's not a long-term commitment.
He's irreverent about all the old morality.
Everything's sacred and is for him old and weak.
And he's cheerfully ignoring everything that's been taken seriously and making fun of it.
And he understands and enjoys that the answer to the why is lacking and uses it to make up a life story for himself, or many several lives, and use it to make a sort of nihilistic poetry.
He lives dangerously, and I hadn't really noticed, but if you look at 228, you have to have the, he fits perfectly into the free spirit.
If you go after the live dangerously in 228, I think I even read it, but I didn't really, it didn't soak in.
He says, live at war with your peers and yourselves, be robbers and conquerors as long as you cannot be rulers and possessors.
Well, he's a robber.
He's an outlaw.
He's a car stealer.
He's one of the people that actually gets listed here as the kind of people who live dangerously.
But how does he fall short of being a free spirit, of being, which I take to be the highest kind?
See, I used to say in all last lecture, I said he was a free spirit.
I take that back.
If you go back over your notes, I would take out every time it says free spirit and put positive nihilist, because he is a positive nihilist, but he's not a free spirit.
Well, what does he lack as a free spirit?
Something absolutely essential.
He's not creative.
He's a kind of negative, reactive kind of free spirit who's tearing everything down, making fun of it, but even a positively cheerful way.
But he's not contributing new values.
He's not opening up new horizons.
If you look at that on page 242, you see in aphorism 302 in the fifth line, two sentences that are side by side, one of which characterizes him.
Uh-oh, we're out of valuation forms?
That's amazing.
There must be some around.
I brought it a whole.
Anybody else without evaluation forms?
Well, that's pretty amazing.
We seem to have exactly the right.
Okay, spread them around.
I'm going back to where I am.
Two sentences.
He says, Nietzsche says, a strong, bold, audacious soul to go through life with a calm eye and a firm step, always prepared to risk all.
That fits him.
That's okay.
That's already to be a positive nihilist.
And then he says the next sentence, impelled by the longing for undiscovered worlds, fees, people, and gods.
Now, you just don't find that in him.
I don't find him looking for other worlds, people, suns, fees, gods at all.
He's perfectly happy just cheerfully making fun of the ones that are left over from the previous age.
So that's the sense in which he lacks the energy and strength, I think, to go all the way.
The free spirit goes all the way.
He not only gets rid of this world, he opens new horizons, new perspectives.
Just again, these news, new suns, new worlds, new eyes, new gods, and now even new values.
So now I want to say a word about new values.
But before I do, I think I stop a minute.
Do you think I have mischaracterized him, given him too much credit as a positive nihilist or too little credit as the lowest form of the positive nihilist far from a free spirit, which is what I now think you were sensitive to, some of you, when you wanted to complain that he didn't really seem quite as the free spirit I was making him out to be.
I I'm pretty satisfied with this, and so I'm not going to stop long unless anybody has strong protests or comments.
I'm going on to the next point.
There's so many.
So, on this list of new, the most important new is new values.
That's something really special that only the most free spirit can do.
Maybe something even higher than a free spirit, which Nietzsche calls in another book of his, the book Thus Spake Zarathustra, there are overmen, Über mentioned, literally supermen, and they invent new values.
So, I haven't said much about that, and it's a little late to say much, but I'm going to have to say something because it's important.
At the bottom of 265, he talks about, very bottom, the creation of our own new table of what is good.
And that means, again, sometimes he calls it creating new values.
And now he says, let us, we, where, do I say, does he say new values in this quote?
No, but in other quotes.
So now, what is it to create new values?
Well, it's not just to change values.
The last time I talked about this, I said, well, he goes from certain Christian values to values of overcoming.
That is, he substitutes life values for what he thinks of life-denying values or sort of strong, energetic, for weak ones.
But I now think there's something much deeper and important, too.
So he doesn't just substitute new values, he changes what it means to be a value.
Up to now, values were our fixed.
They're true.
So if they really are values, then they're values for everybody, everywhere, and they're not local, and they're not changeable.
The very notion of a value is like ethics.
It's universal.
Well, he's got a new kind of value, which is changeable.
You can create new values and change values and are not objective, they're subjective.
Everybody can create their own values, the values that they like.
Remember, that's what he likes about polytheism: that everybody creates their own gods, and in effect, that is also like creating their own values.
We can change the values at will.
That's a new idea.
That's a very radical idea.
And at the same time, we can change what it is to be a human being at will.
That's also on 266.
We want to become those we are, human beings who are new, unique, incomparable, who give themselves laws, who create themselves.
So the two things, or maybe three things, if you want to put it, I don't know how many, how to count them, that Michel Poitard lacks is he doesn't open new horizons and new worlds.
He doesn't change values and change even what it is to be a value.
And he doesn't create new human beings, change what it is, our understanding of what it is to be a human being.
Those are big deal things.
Only the free spirit does that.
And maybe only the overman does that.
I don't know myself how the how to distinguish them, but that's my guess that that's how you distinguish them.
That the overman finally is the one who posits new values and new understandings of what it is to be a human being.
That's the most radical kind of life you can have, presumably the most fulfilling.
And I want to say one more thing about that, and I wouldn't want to say that that was just plain cheerful.
Cheerful seems to me to go with this minimal kind of free spirit.
I mean, there's no doubt Michel Poicard is cheerful, and we keep hearing about cheerful, but this isn't, this book isn't called a cheerful wisdom.
It's called The Joyful Wisdom.
I'm sure, I haven't really had time to look it up.
I thought I had the German when I looked.
It's gone.
Anyway, I think the joyfulness goes with being this top kind of free spirit, when you're opening new worlds.
And that's when wonder comes in.
I don't think there's much wonder, or any maybe, in Michel Poicard.
The nearest he comes to wonder is saying, look at the Place de la Concorde at night, isn't it beautiful?
And so he's cheerful and he likes, appreciates lots of things in the world, beautiful things, opposed to her who thinks the only beautiful thing is herself in the mirror and looking like Renoir and so forth.
He's open to all sorts of beautiful things, but I don't think he's joyful.
And I don't think that he lives in a wonder world where things are so amazing because they're new, really new.
Okay, that's all I have to say about the movie.
I don't really want to go back to discuss it.
I just wanted to sort of set the record straight about it from what I said for the last, I don't know, 30 years.
I think I've been wrong.
Who's the one who pushed me on this?
Somebody ought to get credit for making a fuss about him not really being seeming like a free spirit.
Was it you, Beatrice?
Sort of.
Oh, well, you go down in history for having fixed it.
Okay, now, here we go.
Next.
So now we're going to go through for the rest of the time.
I want to sort of carry on a debate between Kierkegaard, Dostoevsky, and Nietzsche, sort of asking, in effect, well, who's right?
Who should we believe?
Whose way of acting should we strive for?
So forth.
And I've just got a whole lot of comments to make, really, and how they relate to each other.
So let's, and there's no sort of, I'm afraid there's no sort of special order in this.
There's not like an outline.
They could be in any order.
But here it comes.
So, one, Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky both value unconditional commitments.
They both remember want an experience of eternity in time.
Whereas what does Nietzsche think?
He thinks that that's weak, that if you're strong, you will get over all such.
And I had in my notes that we should get over all sorts of commitments.
But that's too much like ethics.
There's nothing in the universe that tells us what we should do.
That's part of the realization of nihilism.
The universe is just a kind of chaos.
But then, what is he, what's his argument if it isn't the what we should do?
Well, it's that you, if you're strong and you will outgrow and get over your commitments and your convictions, and you'll keep getting over them as you get stronger and healthier.
If you insist on holding on to your commitments, that shows that you're weak and sick.
Nobody says you shouldn't be weak and sick, but it just built in.
Nobody wants to be weak and sick if they can be strong and healthy.
That's the ethics get smuggled into the story about we are that that's how life works.
Remember on 100, I'll just read that he says, What is life?
It's continually shedding something that wants to die.
Life is being cruel and inexorable against everything that is growing old and weak, and not only about us, meaning everything in the culture and everybody who is old and weak.
You should just be tough on them.
It's for their own good they should be stamped out.
Or as he says on page 127 of the twilight of the idols, what is good?
All that heightens the feeling of power, will to power, power itself in man.
What is bad?
What proceeds from weakness?
What is happiness?
The feeling that power increases, that resistance is overcome.
Somebody should really look up joy, happiness, and cheerfulness.
Who knows about it?
No, but my German can tell me.
Help me.
I want to know the difference of the German words.
For Iliche Wissenbau, that's the joy.
Hydra is probably cheerful.
I don't know what the feeling of, where is it, happiness is.
But it's interesting.
You have aha.
Well, I bet those are the words behind this.
And you just have to have a feeling for these words.
I mean, joyful is the most extreme, cheerful is the least, and happiness is somewhere in between, I think.
And I bet if you followed it through, you'd discover interesting things about which of these words he uses at which points.
You're looking worried.
More German consultants, yes.
He just says at the bottom of 127: what is happiness?
The feeling that power increases, that a resistance is overcome.
But without the German, we don't know.
I mean, Kaufman's a very careful translator.
I suspect if he uses three different words, there are three different words.
And we've got a sort of feel for them in English.
I just don't want to make a fool of myself and make a fuss about a distinction and then discover that it's the same word.
So I want to check it.
Okay, let me go on here.
So, and remember, even life has to be constantly overcome.
That's what life is.
Even stability and survival are already decay.
Nietzsche wrote against Darwin, who thought that what goes on in life is survival of the fittest.
He said, no, that was wrong.
The really fit ones don't just survive.
They outgrow.
And that's his view.
Now, and then back to the Christians.
Well, if they make such a fuss about eternity and time, Kierkegaard says, that must be because they are thick and life-denying and not strong enough to outgrow.
And they want to stabilize what they got.
And that, and he's clear that any sort of unconditional commitment or conviction shows weakness.
He talks about that in Twilight on 184.
He says, oh yeah, the need for belief, some unconditional yes and no, if I may excuse the expression, is a requirement of weakness.
The man of faith is a dependent man and so forth.
He is not strong enough to posit his own ends.
Okay, so when you find something as firm as the vault of heaven, remember that's what Alyasha experiences when he falls on the ground having that religious experience.
If you're so happy that you found something as unchanging as the vault of heaven, what does that show?
Not that you're in touch with a super mystical experience, but that you're just not strong enough yet to go on your own.
On page 287, he says, believers and their need to believe, how much one needs, how much one needs a faith in order to flourish, how much that is firm, that's as firm as the vault of heaven, how much that is firm, and that one does not wish to be shaken because one clings to it, that is the measure of the degree of one's strength, or to put it more clearly, one's weakness.
That's a complicated sentence, but it says, the more you need something firm that you can cling to in your life, right in an eternal memory whose meaning is safe from all change, that shows how weak you are.
Convictions are important, he says, and they're necessary, because nobody starts out strong.
You have to grow and get strong.
But you shouldn't hang on to them.
You should outgrow convictions.
You should outgrow them.
Otherwise, they become prisons and they stop your growth.
He says that on 184, too, that convictions are prisons, which is way, way different than Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky.
And now, I'm repeating all this because it's going to turn out to be important in what I want to say at the end.
It's all sort of the same point over and over from different angles.
When you're strong enough, what happens?
Well, you shed your old skin, or like a living thing, or you don't need anymore the beliefs and the experiences that you did before, so you leave them behind.
That's what he's talking about on 245.
This is an interesting one, and I love the way he writes it.
This is about how your beliefs grow out of your weakness, not out of your rationality.
And when you get strong enough to shed these beliefs, you shed them not because you've seen through them and seen that they're irrational.
They always are and always were.
It's because you're strong enough to live without them.
Here it is: a meat quote, the bottom 245.
Now, something that you formerly loved as a truth strikes you as an error.
You shed it and fancy that this represents a victory for your reason.
But perhaps this error was as necessary for you then, when you were still a different person.
You're always a different person.
As necessary for you then, as are all your present truths, being a skin, as it were, that covers a great deal that you're not prepared to see.
What killed that opinion for you was your new life and not your reason.
You no longer need it.
And now it collapses, and unreason crawls out of it into the light like a worm.
That amazing, he's a great German writer, the greatest German stylist, I guess, maybe there is.
So when we, and then the next sentence, when we criticize something, this is no arbitrary, impersonal event.
It is at least very often evidence of vital energies in us that are growing and shedding a skin.
That is the, I'll come back at the end to that.
What follows from this, of course, is that the reasons for what you believe, or reasons for what you don't believe, are really irrelevant.
They're simply, or to put it another way, they're relative to your weaknesses, valuable, they're symptoms, not reasons.
Once you're strong enough to see through it, any error you have, which you need, you can get over and then you can shed.
So what would Nietzsche say to Dostoevsky, just to put it in a funny, unfortunate way, because I am a big Dostoevsky fan, but I'm trying to think like Nietzsche next.
Well, he would say to Dostoevsky, why in the world would you hold on to a childhood memory all your life?
That just shows that you're weak.
If you don't outgrow and reinterpret your childhood memories, you just haven't grown up.
What's so important about a pound of nuts or being held up to an icon?
I mean, sure, it shows that you were loved at that point, and that's something sort of important, but now you're a different person, and the fact that you were loved way back then by your mother or befriended by a German doctor is no longer what you need and what you should be thinking about.
And if you should be open, for instance, to act in the appropriate way, that is the most powerful way in the current situation.
And that may mean holding on to these memories and letting them tell you what you can't laugh at, which is what Dostoevsky thinks.
And it may mean laughing at these memories and becoming ironic about your childhood and going on to some different understanding of who you are that increases your power.
The only point, the only real issue in the end is how strong, how healthy, how much you can overcome, how much power you've got, and childhood memories are, you know, probably not going to do it, but they're going to drag you down.
That's what he thinks.
Now, the question is then, we're going to go on now.
Well, now I don't want to just keep going on.
That's the first big confrontation over eternity and in time and whether it's a good thing or a bad thing.
One way to put it is: remember, I've said this before, but I should say it again.
Whereas Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard think that the truth of Christianity can be captured in this existentialized way where you don't need a supreme being anymore, but you have some experiences which capture what the importance to you as a human being is of what once upon a time was put in this magical, metaphysical way.
So there isn't any such thing as eternity outside time, and neither Kierkegaard nor Dostoevsky nor Nietzsche believe there is.
And then, but Nietzsche, sorry, Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard believe there is eternity in time.
That's this defining commitment story or this vault of heaven connected story.
And they have, so they're saving what they think is the truth of Christianity by existentializing it.
They're the two most important Christian thinkers of the 20th century for us now because they managed to preserve it even though, even in the face of our not believing in this magical metaphysical, some of us not believing in that anyway, fewer and fewer people believing in that.
But then Nietzsche's, remember, one step radical.
He wants to get rid of even of the existentialized, supposedly deep understanding that the original Christian community had before it got even metaphysicalized by the Greeks or was just magical because it would magic because it was primitive culture.
And he wants to Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky want to capture the deep truth that Christians had at the beginning and bring it back so they can change the world with it.
And Nietzsche says, no, it was sick from the start.
Even what you think is the saving thing was still sick.
Only, remember, oh, the only good Christian died on the cross.
Jesus was a free spirit, that nobody, that Paul killed it, nobody after that was.
Oh, yeah, that's very interesting.
How come you're asking it in that language?
That's my language.
Where did you get that talk?
Did I say that ever?
I've said that in lecture.
Oh, really?
Okay, that's a very important idea.
I got it from sort of the margins of Heidegger, where I get everything.
But Heidegger doesn't make such a fuss about it.
But he does talk about, Heidegger does, taking up something from your past and bringing it into the present and giving it a new meaning so that it can make the present meaningful to you.
And that's what Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard are doing.
They're taking up these Christian practices and making a new and bringing them from the margin to the center of our understanding of Christianity, and they want to put it in the center of our culture.
And they want to put Christianity back in the center of our culture, but with this new understanding of it.
And Nietzsche talks in another place about the leap from the wings to center stage.
I mean, that's the same idea.
That is, something that was already there, understood, sort of, gets taken from the margins where it's sometimes understood and sometimes practiced and made the central thing.
And that's what they're trying to do.
Did that help?
Ah, well, okay.
Because if you do it, you change the, when you take something, good way to put it, very good.
Yes, what happens when you take something from the margin and to and make it central, and central and make it margin?
I may have told you this already, I'm sure I have, but I'll remind you.
The most important switch that opened a new world, gave everybody new values, is Jesus' switch from what from the law to the heart, or the or a purity issue.
Remember the story that Jesus says that he who commits adulter who he who lusts after a woman in his heart commits adultery.
That's a minor that's one of the ten commandments that you shouldn't commit adultery.
But all the rest of the commandments are against things that you do, not how you feel.
It's nobody's business whether you lust after your neighbor.
It isn't hurting anybody.
And moreover, it's terrible because you can't control it.
And the more you try not to lust after your neighbor, the more you will.
And this is and now what happens when you make a little change like that?
A marginal concern, one out of ten, and make it the only important concern, not adultery, but your desires.
Instead of what you do, you're defined by what you desire.
And when you make that switch, everything changes.
You can't save yourself by your own willpower the way you can for the Jews because the Hebrews understood that what you did, it was only what you did against the law that was wrong.
And you can stop doing whatever you're doing against the law that's against the law.
But if you make people's desires what makes them good and saved and they or damn, then you have to have a Savior who comes in and helps you.
There's no and and Jesus then beget gets to be the Savior.
So you just so there you are, making a marginal change, but it's changed the whole values.
It's changed the system, it's changed the world, and lo and behold, you've got the the Christian world instead of the pagan world or the Hebrew world.
Okay, that's good.
Make me review and explain that.
Okay, now I'm taking up the next point, and that is two opposed views about another issue and whom should we believe.
And that is there's some two opposed views, or three.
No, why do I say two?
Well, maybe.
Let's see what happens.
Anyway, I'm going to say what they have in common, Nietzsche and Dostoevsky, and where they differ.
Just like I tried to say already, what they do, how they have what they have in common with Christianity, Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard, and how that differs from Nietzsche.
Now we're going to look at what Dostoevsky and Nietzsche share.
So, in fact, they share it with Kierkegaard, too.
I don't know why I don't have him on here.
So, what is it?
Well, they have the anti-Platonism in Christianity and in the whole view we have how truth is important and universal ethics is important.
The things I wrote on the board the very first day of the course, that ethics is universal and it's rational, and everybody should have the same ethical principles, that truth is true for everybody at all times, and there is truth, and we can work at finding it out.
That's all Platonism, and they all d deny that.
And they deny the latest version of it.
And that's important.
They deny, and this is a new thing I haven't talked about, they're against the Enlightenment.
The Enlightenment is us.
The Enlightenment is what starts with Descartes in 1650, and then it gets where we become the center of the world instead of God, but it doesn't get fully understood until Kant, when Kant puts us and our rationality in charge and says that, I mentioned this, human beings in the West anyway, in Europe anyway, become mature when they understand that they're the ones who are in charge of their lives and they have a rationality, they can understand what's right and what's true and live by it.
But that has all sorts of implications.
Then you'll recognize that it's us when I read you what Nietzsche is against.
And Dostoevsky would say so too.
Remember, Dostoevsky thinks bad things are going on in France and Germany.
In general, you don't see it in the brothers, but he thinks Germans are stupid and dense.
He thinks the French are dangerous because they are believers in this sort of last stage of Greek thinking.
So here's Nietzsche.
Among Europeans today, there is no lack of those who are entitled to call themselves homeless.
Okay, oh no, that's him.
Those are the people who live in the gay science.
But let me skip to the where.
Okay, yes.
Here's now.
Here are these new people, the free spirits.
We can serve nothing.
Neither do we want to return to any past periods.
We are not by any means liberal.
We do not work for progress.
If you just, you could hear this, you could just check off all the things that we believe in.
We do not need to plug up our ears against the sirens who in the marketplace sing of the future.
Their song of equal rights.
This is what we don't believe in.
A free society.
That there will be no more masters and no servants.
All that has no allure for us.
We simply do not consider it desirable that a realm of justice and concord should be established on earth.
Well, that is pretty amazing.
I mean, that's, so Nietzsche is always very, very far out and very clear.
I mean, that really questions all of the things we believe in and care about and vote for people who promise to help us achieve it.
And so, and Kierkegaard, they're all sort of, if they have any views at all, anti-democratic, because they think that's just for the masses, then they're all worrying about the individual and their own free understanding and thing.
Yes, they want.
They promote this progress by which the West has gradually understood more and more how to make individuals free, how to bring about justice, that there should be progress, and it all happens by reason, which is the way Kant and Descartes said it would.
And that's what Nietzsche claims is coming to an end, that the free spirits don't believe in that anymore.
They are the wave of the future.
And the wave of the future is not progress.
It's cataclysmic disaster to begin with.
And after that, hard to understand what it is.
A lot of overmen are free spirits, seemingly sort of wandering around on their own.
They don't have much of a positive story, what should replace the values that they but they don't but they don't think that there's any hope to save these values.
I mean, God is dead, and God is what supported all this belief in progress and whatever else I had was on that list.
So, and therefore, all that is going to collapse, they think.
And they think it's good news.
So, there's Yvonne's geological cataclysm, which where the devil talks about how all of the current culture is going to destroy itself and that we will have this new man who is boy, this is, I just realized how funny this is.
Well, I think this is what you'd expect.
I mean, in a certain way, remember, or you don't remember, but you've got to think that Dostoevsky is against the new man that's going to come after the cataclysm.
Because the new man that's going to come after the cataclysm is going to be, and this is where it gets hard to follow because it's, but it's right, that the new man, from a Dostoevsky point of view, is still part of the Enlightenment.
That's the tricky part.
I mean, Dostoevsky would say, but Nietzsche thinks that we should be free and we should be self-egoist and that we should give our own life meaning and so forth.
And that we shouldn't be have any higher authority in our life.
That's weakness.
I can't just switch to that passage, but that's tied up with we should become gods ourselves.
And I could lose you if I'm not careful because I am not saying this as clearly as I should.
So Nietzsche is against the Enlightenment.
And this is what I just read you.
I'm going to go back and read the beginning.
There's a kind of interesting sort of game being played at this point, which is who's more enlightenment than whom?
And is that a good thing or a bad thing?
That is, Nietzsche is against progress and justice and equal rights and each person being a free society.
Nietzsche is against it in the name of the fact that there'll be new gods, each one of them sort of ruthlessly and egotistically pursuing his own outgrowing and so forth.
And now is what I have to think clearly.
So Nietzsche thinks that he is going to go against the Enlightenment.
And Dostoevsky is also against.
And Dostoevsky is against the Enlightenment because it's lost touch with the receptive religious experience of finding a higher authority in your life than your own will.
And he, therefore, that's what he's defending when you, when Alyasha experiences the love and connectedness of everything.
That's not human freedom.
That's not progress in the sense that in the Enlightenment, let me remember, remember the difference between Christian socialism and the Grand Inquisitor.
Dostoevsky thinks the only kind of politics you can have is that you have to be Christian first and receive the love connection.
Whereas Dostoevsky is against the Enlightenment, our way of thinking, our Western European way of thinking, in the name of his Christian way of thinking.
The Enlightenment is a secular way that people are going to supposedly all become free and get progress and get rid of all the evil in the world.
Kierkegaard thinks that's impossible.
You can't, the kind of overman, the kind of free spirit that you're going to get is going to be just dangerous and destructive because they won't be in touch with the love of everything.
So now comes the tricky part to think about it.
So from Kierkegaard's point of view, the Enlightenment's a bad thing.
And from Nietzsche's point of view, the Enlightenment's a bad thing, because the Enlightenment doesn't give enough emphasis to individual free spirits doing their own individual thing.
It wants justice, it wants fair progress, and so forth.
So they both think the Enlightenment is not a good thing, is a bad thing.
But Dostoevsky thinks it's a bad thing for one for this reason that it's not, it's given up the Christian sense of a world outside of our own control and our own power, this love world that we have to get in touch with.
And therefore, now comes the tricky move.
Kierkegaard thinks that Nietzsche's way of opposing the Enlightenment, the Greek, the philosophical story, is just more extreme enlightenment.
Because, after all, Nietzsche thinks that you don't need Christianity.
He doesn't think you need Christianity and he doesn't think you need liberal democracy either.
Now, Dostoevsky agrees, I think I'm getting clearer, that with Nietzsche, liberal democracy is not going to do us any good.
They both share that.
But then Nietzsche thinks we'll just go beyond it.
Everybody will become like gods.
That's sort of the ultimate beyond the Enlightenment Enlightenment.
They're all totally self-willful, rational, well, not rational, willful, powerful individuals, but it's beyond the Enlightenment.
It's after the collapse of the Enlightenment, but it's still the view that each human being doesn't need God anymore.
They become God.
Whereas Dostoevsky wants to say something very different.
And now let me try to say it.
There's something, human beings are hopeless.
They are, remember I said the Hobbes' famous phrase, nasty, brutish, and short.
They are they are that is life is natural, nasty, brutish, and short.
And the uh, but mainly people are selfish.
That's what the mysterious visitor understood.
And the you can't build a world on people.
And Nietzsche sort of thinks most people are hopeless and weak and herd-like and so forth, but there'll be some people who will be strong.
It's sort of the Grand Inquisitor-like.
But Dostoevsky wants to say, no, Nietzsche trying to make human beings into gods is just the last stage of a complete misunderstanding.
Human beings can't be gods.
They're on their own only by being saved, only by being in touch with the love that Alyasha experiences, that connects all the worlds, and that will be, if Dostoevsky gets it right, spread all over the world when the star rises in the east.
Now, so the bottom line is they're both against our kind of values in the Enlightenment.
But Dostoevsky thinks Nietzsche is just an extreme form of the kind of values that he's against, that Kierkegaard, that Dostoevsky is against.
And so Dostoevsky wants to be against Nietzsche as the last stage of the Enlightenment.
Whereas Nietzsche thinks that he's against the Enlightenment because it's not gone far enough.
And that Dostoevsky is the old wrong way that hasn't even understood yet that human beings had to be healthy, have to be independent, and be something.
I shouldn't have ever launched into this.
I'm feeling unhappy.
Go ahead.
Making this creation of information.
And that's nature's way of participating.
So it wouldn't be in a full individual.
There wouldn't be creating.
You wouldn't be following the nature of the creative force by.
That's good.
A stable individual is it would also be like finding your position in nature, because there is no position.
Okay.
What you're saying is extremely interesting and complicates something because it's really, this is going to drive you completely crazy.
Because what's happening is where Nietzsche is saying, you should have no authority.
You should give the law to yourself and create yourself, create the kind of human being that you want to be, and so forth.
But we do that all by being responsive to the way life works, to the creative overcoming in nature.
And that means somehow that you have to be, and this is the craziest weird thing to think, receptive to a power that makes it makes that you express in your life by allowing no higher authority over you and the claim that all values are in your power.
So it's a very, in that funny way, paradoxical position.
You're bringing out the other side.
I want to leave it.
For those who understood it, good.
If you understand it, come and tell me.
I mean, I got, it's, it's too complicated to try to do anyway.
Let me see where I am.
I'll just one way, I sum it up here.
Dostoevsky would say that Nietzsche is part of an individualist, willful, enlightenment tradition.
And Dostoevsky would say, you have to have the strength and courage to serve something higher than yourself.
And Nietzsche says, it's weakness.
That's the final issue between them.
Now let's see if I can skim to where I, because I've done this already in a sort of a way.
And I want to make sure I get to the end.
So I'm summing up something here.
So both Nietzsche and Dostoevsky think that they're the wave of the future.
Dostoevsky expects a new secularized Christianity, that is a new demagicalized, existentialized, Christianized world, and that's the star in the East.
Nietzsche expects that now that God is dead and all things are possible, we all become gods ourselves.
And so, okay, now, who should we believe, having gotten through all that?
Well, if you try to figure out which one to believe, you just don't know what to think.
I mean, should you serve a higher power?
Is there a higher power?
Even if there were, would it be weakness and sickness, or would it be the highest strength to get in sync with it, and so forth?
Well, at that point, Nietzsche makes an incredibly interesting move.
He changes the whole rules of the debate.
He says, don't try to figure this out like a philosophical issue and ask yourself which is the best argument, who has the best description of the phenomena?
Who should you believe.
It's not a question of belief at all.
It's a question of taste.
That is such a strange move.
It's an aesthetic question.
Here is what he says on page 106.
The change in general taste is more powerful than that of opinions.
Opinions, along with all proofs, refutation, and the whole intellectual masquerade are merely symptoms of the change in taste, and most certainly not what they are still often supposed to be, its causes.
So what's happening is it's not what's changing us from Christianity, either, even Christianity of the Dostoevsky or Kierkegaardian thought, from all forms of society up to now.
What makes us able to understand that God is dead is that there's a change in taste.
People just don't believe in the religious experiences anymore.
They don't admire them anymore.
So Nietzsche says it's not a question of truth.
Namely, it's given that the way our culture has developed, we can't continue believing in love, connectedness, morality, and meaning, and we've become strong enough to do without it.
And that's the issue, not whether it was right or wrong.
It was right for us when we were weak, and it's wrong for us once we get strong.
This is what he's saying on 287, which is, in general, he says, an article of faith can be refuted a thousand times, but before a man, in front of a man, can be refuted a thousand times.
If he needs it, he would consider it true again and again in accordance with period.
And then he says, well, he says, he's saying again, I don't know if I need to read it, but let's do it because it's got to do with firmness again.
He's saying that all this talk about demanding firm things is just the result of weakness at the top of 288.
The demand that one wants by all means that something should be firm.
This too is still the demand for a support, a prop, in short, an instinct of weakness, which to be sure does not create religions, but it conserves them.
So all of this is to say that as free spirits, we are outgrowing religion, not because we discover it was wrong and told us something about the world.
It's because we don't need it anymore.
At the top of 186, he says, what's now decisive against Christianity is our taste, no longer our reason.
That's an amazing thing to say.
Or 340.
You feel the really weird thing that Nietzsche is changing the subject.
At the middle of 340, he says, we have outgrown Christianity and are adverse to it because we have grown out of it and so forth.
Now, he also says, I mean, now that's how it's in here.
What does this mean?
This means that which one of these views is right isn't the right question.
It's the question of which one of these views is going to be the one that feels right, that we find attractive, that fits our taste in how to live and look at things.
And Nietzsche says that by the year, I think it's 1910 or something, I forget where he gets that number, that people will begin to appreciate this, and that will be as the three spirits begin to find the receptive recognition of a higher authority, which has been going on for 2,000 years, no longer acceptable.
Now, what follows from this?
Well, who's right?
The answer becomes: well, who's what is your sensibility about it?
How do you feel about it?
So I'm going to take a sort of a poll now, because I do this every year, and you can see that I'm checking whether Nietzsche is right, whether we are outgrowing it or not.
Because that's the only interesting question Nietzsche says.
I mean, we're not going to settle any kind of argument.
Is there a web of love and connectedness?
Are we in despair, all of us, unless we have an unconditional commitment?
Are we all weak unless we can leave all that behind?
You can't settle that.
It's important to understand that those are the options.
It's important to understand that those are possible ways of life.
But when you finally come to choose which way of life, I'm afraid philosophy can't help you.
It's going to be a change of taste.
It's going to be the way people feel, aesthetics changes.
Okay, so what I want to do is take this poll, and I'll tell you, so and we just have time to do, there is a whole bunch, I'm going to give you a bunch of options, which so how many I'm going to ask you how many sensibilities prefer or admire or uh you know uh want to live by the following.
So there's one, the obvious one.
The obvious one a good old-fashioned Christian, Judeo-Christian religion.
Or better yet, I'm not giving you that option so much, to put it that way, but as it is in the Course, sort of Platonized Judeo-Christian religion.
The way Christianity and Judaism has come down to us with the idea of a supreme being, with the idea that we should be in the proper relation to that being and that there's a truth about that being.
In other words, um in a way, who who still holds the the orthodox kind of beliefs that that Nietzsche wants us not to hold?
Let me just count you.
Tell me because it's important to so here's I'll tell you also the votes and over the last few years.
On on this on that, there were ten.
Of course, you have to see how many people are in the whole class.
You have to see that little by little.
Sixteen.
That's where we were for this.
How many here are believers in the in the Orthodox Judeo-Christian sense?
There must be quite a few still.
Okay, let's see.
There don't be um it may be right.
I mean, i if there's no right.
If enough of you raise your hand, you will be right.
One, two, three, four, five, six, you, seven, eight, you'll be telling me, it looks like eight.
You'll you'll be if you maybe I mean, you are you asking something or voting?
Okay, nine.
Then, uh so so if it if everyone had raised their hands, then it would have turned out that Nietzsche is wrong, that our sensibility is not changing, that we have our taste has not turned against it.
But then there's there's a whole other possibility.
And that got, well, then there's two sub-parts.
There's the unconditional commitment, people, and that's Kierkegaard.
And there's the Dostoevsky connectedness.
I can't tell you ahead of time how it was.
So how many believe in the unconditional commitment story?
Not so many.
One, one, two, put your hands up high.
Three, four, five, six, seven, eight, eight.
I'm voting.
I can't count myself, I think, because that wouldn't be fair.
So there's seven, nine, and nine.
That's holding a constant.
At this point, when I was doing this, my TA, a woman, said, so you all believe in this unconditional commitment.
Wait, no, forget it.
I'm telling you that too soon.
So there's the unconditional commitment to all human, to all other beings.
How many of the Dostoevsky?
Ah, wow.
Dostoevsky is, I need help.
Beatrice, help me count this.
This is fascinating.
What do you get?
That's pretty, I got 42.
We'll call it 43.
That's pretty.
So this has gone, but this has always been a popular one.
Things are sort of staying the same.
Okay, then there's the Enlightenment, after all.
There's the values of individualism, autonomy, lucidity, social justice, progress.
And how many believe in that?
There ought to be quite a few.
That's what we're supposed to believe in.
Yeah.
No, you only can vote once.
Although I see why you could, no, if you really push these two views, these views, I think each of them sort of claims to be such that it would let you.
So, how many believe in the Enlightenment project that we're all in?
In progress toward justice and fairness and getting over?
No, no, Dostoevsky wouldn't like that.
Dostoevsky did.
I mean, I mean progress, good point.
I don't mean progress by way of love, which is the Dostoevsky story.
Maybe, but I mean the Enlightenment version.
If you get it without love, in fact, you get it by not having it.
You don't need a Christian culture.
That's the one.
Okay, so the secular Enlightenment people.
Now let's see their hands again.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
Okay.
Oh, nine.
Okay, so we have the Enlightenment people, and they had before four.
Now they've got eight.
And now, of course, where Nietzsche thinks, Nietzsche will only say that he's one if you now, if we get, if constant overcoming is what people's taste has gone towards.
So how many Nietzscheans?
How many has Nietzsche convinced?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen.
Did I see you?
I don't know.
Let's say sixteen.
Okay, so, and that, what they had four game, Nietzsche may be losing.
It's been, Nietzsche's been steadily gaining until this year.
And that's probably true, I think.
Maybe this is not what people sensitivity is for anymore.
When I did do the Nietzsche one, which was about danger, struggle, wonder, winning, outgrowing, and healthiness, and so forth, and it got a big boat last time, 60.
This is what I was going to tell you.
A woman, one of my TAs, said, and would you like, and how many would like their lover to be a Nietzsche?
And that reversed the boat completely.
But we're not going to ask that question.
So now I have exactly five more minutes before I have to go and let you fill out the evaluation forms.
I want to say something about what existential philosophy is, which you all want me to do.
But I must admit, as I said already, that's not what's important.
What's important is each of these thinkers' own way of setting out their whole experience and their whole world.
But there are some things in common.
And you start, I think, when you ask a question like that, looking at paradigm cases.
What are the most striking versions of existentialist philosophy?
Well, I think they're Kierkegaard, Dostoevsky, and Nietzsche.
That's why we did them.
They're the paradigms.
But I did leave out two crucial ones: Start and Heidegger.
And, of course, Pascal is in there as the first existential thinker.
But now the question is: what do they all have in common?
That's what, in the old Greek way of thinking, is what the essence of something is.
So, what is the essence of existentialism?
Well, the most important, I think, is that there's no human nature.
Pascal already says, custom is our nature.
Remember, Nietzsche says that's what makes us different from the animals.
We have no fixed horizons.
We are the undetermined now.
And so that's the first thing.
There are cultures in which there are saints and heroes and saints and sinners and cultures in which there are heroes and villains and probably cultures in which there are devils and enlightened beings and so forth and so forth.
And human beings create what it is to be a human being.
Okay, second point.
And since there's no human nature, we can change it.
And history is not fixed forever any more than human nature is fixed forever.
History isn't outside time.
History is the story of these changes, in the West anyway, of these changing understandings of human nature.
That's the story I've been telling.
Okay, number three, the individual is higher than the universal.
That sounds familiar if you remember for the first day.
That's the Hebraic, Socrates, anti-Plato, anti-Greek.
It's Kierkegaard's big deal that the ethical is suspended.
The ethical, which is the universal, is suspended when you have an individual commitment.
They all, in some way or another, think that universal ethics is not what is somehow a a not maybe not, most of them think that universal ethics is just going to get in the way of leading a good life.
That's pretty extreme.
Kierkegaard thinks that, of course, that the ethical is important.
It makes your life intelligible to you and other people, and that's a good thing.
But in the end, the really, really good thing is somebody like Huck Finn, who can save Jim, even though he thinks that it's the worst thing he could do to not turn in a slave, he won't turn him in.
So the individual understanding of what they have to do is higher than the universal principles of what everybody has to do.
That's three, four.
Remember the one on reality.
For the Plato, the detached theoretical point of view is how to understand how things really are.
But to the existentialists, for all of them, it's from the involved point of view that you find out the truth in Kierkegaard language, and you find it out for yourself or for your time.
There is no truth for everybody everywhere.
In Kierkegaard language, truth is subjectivity.
That means that in Nietzsche language, it's perspectivism.
I haven't talked about that in Nietzsche.
But everybody can have their own truth because they have their own perspective on the world based on their own experience.
And that's what we've been doing.
We've been seeing these various existentialists, each of them with their own perspective based on their own experience, telling you their own truth, which they all understand is not a truth for everybody, but only a truth for those who they can convince to see things their way.
Okay, one last one.
They are all against the belief in a supreme being in what I call, once writing it on the board, onto theology.
Onto theology is the view that there is one supreme creator, God, who is the truth and explains it all and grounds universal atheism.
They all think that that kind of God is no longer possible, believable, or necessary.
That they all, in some sense, think we've outgrown that.
They share that with Nietzsche.
And they all think that that opens up the possibility of other ways of understanding and relating to the divine and the sacred.
They don't turn out to be just naturalists believing that science tells us all there is to know about human beings.
They've all got a place for something very special, namely the sacred.
Whether it's the unconditional command, the calling, in Kierkegaard, a calling without a caller, but you know what you have to do.
Or it's the connectedness of all these beings, even though there's no supreme being.
Everything is connected to everything else.
Or it's something in Nietzsche, it's harder to say than he was saying.
I mean, it's not the normal sort of sacred.
There isn't anything about it that's sacred in that sense.
But in Nietzsche, there's still some, how will I put it?
That, well, I guess you have to say, since there's no onto theological God in Nietzsche, what you got is not just the sacred, but everybody being a God themselves.
But they all share.
There's no one single supreme being in theme.
Now, the one other thing I just want to make one quick plug for Philosophy VI.
I'm going to get Philosophy VI in the fall.
If you want to know how we got here, it goes from the Odyssey to Moby Dick.
And Moby Dick is the same year Melville, the same year as Kierkegaard.
So it's a prequel, in a way, to this one.
And once you get it, once you see how the culture gradually lost the sense of the sacred from Homer's gods to Moby Dick, and then sort of got it back again, that's what I want to talk about next time.
Okay, now I'm going to run and you're going to.