I was talking about Alyasha and Yvonne, and then I jumped ahead to Dimitri just because I wanted to convince you that there really was a Kierkegaardian story about the self.
Remember, and then here's another sort of thing I wanted to say.
The TAs tell me that I didn't make clear enough why we suddenly jumped from fear and trembling to that excerpt from sickness unto death about the self.
And I think that's right.
I didn't make clear enough.
It's so obvious to me that I realized it.
I tried putting myself in your shoes, and I realized it wasn't obvious at all.
But it has two functions, of which you only would know one at the beginning.
It is amazing, abstract summary of the whole Kierkegaard picture, of which fear and trembling is a piece.
And then you see the two sets of factors.
You hear a lot about the finite and the infinite, the temporal and eternal, but there you see how they are related to each other and how you have to take a stand on them.
And then, of course, it's very important that you see that you have to take a stand, and you can't relate yourself to yourself without relating in a way that's not despairing, without relating to someone or something outside the self.
All that was supposed to be a kind of summary of the basic picture that Kierkegaard has of what human beings are and what human beings need and what they will get despair about if they don't get.
So I should have said it.
I'm saying it now.
And secondly, you should have, or if you haven't got it, get it from Beatrice, the self, the heart, in the brothers Karamatsov, because I want to refer to that a lot.
Because it's an amazing, I don't know if it's a coincidence or what it is, but it's an amazing fact that the picture of the self that you get in the Kierkegaard passage is the same structure of the way the self relates to itself and to the world and others that you get in the brothers.
So the other reason that we made this sort of crash change to the self passage is because it's a transition to the brothers.
And we're in the middle of that transition now.
We've talked about Yvonne and look at your self-picture.
Keep it in mind every once in a while.
And if you haven't got it with you, then now is the time to get another copy from Beatrice so you can have it in front of you while we talk.
Okay, we've already done the way that Yvonne thinks about the two aspects of the self: that's the base and the noble.
And I I don't know why I put them in the order I put them.
I I think, well, I do know why, because you start at the top on the right with Theodore, and he's this R1 of spiritlessness that we talked about.
And then there ought to be a negative relation of the self to the self and the negative relation it will prioritize one part and reject the other part.
And that's so far we've seen that is Ivan with his notion of what's noble or lofty and what's base.
And those are the two aspects that he wants to not get together, of course, because he's a negative relation.
Those are the aspects one of which he wants to be and the other one he wants to get rid of and deny.
And of course it's a no-brainer question, but I'll ask it anyway.
Between the noble and the base, which does he want to be?
Noble, of course, and he's going to try to get rid of all the part of him that's base.
And he, like everybody else, considers the base part the Taramatsov part, because that's, they think of it as like the old Taramatsov, lecturous and selfish and evil in all sorts of ways with no redeeming features.
Now, so there's something you should write onto your chart that's related to what I just said.
It's clear that the column on the left, which is the base insect sodom and so forth column, is what everybody calls the Terematsov cell.
And you would really want to write it in in pencil.
I mean, not literally, but if you have a pencil, so much the better.
Because I'm not telling you that that's where the Karamatsov is going to stay over there on the left.
But for the whole first part of the book, anyway, Karamatsov is the name for the column on the left, which looks like something bad that you want to get rid of.
And the hint that it may not be something bad you want to get rid of comes with Zosima.
Because in Zosima's on the right there, it's not clear where to put him.
He's not any of these because he's already out of the problem.
He would be sort of relating to himself, relating to another, but he doesn't really get described that way.
But he does have a view of the factors.
And you see, the factors for him are the earthly and the heavenly.
And that's beginning to suggest that if you define the factors in the right way, you might be able to get them together.
And that the people who can't get them together, like old Karamatsov, who doesn't even try, and Ivan, who's trying hard, and as you'll see as the book goes on, failing miserably to get rid of half, and Dimitri, who's despairingly trying to get it all together, the hope is that you could somehow get the factors together if you could only describe them in a way that made them compatible.
This is all the same as Kierkegaard.
You want the factors to support each other.
You want it to be the case that all the factors on the left and the factors on the right, you could say the more one, the more the other.
And you can hardly say the more base, the more noble, or the more insect, the more angel, or at the bottom, the more good or the more bad.
But you've got a hope of saying the more earthly the more heavenly and the more heavenly the more earthly and so you've got to keep an eye on that now let's sort of plug back in I mean that's meant to be a transition that I should have said, but it's probably just as well to say it now and not earlier, because until you have the Kierkegaard self and you read enough, oh, speaking of reading enough, aha, yes, be sure and read up to 279.
That's not further than I said last time, but I didn't get there last time.
But now I know I'm going to get there next time.
That's rebellion.
If you haven't read the chapter on rebellion, don't bother to come on Thursday because you won't understand the thing.
You've got to read the chapter.
You've got to ask yourself whether you agree with Yvonne or not.
That's how it's done.
And so that means you have to read up to 279.
You should be reading much further.
But I'm saying this is the minimum.
If you haven't read more than that, you're heading for trouble.
Okay.
Now, connecting up, we talked about the fact that Alyasha and Yvonne, being both of them the sons of Sophia, who is a saintly, meek, Christian person who, as we'll get to later, has icons and worships them and so forth.
They are both striving for purity, but there are these two different kinds of purity.
The kind of purity that tries to get rid of all with the dark stuff, and the kind of purity that tries to purify the dark stuff.
And that Yvonne is one of them.
His kind of purity is like dry cleaning.
You get rid of the bad elements.
He's really into cleanliness.
I picture him, I haven't really reread it with this in mind, as always natally dressed, impeccable, with a recent haircut and so forth.
That's just, he's always trying to be impeccable.
Any sort of bad thing, he wants to get rid of it.
He wants to be just the noble, lofty side.
That's what he wants.
And he wants to get rid of the lackey side, the base side.
And so he's a negative R2.
He relates himself to himself as trying to get rid of everything he doesn't like about himself.
And so he is, in Kierkegaard jargon, in despair at not willing to be himself.
Or I think the same thing is desperately not willing to be himself, meaning desperately not willing to be the part of himself that he doesn't like.
He wants to be an angel.
Now, remember Pascal says that we're neither angel nor brute, and he who plays the angel plays the brute.
That you could carve over Yvonne's tombstone if he had died in the course of the book, which he doesn't quite.
And he's very dangerous.
And that's all I want to say about him for the time being.
And then there's the plur p the purity of sublimation, taking up and transforming the impurities.
Alyasha is trying to be pure in that way.
He would like to be able to accept all of his impulses.
However, he's not succeeding at the beginning of the book.
In fact, not succeeding really in the course of this book.
It must be something that happens in the next in volume two.
But he makes a lot of progress in the course of the book.
And that, and now, just to remind you of the whole structure of the Course, so Yvonne is a kind of Greek form of purity because he's trying to get there by saying only part of him is essentially him, and part of him is stuff that he's trying to deny and get rid of and say isn't him.
And Alyasha is a kind, and you could say Yvonne is a kind of Plato.
And there's some place in here where Muava mus mus muse musov?
I can't say it right now.
What?
Muazov.
Yeah, Muazov says that Yvonne has an idea.
I mean, in Plato, that's Platonic thought.
There's no doubt that he's, and Plato says you should die to your body, and Yvonne would like to die to the lackey side of him, which is mostly very close to his body, but also all of his stupidities of his.
And Alyasha is trying to be pure like Jesus.
He's like the Judeo-Christian side, or really just the Christian.
They don't think it's a Hebrew problem.
He's trying to be pure like Jesus, and that's the sense in which they are similar, trying to be pure and super different in their approach to how to do it.
Another way to put it, Yvonne is passionately trying to be lofty and dispassionate.
There's a kind of contradiction in what he's doing because you remember he wants to be a spectator of everything.
That's going to turn out to be all very important and clear next time when we read the chapter on rebellion.
He wants with all his might to make him, and passionately he wants to make himself detached, eternal, infinite, and impeccable.
Now, remember a question left over from last time, and something that I find just fascinating and fun about the book, is that they've all got their doubles.
And we've seen already that the spiritlessness one of staying in a kind of complete dither and craziness, diversion, in order not to think about whether you've got an immortal soul or not, and so forth, that old Karamatsov has it, and his double, though I don't even know if they ever speak to each other.
They know each other.
They live in the same little town.
But they don't have to know each other to have the same approach to their selves.
They both have spiritlessness.
That is, they are not facing up to the problem of having a self.
And we talked about that already.
So, and now the question is: who's the existential double of Yvonne?
That would be somebody trying to be perfect and lofty and better than everybody else.
And it would have to be a woman, and it would have to be somebody involved with Yvonne.
Now you could be able to get anybody.
How about a woman involved with Yvonne and Dimitri?
Yeah, Katerina.
I know this.
She's the double.
And she's trying to be lofty and better than everybody else.
I'll read you just a few quotes because she is somebody I just haven't got the time to talk about this very few minutes.
I'm just doing it now.
She's a possible paper topic because there's lots to be said about Katerina and her way of having a self and whether it works or not.
And it's fine if you do it, but I couldn't do it because there just isn't time.
I can't even find why I can't.
I don't understand this.
Very strange.
I put down one wrong page number, two wrong page numbers.
Let's hope when I get to page 58, I've got the right page number or we won't have any.
Ah, yeah, 58 will do, about a quarter of the way down.
Somebody is saying, doesn't matter who, about Katerina, how she wants to be perceived.
Oh, she is such a fine, wonderful creature.
If only for her suffering.
Think what she's gone through, and so forth and so forth.
She wants to be this very, very special person.
And I do wish I had the other one.
There's a place where Dimitri blurts out, and you can find it when you're reading.
It isn't important stuff, and I'm not going to spend time looking for it.
Dimitri sort of says all she really wants to do is she loves herself and she wants to be perfect.
And then he realizes that he shouldn't have sort of blurted that out.
But that's true about her.
That's the Yvonne side of her.
That's why Yvonne loves her.
These people love each other because they've got the same existential perspective.
I want to mark those pages.
Now, we're ready to go back to Dimitri in order.
Remember, I jumped ahead.
I'm not going to repeat what happens, but we talked last time about how on page 73, when he comes on, he comes on as a living, walking contradiction, old and young, muscular and sallow, vague and determined, stern and laughing.
And that's on the top of 74 because he's of an unstable and unbalanced mind at the end of the top paragraph.
And that is, he's a walking contradiction and trying to get it together and not succeeding.
That's what we see.
And now, more about him.
Well, he's this contradiction in an extreme form.
And now we can look at the self again.
He's got these versions now.
His factors are insect and angel, Sodom and Madonna.
And what's interesting about the way he's got these factors is that he sees that they're both essential.
He's not trying to just prove that he is noble and lofty and impeccable and get rid of the other side.
He sees that he can't get rid of either side.
And he's got a kind of despair version of the more one, the more the other.
He says that when he's plunging into his sensuality, he, I hope I got the right page for this one.
Yes, on 122.
You can see him saying the more he's base, the more he's noble, only those aren't his terms, the more he's indulging in sensuality and sodom, the more he's being spiritual and loving the Madonna.
And he says that, where does he say it?
Somewhere around 121, 122.
Let's look on 120.
He quotes this insect thing, and then he says, all the Karamatsovs, the middle of the page, are such insects.
You see, that's where Karamatsov gets put on the left column.
And he says, God sets before us nothing but riddles.
The boundaries meet, and the contradictions exist side by side.
And not even side by side, if you skip down a little, but they support, they promote each other, these contradictions.
About ten lines from the bottom, beauty, I can't bear the thought of a man of lofty mind and heart, that a man with lofty mind and heart begins with the ideal of the Madonna and ends with the ideal of Sodom.
What's still more awful is that now is where you get the two so intimately connected that you can't even think of getting rid of one or the other.
That's why he's a case of desperately trying to get them together.
That's why he's an R too positive.
Let's go on.
I can't bear it that I can't bear the thought that a man of lofty mind and heart begins with the ideal of the Madonna and ends with the ideal of Sodom.
What's still more awful is that a man with the ideal of Sodom in his soul does not renounce the ideal of the Madonna.
You see, that would be negative relating.
And his heart may be on fire with that ideal, genuinely on fire, just as in his days of youth.
Yes, man is too broad, too broad, I'd have him narrower.
And the famous line at the end of the chapter: God and the devil are fighting there for the thought.
Fighting, and the battlefield is the heart of man.
That's sort of not very, I mean, that's a sort of dramatic way to put it.
It's not so much that they're flipping back and forth in the heart of man, and that's the interesting part.
And then he goes on being a bug and being full of baseness.
Where's this?
I can't find what I want.
But at the very moment when he's going into his sort of heads up, I mean, feet up, heads down into his sensuality, he's already beginning his praise of the Madonna.
Now we have to find that.
Let's see if I can find it.
120.
Help me find it.
He says the most terrible thing, even more than what he says here, is how he begins a hymn of praise to the Madonna just as he's sinking into the viciousness.
Somebody will find it.
Maybe not.
Maybe, I mean, it's there.
I'll take one more look and then I will give up.
Well, I don't know.
But it's clearly his view, and I've got you enough quotes to tell you that as the very time, the more he's plunging into his sensuality, the more he's also feeling his spirituality at the very same time.
And that's what he, and he can't get rid of either one because they're both essential.
That's his picture.
Now, that makes him a very interesting case, the case of the despair of recognizing the true nature of the self and recognizing that both factors are essential and not being able to get them together.
And now you understand, if you see that, why Zosima does this amazing, strange thing that he does in his cell after he's heard from all the Karamatsovs freaking out in various ways.
What's the last move that Zosima makes that everybody's very puzzled about?
Yeah, he bows down until that forehead touched the floor in front of Dmitry.
And we have to look at where that happens because lots of interesting things happen at once there.
Okay, at the bottom of 81.
Father Zosima rose from his seat, almost distracted with anxiety for the elder Alyasha, supported him by the arm.
I put it there because Alyasha is always so involved.
Remember that I read last time where Ivan was watching this whole scene in the cell and like a reporter, which is his job, and he doesn't try to jump up and help Zosima, but naturally, Alyasha does.
And then Zosima goes to Dmitri, and they thought he was falling from weakness.
But the elder distinctly and deliberately bowed down at Dmitry's feet till his forehead touched the floor.
And Alyasha, and now this is typical of Dostoevsky, who loves to make these sort of verisimilitude remarks.
He loved Dickens because Dickens did.
I mean, he just adds at the end there something not at all necessary for all this fancy psychology and philosophy, but just reality.
He says Alyasha was so astonished that he failed to help him when he got up again.
And that's neat.
And now the question is: why did he bow down like that?
And the answer is: Zosima says, he bows down for the great suffering in store for him.
I won't find you the quote because I don't know where it is.
But that's, I explained that already.
I mean, he's got the extremist form of the difficulty of being a human being short of getting out of it, which namely getting out of it.
He's got the most extreme form of despair.
Once you realize that the two sides of the self are not only both essential, but sort of reinforce each other, and you want to get them together, but they're a contradiction, as well as reinforcing each other, you're in real trouble, and you're in despair, and that's where he is.
Now, how about Dmitry stuff?
Well, you always have to ask yourself, who is the girlfriend?
It can't be Katerina.
She's really taken by Ivan, and that's how it has to be.
They both got the lofty, impeccable approach.
So, who's Dmitry's real girlfriend?
The one he's really, really Grushenka.
Right, Grushenka.
So, you'd expect to find somewhere, once you get on this sort of existential kluke trap, that Grushenka has the same thing as Dmitry about the self, namely that it has two factors, one good and one bad, and that the period well and that, they're both essential.
So we find her on this I have to skip way ahead to 510, but it won't spoil the plot.
It's just that happens to be where she says it.
And it goes by very quickly.
The Dostyvsky's got it always in here.
He's, I mean, instead of the insect, she says she's a beast at the second one.
I'm a beast, that's what I am, but I want to pray.
That's the Madonna part.
I gave, never mind the onion.
We don't know what that means right now.
Wicked as I've been, I want to pray.
And then let them dance.
And then the summit up at the end of that little paragraph or halfway through it.
Though we're bad, the world's all right.
We're good and bad, good and bad.
That's in her simple, direct way.
She's got this thing, which same thing that Dimitri's got with poetry and insects and angels and Madonna's and Sodom.
She's just got it in its basic form.
We're good and bad both.
And it's okay.
That's what she's saying at that point.
And so that's on the chart where we get Grushenka down at the bottom where you get good and bad.
And she said someplace else.
I don't think it's right here.
But she says, I'm a beast, but I want to pray.
That's the same thing as the I'm going into Dimitri's, I'm falling, I'm plunging headfirst into sensuality, but I'm loving the Madonna all the same.
Even the more sensual, the more I love the Madonna.
She's got the same thing.
Naturally, she's got it because that's her job, so to speak.
Existential double for them, for him.
Anyone want to say anything?
I'm just going sort of talking on because there's a lot to say, and the structure of the book is so amazingly rich.
I mean, there's so much more going on than anybody knows.
I'm sure so much more going on than I know, because every once in a while, a whole new thing, I'll tell you when I get there, a student will say to me, and I'll realize that, sorry, I've been missing 20% of the book.
It happened a few years ago.
But anyway, by the way, I just read the foreword and the afterword of the version of the book that you've got.
There's nothing wrong or stupid about them, but there's absolutely nothing illuminating about them either.
They sort of see the structure all in very vainal, very murky and, well, vanal terms.
So read them if you like.
There's lots of sort of interesting facts about the life of Dostoevsky in there.
I don't think that they're going to cast any helpful light.
Okay, back to the next one in the family.
So now, what have we got?
We're getting ready to go on to Alyasha.
But just want to, in passing, tell you, get you to sort of recognize, remember I said these brothers are very much your age, but the ages of the brothers play an important significant role.
So I'm going to read this.
I'm 16.
Alexey, that's Alyasha, was only 20.
His brother Ivonne was in his 24th year at the time, while their elder half-brother Dimitri was 27.
And so Alexei or Alyasha and so forth.
And that's, we're going to find out pretty soon that there's another brother the same age as Yvonne, but I don't want to talk about it yet.
So, but I do want to talk about something funny that happens right here.
The omniscient narrator is still around showing his stupidity here early in the book.
When you go, it goes on and says, they were all fond of Alyasha.
He wasn't a mystic, that's true.
I may as well give my full opinion.
He was simply a lover of humanity.
And that he adopted the monastic life was because it struck him as an ideal escape for his soul, struggling from the darkness of the world, the light of love.
Well, that's half right.
But he wasn't a lover of humanity.
Being a lover of humanity would be to love all human beings.
And if you understand anything about sort of Christianity and Alyasha as a Christian, he loves each particular human being that he's with.
But Ivan says at some point that he loves humanity, but he can't stand particular people, any particular people.
He's very disdainful and aloof.
The point is, Alyasha loves the particular people that he comes in contact with, all of them, even old Karamatsov, who says to him at one point, you're the only one who doesn't despise me and condemn me.
But it just shows how sort of stupid the commentator is.
He's not a lover of humanity, he's a lover of, you could say it in Christian terms, his neighbor, whoever that may be, at whatever time.
And now where are we?
So Alyasha has a problem with the sensual, which what he considers the dark side of himself.
And he hasn't resolved it.
In that way, he is sort of like Yvonne, except that where Yvonne knows how to resolve it, in his idea, get rid of it, deny it, and so forth.
Alyasha doesn't, so to speak, know what to do about it.
So he just tries to not have to face it, but not by distracting himself, but in a funny way.
Let's see where it is now.
Yeah, on 19 is where you hear about it.
And you hear a lot about the sensual side of Alyasha and how he is not repressing it, because that would be sort of like denying it, which is what Yvonne is trying to do.
He just doesn't know how to cope with it.
And that's as far as he's gotten.
On 19, about 10 lines down, he talks about the fact that he had a wild fanatical modesty and chastity.
He could not bear to hear certain words and certain conversations about women.
There are certain words and conversations unhappily impossible to eradicate in schools, of schoolboys.
And so, then skipping down to the second paragraph, seeing that Alyasha Karamatsov put his fingers in his ears when they talked of that, his schoolfellows crowded around, pulled his hands away, and shouted nastiness into both ears while he struggled and fell to the floor.
And that's just, he just doesn't know how to deal with this.
And you'll find out more later when I don't think I wrote it down here, but you have to bear it in mind when Rakit tells him.
I'm surprised I don't have it with him.
Maybe I do.
We'll see if I get there.
So anyway, we've seen this: that Alyasha has got this dangerous side, and Rakitin tells him he's a Karamatsov and a centralist like everybody else.
And Alyasha gets all very upset because he says he knows it's true that he's a Karamatsov, and that means he got this dangerous, dark, destructive impulses.
Okay, so now let's see, I'm 16.
I think that's what I just read.
Yeah, and when I said that he's no lover of humanity, I said that the other half of that sentence is true.
He's struggling from the darkness of worldly wickedness to the light of love.
He says that himself.
That means that he's not yet understood how to integrate the dark side and the other side in some positive way.
And that's why on the chart, when you get to Alyasha, you don't have Alyasha on the chart.
Or really, you do at the bottom.
There are two ways to talk about Alyasha.
One is that he's got a defining commitment.
We'll get to that.
But what I think we should write into the chart, I wrote it into mine.
I will change it the next time I give it out.
There is where we talk right before base and noble.
You should add dark and light.
There's the darkness, and there's the light.
There's the darkness of the world and the light of the spiritual.
And Alyasha belongs there in a kind of R2 because he's trying to go in the monastery to get to the light and get out of the darkness.
I mean, he says it on his own terms.
When the narrator says we could believe it, he's a soul struggling from the darkness of worldly wickedness to the light of love.
That's how he understands it at this point.
That would make him a negative.
Get rid of the darkness, go to the monastery, leave the dark behind, go to where Sasam is, and everybody loves each other.
That's not satisfactory, of course, because you've got to get it together.
So let me see now.
He enters the monastery on 37 for this very reason, to get out of the 26.
I have so many different versions of this.
It drives me crazy.
But on 26, but I'll never use this version again because of the way it left out that part I passed out to you.
Not pardonable.
So I'll read you again what the omniscient narrator says, but I do think it's true about him.
The first paragraph on 26.
I shall be told perhaps that Alyasha was stupid, undeveloped, not finished in his studies, that he'd not, and so forth.
I'll simply repeat, as I have said, he entered upon this path into the monastery because at that time it alone struck his imagination and seemed to him to offer an ideal means of escape for his soul from darkness to light.
I mean, escape is, of course, the clue.
If you go to the monastery to escape some aspect of the world in yourself, you're not facing up to what your job is, is to somehow integrate them, purify them, not hold your ears and run into the monastery.
So Alyasha has a lot to learn and a long way to go.
But there's this fascinating comparison between him, about him and Yvonne, that I want you to read.
If I can get this book untangled from the other ones, just a second.
Yeah.
At the bottom, there are two different things.
Don't let me confuse you.
I am going to talk about how he's different from Yvonne, but then I'm going to talk about another way that he's different from Dimitri.
But this is how he's different from Yvonne at the bottom of 19.
Remember that they both have the same condition, that they've been living off relatives who had to take them in because their mother died and old Karamatsov just abandons them.
On what terms he lived with them, these relatives, he didn't know himself.
It was very characteristic of him that he never cared.
Now, consider this contrast with Yvonne, who was so embarrassed by having to be dependent on these people.
He wanted to be self-sufficient and impeccable, and here he was sort of treated as a scruffy relative.
But he didn't care at whose expense he was living.
In what respect, in that respect, he was a striking contrast to his elder brother Yvonne, who struggled with poverty for the first two years in the university, supported himself, and from childhood and had been, had from childhood been bitterly conscious of living at the expense of his benefactor.
And this is all the way Alyasha is sort of saintly already.
The bottom of that paragraph.
When he was given pocket money that he didn't ask for, he was terribly careless with it so that it was gone or he kept it for weeks not knowing what to do with it.
And what happens is then everybody takes care of him, everybody loves him, he doesn't ever have to buy any food or find any place to stay.
People are just happy to have him around.
Now, at the bottom of 21, Alyasha arrival.
I just want to, I was looking for a quote about old Karamatsov that I didn't find, but I found it now, and it comes right here with Alyasha, so I'll put it in.
You can push it back with old Karamatsov.
It says, Alyasha's arrival seemed to make him, that's old Karamatsov, make his moral side, sorry, seem to affect even his moral side, as though something had awakened in this prematurely old man which had long been dead in his soul.
That's another way of saying spiritlessness.
And when Alyasha's around, old Karamatsov worries about, admits that he worries about heaven and hell, and that he's got this side that he's trying not to think about.
So on 24, he goes on the typical of not thinking about it, old Karamatsov.
He says, I keep thinking about hell, and then I will the devils drag me down with their hooks?
But then, what about hooks?
Where do they get them?
Are they iron hooks?
How do they forge them?
I mean, this is how not to think about the seriousness of whether he's going to hell or not.
And that's his way of distracting himself.
But it's clear that he's worried about it.
And on the top of 25, the quote that I mentioned but didn't write down, he says, I feel that you're the only, I feel that you're the only creature in the world who has not condemned me, my boy.
And that's interesting.
Okay, now where am I?
So compared to Dmitry, we've just talked about that.
He's self-sufficient.
I mean, not making any sense at all.
Compared to Yvonne, Alyasha is happy to depend on everybody.
And while Yvonne wants to be self-sufficient, now I'm switching to another thing, comparing him to Dmitry.
That's really interesting, because this brings out the sensual, common sensuality, common Karamatsov-in-ness in the two of them.
And that's on page 121.
Dimitri is going on and on about how bad he is at the bottom of 121.
I loved cruelty.
Am I not a bug?
Am I not a poisonous insect?
In fact, I'm a Karamatsov.
That again.
But he says now at a new issue on 123.
Though I'm full of baseness and love, what's and love what's low, I'm not dishonorable.
You're blushing.
Enough of this filth with you.
And now comes what I want to lead up to.
Below the middle of 122, Alyasha admits that he's got the same impulses.
You say that because I blushed, Alyasha said suddenly.
I wasn't blushing at what you were saying or what you've done.
I blushed because I'm the same as you, the same as you are.
You?
That's a little too far.
No, it's true, insisted Alyasha.
Obviously, the idea was not new.
The ladder's the same.
I'm at the bottom step, and you're above somewhere about the 13th.
That is so strange that I have to talk about it a minute.
It looks like he's trying to say that Yvonne is in some way better than he is, higher up than he is, because Yvonne is more sensual, more disgusting, more cruel, more despairing than he is, than he, Alyasha, is.
And that's a very interesting sort of Christian and Kierkegaardian too, of course, therefore, theme, that you've got to go all the way into despair before you can fight your way out.
And Alyasha is in effect admitting that he hasn't faced up to his sensuality.
He's thought about it, but he hasn't acted on it.
Yvonne has acted on it and hates himself for it and can't resist and yet knows that somehow he's being dragged down and so forth.
So, in a funny way, you've got to go down before you can go up in this Christian picture.
And you see it in formal terms in the despair chart.
And you see it if you would read the divine Comedy, you would see that Dante has to go to the bottom of the inferno before he can climb up purgatory and get to paradise.
Or you see it in a strange way in Third Man, where this reversibleness of up and down of the porter, and then the guy burying, the priest burying the supposed hairy line, is reading the passage that Jesus descended into hell for three days.
Now, why in the world did he do that?
And, well, he did it because it's part of the idea of being really the most fulfilled human being that you've got to confront the dark side and somehow make it not dark anymore.
And you have to go through the, but to do that, you have to go through the despair.
I've got it explained, but I do I have it later?
Must be earlier.
You can see it best in Madame Holokoff's way of dealing with Zosima.
Let me see if I had it.
I wrote it down.
I wrote it down, but then I didn't.
I only have the page numbers in this book.
That's so annoying.
It's around 66.
Because it's all very important Dostoevsky and thinking here.
And it comes out with Da when Zosima talks to Madame Holokoff about it.
I hope I can find it.
Boy, I'm not going to.
It's 60.
Oh, good.
How'd you know that?
That's terrific.
Not in my 60s.
Where do you see it?
I'm looking at what Zosima says to Madame Holokov, that she's got to contemplate she's got to confront her evil impulses.
And if she thinks about them enough and dwells on them enough.
What?
Ah, 62.
Let's yes.
Oh, Rob, you got it.
Terrific.
I don't know.
So let's look at it.
Because this is what why Alyasha thinks that Dimitri is one step ahead of him, ahead of Alyasha.
Because Alyasha isn't confronting his sensuality and his Karmatsu, you know.
He's just worried about it, obsessing about it, sticking his fingers in his ears when anybody talks about sex.
And that's, and Dimitri is plunging into it.
You'd think that would be worse, but that's better because he's not lying to himself or covering it up.
On 62, Zosima is saying to Madame Holokov, who's worried about her dark side, above all, this is in the second paragraph, avoid falsehood, every kind of falsehood, especially falsehood to yourself.
Then comes the crucial Dostoevsky talk.
What seems to you bad within you will grow purer from the very fact that you're observing it in yourself, instead of hiding from it.
Certainly Dimitri is observing it in himself.
Alyasha is just sort of frightened and finding it in himself, but he doesn't want it and he doesn't want to think about it.
And then comes the crucial thing.
At the bottom of that long paragraph, Zosima says, I predict that just when you see with horror that in spite of all your efforts you are getting further from your goal instead of nearer, at that very moment you will reach it.
That means that there is a way to transform these sensuous and could be destructive and disgusting and dangerous impulses into something positive which supports the spiritual.
And Zosima knows that.
And we will get to see that in Dmitry, in Grushenka.
That may be the only two.
I think they're the only ones who do it, who convert what seems to be negative and bad into something positive in facing up to it.
And that's why it's important that Dmitry is 13 steps.
Let's see, how does it go again?
That Dmitry is 13 steps higher than Alyasha.
In a funny way, you would think, you know, he's closer to salvation because he's more despairing.
But that's the way it works in any of these people who have this kind of Christian psychology.
Okay, now I know where I am.
We've seen, have I just finished Alyasha or no?
I just put this page back here.
Okay.
So now we just have to say the obvious, that Alyasha has got a kind of provisional, unconditional commitment.
That means really that it's an unconditional commitment, which he never changes.
Zosima always become is super important in his life, but it's an unconditional commitment that he is able to internalize and be open to marrying somebody and presumably having an unconditional commitment to them.
But the important thing is that at this stage in his life, he's already got a relation to himself that comes by his relation to another.
And that's so he's at R3 on your chart.
Now, how does that work?
Well, there's plenty of talk about it.
And I will read a little bit just to convince you that it's something like a defining relation.
As soon as I find where I want to read it, well, he, at the bottom of 16, and the reason this life in the monastery struck him in this way was that he found in it at that time as he an extraordinary being, our celebrated elder Zosima, to whom he became attached with all the warm first love of his art and art.
That's a kind of unconditional commitment because he defines himself in terms of that relation to Zosima as sort of through Zosima, he's going to have his whole life gets its meaning.
You see that on 31.
By the way, still nobody wants to say anything.
I think this is probably not.
I would despair of the fact that nobody's saying anything, except I couldn't imagine what I would be saying either if I was sitting there listening to me.
But next time, to save me from despair, be ready to say things, because next time you're going to have to just take up your stand on whether you agree with Yvonne or not, and why you agree with him or not.
But this isn't yet like a debate.
This is just a bunch of assertions.
Yeah.
Oh, you have something to disagree or something good.
No, I don't agree.
These characters, are they supposed to be identical to the intelligence towards the whole size of human beings, or human beings that are already constituted?
Ah, oh, I see.
Yeah, so I'm going to answer that.
That's a good question.
You're absolutely the perfect straight person.
We've got just enough time to do it.
I mean, we've talked about the heredity part about how they got that way, but we haven't talked about the important.
Here's a way to put your question.
Look at this.
People with the same background, Dimitri on the one hand and Yvonne on the other, who lived off their relatives, come out utterly different.
One of them, you know, totally independent and self-sufficient and obsessed with being impeccable, and the other one not caring about how they look and just going about their life without reflecting and so forth.
Where did that difference come from?
Is it internal, somehow they're just in their DNA?
Or if it isn't, what in their experience makes them like that?
And how come Yvonne, who's after all the brother of Alyasha, hasn't got any of that religious saintliness from his mother that Alyasha got from his mother?
Okay, that's the right question.
We will go to it immediately.
As soon as I read you one more quote, just to convince you that Zasima is what gives Alyasha the meaning of his life on 31.
The bottom paragraph.
He is holy.
He carries in his heart the secret of the renewal for all, the power which will at last establish truth on earth, and so forth.
That was the dream in Alyasha's heart.
So he is absolutely sort of taken up with Zosima as the kind of really messenger of the good, and he wants the good, and he loves it in Zosima.
That's all I have to say about that, except one, maybe one more thing before I switch to your question.
Or two, I see there are still things to do.
But one is we got to go to page 112.
I don't know why.
If I say so, we have to do it.
Oh, it's just somewhere.
We're talking about Alyasha, remember.
Another way to describe his religiousness is that he thinks that in the world of the spirit where he lives, everything will always turn out all right.
He has that Tyric Guardian thing.
And it comes out at the bottom of 112, the bottom of the big paragraph.
Now, Alyasha was certain that no one in the whole world ever would want to hurt him.
And what's more, he knew that no one could hurt him.
This was for him an axiom assumed once and for all without question, and he went his way without hesitating, relying on it.
I mean, that's like seeing the sword of the heavens.
Nothing can hurt him.
Even the death of Zosima couldn't hurt him, though it would certainly cause him to go into a shock.
And one more thing about Zosima.
Remember, I said that the test of how you live your life, which is the right way to live your life, is that the right way is the one that gives you joy, and the wrong way is the one that leads you to despair.
I mean, there's no independent story about what rationality tells you or revelation tells you.
It's, so to speak, existential psychology tells you by looking at the types of people and seeing what happens to them.
And therefore, the truth of the Christian way is that the Christians are joyful.
At the top of 30, we read: Alyasha, that is he, at the second line on the right, he was particularly struck by the fact that Father Zosima was not at all stern.
He was almost always gay.
And now, further, the same thing on 59, he's in this constant happy state, and he says so.
At the middle, on 59, about a third of the way down, Zosima says, Men are made for happiness.
Anyone who is completely happy has a right to say to himself, I'm doing God's will on earth.
All the righteous, all the saints, all the holy martyrs were happy.
So that's the divine comedy aspect.
In the world of the spirit, if you're living the right way, you will be rewarded.
Okay, now one more, and then I get to his issue.
We haven't done Alyasha's existential double.
Who is Alyasha's existential double?
Exactly.
This sort of crazy, crazy kid.
We'll get more back to her craziness later.
But right now, all we want to just say is something to sort of notice that she's there.
That is, that she's mentioned on 48, a daughter, 14, partially paralyzed, full of gaiety, with a gleam of mischief in her dark eyes, and so forth.
How that cashes out, that she is really a practically insane sadomasochist person who slams the door on her finger and does wonderfully crazy Dostoevsky things and who spends her time dreaming up devils is that she's got the sensuous side like Alyasha, except that it's completely out of control on her part.
But she's the one.
I'd love to see how it works out in the second volume.
He's going to marry her.
Zosima tells him he's going to go out into the world and he's going to take a wife.
And it's clear that it's, I forget where it's clear, but it's clear that it's going to be Lisa and that she's his double.
And that somehow she's going to sort of get control and purify this, but not in this book.
So I don't have to say more about her.
So now we go on to something else.
But I told you that Alyasha would have to return to the world, and I see I've got a quote about that one.
So let's see if it's important.
No, I don't think we need to think about that.
So we've got the four Karamatsas.
We've got the four views of the self.
I'll just quickly run through them one more time.
So Fedor runs away from facing the contradictions, impulses in himself.
You know, okay, we've just seen that.
Ivan wants in despair desperately to repress the lackey side.
Dimitri's desperately trying to get the two factors together.
And Alyasha has provisionally solved the problem by sublimating all his impulses into his love for Zosima.
That's all we need to know about that.
Now, I was going to talk next about Smirzhikov, but there's no reason we have to, because I like his question.
So we're going to go to his question.
And that is, why are these people who, in their environment and their life history, are so similar, so different?
And for that, we need a whole new category.
What happens to what, how, what experiences they have, which, under the category, childhood memories, going to play a big role in the brothers Baramatsov.
So let's start thinking about childhood memories.
We're going to skip to that.
Dostoevsky believes that the kind of person you are depends on your environment and heredity, but it's very important that it also depends on what happens to you when you're very young.
So Yvonne and Alyasha have the same meek mother, Sophia.
They're terribly different.
And heredity can't explain that, and DNA can't explain that.
What does explain that?
Well, I'm going to go quick over some things.
I just want to give you the context.
So the question is: why are Alyasha and Dimitri in the Christian dimension, even though they've got different mothers, while Yvonne is a philosopher and a Platonist, even though he's got the same mother as Alyasha?
And that is that somehow there's got to be experiences in their childhood, Dostoevsky thinks, that influence their fundamental take on their the self.
It's a kind of Freudian idea, if that's any help.
And you probably read Freud in some course or other.
How many have come across Freud already?
Not only a few.
Well, anyway, I'll just give you a very quick thing.
Dostoevsky, Freud thinks that childhood traumas are very important in shaping people's personality.
A trauma is a painful, bad event.
And Dostoevsky has the reverse view.
He thinks that what's really important are positive childhood memories.
Freud thinks that you have to repress these childhood traumas, and they're very hard to uncover in later years.
And that's what the therapist has to help you do.
Dostoevsky thinks that since these memories that are important are positive memories, they're not things that people repress, but things that people remember frequently.
As he puts it every once in a while, they remember them all their lives.
Now, and here we go now to one of them in Alyasha.
Here's why Alyasha is different.
Here's why Alyasha is in a spiritual dimension.
And so here's he's saying on 17, second sentence of the first full paragraph.
I've mentioned already that although he lost his mother in his fourth year, he remembered her all his life, her face, her caresses, as though she stood right before him.
Remembered her all his life.
You see, not repressed the memory of her, Freud-like, but kept it in front of him, so to speak.
And he says such memories persist from an early age, from even two years old, and stand out through a whole lifetime, like spots of light out of darkness, and so forth and so forth.
Now comes his childhood memory.
He remembered, and it's all just absolutely amazing and fascinating what he remembers.
He remembered one still summer evening, an open window, the slanting rays of the setting sun.
He recalled this most vividly of all.
Nobody that I know thinking about Dostoevsky stops to think, what's going on there?
Now, I'm going to, you won't know for a while.
I can't tell you today.
But you should ask yourself, when you continue this, you discover that all kinds of wild things are happening.
And what he's remembering is the slanting rays of the sun.
We'll get back to that.
But now, what's happening in a corner of the room, the holy image, before it, a lighted lamp, and on her knees before the image, his mother sobbing hysterically with cries and moans, snatching him up in both arms, squeezing him close till it hurt, and praying for him to the mother of God, holding him out in both arms to the image as though to put him under the mother's protection.
And suddenly a nurse rushes in and snatches him away from her in terror.
That was the picture.
And Alyasha remembered his mother's face at that minute.
It was frenzied and beautiful and so forth.
But he remembered most of all the rays of the sun.
Just put that aside, but that is really weird.
You'll see in a minute that it's why that's important.
The question is, what influence this memory has on his life?
And it turns out that this memory literally guides his life.
And the first place you get it is on 27 when we're finding out why he went into the monastery.
So, and was a Christian and so forth.
But the three lines down.
Perhaps his memories of childhood brought back our monastery to which his mother may have taken him to Mass.
Perhaps the slanting sunlight and the holy image to which his poor mother had held him up still worked upon his imagination.
So there's something in that whole scene, the love of his mother and her dedication of him, so to speak, to the icon, to the Virgin Mary, and so forth, which made a lasting impression on him.
And the first example there more coming up of how it made a lasting impression on him was that the slanting rays of the sun play an interesting role.
I just tell you a hint, but somehow the slanting rays of the sun are the nearest thing you get to God in the book.
But I can't explain yet why and what that means.
But in any case, now we just have time to see the Dimitri memory.
Because Dostoevsky is doing something, which I'm going to tell you by the end of the time, special, original, important, that's going to happen through the whole book.
And it's happening already in the Alyosha case, but you don't really see what's happening until you see the Dimitri case.
So we have to jump way over to page 780, almost the end of the book, but nothing is going to be given away, I promise you.
But here we go.
Something really interesting happens.
Somebody's being called in a witness about Dimitri at a trial.
And at the bottom of 780, this old German doctor says, about two-thirds of the way down, I remember him very well, a little chap, so high, left neglected by his father in the backyard.
He ran about without boots on his feet and had his little britches hanging on one button.
And now he starts to tell the story at the bottom paragraph.
Oh, yes, I was a young, man then, I was 45.
And I asked myself, I'm skipping a little, why shouldn't I buy him a pound of, a pound of what?
And then there's all this craziness where he's trying to remember the name.
And finally, he does.
Nuts.
Yes, nuts, he says at the top of 781.
And then he says, I bought him a pound of nuts.
And now, pay attention.
Everything that happens is absolutely amazing.
For no one had ever bought him a pound of nuts before.
And I lifted my finger and I said to him, Boy, got their father.
He laughed and said, Got their father.
Got their son.
And he laughed and said again with a lisp, got their son, and got their Heiligegeist.
And he laughed and said it as best he could, got their Heiligegeist.
And I went away, and two days later I happened to be passing and he shouted to me, Uncle, got their father, got their son.
He'd only forgotten Got their Heiligegeist.
And I reminded him of it and felt sorry for him again.
What's going on there?
First, I was just leaving it the way it is here, but it's in German.
Does anybody know what was just being said?
God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghost, or God the Holy Spirit.
And that's what the German doctor says as he gives him the pound of nuts.
What in the world is going on there?
That pound of nuts is going to be the thing that Dimitri remembers all his life as an act of love and caring of which he had very little.
But that was enough to get him sensitive to the loving, caring dimension, just like Alyasha was sensitive to it when being held up to the icon.
Because it turns out to be a lasting childhood memory.
It would just go on.
Then he was taken away, and I didn't see him again.
23 years passed, and I'm sitting, this is the doctor talking.
One morning in my study, a bald-headed old man, where there walks into the room a blooming young man who I never would have recognized, except that he held up his finger and said, laughing, got their father, got their son, and got their Heiligegeist.
I have just arrived and have come to thank you for that pound of nuts, for no one ever brought me a pound of nuts.
You were the only one who ever did.
Okay.
Can you tell what's going on there?
On what occasion do you say to child or to a baby, God the Father, God the Son, baptism.
This is baptism.
Dostoevsky has the peculiar thing that when he's doing anything of this sort, I'll tell you what sort it is as I go, he tells you.
So he's telling you what?
That the German doctor baptized him, said over him the words that helped, that expressed the fact that he was entering the dimension of possible love and possible despair, the Christian dimension.
And that's now one wants to say, look back at what happened with Alyasha when his mother held him up to the icon.
That was also the same kind of baptism, only Dostoevsky didn't hit you over the head with it using the words that are used when you baptize a baby.
And what is baptism for Dostoevsky?
Well, it's getting a saving childhood memory that puts you in the Christian religious dimension.
Now, the question is: what is he doing when he does this strange mood with baptism?
Well, now that's very important.
What Dostoevsky's doing is taking what looks just like some kind of magical formula where you say these special words, and lo and behold, the child somehow becomes part of the Christian community.
And the point is, Dostoevsky's telling you the psychological, existential meaning of baptism, according to him.
I mean, baptism is just a kind of magic, and he wants to get all the magic out of Christianity.
And he wants to replace the magic with an existential account of what it does to the person's psychology to have these Christian rituals.
And now, and we'll see what I want to say next.
The whole book on one level is dedicated to the project of saving Christianity by converting all the magical mystery things that happen in Christianity into existential things.
He's demagicalizing it.
The way theologians talk, he's demythologizing Christianity.
I think that's a bad move.
The student pointed out: myths are good things, and we don't want to demythologize.
But magic isn't a good thing.
And why isn't it?
Because you don't want to get yourself in the position of thinking of Christianity as some kind of causal thing, in which those magic words said over the baby transform the baby in some way.
That's, if you do that, you're in serious trouble.
Because if you start thinking of Christianity as sort of magical ways of causing things, then you run up against the laws of physics and chemistry and neuroscience.
Believe it or not, Dostoevsky has already just gotten news of neuroscience, and that seems to compete with these Christian magical practices.
But if there are these existential practices, then there's no conflict.
And Dostoevsky is very dedicated to this, between the laws of physics and chemistry, and we can now add genetics and evolution, and the truth of Christianity.
But that requires converting every one of the Christian symbols into an existential experience.
And you just saw baptism converted.
And Dostoevsky has this game, which I find just wonderful, and you have to learn to play it.
He never misses a chance to tell you once and once and clearly which Christian thing he has just existentialized.
That's why the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit gets in there.
When you give somebody a bag of nuts, it's not the normal thing to say.
You'll see, I'll just read it now in a minute, Beatrice, that he wants to existentialize.
I'll just give you a list.
Confession, the incarnation, and big deal things.
Ordination of priests, the crucifixion, immortality, angels, and devils.
All of them get existentialized.
And even, and this is the most fun in the book, if you're liking this kind of thing, miracles.
You'd think you could hardly do it with miracles, since miracles seem to be the things that go against physics and chemistry.
But he's going to save the existential meaning of miracles in a way that has nothing to do with the laws that govern the way the world works.
And when he does, and you keep your eyes open for it, he's going to tell you that was a miracle.
Because he's always telling you that.
Go ahead, Beatrice.
I understand that it's not causal, but it could work on the memory.
Oh, well, okay, good.
How is it causal and not causal?
It's not causal in the physics and chemistry and neural way.
That is, he doesn't have a theory, and he doesn't need one, and he probably doesn't think there is one, of how these existential experiences happen on the level of the way the brain works and so forth.
He wants a description that captures the whole meaning of it.
You could say the phenomenology of it, the existential phenomenology of it, and shows that it doesn't matter how the neurons do it and how, you know, and so forth.
What's important is that this, you have to understand the meaning of how it is that holding up the baby to the icon or giving the pound of nuts can influence somebody all their lives.
It doesn't matter whether you have a neuron story about it.
Anybody else?
And this is one of the most exciting things in the book.
I'm going to write a book about this someday.
When I do, I want to say Dostoevsky's attempt, he's very important.
I mean, if you want to save Christianity in some form, you've got to one decide what form, and we'll get to that in not next lecture, but the lecture after.
And you've got to do it in a way that physics and neuroscience and evolution, the latest, isn't going to undermine what you want to do it in a way that doesn't get you in competition with science, because that's a losing thing.
They've been losing ever since the church tried to keep Galileo's views that the earth wasn't the center of the universe a secret.
And Galileo, supposedly, after he said, after he gave into the Inquisition and said he, okay, so the earth doesn't move, then he mumbled under his breath, but it moves just the same.
I mean, science is going to win out if you get into the science business.
So, but who cares?
Dostoevsky's view is.
There is a certain understanding of humans' beings and what they need and how they get it, which the Christians have got.
And that can be preserved and had better be preserved.
Okay, anybody have anything to say about that?
But now you see how this relates to what you asked.
I mean, now we know why, I'm going to just sort of sum it up.
Now we know why Alyasha is in the Christian dimension and has love at the center of everything he does.
And Yvonne, who's got the same heredity and the same environment, but no childhood memory, isn't.
And Dimitri, who hasn't got a religious mother, is nonetheless in the religious dimension, because it doesn't have to be your mother who baptizes you.
In this case, it's the German doctor.
But the crucial thing is Dimitri's in the religious dimension because he's got a childhood memory.
It follows from this that if you wanted to make everybody that you were in touch with religion, religious and Christian, you'd have to go about the job of creating the appropriate childhood memory.
And indeed, I won't tell you more.
That's going to turn out to be important.
Yeah.
We talk real loud.
I can't hear you.
It's funny.
Your voice is on a wavelength I can't hear.
Either you're going to have to shout or somebody's going to repeat.
Somebody repeat in a voice I can hear what you just said.
Is he trying to convert faith or symbols?
Angels and demons, trying to give it a different way of looking at it.
He's trying to capture the truth about human experience, which faith has got, but which is covered up by lots of sort of magical stuff.
And in actually faith, I should have put that on my list.
Christian, actual faith in God gets demagicalized explicitly at the very middle of the book.
I'm going to add it to the list.
Yes, faith has to be transformed, that is, explained like all the rest.
Okay.