The plan for today is to discuss what I sort of said very quickly at the end last time, but I wanted you to have it in mind when you were reading the preamble from the heart.
And that was, what's the basic experience that Kierkegaard has that he claims is this revelation of something absolutely important about human beings.
I'm passing out, by the way.
This is old stuff.
But I said I would write up the difference between the Judaic Christian understanding of everything important for us and the Greek understanding.
Just sort of file it away as something to remind you of the first lecture.
Now, back to the basic experience.
I said last time, but I want to say it again, what's the new experience that was around for a while, though not forever.
It was around since Dante loved Beatrice.
That is around since there were knights and ladies.
That's why you hear about knights of resignation and knights of faith, because all of this experience was sort of focused and dramatized and lived in the chivalric way.
But it's the same as our experience of romantic love, and it really goes back to the not probably to the Hebrew experience, but to the Christian experience of the total commitment that the disciples had for Jesus, and that they gave them a new identity.
He went around giving them all new names.
So Saul becomes Paul and so forth.
And they were all ready to die for this commitment they had.
And that's unique.
I mean, that's, from Kierkegaard's point of view, and I think I like it, I think it sounds right.
The big discovery, the big new thing that the Judeo-Christian tradition finally produced was the idea was, you could say the idea of the God-man.
You could say something like a Savior.
That is some, but the important thing for Kierkegaard and for the chivalric people was the important kind of relationship that the disciples had for Jesus, that they made him the central thing in their life, that when they got related to him, they got a new identity, they got a new world, and they had a whole new kind of experience.
And the Judeo-Christian religion is the only religion that's got that, that makes what I'm calling unconditional commitment absolutely important for what it is to be a fulfilled human being.
In Kierkegaard jargon, what it means not to get out of despair.
We'll talk about that way of describing it later.
And in its romantic love version, where it comes down to Kierkegaard and Regina, it's still the same important and unique idea of what's important, what's the most important, exciting, meaningful possibility for human beings.
So, in Kierkegaard, it sounds so trivial, but it's not trivial.
I mean, it's whether it's, they are all about some kind of commitment that makes, that changes your life completely.
And it could be something as sort of, what, I don't know, literary or something as the bottom of page 70, where a young lad falls in love with the princess and the whole content of his life is in this love.
The crucial thing is this whole content of your life being bound up in some commitment.
And remember, it says on 71, these are all things we said at the end, I said in the end in a hurry, that, of course, this is the footnote, any other interest whatsoever in which an individual concentrates the whole of life's reality can, and then he goes on to talk about resignation, that I'm not ready to talk about that.
But the main thing is he generalizes it to any commitment which gives your life its whole meaning, gives you an identity.
Dante is the lover of Beatrice.
The disciples are the disciples of Jesus, and the knight is the knight for this lady, and that's their job description.
That's who they are.
That's what defines them.
And then, and now that's about how far I got last time, because I jumped ahead.
If I had done it in the normal order I usually want to do it in, we have to go back a little and see that Kierkegaard was looking for this ever since he was 22, that is about your age, writing in his journals what he was later going to sort of try to live out with Rodino, although it didn't work, and what the lad has for the princess or the knight for the lady.
Here's what he wrote in when he was 22 in his journal: What I really lack is to be clear in my mind, underlined now, what I am to do, not what I am to know, except insofar as a certain understanding must precede action.
Well, that's the Greek-Hebrew thing in a nutshell.
That is, what's important is what he does, not what he knows.
And of course, you have to know something in order to act, but he's looking for this defining action in his life.
So the next thing he says, the thing is to understand myself, to see what God really wishes me, underlined, to do.
That is, he's looking for his calling.
He's looking for his vocation.
He's looking for what, that is something that grabs him and makes him into the kind of person he becomes and will be the rest of his life.
So let me finish.
I'm looking for what God wishes me to do.
The thing is to find a truth that is true for me.
You recognize the Hebrew kind of truth, not a knowledge kind of truth, not something that you objectively, theoretically know that corresponds to reality, but what Kierkegaard is going to call a subjective truth.
That is, the truth for him.
That, whatever it is, let's stick to Beatrice, but if we don't, Kierkegaard's life is so messed up.
So that Dante knows that he's the lover of Beatrice.
That's his truth.
And Kierkegaard says, then, the final bit of the quote: to find the idea for which I can live and die.
That's a little bit wrong.
He's young and he's just getting used to it.
It's not an idea.
It's a positive person, something or somebody, finite and temporal, to talk Kierkegaard kind of jargon.
It could be a person.
It could be a cause, like, as I said last time, I think I said it, Martin Luther King feeling that he's defined by being the leader and organizer of what's going to get justice for the black people here and now.
It's not enough that it be a good idea.
It's got to be something specific.
And the crucial way to think about it is: whatever this something is that is the truth for you, it's got to be something that you know, it tells you what to do now in the world.
Every morning when you wake up, there is something important for you to do, and lots of other things are just trivial and irrelevant.
And if all you're dedicated to is some very general something or other, like the ultimate triumph of the proletariat, and then if you could stay in bed on a rainy day, it doesn't matter because the proletariat will win out someday anyway.
And it's not a truth that is concrete and finite and temporal enough to tell you what you are to do, as Kierkegaard says, all the time.
So, okay, now that, and that's what I'm calling unconditional commitment.
You know, a theologian named Paul Tillich called it ultimate concern.
Kierkegaard calls it infinite passion, which is a little bit unfortunate because it makes it sound like you're all excited by it all the time.
And you have this kind of commitment even when you're half asleep in the morning drinking your coffee or washing the dishes.
It doesn't something that you're always all excited about.
It's more basic than that.
It's something that sort of structures your world so that what shows up for you is important to do is there all the time.
Whether you're sort of excited by it doesn't matter.
You're defined by it.
That's much more fundamental.
So it's not a strong feeling, as he says on 71.
That's where he wants to make sure it's not intoxication, it says here.
That would be all right.
Intoxication is probably, I thought, the right word, certainly not getting drunk.
But the same word that means getting drunk in English is like intoxication.
Only intoxication is supposed to be this sort of emotional thing.
It doesn't have to come from drinking alcohol.
And that's what he, and that's why an infatuation is also an intoxication in this broad way.
And he wants to make sure that this is the content of his life, it says on 71.
And that means not just a kind of temporary overwhelming feeling.
That is, his soul is too healthy and proud to squander the least thing on intoxication.
And then what happens?
Well, for one thing, let me say a word about something important.
That I have to say it somewhere.
That Kierkegaard is the only one of the existentialists who thinks that philosophy, the Greek way of thinking about things, is important and even necessary and valuable.
Pascal thinks that Descartes is just somebody wasting their time in a warm room trying to prove theorems and geometry, and that's just a way of avoiding facing the wretchedness of the human condition.
But there is something for theory and rationalness.
And it's just exactly to get rid of these strong irrational feelings, these intoxications, so that you can have a real commitment.
So, in that sense, the Greek philosophers were right.
In Kierkegaard language, you have to get over your infatuations, your moods, your superstitions, your passions, all of that is something that he calls, and I'll explain this in a minute, lower immediacy.
And it needs to be mediated.
Now, that's two bits of Hegel jargon.
One thing I didn't say last time, which needs to be said at some point, is if this book isn't hard enough because it's so original and because it's a secret code for Regina and because it's trying to say something in thinkable terms, which is in principle unthinkable, namely the Christian story.
He doesn't want to just put it into Greek terms.
He knows that isn't going to work.
So the book is bad or hard already.
And he does it using the Hegel jargon, which is some whole thing that I haven't got time to teach you.
I'll give you a chart next time in which you can, I'll sort of lay out the Hegel jargon.
But I'll just tell you enough of it right now so that you know, you've got to know immediacy, lower immediacy, higher immediacy, and mediation.
So these are super important terms for Kierkegaard.
So at the bottom is what he calls lower immediacy.
Now, lower immediacy is what we have with the animal, like animals, like children.
It's just sort of where we start in our lives and in our experience.
Immediacy is, I don't know exactly, I'm trying to give you a feel for why he would call it immediacy.
And I haven't got a very good one.
The best I could do is immediacy is where you start right off.
What's spontaneous, what hits you right now without reflection.
It's supposed to cover feelings, impulses, stuff like that.
Babies have them, and cats certainly have them.
Feelings, impulses, and so forth.
And he wants to say that the philosophers were right, Plato and Socrates and so forth.
We have to get, outgrow, get over that kind of lower immediacy, which is a kind of getting what you want right away.
What if there's a word for that, that children have that, that they have?
What?
I forget.
Well, gratification, immediate gratification.
Good.
Yes, it's the immediate gratification.
That's how immediacy comes in here.
They talk about immediate gratification.
I wanted to make the word, I have to write that in my notes for next time.
You see, that's why I need people here to tell me things that I wish I knew.
Why is it called immediate?
Well, temporally it's immediate.
They want it right away.
But then Hegel generalizes it into just the any time, the impulse to have it.
But that sort of immediate gratification is good.
Okay, now mediation is even harder to give you a feeling for why that word.
What Hegel has in mind with mediation is obviously got to do with doing something.
Did I misspell immediate?
Does it have two M's?
I think it needs a few more things like that.
And next is mediation.
Okay, so up here is mediation.
Mediation gets you out of immediacy.
So what is that?
What is that?
How do you get a feel for that?
Well, I finally thought last time I thought this of the only place I can think of where mediation in English means this thing.
It's like being what mediators do.
What mediators do is sort of calm down the labor department, the labor union, and calm down the management.
Both of them are all excited and trying to get what they want and get them to spell out explicitly what they want and then sort of settle on what they need and manage to make, by being philosophical, they can get together.
That's only a special case, but it's there.
But anyway, labor mediation is my model for this.
It means to reflect, explain, understand what you really need, not what you want, and not trying to get what you desire right off and not getting all worked up if you don't get it, but instead being reasonable, articulate, realistic, and so forth.
That's mediation.
Everybody ought to go through that.
If you don't, you just remain childish.
And now I'm back to my point.
Kierkegaard is the only one who sees that the philosophers have got that.
They've understood that lower immediacy is not a good thing to have, and you can do better.
And they've understood that being theoretical, rational, reflective, and so forth gets you out of lower immediacy.
You can get over your superstitions and you can get over your tradition and what your family thinks you ought to do just because that's what people have always done it.
You can get out of all that if you learn to think reasonably, like we try to teach in the philosophy department.
And Kierkegaard thinks that's a good thing.
He doesn't think it's sort of bad news, like Pascal thinks Descartes is sort of making a terrible mistake in spending his time this way.
He calls it diversion instead of relating to God.
And you'll see, Dostoevsky thinks that philosophers are bad guys, all of them, sick.
And Nietzsche certainly thinks literally that philosophers are sick.
We'll read the part where he talks about Socrates as a great degenerate who has done all kinds of bad things to undermine Athenian culture.
But that's unfortunate, I think.
I mean, the existentials see only the bad side of mediation.
See that if you stopped with mediation, you would indeed miss what's most important for human beings.
But they don't see the good side of mediation.
That if you don't have it, you just couldn't tell if any, there wouldn't be anything.
There is something higher than lower immediacy.
And mediation is one step toward it.
And so far, this is straight Hegel.
The terms and the idea is Hegel.
But then comes Kierkegaard, and he says this weird thing that there is a higher immediacy.
And the higher immediacy, this is Kierkegaard's idea.
Well, you know what higher immediacy is already.
Higher immediacy is unconditional commitment.
It's not just subjective, infantile impulses for immediate gratification.
That's gotten rid of by mediation.
But mediation would just give you, make you into a theoretical, detached, universal member, a rational being that did what every rational being does and all these things that the Greeks thought were good and which are good as a step.
But you don't want to end up there.
You want to end up as, and now comes his crucial term, higher immediacy makes you an individual.
To be an individual is just another name for being defined, having a concrete content, a defining content, a whole content in your life, which defines you as the lover of Beatrice or whatever, or the lover of Regina or the leader of the black people.
Those are all individuals.
Kierkegaard said that he wanted carved on his tombstone: here lies an individual.
He thought it was the most important, the most meaningful, the most rewarding thing you could do is get a commitment that made you an individual, and that it was very hard.
And there are very few people who are individuals.
Most of them just do what a normal American or intellectual or whatever are members of some general class or other.
Now there's another important thing, not to be written over here, but maybe over here.
This is individual is not the same as particular.
And now becomes another unfortunate reason why this book is so hard.
Because there seems to be only one word in Danish.
I can't believe this, but I've asked every time I find anybody here in natural language Danish?
But there's some word like Enkele, which apparently doesn't make a distinction between particular and individual.
And you don't normally do it either.
I mean, it's built into English, but you don't know it because we don't need it.
I mean, we don't talk about this very often.
But a particular is just an instant, a particular example, we say.
So, for instance, if you buried your dog, you could write on the tombstone, here lies a particular, it would be silly to do it, but you can't write on the tombstone of your dog, here lies an individual, because an individual has got this thing of having a unique defining commitment.
So everybody is always a particular.
That's not a big deal.
You can't help but be a particular.
That is just an instance of something, one example.
And I'll have to keep pointing out to you, this is what makes it so annoying and hard.
The translator, who always seems, doesn't understand the book.
I mean, it isn't as hard to find a version better than Alistair Hanney's.
But when Kierkegaard is throwing around this term Enkela, if you don't understand the context, you can't tell whether he means particular or individual.
It's the same Danish word.
But if he doesn't even notice it's a problem, I think, because for him, he understands the context.
He knows whether he's talking about whether it's something that everybody has down here, that they're a particular.
We can put that here.
And I'll tell you when it happens so that you, in crucial passages, won't get confused.
And pretty soon, hopefully, you'll get so that you can tell, even if the translator can't, which Kierkegaard's doing.
So up here, you've become an individual.
Down here, you're a particular.
Anybody want to say anything?
I feel I've been talking a lot.
Somebody must be thinking something.
Yeah.
Aha.
A terrific question.
I know the answer.
It's not a hard, I mean, but it's the right question to ask.
And now I have to see how to formulate the answer.
They both aren't mediated.
They both have both ways of making an exception of yourself.
I mean, in a way that the child makes an exception of himself is he just doesn't care whether anybody else gets the ice cream at the birthday party.
If he could get it all, he would.
And in general, I can put it in ethical terms.
Down here, people are just like animals and children making exceptions of themselves all the time.
Here, people are doing the universal, that's another Kierkegaard term for this.
They're doing what every good, they should be doing what every good rational person should be doing.
Up here, they're making an exception of themselves again, but in a different sense.
That's the answer.
They're making an exception because there's only one lover, Beatrice, and other people can love other people.
But when you have a defining commitment, then you aren't in the universal anymore.
I mean, what we'll talk about next time, okay, in just a second, is the dramatic way that Abraham is not in the universal because his particular commitment, well, it's his is so weird that it takes a lot of explaining.
But one thing is sure, if you have a commitment that requires you to kill your son, you look like you're down here in the level of the crazies.
But if you have it as part of your unconditional, if it's your unconditional commitment who defines who you are, and we'll go into that a lot later, not yet, then you are an exception.
Or sometimes he says the exception.
So being an individual is also called being an exception.
That goes down with this universal down here.
And that's got to do with problem one and problem two, which you haven't read yet, one thing at a time, which has to do with how the person relates to the universal.
But that's what's really at stake.
The immediacy wipes out this kind of everyone for himself lower immediacy, but it gives them, it gives you that when you become an individual, you're beyond the universal, you're unique, and so forth.
Does that help?
Good.
It's a good question.
I think that's a good answer.
So we can go on.
Back there, yeah.
Why would you say that?
I mean, it seems to me both of them could be higher immediacy.
Both of them could be giving you the whole content of your life.
Ah, ah, ah, I see, I see.
Hmm.
Interesting.
You want to say something about that?
Well, somebody knows that well, not exactly, but I can see sort of.
I mean, everybody's going to have their own unique way of having their infinite passion or their unconditional commitment for Jesus or for Beatrice.
Let's just stick to that.
I mean, if Dante loves Beatrice, and so does somebody else love Beatrice, that doesn't mean that it's sort of an accident.
I mean, it could have been one person, it could have been a group.
Now, if they get together, which is his point, like the Christian community and all follow Jesus, that's a problem for Kierkegaard in a way.
I mean, Kierkegaard is a radical Protestant.
He does, I mean, he's a Lutheran.
But anyway, he doesn't think there's any place for community, for everybody, in some sense, getting anything positive out of doing the same thing as everybody else.
Every Christian is in complete isolation.
He says, I'll read it to you when we get to Dostoevsky, because Dostoevsky is interested in this, what he considers crazy version of Protestantism.
But so I'm just curious, are you religious in some religion?
You you?
Yeah.
Ah, good.
That's just what I want.
That's what I wanted to hear.
And the Catholics have certainly got the sense of the absolutely essential character of community in religion.
And there's just a new book out by Charles Taylor, which is making a big splash, 800 pages of it, make a very big splash, called The Secular Age.
Taylor is the most intelligent religious Catholic writer.
And he's got certainly the importance of community.
He wrote a book about William James about two years ago.
And James has lots of interesting things to say about religious experience in the varieties of religious experience, which is the name of his book.
But what he doesn't have is any sense that religious experience is communal, which you do with Catholics like Charles Taylor does, but Tierkegaard doesn't.
Kierkegaard thinks that being an individual is just something that is your way of being an individual, even your way of loving Jesus, if that was what the issue was, is so special and so unique that there's nothing you can share about it.
If you did, you'd be mediating it.
I mean, from a Kierkegaard point of view, the church is a disaster because it's mediating things.
I might as well say that right now.
Kierkegaard thinks that the Lutheran church, which isn't Catholic but is the state church of Denmark in his time, and maybe I think even in our time, is undermining just this kind of isolation of the true committed person.
His last book was called Attack on Christendom, in which he claimed that the church as a community was an obstacle to being able to lead a Christian life.
You really raised a can of worms in a way there.
But that's how it is with Kierkegaard.
And he certainly got some very important insight about being an individual, but he's lost something important because he can't understand any sense of community except mediation, where everybody gets together and believes the same thing.
And he thinks that's certainly not the highest thing.
So we'll get back to that when we read the Grand Inquisitor story in the Brothers Karamatsov.
But for the time being, I just, you're right to put that issue on the table.
Anybody else?
Okay, yeah.
Well, yes and no.
I mean, it just isn't individuality.
It's having this very special kind of uniqueness that gives you your defining commitment.
And the idea that he should be open to other religions, which is what you're sort of saying, that if he thinks that everybody should do their own thing, so to speak, why shouldn't they do a Buddhist thing or a whatever, Hindu thing or something like that?
That's not it.
He definitely thinks that Judeo-Christian understanding of what it is to be a self is right.
And that kind of being an individual is, if a religion denies that kind of being an individual and tries to sort of find in everybody some common thing, which is the important thing, then they're in the philosophical tradition.
And he isn't saying, well, they should do their individual thing, say, be Platonists, because if your individual thing is believing in any kind of universal human nature, then it's not the kind of individual thing Kierkegaard means.
And so, but your point is, in a way, it turns into a kind of, I don't think, intolerance is right.
I mean, Kierkegaard's more intolerant of the Lutheran Church than he is of the Buddhist, because it's the Lutheran Church which is in his way.
But it turns into a belief that once you understand what it is to be a human being, and I can't talk about this yet, but I mean, there are two possibilities.
The Kierkegaard thinks that once you understand what it is to be a human being in the West, where you were born and raised, if you are, then you will be in despair if you don't have a defining commitment.
But I think Kierkegaard thinks that if you're a Buddhist and raised in that tradition, you've got a different nature.
Remember, custom is our nature.
And you won't be in despair for being a Buddhist.
However, it's a higher kind of non-despair to be a Christian, I think he thinks, than any other, harder and better than any other religion.
And that's, you're looking worried.
I mean, that's how he thinks about it, I believe.
And remember, you don't have to believe everything Kierkegaard says.
You can do what I'm trying to do.
There's some very original and very deep insights that you could only have if you were in the Judeo-Christian tradition and if you were in there after the chivalric people and so forth.
And then there are things you don't, Kierkegaard doesn't get.
I mean, that's like community, and that's like that the other religions might be just as rewarding as the Christian, Judeo-Christian.
Okay, those are all the right, you're in the big ballpark of the right issues.
Yeah.
Doesn't that make you narrow-minded?
Yeah, I think it does.
I think it makes you, I think Kierkegaard thinks that being narrow-minded in the sense of having your own unique calling is a good thing to do, to be.
It only sort of sounds bad if you make it narrow-minded.
If you think that the universal is the highest thing and important, and that sort of the shared truth that you could get by detachment and theory and so forth, or even by other religious practices like meditation or something, if you think that's the highest, then it looks narrow-minded.
But if you think that this, the higher immediacy satisfies more of what human beings, at least in the West, really need, then it doesn't look narrow-minded.
It looks deep, that's all.
So obviously, it's the same point as his.
I mean, it's definitely not meant to be for everybody.
But remember, the Judeo-Christian tradition wasn't really meant to be for everybody.
It was a covenant with God for the Hebrews.
It got messed up by the Greeks when they thought that the Ten Commandments were for every, when later they thought the Ten Commandments were for everybody, as I understand it.
And I'm not sure I'm right, but anyway, I like to think that when God gave the Ten Commandments to the Hebrews, they were for the Hebrews.
I mean he didn't say to everybody that you should have no other God before me he just said it to them and it's it's not I've lost my train of thought what am I trying to say here Oh, just that this way of understanding what human beings are and what human beings need is what the kind of human beings that we are, given insofar as I'm talking now to Judeo-Christians in the West, insofar as custom is our nature, this is what human beings need.
And it's just part of the whole way of, the whole really different Judeo-Christian way of looking at things is to say, well, there isn't any human nature and any big universal story about what all human beings need.
Different human beings raised in different cultures have different gods, and we're talking about the one that got raised in this culture with this God.
That's part of the existentialism thing.
If you don't buy that, you're into something else, namely, you're into not the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, to talk like Pascal.
You're into the God of the philosophers.
And that's just a different ballgame.
And that's the one you learn from all your other courses here, to be rational, critical, theoretical, universal, detached, and so forth.
And that's why a course like this is very important to tell you that part of your tradition is something entirely different.
Okay, I think that's one last question, then I've got to go on.
Okay.
Dependent on what?
Ah, wow.
I think this is amazing.
Every one of the hardest, deepest issues has come out in this discussion.
Another, you guys have got, I mean, I think it's partly because I make Kierkegaard's position so clear, I take some credit.
But you guys have seen you all, you've seen every limitation in it.
And this one is that he doesn't have any notion of reciprocity at all, of what the other person cares about.
You.
He sat on his terrace of his cafe and had a defining commitment for Regina.
And it just doesn't matter to him, really, whether Regina has a defining commitment to him or not.
He sort of assumes, of course, she has, after all, he's a brilliant young man, rich and in the university and about, I think, maybe 10 years older than she and so forth.
But it never occurs to him that it matters.
And that's bad.
I mean, certainly somehow you have to get into this story relations to other people at the level of higher immediacy.
Dostoevsky tries to do it, and maybe he does do it.
Anyway, it's not that Kierkegaard couldn't do it.
Nobody can do everything.
And you're seeing the limits of what is nonetheless a very, very worked out and brilliant and deep position.
So let's go back to the one that we've got, because there's certain stuff I have to cover before the first movie.
Otherwise, I think things will be in bad shape.
The movie isn't next time, thank goodness, but it's next Tuesday.
But I've got to get enough done today, but Thursday I could do the rest.
So let's see where we are.
So, this commitment is something worth living for.
It's also worth dying for.
Malrau, a famous philosopher, said that if nothing is worth living for that isn't worth dying for, and Kierkegaard really believes that, and that leads to martyrs, the old Christian martyrs, but also Martin Luther King.
I wondered if anybody has, if anybody has the DVD of his last sermon before he died, I'd love to have it because he's got all of this in there.
He says, I think, if I remember, I don't think of me as the man who won the Nobel Prize.
Don't think of me, and there's a whole lot of things that might have defined him, but think of me as the one who led my people out of their misery into a world of justice.
And then he says that he's ready to die for that.
I remember he said it's nice to live along and have a rich old age, but I've been on the mountain, I've seen what I have to do, and I've done it, and that's so I can die tomorrow would be all right.
That's pure Kierkegaardian thinking.
Yeah, I'd love to have it.
And then I'll copy it and listen and see, because I want to see the places where I think he lists all the other possible definitions of him that aren't really his defining commitment.
Okay, let me go on here.
So the difference I've written down here, when JFK says we're going to the moon, or Bush says we're going to walk on Mars, that's interesting.
And that's a kind of commitment, but it's not a defining commitment.
Unlike with Martin Luther King, if his life is meaningless and he's in grief, if they fail to get the peace marches and fail to, if the northern whites don't show up because they're frightened by the fact that they're being killed in the peace marches, then if what he stands toward is gone, he's just lost like somebody who's loved one has died.
But of course, if it's just something else you're committed to, not an unconditional commitment, well, if JFK doesn't get to the moon, then he won't experience grief, he'll just be sorry.
And the same with the Mars thing.
We're talking about something that somebody is ready to die for, and if it fails them, then if they fail at it, then their life is lost, and the point of their life is gone.
Now, that's going to get us, but we've got to go through a lot to get there yet.
The big question, which I still have to get into, at the end last time, no, it's too early.
Sorry, I'm not going to say that now.
I'm going to get there soon enough.
Let's get back to the defining commitment because I'm still sort of telling you all about the sort of phenomenological structure, that is the description of what it's like experientially.
And now, the next thing to say is about it that in the middle of 72, you can't forget the whole thing, of course, and remain the same person.
The knight makes the movement, but what movement?
Well, movement, remember, is a way of acting.
Commitment is the one we're talking about.
Does he want to forget the whole thing?
Because in that, too, there's a kind of concentration.
No, for the knight doesn't contradict himself, and it's a contradiction to forget the whole of one's life content and still be the same.
So that is the you can't you can sort of refuse this love, this calling.
But if once you've got the calling and it defines you, you can't just drop it.
You can't say, well, this person is crazier than I realize.
I just not going to stick with this anymore.
And so forth.
Once you're in it and it defines you, you can't drop it.
Otherwise, you will be, as he says, only lower natures forget themselves and become something else.
The butterfly has forgotten it was a caterpillar.
Perhaps it will turn, the butterfly will become a fish.
Now, that's what is the lower nature?
That's lower immediacy, where they just, you go after this thing and that thing, and since none of them define you, if they don't satisfy you, you don't, you drop them and go after something else.
Deeper natures never forget themselves and never become something other than they were.
What's that?
That's higher immediacy.
The knight will remember everything, and so forth.
Yeah.
Well, it's interesting that you may have it without realizing it.
It's certainly not something, but it's something you all know about because there are so many, I mean, in our tradition, romantic love has been described and analyzed in so many movies and so many novels and so many poems and so many TV shows.
You know that you can be in love and not realize it.
Proust has it, the French are best at this.
Proust has a great description of that when Swan is in love and doesn't know it.
But what's happening, somebody observing it might know it, that they want to be near this other person all the time, that they're maybe, in the case of Swan, jealous that somebody else might be with them, and so forth.
Now, sooner or later, you'll presumably discover it, but maybe not.
I mean, it's not a question of what you think.
It's a question of how your world is organized.
If everything that person does is centered to you, and what you do, you decide on the basis of where they are and what kind of thing they're into and so forth.
You could be in love with them in the sense of they could be the defining thing in your life, whether you thought about it or not.
I think that's important.
And we might as well say another thing.
It takes a while.
This is all stuff you all know already to get into being in love.
It doesn't happen in an instant, where an instant means sort of, I don't know, an hour.
Kierkegaard says it does happen in an instant, with a capital I, so to speak, as a technical term.
That he calls an instant whatever amount of time it takes for this relationship to become defining for you.
And that might happen in, you know, love at first sight in an evening or something, and it might take years.
And he talks about it on the next page.
I think it's the next page.
No, the next page is a bad page, but we're not ready to see Kierkegaard's mistakes.
Well, let me see.
It should be very near here.
It must be right in front of me.
Where he lets it twine about every league.
Yeah, on 71.
All of this, all the kind of description of the essential experiences taking place here on 70 and 71 and 72, about eight lines down on 71.
He first makes sure that this really is the content of his life, and his soul is too healthy and proud to squander the least thing on an infatuation.
He's not cowardly, not afraid, and now this is what happens in this instant, which may be a year, who knows.
He's not afraid to let his love steal in upon his most secret and most hidden thoughts, to let it twine itself in countless coils around every ligament of his consciousness.
You see, it colors everything that he experiences.
If the love becomes unhappy, he will never be able to wrench himself free of it.
That's important.
But let me read a little bit more.
He feels a blissful rapture when he, so every nerve and so forth for the moment, for this moment is life and death.
Well, that means, in a Kierkegaard view, now this is sort of super romantic love.
And you'll see in the end, he sort of takes back this claim that he makes it now at the right, and it's right to make it at this point.
You'd only get one defining commitment.
After all, if that's your definition, it's like the definition of the triangle having three sides.
Necessarily, triangles have three sides.
They always have three sides.
They couldn't stop having three sides.
And if this is your defining thing, being the lover of Beatrice, say, or whatever, and then you got, and you let that become your way of seeing yourself and your way of seeing everything else, then it's become so much a part of you, so embodied, so much in your way you see and do everything, that you can't get rid of it.
You could betray it.
That is, you could, in some way, the only case I know of, and it is sort of dramatic.
How many have read 1984?
Okay, great.
Wow.
Well, if I remember it right, and tell me if I don't, that the whole thing that keeps, what's the name of the main character?
I don't remember.
I can't hear you.
Somebody in the front.
Winston, the only thing that keeps Winston able to be his own self is his love for this woman.
What's her name?
Sylvia?
Julia.
Okay, Winston and Julia.
Anyway, but in the end, if I remember right, because the bad forces know this fear of rats, when he's finally about to be eaten alive by the rats, he says he wishes it would happen to her and not to him, right?
And at that moment, he realizes that he's, instead of being a martyr, he has betrayed the love.
And from that moment on, he's just a zombie.
I mean, they can do anything they want with him, isn't that right?
I mean, he's no longer got any principles, any focus, any meaning on the basis of which to resist the powers.
So, I mean, that's what it would be to betray him.
That is, to do some, to actually put your interests ahead of what this calling requires of you.
You can do that, but if you do, this is the metaphor, you'll pull out your whole consciousness.
That's what Kierkegaard's trying to say with the twins about every ligament of your consciousness.
That's what happens to Winston.
Okay, let me see.
I've got to find out fast where we are.
It related to your question about how you know about it.
Who asked that again?
Okay, it's interesting that that's a Greek kind of question, and I've written down here.
It's not, from a philosophical point of view, you ought to reflect, you ought to analyze your life.
An unexamined life is not worth living, a famous Socrates comment.
This says, never mind examining your life.
The important thing is to do what in each moment is required of you according to your calling.
And you don't have to know what it is, what the calling is in a reflective sort of way.
All you have to do is see the world in the perspective that it gives you.
So the idea that it's important to get the only reason it's important to examine your life is to get from here to here, from lower immediacy to mediation.
Once you get here, then if you get called to go here, and you can't do it by your willpower, it has to be, you don't fall in love by deciding to fall in love or get a cause by deciding to have a cause.
But if a cause or a person grabs you, then up here, you don't go back here and try to analyze whether you're really up there.
That's part of the, again, the Judeo-Christian versus the Greek.
And another way to put that is you don't try to find out what are the defining features of the person you love.
That's sort of interesting.
That's to treat it as objective.
And then you think, well, let's see.
The person is smart, strong, sexy, and stylish, and witty, and compassionate.
That's all these wonderful features of the defining, of the lady, let's say, for the night.
But that can't be right.
Because if that were right, then if there were a bunch of objective characteristics that made that person adorable for you, then somebody could come along and score higher on the scales of sexy, strong, smart, stylish, witty.
And then you'd have to drop the first one for the second one.
And that's just exactly against the whole notion of this defining commitment.
So, what you have to think is, this person defines what it is to be smart, strong, sexy, stylish, witty, compassionate.
There couldn't be any higher case of it because they're the paradigm case of it.
Anybody else would just be stupidly funny or brutishly sexy or whatever.
And this is the adorable one must look to you like not like just the best thing.
Here's another way to put it: not just like the best thing in the world, highest ranking on all the scales that matter for you.
It's something that defines your world.
And it's the paradigm case of all the things that matter to you.
And therefore, it can't be mediated.
We're back to that.
That got just another way of saying it can't be mediated.
And yeah.
Okay, wait.
This is a very important issue.
It's exactly the issue of nights of resignation for next time.
Yeah, so there is all this about whether it's better to have loved and lost than never to have loved at all.
I think, well, never mind.
No, well, you're a knight of resignation, but I can't explain what that means yet.
Go ahead.
I think he thinks that if you're, he doesn't say anything about this, but I think he thinks that, and it may be tied up with because he's still got a view that, no, no, no, no, I'm not thinking out loud.
I mean, he doesn't say anything, but it ought to be the case.
It better be the case, that anybody has plenty of opportunities to have a call, and if they're not resisting it, resisting the vulnerability of it and so forth.
We'll get to that.
But if he didn't, he'd be in this position of sort of saying that some people are just damned.
That is, some people are stuck in despair all their lives, and it's not their fault, and there's nothing they can do about it.
I don't think he thinks everybody, I know where he says it in the introduction, just a second.
He says, in the world of the spirit, it always, so to speak, turns out all right.
I'll show you the passage.
And that really commits him to the view that we're talking about.
Where is that?
It's very important.
I was going to read it anyway.
Huh?
It should be right before the reflections on Abraham.
It's going to be here somewhere.
No?
Way back there.
If you're right, that's a good thing you told me before.
Yeah, that's where it is.
The beginning here.
He says in the first paragraph that in the ordinary world, it isn't the case that every time the one who works gets the bread.
There are people who don't have to work at all, and they get all this good food.
There are people who work and work, and they're in the working class, and they're very hungry lots of the time.
That's how it is in the outward world.
But, and now about 15 lines down on 57, it is otherwise in the world of the spirit.
Here there prevails an eternal divine order.
Here it does not rain on the just and the unjust alike.
Here the sun does not shine on both good and evil.
There's only the oh here only one who works gets the bread.
And that, and every, and I think it follows that everyone who works gets the bread and so forth.
But so that's okay.
That's the yeah.
What's your free?
You are free.
That's right.
You're free to accept it or not accept it.
And it's very important.
And you're free, once you've accepted it, to take different stands on it.
Both of those things I want to say for a minute.
Because that's the next question is what do you do when something's calling you, when you're about to be taken up into one of these relations?
And you can resist it.
And there's good reasons to resist it.
Okay?
Do you believe the legal or whatever that feels?
I don't know, but I don't think it matters, Kierkegaard.
I think it's at the level of everybody, you're all asking me to say things that he doesn't say, but I think he would say.
Everybody's open to getting a calling.
Everybody can have one if they're just ready for it.
It's sort of, again, the romantic love tradition.
There's nobody, no matter how sort of peculiar or seemingly unattractive, who can't find somebody who loves them or can't find somebody to love.
It's that kind of story again.
And it's open to everybody to resist falling in love because they just don't want to take on that vulnerability.
I've got to get there.
Yeah.
Yes, but you are, yes, you're showing that he's a knight of resignation.
Don't do it yet.
Next lecture.
Okay, now I've got to stick with this one.
There's so much I want to cover.
So I want to go back and tell you something that I didn't, that I'm making, that I'm, I didn't really stress it.
It doesn't change anything I wrote here, but you can't give it up.
I'm going to see.
Okay, I'm going to give you nine characteristics of the defining relation now.
What I've done is given you a few of them without naming them.
So let me go catch up.
So what makes you an individual gives you a world in which the and in that world I want to make that distinction again between the most important thing in your world is not what this is about.
The defining commitment isn't the important thing in your world like any other important thing in your world.
It gives you a world.
Why that I mean it determines what is trivial and what is serious, what is relevant and irrelevant, what is meaningful and meaningless.
So in that sense, it focuses your world.
And you didn't have a world in this Kierkegaard sense until you've got it.
Everything that's crucial for you gets referred back to this relation.
And it determines what's important.
It determines how you behave.
Not determines in the sense of make you're not free.
It's just the things that show up to do, to freely do, are all come out of this relationship because it's always been promoting this relationship and remaining true to this relationship.
The things look important, or if they're not doing that, they look unimportant.
Now, number three, and that was what I did when I talked about the strong and stylish and witty and all that, it can't be mediated.
You can't put the divining commitment into concepts.
And now I'm ready for another one.
And this is a very Kierkegaardian one: your passion or your commitment produces its object.
And what does that mean?
That means that it's because you have this infinite passion for somebody.
We'll take a person, of course, it could always be a cause.
But let's just say, but if you have this infinite passion for somebody, then they are adorable for you.
And they are your savior.
That's what Dante thought about Beatrice.
That's what the Knights thought about their ladies.
They aren't objectively adorable.
And objectively the same.
It's only while you're adoring them that they're adorable.
And only while they're saving you, that is giving your life a meaning and making you an individual that they're your savior.
So Kierkegaard makes the slogan: truth is subjectivity.
That means that they are your savior is a result of how you are true to them.
Yeah.
To commit to God.
Wow.
Have you taken Philosophy VI?
Have you read Dante?
This is a whole story behind this, and I'm so tempted to get into it, but I can't.
Dante blows it at the end.
At the end of the Divine Comedy, he drops Beatrice for God.
That's a big mistake from Kierkegaard's point of view.
That's what happens when you let the Judeo-Christian tradition get gobbled up by the God of the philosophers.
Dante finally drops Beatrice for the God of the Philosophers.
He hasn't really got it yet.
That's the move that Kierkegaard makes beyond Dante.
Anyway, so when I talk about Dante and Beatrice, I always talk about Dante before he gets to the top of paradise and gets zapped by God, after which he just becomes a kind of zombie.
That is, a quote, the end of the divine comedy, the last two lines.
Didn't I say this?
I don't guess I didn't.
His love becomes one with the love that moves the sun and the other stars.
Wipes him out as an individual.
He's just one more something or other contemplating God.
That's a medieval idea.
That's the Judeo-Christian tradition sort of gobbling up the...
Sorry, that's the Greek tradition gobbling up the Judeo.
Is that what you're asking?
So, yes, Kierkegaard thinks Dante did give up Beatrice, and that was really a bad thing to do.
I have there's words for that, but I don't want to stop with them.
So the next, that was number four.
The passion produces its object.
Truth is subjectivity.
It's not, in Kierkegaard jargon, he also says, it's not the what, but the how of the relation that matters.
Meaning, it's the infinite passion, not any objective features.
Okay, next, it's necessary and accidental, which is a very peculiar, interesting thing.
Normally, if something is necessary, it's true for all time, and it's true under all conditions, and that would be like a triangle has three sides.
And that's a definition.
And definitions should be necessary and true for all kinds.
If it's a triangle, it's going to have three sides.
That's true of any definition.
But this peculiar kind of definition is bizarre.
And it starts at a certain moment in time that you're defined as, say, the lover of Beatrice.
And if you now think of it in terms of romantic love and so forth, it's a sheer accident that you happened, that you were in this college and in this lecture, and that you met the person who was your defining commitment if you did.
It's on a plane.
And how you get this defining object for you seems totally accidental until it becomes your defining relation, at which it becomes necessary for the new you that is produced by it.
Because if you are defined as the lover of Mary, then you weren't, and then you got zapped by Mary, and now you are, and now the kind, the you that you've become couldn't have been otherwise.
Now that's very peculiar, and it leads things, people to say things like they were destined for each other for all eternity.
Because look at that, how could they be defined in terms of this love if it wasn't already somehow settled?
You can't just be that they accidentally signed up for this class and not some other.
So Kierkegaard's got this peculiar interesting story.
What from a Greek point of view is definitions are necessary and if they aren't necessary, they're just accidental.
He got a notion that something could become necessary in time and then you become defined that way and then even your past gets redefined.
So you can only remember that you once were a person, once we're living in a world that was empty and you didn't know who you were because now you know who you are and you know that you were missing it.
But at the time, you didn't.
It's just a funny, very funny kind of thing.
There's a Platonic detached necessity for triangles.
And there's a Judeo-Christian existential necessity that Kierkegaard's onto.
Something can start to be necessary at a moment of time.
That's number five.
And that structures the whole temporal field in an instant with a capital I.
That is, at the moment that you get your defining commitment, when the moment could last a year.
I'm going to call it the instant, could last a year or two or whatever.
At that instant, everything gets redefined in such a way that your past looks different to you and your future looks different to you.
And that's what I call restructures the temporal field.
Now, moreover, you get a new kind of eternity.
Not the kind that you get in Plato where you contemplate the formal structure of the universe and the mathematical relations, but a kind of eternity that happens in an instant.
And now I have to explain that, where Kierkegaard says, only in existing do I become eternal.
I mean, that sounds like complete wackiness, because after all, the logical relations are eternal, and math is eternal, and even the laws of physics are presumably eternal.
But this is a kind of eternal that's quite different.
And now I can do it fast by sort of drawing on how he pictures it.
So if you're living in time, these are moments, not instants, moments, moments, moments.
And the thing about these moments is they're always up for grabs retroactively.
So now you think you're having a great time being in Berkeley, but at exam time you may think that it's the biggest mistake you ever made.
And then you finally recover from that and you're happy again.
And you go back and then you graduate and you think this was a great experience and then later you think not and so forth.
You constantly have to reinterpret your experience because it's in time and time is just up for reinterpretation.
But if there's an instant in it where you get a defining relation, it all gets to be different.
You now know that for the whole rest of your life, which for you is forever, it's the only kind of personal, we're talking about a personal kind of eternity.
For the whole rest of your life, everything that's important will hang upon the justice of the black people or for your relation to Mary.
And even the past gets reinterpreted as it was empty.
I was lost until they found it.
I mean, Gustin is very good about explaining the different way he experienced his life before he became a Christian and how he looked at the same experiences afterward.
So there is this retroactive quality to it, and you get to be eternal in this peculiar sense, which is the way to do it is to always think of this as eternal equals forever.
Because eternal sounds too Greek, it sounds like what mathematical relations are.
Forever is the eternal for me.
It's the existential eternal.
I mean, it means for my whole life, for anything I could care about, the meaning is fixed.
And that's the eternal forever story.
Now, it's also reversible.
You can't go from one defining relation to another.
Now, we've talked about that.
It would be like tearing out your consciousness.
Luckily, I don't have to go into it again because there's not much time.
But the bottom line for all this is number nine.
That was eight.
It was irreversible.
Number nine, it makes you completely vulnerable.
That's the problem.
You put all your eggs in this basket, so to speak.
The meaning of your life and your world and what it makes sense to do it all is tied up in this.
And it has to be a relation to something finite and temporal.
It can't be a relation to a scientific theory like Galileo.
When they said that the Inquisition would torture him if he didn't take back his claim that the earth moves around the sun, he took it back and supposedly muttered under his breath as he left the courtroom, but it moves anyway.
It doesn't require him.
It's an objective truth.
But it turns out that if it's a kind of existential commitment, not a scientific theory, then it has to be to something concrete enough, finite enough, temporal enough, like a human being or a cause, to give your life meaning every minute of the time.
So when you wake up in the morning, you know what you have to do, like Martin Luther King in my picture.
But if it's relation to something finite and temporal, then of course it's something vulnerable.
The cause may fail, the lover may leave, and this is terribly crazy and upsetting.
Nobody would want to get into a relationship that's going to plunge them into grief and destroy their happiness and their world if it fails when it could fail any time.
I think this is what it means to say that this relationship is impossible, as Kierkegaard said sometimes.
It's impossible in the sense that if you think about it rationally, it doesn't make any sense to get into this relationship.
Anything that this is important ought to be completely solid.
And yet this is so important and unsolid that, and therefore, I'll just jump ahead to the night.
No, I don't.
No, I won't.
I stick to this for a minute.
So it's fragile, it's not guaranteed, and yet you're building everything on it.
And the temptation is to avoid it by doing a kind of Buddhist move, say, for non-attachment, a Plato move, merging with the good.
Every religion has a way of taking the risk away, making it possible that you can have some kind of meaning without it.
But Christianity wants, even Christianity, and that's the Dante question.
Even Christianity says, well, Dante doesn't finally really need Beatrice in the end.
It doesn't matter whether she dies or not, or whether he gets married to somebody else and all that.
It doesn't matter because his real goal is contemplation of God and God is eternal.
And so the eternal in him merges with the eternal in God, but not in Kierkegaard's Christianity.
Kierkegaard thinks that the unconditional commitment has to be to something finite.
It's the most rewarding of all human experiences and the most risky.
And now what do you do about that?
That's what I wanted to be sure and get to by 5 o'clock.
It would be great, wouldn't it, if there was a way to save the meaning of the unconditional commitment while at the same time getting rid of the vulnerability?
That's whoever, somebody here came up and said after class, is there any way to do that?
And who is he?
Somebody here?
Anyway, that's the right question to ask next.
And now, next time, I'm going to tell you about all the possible maneuvers that you could make to avoid the vulnerability and the one particular interesting maneuver you could make that not only avoids the vulnerability but saves the meaning.
That saves the fact that your life is defined by this relationship, but puts the relationship out of risk.
That's the final thing.
Now, I think we should stop with that.
That's the subject for next time.
But just so you know when you're reading what we're talking about, that's the move of the night of resignation.
Okay.