God is dead.
That is the monotheistic Supreme Being.
It isn't as if there's nobody, by the way, left in the culture who believes in the monotheistic Supreme Being.
It's just once upon a time we had a religious culture where everybody did.
Or if you didn't believe in the Supreme Being, you had to give an explanation.
Now we've got a secular culture in which the general view is irreligious, naturalistic, atheistic, or nihilistic or variations thereof.
So now, if you believe in the Christian God, you have to give the arguments for why you do.
Then that's the sense in which God isn't anymore sort of the taken-for-granted center of the culture, which we all agree on and which gives us values that we all agree on.
So all you have to do is find out what the Bible tells you or the church tells you about these things, and then everybody knows what then there's shared intelligibility.
It's not a bad idea, but it doesn't happen anymore.
And that's the sense in which Nietzsche's thought early on that there's something switched in the culture.
It's become a secular culture.
And then the interesting claim that Christianity undermined itself.
And remember, I said, this is sort of a quote I owe you, which I couldn't find, about the way it undermined it.
Well, two quotes.
On 178, the general quote: Christianity, too, has made a great contribution to the Enlightenment and taught moral skepticism very trenchantly and effectively.
It's destroyed the faith and virtues and so forth.
Never mind that part.
The idea that Christian confession and so forth have made people very sensitive and critical to their inward desires and to whether they're fooling themselves about their desires has helped undermine the Christian story.
Once upon a time, there's a kind of interesting story, I think, in here, which I didn't realize until this year.
There seem to be two contradictory views.
One, that Christianity has become so critical that it done itself in.
And I'm going to read you one that I was looking for last time.
Christians aren't critical, and they should be.
This is where I said that it looks like he's criticizing Alyasha and religious experiences.
And so here's this is an important one.
And I'll tell you what I think.
I think that he's got one view of how normal Christians normally behaved, or maybe still behave, and how really sort of cultivated Christians behave, and they've become more and more critical until they've become critical of the very idea that there is a God.
But now we're going back.
Here's how you can either say the original Christians behave, because after all, Dostoevsky is trying to get back to them, or how the current Dostoevsky-like Christians behave, which haven't got the news that God is dead.
The middle of 253.
And as interpreters of our experiences, that one, 319 aphorism.
One sort of honesty has been alien to all founders of religion and their kind.
See, you can view Dostoevsky as trying to get back to the mentality of these founders.
They have never made their experiences a matter of conscience for knowledge.
That's what people are doing now.
Now that we ask, what did I really experience?
This is what Alyasha should be asking himself, according to Nietzsche, and would be if he were a really sort of a cutting-edge Christian, but he's in the Russian back woods, Nietzsche would think.
What did I really experience?
What happened in me and around me at that time?
Was my reason bright enough?
Was my will opposed to all deceptions of the senses and bold in resisting the fantastic?
None of them have asked such questions, nor do any of our dear religious people ask them even now.
See, those are the people who are still like the early ones.
On the contrary, these people, the original ones and even the current Dostoevsky ones, thirst after things that go against reason.
And they do not wish to make it too hard for themselves to satisfy it.
So they experience miracles and rebirths and hear the voices of little angels.
That was the passage I was trying to find.
So, of course, it's complicated because Dostoevsky's ideas about miracles and rebirths and so forth are so different than the kind of credulous belief in miracles and rebirth that goes against science and our understanding of nature.
So these whole views sort of cross and mix each other and don't quite grab each other.
But Nietzsche certainly got a view that Alyosha should have been in a much more critical mind vis-à-vis his revelation.
Did I say Dostoevsky?
I mean Nietzsche.
Nietzsche should think that Alyasha should be in a more critical state.
vis-à-vis his big deal religious experience.
And of course, Dostoevsky thinks no.
I mean, nothing could be more absolutely overwhelming and therefore true because it's going to last for the rest of your life.
What more do you want than Alyacha's religious experience?
It isn't as if one or the other of them has got the right answer.
But Nietzsche's at least just sort of aiming for a non-existentialized, modern Christian who hasn't understood that they had better be much more critical of any kind of notions of miracles and rebirths that have to do with sudden cures or faces appearing on veils and such things.
He thinks that kind of belief is something that either you should have, Christians should have already talked themselves out of or are talking themselves out of.
Question back there.
He says the most important thing in an final impossible is to be relying on instinct and not even...
That's interesting.
That's very sensible.
I don't at first know what to say.
I have to think about it a minute.
I do think there are all these cross currents going, and now you've added a cross-current within Nietzsche himself.
Yes, Nietzsche thinks you should be impulsive, rely on instinct, don't sort of get detached and analyze.
He's got that whole story that Socrates is decadent and the Athenian Greeks because they step back from their sort of involvement and stop to analyze and criticize and then destroy sort of their commitment.
Good point.
How is he going to get these two things together?
Well, this may be a lesson in Nietzsche that you can't expect Nietzsche to sort of add up into one coherent system.
He doesn't want to do it.
He doesn't want a coherent system.
I think he thinks that's part of philosophy and metaphysics.
He wants a lot of perspectives and interpretations, but he doesn't want, he doesn't and he doesn't mind, I think, maybe even if they contradict each other and would say something like, well, in some situations, this is, I think, Nietzsche's way of answering, in some situations, you better be self-critical.
If what's going on is something that goes against nature and the rest of common sense, and you're going to build your whole life on it, you better be critical of it.
In other situations, the best thing you can do is trust your instincts and go with them, and there's no higher position in which to tell you which kind of situations you could do which.
That's already a question of everybody has their own interpretation.
That's my best answer to you.
It's something like that in Nietzsche.
Nietzsche's got and and Nietzsche says anything that he thinks is true from any perspective.
And he's got lots of perspectives.
And he thinks there is only perspectives.
There's not, remember, one answer that adds up to the truth.
That's part of what it is to believe in God.
That's part of why scientists still and metaphysicians are still believers in God in this sense where now God isn't the Christian supreme being, but is what the Greeks and the Christians both believe in, namely one unified, objective truth.
So that there must be some right answer to what's happening.
There's no right answer to what's happening.
It's all interpretation, all the way down.
I haven't read the interpretation passages, have I?
Okay, I've got to write a note to myself.
Split through the cracks somehow.
I haven't said that, except just asserted it.
I haven't read any passage ever.
I don't think so.
Did I?
No, I don't know.
It's fine.
Bring it up now, but I better write it down.
Okay, good question.
That really brought out something important.
Okay, so now we're critical.
And now that's all the sort of bits of leftovers from last time that I promised to read you, like the Voices of Little Angels passage, which I couldn't find.
Now I'm going on to where we were last time, still a little bit of reviewing.
We've talked about the collapse of all meaning because the cataclysm that occurs uniquely in a civilization, in a culture that has been completely monotheistic and built all of their values into one God and one religion, and then loses that.
Then there is this total collapse.
And now we've also, we talked about that, and we talked about how it's going to cause all kinds of chaos and disaster because nobody will have any guidelines anymore.
And that for Nietzsche, it's cheerfulness.
That's the 279 important passage.
I want to go on about cheerfulness now.
What kind of cheerfulness can you have?
Well, you can't get meaning back.
Remember, we talked about that.
You burn the bridges behind you when you put everything into one basket and then lose the basket, so to speak.
There's no going back to the old unified, rationally justified or justified by revelation world.
When once everybody realizes that God is dead, that's finished.
So what do you do?
Well, the short-term statement of it is: we must become gods ourselves.
But what in the world does that mean?
Now we've caught up to where we were.
We want to understand what it is to live like a free spirit.
Because Nietzsche's name for the people who are cheerful and know how to live and live better than anybody ever lived, thanks to this collapse, who have got a new health, who have got because they have, they're, so to speak, the cultural convalescence who have survived this disaster and therefore are stronger than ever, or anybody ever was.
Okay, the free spirits, we've got to understand.
A whole new way of life.
Nietzsche understands, and this is where he's so fascinating.
And today is perhaps the most, I hope, fascinating lecture because it's what's really interesting is that Nietzsche understands that he's got to invent a whole new understanding of values.
What makes life worth living?
What are human beings at their best doing, etc.?
I mean, he's got to start from scratch and substitute a whole new way of understanding us and the world and our life in the world for this complete collapse.
And there's nothing to, almost nothing to go on.
But there is one clue for him, and he takes it.
But first, let me just say, he knows that he's trying to invent a whole new set, a whole new set of values, as he puts it.
It comes up at the bottom of 265, for instance, the creation of our own new tables of what is good.
That's that the most important statement of it, and I think there are other places, but the one you've got in your hands, if you brought Twilight, which I didn't tell you to do.
But anyway, the last sentence of Twilight, sorry, of Antichrist, which is the last sentence of that book that you've got, is he's going to talk about the re-evaluation of all values.
Which book does he, some of you may know Nietzsche better than I do, which book does he have as the epigraph?
This is the book.
Is that the genealogy of morals?
One of them says this book is the re-evaluation of all values.
Or is it Beyond Good and Evil?
Anyway, he knows that that's what he's up to.
And he even says that that's what one of his books is about.
Somebody has a hand up.
You have?
Good.
I thought Laura's the entire category was on the philosophy.
Terrific question.
Absolutely the right question to ask.
The answer is: if he gave you any specific values, he would be contradicting himself in a way that even Nietzsche, who doesn't mind contradictions, wouldn't want to do it.
There's no more universal truths.
There's no more values that everybody can see our values and agree on.
Well, what in the world has he got then as new values?
Well, they're sort of meta-values.
It's really the values of having no new values, but that you have to explain how that could be a value.
That's what he's up to.
And how do you do that?
Well, you do it by, remember I said there's one thing which he holds on, one idea which he holds on to as the kind of guideline.
He's got to have something to go on.
And I said it last time.
The one value that he accepts and is going to build all this on is life.
We are part of life, and life is constant overcoming and outgrowing.
And of course, that's a funny kind of value.
It's no particular value.
It says, in fact, just what he said.
Nietzsche's against you thinking you've got some universal, eternal value to hang on to.
But there is something to hang on to.
You want to be powerful, healthy, expanding, constantly overcoming.
Those are all the kind of values that he's putting on when he transvaluates the table of values.
And one of the places I got it, I marked it where I find it on 291 at the bottom.
The wish to preserve oneself is the symptom of a condition of distress at a limitation, distress, of a limitation of the really fundamental instinct of life, which aims at the expansion of power.
That's just one of the places where he says it.
And he says, and at the end of that aphorism on 292, the great and small struggle always revolves around superiority, around growth and expansion, around power, in accordance with the will to power, which is the will of life.
So you see what I mean?
I mean, you're right, no fixed, no universal values, but a new table of values nonetheless.
That's now what is it that everybody can't help but pursuing?
But some of them are so weak they don't do it very well.
But the more, the better the human being, the more they understand that their job is to have this, to do this living thing.
Now, what the living thing is, I haven't explained yet.
We have to understand that.
But whatever it is, just to say it again, this person in tune with life and constantly going beyond wherever they are, growing, expanding, and so forth, they are the free spirit or the new man.
And that's what we got to find out about.
So, I've talked about everything, but page, did I do page 100?
I don't think so.
No, one more quote.
The middle of 100.
What is life?
Life, that is, is constantly shedding something that wants to die.
Life, that is, being true and cruel and inexorable against everything about us that is growing old and weak, and not only about us.
Anybody, who's old and weak, anything old and weak, you could be cruel and try to put it out of its misery.
Yeah.
Hang on, you sort of forgot those guys that didn't want to.
Yes, well, yeah, we've got to be careful.
I forget, did you say the Homeric Greeks?
You've got to be, you know, you're very careful when you say Greeks.
I'm sure that's what you meant.
The question is whether the Homeric Greeks have somehow already got a sense of this, which the culture has lost thanks to the Athenian Greeks, those decadent and weak Plato and Aristotle trying to find universal moral principles, and thanks to the Hebrews and Christians, those decadents trying to find the same kind of universal principles by revelation.
The Homeric Greeks were happily polytheists.
We get to that now.
He really likes that.
But that would jump me way ahead of where I'm in my lecture.
You do this.
But let me see if I can do that and still come back without confusing things.
Let's try it.
Yeah, okay.
There are two things one could talk about at this point.
I was going to talk about the way the current free spirits should live.
And that is having brief habits.
Just put that in aside for a while.
It'll take at least half an hour when I get back to it.
But we could instead, instead of starting with how you should live as a free spirit now, we could start with how did the people who were nearest to free spirits before all this decadence set in lived, and that would be the Greeks.
So let's look on the Homeric Greeks on 242.
Okay, this is about the happiest of 302.
To have refined senses, including a sense of taste and so forth.
We don't need that.
To enjoy a strong, bold, audacious soul, to go through life with a calm eye and firm step, always prepared to risk all.
That's part of the free spirit.
Festively impelled by the longing for undiscovered worlds.
See, going beyond, to undiscovered worlds and seas, people, and gods.
We're going to come back to that a lot.
It's the constant discovery of new stuff, new horizons, new worlds, new gods, to hearken to all cheerful music as if it were a sign that bold men, soldiers, and seafarers were seeking their rest and pleasure, and in the most profound enjoyment of the moment to be overcome by tears and crimson melancholy of the happy.
Who would not wish all this might be his possession, his state?
That was the happiness of Homer.
So that's the answer that you were pointing to.
Yes, the nearest thing to what he wants people to have is what the Greeks, what the Homeric Greeks had.
And he finds it in polytheism.
Now we're on page 191.
The greatest advantage of polytheism.
For an individual to posit his own ideals and derive from it his own laws, joys, and rights.
Remember, keep your eye on what he said.
He can't be proposing any particular laws or rights, but each person has their own.
And that may well have been considered hitherto the most outrageous human aberration as idolatry itself.
I mean, he thinks that up to the Homeric Greeks and their kind of polytheism, every culture was trying to make everybody into conformists, because that's how cultures work best and start indoctrinating their children into the universal principles.
He talks a lot about that sort of training, which he's against.
But now let's go on.
The few who dared as much, that is, to make up their own laws, always felt the need to apologize to themselves, saying, it wasn't I, not I, but a god through me.
The wonderful art and gift of creating gods, polytheism, was the medium through which this impulse could discharge, purify, protect, perfect, and ennoble itself.
Skipping down now, the bad thing is, about five lines down, there was only one norm, man, and every people thought that it possessed this one ultimate norm.
That's what I just said.
Every culture has some idea of what the essence of human being is, what human beings are here for, what human beings ought to do that's good, what human beings shouldn't do that's bad.
But above and outside, in some distance overworld, one was permitted to behold, and now what the Greeks saw, a plurality of norms.
One God was not considered a denial of another God or blasphemy against him.
The invention, skipping a little, of gods, heroes, and overmen of all kinds, as well as near men, and undermen and dwarfs and fairies and so forth and so forth, was the inestimable preliminary exercise for the justification of the egoism and sovereignty of the individual.
Remember, egoism is a good thing, because that means that you are making up your own laws and doing what you decided is a good thing for you to do.
Now, of course, that makes monotheism the enemy going on.
Monotheism, on the other hand, this rigid consequences of the doctrine of one normal human type, that is, one human nature, the faith in one normal God, besides whom there are only pseudo-gods, that's the supreme being.
There are lots of idol worshipper gods and lesser gods, but that's the creator god.
The faith in one normal God, and so forth, was perhaps the greatest danger that has yet confronted humanity.
He had plunged humanity into 2,000 years of darkness, he would say.
The only happy news is that out of that sickness, finally, the culture overcame it and became healthier than ever, namely Nietzsche.
But it was a close shave.
Now, the end of the paragraph.
In polytheism, the free-spiriting and many-spiriting of man attained its first preliminary form: the strength to create for ourselves, and this is now typical, our own new eyes, and ever again new eyes, ever more our own.
That means new interpretations, new ways of looking at things.
There are always more possible new ways of looking at things.
As I'll say more later, artists are his model of this.
There's an endless number of new ways to see the world, to paint the world, to make buildings, to make music, and so forth.
And the free spirit is doing something like that.
Though they may be, and I'll get back to that later too, turning their own life into a work of art.
That's okay, too.
But polytheism was the beginning of that.
And now comes a crucial sentence.
Ever get new eyes, more our own.
Hence, man alone among all animals has no eternal horizons and perspectives.
That's a funny line.
If you've thought about, for instance, Kierkegaard, Kierkegaard thinks that animals, like the caterpillar that turns into a butterfly and might turn into a fish, are just exactly not eternal.
What's great about human beings is they can get the eternal in time and get an identity that they have all their lives.
But animals go changing all the time.
And Nietzsche just flips that around and says, no, no, animals never change.
They've got their fixed way of being, cats or dogs or even caterpillars and butterflies.
They always do turn from caterpillars to butterflies.
It's all built into their genes.
It's just that that's what that species does.
Species are eternal, in the sense now Nietzsche's eternal.
Namely, they can't change, they can't get new eyes, they can't get new understandings.
Only human beings can change.
And so now it turns out that for Nietzsche, what Kierkegaard called lower immediacy, namely being able to change your nature and never having anything fixed and eternal about your nature, that man is constantly reinventing what it is to be a human being, that turns out to be the highest thing.
That's a new kind of higher immediacy.
That's a Nietzsche kind of higher immediacy.
Constantly reinventing yourself.
We'll get back to that.
But we can do it in this order.
So now, yes, I just want to.
So, yes, so we can create, I'm going to keep track of these way of doing this now.
We can create new gods and give our life a new style, and animals can't do this.
Man is, as Nietzsche says somewhere else, the underdetermined animal.
That is, man has no nature.
That makes Nietzsche an existentialist.
Remember, in the very beginning, I said Pascal says that custom is our nature.
That's a step in the right direction, Nietzsche would say.
Only you shouldn't let custom give all the people in your culture your nature, even relative to your culture.
Each individual should give themselves their version of human nature.
That doesn't have any content.
It doesn't offer any guidelines.
It's way beyond metaphysics and revelation.
And in a certain, so far, so good.
Yeah, a hand.
Okay.
Has that been your hand up long?
I suddenly felt the strange power from over there.
Go ahead.
Ah, well, yes, Sartre, of course, is living off Nietzsche, like all of the existential thinkers.
Sartre thinks that there is no human nature, and we had existence precedes essence.
And he says this: how many have read the Sartre existentialism as a humanism in high school?
Probably several.
Okay, but Sartre sort of blows it.
He even was sort of ashamed of that talk, and tried to keep it from being published and reproduced, and now everybody reads it.
Because then he said, but each person who chooses chooses for all human beings, remember, and turns it into something universal, which makes no sense because what about these other human beings?
They're supposed to be choosing for themselves.
So how could you choose for them?
Each person, that just contradictory.
But he was trying to be to sort of make existentialism look less radical for some reason or other at that point.
I guess to make it more acceptable to people.
But he was losing it.
So Sartre took the part of it that he should have been the main part of it, that existence precedes essence, that human beings have no nature.
That's the Nietzsche claim.
Go ahead.
He would assume the entire universe for all persons I can't come describing a person unable to experience everyone else, unable to purely know how things are experienced by another person.
And because of that, that if you choose, you choose, because you are the only human that actually can experience what you're experiencing.
But that's good.
But then doesn't he also say that and you do it as if you were choosing for everybody?
Well, good.
I mean, maybe that we could go back and look and see if we can help us help him out that way.
But since he's not in the course, we won't we I won't worry about it.
You guys can go back and look.
But but if you at least we can all agree that he's that Nietzsche and Sartre are following out what Pascal started, namely that human beings have no essence.
In Kierkegaard, it's going to be tricky because it looks like they've got a self with a lot of content and structure.
The way I read Kierkegaard is like Pascal.
That is, Christianity has created a human being.
Remember, Nietzsche thinks that Christianity creates a certain kind of human being, namely a meaning addict.
And Kierkegaard would think, too, only where Nietzsche thinks that's sick.
Kierkegaard would say that's the culmination of human culture.
Christianity created a self which has to have an unconditioned commitment in order to stay out of despair.
But it's still nothing, it's not human nature, if I understand Kierkegaard.
It's this particular Christian culture which did it.
But then Nietzsche goes one step beyond Kierkegaard because it isn't something that's shared by every Christian anyway.
It's each person on their own has to choose what it is to be a human being and live by that.
And then we're at Sartre, which is fine.
Okay?
I think that's, you guys are getting it as far as I can tell by looking at you.
So there's one more little wrinkle on it.
I mean, we could stop right there.
But I think it's interesting in the light of the third man movie and Orson Welles' great speech, which we haven't really done enough justice to, that of course all the people who are free are free spirits and have become gods themselves in the sense that they are defining their world and their eyes and so forth.
All of them will naturally naturally be perceived as evil.
That's because, of course, they're denying the current world and its values and acting against them, or at least as if they had no claim on them.
This is what Anietch is talking about on page 79.
The strongest and most evil spirits have done the most to advance humanity.
What does that mean?
Well, it means that, skipping down, they have been toppling boundary markers, violating pieties.
Oh, there's this great quote very near the end of the book, which I wanted to bring in but didn't see how.
Now I can see.
On 347, you can see how they're violating pieties.
They confront about the last eight lines of the cop aphorism.
These are the free spirits.
They confront all earthly seriousness so far, all solemnity in gesture, word, tone, eye, morality, and task, as if it were their most incarnated involuntary parody.
In spite of all this, okay, that's enough.
That they laugh at the current rules, at the sacred, and so forth.
So let's go back to 79.
In every teacher and preacher of what is new, we encounter the same wickedness that made conquerors notorious, skipping down.
What's new, however, is always evil, being that which wants to conquer and overthrow the old boundary markers and old pieties.
And only what is old is good.
Yeah, okay, so now you can, and that, remember, is supposed to be in the Orson Welles version, the famous line in that under the borgias, we had there was bloodshed and murder, and I forget all the bad things that happened, and they produced Leonardo and Michelangelo and so forth.
Under the Swiss, there was 2,000 years of democracy and peace.
And what did they produce, Holly?
The cuckoo clock.
I mean, that's a very Nietzschean speech that says it's only the people who are changing worlds who are advancing the human race, and they're advancing the human race by destroying the current world and setting up new values.
And that's what human beings do.
They're the only animal that does that.
And when they do that, they are doing sort of they are at their best.
And the Swiss are just the normal, boring, conservative people who preserve what is to go on.
They preserve what is old and good.
The good men are in all ages, those who dig the old thoughts and so forth and so forth.
Did I see another hand there?
Yeah.
Absolutely.
And it's, we're going to get to that, but I can say it already.
When you get some new values established, then they pretty soon become old values.
And then people begin to think that's the right way to behave, or the person who has them begins to think if it's an individual, that's the right way to behave.
And then they've lost something crucial, which I haven't explained yet.
And if I just jump in here with it, it'll only confuse you.
We haven't really said what you get out of life if you live in this free spirit way.
But you ought to be able to see that one sure thing you don't get is some kind of eternal meaning.
So Nietzsche is going to have to, if you're going to reevaluate values, give you a new understanding of what it is like to live life at its best, what experience, how that feels.
I'm going to read that in just a minute, but keep that in mind.
But I want to just do one more thing with the thing we're following out, and that is he has this very interesting idea that these new people who change the culture by changing the values do it by picking up some old values that were once important and then got routinized until they didn't have any power anymore and bring them back in such a way that they get new power.
I think that's because of the Homeric Greeks.
There's a kind of circle in this lecture, it turns out.
That is, it's a very interesting idea.
It means that there are sort of marginal practices around from other stages of the culture, which you could go back and retrieve and make important again in some new way.
I mean, we can't go back to Homeric polytheism for sure, but Melival and Moby Dick wants a new polytheism.
I've mentioned that before.
That's the story of Philosophy VI, with the way I think about it.
But here's just the general idea, which is so interesting, of how you get, how you find something to sort of hang on to, to start a new world around, by picking up something from the past.
It's an unusual thing.
Nietzsche calls it in one place a leap from the wings to center stage.
That means some marginal practice which is still around, you convert it into some central practice, and you make the central practice marginal.
That's how you change a world.
That's really an interesting, original idea.
So here it is on 84.
I prefer to understand the rare human beings of an age as suddenly emerging, late ghosts of past cultures and their powers, as atavisms of a people and its mores.
That way one really can understand a little about them.
You see, if they were totally strange, just totally, utterly unrelated to the past, you wouldn't be able to make any sense out of them at all.
Now they seem strange, rare, extraordinary.
And whoever feels these powers in himself must nurse, defend, honor, and cultivate them against another world that resists them until he becomes either a great human being or a mad and eccentric one who perishes early.
Now that's interesting, because one way is to become a new, important, powerful human being.
I'm going to argue next time that, according to Nietzsche, Jesus was in the prank.
But you could, and this gets us to, well, if you had a whole new way of looking at things, like Jesus might, almost totally different than the Hebrews, though not quite, otherwise, it wouldn't make any sense at all.
Then, and one possibility is that you transform the world.
That's what Jesus did, He created the Christian world.
But another possibility is you go crazy because there's not enough in what you under, there's not enough overlap between what you suddenly see in a new way and any way that anybody has ever seen anything before.
Who am I sort of thinking about now?
Who goes crazy because he understands something the way Jesus must have understood it?
Who's the Jesus figure in the brothers?
Markle.
Markle has such an incredibly crazy vision of the world.
Remember, to us, Markle makes some sense, but to Markle, Markle didn't make much sense.
Now he says you should wash the feet of your servants.
But in an age when the servants were servants and the bosses were bosses, that was just outrageous.
And Markle didn't know what he was talking about, except that that's what he felt.
And he felt that you must love the birds and so forth and ask even the forgiveness of the birds.
That's even too outrageous for Christianity.
Christianity doesn't believe that.
I mean, St.
Francis believes it, but it's certainly not anywhere in the Credo that you have to love the birds and ask their forgiveness.
And certainly, I don't think Luther thought so.
But so you can have a view so radically strange that you will go crazy.
That's what happened.
And Nietzsche is considering both.
You either change the world, if you pick up enough pieces of the past, you can change the world.
If you're really too utterly radically coming up with a new world, that's very powerful, but it's so dangerous that it will destroy you.
That's, I think, what Dostoevsky thinks happened with, well, Jesus is sort of in between.
I mean, it was radical enough so that it destroyed him, Dostoevsky thinks, using the Markle example.
But it was just enough understandable that it got caught up by the people who then took it to the monasteries and digested it and understood it and so forth.
That's the three-stage version: a crazy stage, a socializing stage, and finally the stage where we are all in, according to Dostoevsky, the stage where Christianity is going to go out into the world and existentialize everything in a good way.
Okay, that's now back to where I was.
I said the next thing we have to talk about is what it feels like to be a free spirit.
But I was just stopping here.
I'm done with the new opening new worlds story for a while.
I'll come back to it.
Okay, everybody's with it.
Your questions have been very, very on the mark.
So, okay, here's lots of different ways of being a free spirit.
There are at least three.
But I'm going to start with, okay, I'm going to start with the one which I think is the most clear and original and gives you a sense of what sort of feeling could replace meaning and a sense of the eternal in time and a sense of your having an identity, all of which should give you bliss, according to Kierkegaard.
If you're going to throw all that out, what in the world are people going to live for?
And why will they be joyful and get out?
What will they get out of it?
Okay, well, here we go.
We're going to have a new set of values, and Nietzsche is going to explain it first, sort of in a very down-to-earth way, as it is in his life.
I love this passage, which is nobody else needs to pay any attention to, as far as I know.
On page 236, brief habits.
I think brief habits has just everything in it that you need to, at the simplest level, and then you just sort of magnify it enough and you get the whole big picture of the free spirit.
So I love brief habits, he says at the bottom of 236, and consider them an inestimable means for getting to know many things and states down to the bottom of their sweetness and bitterness.
My nature is designed entirely for brief habits, and even the needs of my physical health and so forth and so forth.
Now, what is this brief habits story?
And now we get it.
I always believe that here is something that will give me lasting satisfaction.
Brief habits, too, have the faith of passion, the faith in eternity.
See, that's exactly Kierkegaard.
I don't think he knew any Kierkegaard.
He's inventing Kierkegaard.
All these guys are so smart that they invent all the positions around where they are.
So passion, remember, faith for Kierkegaard is infinite passion, and it gives you eternity in time.
And now Nietzsche is certainly not proposing that.
But it sounds like it.
And he's saying, well, you can be so involved with someone or something that it seems to be your whole world and will be the main thing in your life forever in that special sense of forever.
But he says, and that I am, and going on, that I'm envied for having found and recognized.
That is, somebody you are infatuated with, some way of life.
He gives a whole list a little while later.
And now it nourishes me at noon and in the evening and spreads a deep contentment all around itself and deep into me so that I desire nothing else without having any need for comparisons, contempt or hatred.
Now comes the new mood.
So far it might be any unconditional commitment.
But one day it's time is up.
No eternity for Nietzsche.
The good thing parts from me, not as something that's come to nauseate me, but peacefully and sated with me as I am with it.
So in effect, you outgrow it.
You love somebody, and after a while, I'm sort of skipping ahead of the story, it seems absolutely satisfying and makes you happy and happy with yourself and happy with the world.
And then after a while, it stops working.
And then you just outgrow it.
And then when you lose it, you don't feel grief the way you do when you lose your defining commitment.
Your world doesn't go blank and gray and so forth.
Not at all.
The old habit, the old person, the old commitment just says goodbye.
And then even then, something new is waiting at the door.
Along with my faith, the indestructible fool and sage that this new discovery will be just right.
This will be the last time.
So that was infatuation, but next time it's going to be real love, or that was me being swept away by some city.
He talks about doing feeling this for a city, and then it's never going to change again.
This happens to me with dishes.
It's an amazing list.
Dishes, ideas, human beings, cities, poems, music, doctrines, ways of arranging the day, and lifestyles.
They're all such that you can become completely hooked on them, absorbed in them, think that your life would be impossible without them, that you're going to have them forever, all the Dostoevsky, Kierkegaard, and Eternity story.
And moreover, you outgrow them.
But every time you do, you feel then that the next one comes.
So sooner or later, mostly sooner, something else will come around that you're attached to in this way.
And you'll feel you're never going to outgrow it, but you'll outgrow it.
And now, what's going on there?
What's interesting to me was I sort of thought, why doesn't he experience grief?
Well, because whatever this grief habit commitment is, commitments the word he doesn't like.
Commitments are prisons.
So let's not call it a commitment.
Absorption.
Whatever this special kind of something that you get absorbed in in this way that seems completely satisfying is not giving you meaning, and it's not giving you an identity because meaning is something that you can't, you don't want to outgrow because we're meaning addicts, and your identity is something you don't want to lose, because I guess we're identity addicts too.
And so it can't be, and that would give you grief.
But this doesn't give you grief.
So what's he getting out of this kind of absorption?
Well, what he's getting out of it is wonder, excitement.
And as long as the city or the music or the person that you're with is exciting and constantly showing you new things, then you are happy, cheerful, to use his word.
But unlike meaning, into the very notion of what is fun, exciting, wonderful, is built the fact that it's going to wear down because it will presumably stop being fun eventually.
It'll get boring.
And then you'll need a new one.
Meaning doesn't do that.
When you've got meaning, you don't get bored.
You want to hold on to it no matter what.
And if you lose it, you go into grief.
Your world loses all.
It stops being worth living.
Now, here you see him right at works.
They're inventing a new kind of value, but in this case, a new kind of feeling that goes with being a new kind of person, a free spirit.
I think it's helpful to see what happens to the meaning addicts.
They all think that you've got to hold on to meanings, because if you don't, your world will collapse and your life will become meaningless.
And therefore, you should.
Now comes this interesting move.
Either you either you think like Plato and Buddhists who have a lot in common about this, that you should never become completely addicted to anything, attached to anything in this absorbed way, because you're bound to lose it.
Not out of boredom, but because it's vulnerable.
And then you will go into grief.
So the only way to avoid suffering would be to avoid commitment to anything finite and temporal.
That's the Plato-Buddhist way.
And the Kierkegaard way is, well, you've got to believe in God and that all things are possible.
And then you will be able to get, change your meaning in this way that we talked about, where you can interiorize the old meaning and get a new one.
But you never can give up the old one, because otherwise you lose yourself and your world.
So the meaning story is what we've been having, and it goes off in one direction.
Now, if what you want is excitement and wonder, you get just the opposite.
Whereas meanings you've got to hold on to, or else your world collapses and you're in grief.
Wonder is something you can't hold on to.
It forces you to speak to go into new worlds because any particular wonder world is going to stop being wonderful.
It's sort of like, I just realized, the difference between finding some person that you're involved with as adorable, the way Dante feels about Beatrice.
Literally, you adore them, they are the center of your world, they give your life meaning.
Without them, you're going to be lost.
And if they are lost, if they leave you, you'd be in grief.
That's finding them adorable.
Finding them wonderful is supposed to be they're not like your God and they're not the center of your world, and you adore them.
Well, I'm sorry, you find them wonderful as long as they are wonderful.
And when they start surprising you and filling you with wonder, then they lead you, they leave you, and therefore leave you ready and able, if you're healthy, to get a new world.
So that's, I mean, so Nietzsche's really changing the whole picture of what it is to be involved with somebody or something, and changing the whole value of it, and making, and that's really quite an amazing feat.
So let me say more.
Now, but Nietzsche doesn't claim to be, I guess, I'm not sure about this, a fully free spirit, because at the end of 237, he, I don't know what's happening here.
So far, I can understand that he thinks that you should get some absorption.
Remember, I can't call it a commitment because commitments, he thinks, are forever, and that's a prison.
But get some, what can I say?
Adoration is wrong too.
That's too religious.
Get some, we don't have a good word yet for a wonder object.
That's what you've got to create if you're going to go on being a Nietzschean.
Come and tell me if you've got one.
What?
Connection?
That's too weak.
You've got all sorts of connections, I think, to your bank and to your school and so forth.
Of course, your school could be a wonder object.
But anyway, I'll just call it a wonder object.
Well, whatever's wonderful for you and makes your life exciting.
So, but he's, I don't, I mean, I think he thinks, this is just a tough one.
I leave it with you.
In the brief habits, you establish a habit and then you outgrow it.
What would it be like to be constantly changing your world?
Well, he says that would be awful at the bottom of 237.
Most intolerable, to be sure.
And the terrible par excellence would be for me, that Nietzsche, a life entirely devoid of habits, a life that would demand perpetual improvisation, that would be my exile in my Siberia.
Yet, I think maybe he thinks that the fully free spirit is going to be perpetually innovating.
I don't even know what that would look like, but I'll tell you where he talks about it.
On 290, and I can't tell how 290 is supposed to, but this is Nietzsche.
I mean, sometimes you just can't tell how that's supposed to fit with this.
My way of reading it is that Nietzsche's an almost free spirit.
That's why for him, a life of devoid of habits would be just unlivable.
But habits is a sort of bad thing, I think, maybe for Nietzsche, because that keeps you from having ever new eyes and ever new worlds.
But anyway, here's what he says on 290.
Is that where I want to be?
Yeah, at the very bottom of 289, it starts.
He wants to, one could conceive of a pleasure and power of self-determination, such a freedom of the will that the spirit would take leave of all faith and every wish for certainty, being practiced in maintaining itself on insubstantial ropes and possibilities and dancing ever near abysses.
Such a spirit would be the free spirit par excellence.
Well, that can't be Nietzsche then, because he just said he couldn't stand it if he were wholly, constantly maintaining himself on insubstantial ropes.
So I think that's all right.
I mean, just as who else did?
Well, Kierkegaard didn't claim to be a Christian.
He wrote his Christian books, two of them, under a pseudonym of somebody really who was able to live in this totally contradictory way that he describes the night of faith.
And I think Nietzsche doesn't consider himself a free spirit, but almost.
Now, where are we here?
So I have lots to say about I still have brief habits, so I sort of go on.
Oh, here's a passage I left out now on page 88.
I mean, this is about how I said Nietzsche understands in the brief habits that you outgrow each brief habit if you're healthy.
And here's what he said, and that's just how brief habits are, because brief habits are what's exciting, and things don't stay exciting.
But let's look at the middle of 88, and then I thought Beatrice wants to say something.
But the middle of the top paragraph, a little below the middle.
Gradually we become tired of the old, of what we safely possess.
We stretch out our hands again.
Even the most beautiful scenery is no longer assorted of our love after we have lived in it for three months.
And some more distant coast attracts our avarice.
Possessions are generally diminished by possession.
And it's true of everything.
The music that you find absolutely mind-boggling, if you listen to it enough, it gets to be boring.
And according to him, even a person that you find totally exciting will inevitably get to be boring.
Now, I think I should say he doesn't mean that you couldn't stay with the same person all your life.
It's unlikely, I think he thinks, but possible, that you will just find the same person so exciting and so full of changes, and you and they will change in such a way that it'll always be exciting to be with them.
And that's all right with him.
It's just that you've got to be ready to sort of give up what's become boring when it does become boring.
Now, Beatrice first, and then you.
Beatrice, yeah.
Yeah.
Yes.
How do you make sense of your actions when there's no identity tying them together?
What ties them together is something outside of you, which for a while you become attached to.
And we agree probably that that ties you together.
But what ties you together from that to the next to the next?
I think nothing.
I think there is no lasting self, according to Nietzsche.
At the limit, you are the lover of Mary, and then you are the lover of Florence, where I mean the city, now, not the girl, and so forth.
And your life is a series of short stories, not a novel.
You don't need a, you can't have, you could have a life as a novel.
That would be a very boring life, according to him.
And there's no you.
There's just a series of short stories, it looks like.
I think he'd be happy with that.
You don't need what?
No, well, your past will seem to you something that I guess I'm just thinking about the phenomenon.
Your past will seem to you something that you once found very exciting, but which you can't find exciting anymore.
Just like I felt about Beethoven's Ninth Symphony at one point.
I don't feel that way about it anymore.
But I know that it blew my mind to play it when I was really wrapped up in it.
That just seems the way it goes.
Okay?
Yeah.
To have one habit after the next, you wouldn't, you know, be broadened.
Well, that's the, I see the question.
Yeah, can you be aware?
And the answer is in the brief habit passage, he's very interesting on that subject.
Because that's the sort of where he's a fool.
Remember where it says, now I've lost it.
Tell me where the tell me where the brief habits are.
What?
You believe because you have this fool in you.
I've got to find my quote again.
Where is my brief habits?
236.
You're asking exactly the right question about this.
There's something, and even something new is waiting at the door, along with my faith, this indestructible fool and sage, that this new discovery will be just right, that it will last, this will be the last time.
So you're both in it and think this is the last time and realize that it won't be the last time.
It's something like infatuation.
Because you've got to really think this is it, and know that you've thought this is it lots of times, so why should this be it?
And yet you think, well, all those times we're wrong, but this is it.
And a funny frame of mind is what he's talking about.
Yeah.
How do you prevent something from becoming part of the herd?
Well, you become part of the herd, I think, only if you're weak.
And if you're weak, you grab hold of what one does and do what everybody does as you're giving you your identity, and you won't be able to be a free spirit.
But once you are a free spirit, you won't be able to find any wonder and fun and excitement in doing what normal people normally do.
Is that mind I answering you?
Oh, maybe he's going to say something on it.
So the herd tendency, which isn't that all human nature, the desire.
Yes, I think it is.
It's, well, no, no, it's not human nature.
It's that every culture tries to train people into that.
And that's because it works better as a culture that way.
But it's not human nature, and the free thinkers can break out of it and do break out of it, and then they look crazy or evil.
Okay.
Yeah.
Ooh, I have no idea, but I don't want to talk about it because it's not in our reading.
And it's a whole can of worms all of its own.
There's a dozen interpretations of it, and each one would have its own way of fitting it in.
I take the whatever amendments and not talk about it.
Okay.
Now, now so where are we?
Let's see.
I want to see if I've covered everything about brief habits.
But then we can go on to the next thing.
The brief habits are in the wonder business.
I wonder if I really read the right quote for that, or a quote.
I've been telling you about wonder.
Okay, so here, something called the Great Health on page 346 is about this.
Yeah, I guess we can read it here.
The bottom paragraph.
This is what it feels like to be in the, I'm sort of transitioning from, now, well, yeah, let me get this straight.
I'm going from brief habits, which is the lowest level of this kind of wonder life, to the highest level of this kind of wonder life.
Because the brief habits isn't really opening up new worlds.
It's sort of falling in love with Mary and then falling in love with Rome or Paris or whatever.
But now I'm skipping to what it is to be really healthy.
And now I'm going to read the bottom of 346.
It's the same thing on a grand scale.
And now, after we've long been on our way, we agonauts and argonauts of the ideal, with more daring than perhaps prudent, and skipping a little, dangerously healthy and ever healthy again.
It will seem to us as if, as a reward, we are now confronted with a yet undiscovered country whose boundaries nobody has surveyed yet, something beyond all the lands and nooks of the ideal so far.
A world so overrich in what is beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible, and divine.
Notice, in there, everything is there but meaning.
That's the wonder world.
Beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible, and divine, that our curiosity as well as our craving to possess it has got beside itself.
Alas, now nothing will save us anymore.
That's the way to live if you're a free spirit.
Now, let me see.
Oh, I was going to tell the story.
I get to it here in my notes, but I want to make sure I get there.
Try to think of it in terms of artists, if you want another example.
Like, I'm trying to give this thing of how it is to be in it and not be able to see how you could be in anything else, and yet to know that when you were, that you have been in other things, and you will be out of this eventually.
Another thing is, moods have that quality, it occurs to me.
That wasn't what I was going to talk about.
When you're in a mood, it seems like you always going to be in that mood, and it's what else could you be in?
And yet you know you were not always in.
But a better example, probably, is artists, and I take Picasso.
So, Picasso is in a certain period.
He's painting everything blue.
He's in the blue period.
That's the style of his life right then.
Now, he knows, I presume, that he's been in other styles and that eventually blue will get boring.
But while it isn't boring, sort of blue is just exciting and fascinating, and everything looks like it should be painted in blue.
And he's sort of inside it and can't picture what it would be like to be outside it, to see anything that wasn't sort of asking to be painted in blue.
But so he's both sort of living in it.
Just another example that I was giving, like the infatuation one, living in it, knowing that this experience has happened before and it will end, but not having any sense of how it could have been exciting before it came around and how it could be exciting after it came around.
It just seems to be the only exciting game in town when you're in it.
That sounds like the right description, and that's certainly how Nietzsche pictures it.
So you throw yourself into a style until you exhaust the possibilities of that style.
And then you're bored with that style.
And you throw yourself a new cubism, it's right around the corner.
And as soon as Picasso stops painting blue, he starts painting cubes.
But he couldn't see that in advance.
They know they'll outgrow their style, presumably, but they can't picture how that could be.
Okay, now, I think I got that done as well as I can do it, but let me look here.
Yeah, I don't think I need that one.
So, and okay, now I'm going to just get back again what was going on in the polytheism talk and a talk about animals.
But to nail it down, the highest level of being a God yourself, a new man, a free spirit, is to be constantly opening new worlds, doing the one thing that animals can't do.
And I just want to read you those passages because they are so essential to Nietzsche's.
Remember, I said at the beginning, Nietzsche has to transvaluate values and give you a whole new understanding of what human beings are good for, and of the feeling that you got when you got this, what human beings are good for, and how exciting it is to be doing what human beings should be doing.
He's going to substitute for meaning and commitment and bliss and this whole other wonder story.
And that's, and the dreamless wonder story is just the story that they're constantly creation, we can constantly create new worlds.
So you get, and that's got to do with the new value.
Now we can look at the bottom of 265 again.
He's talking about the creation of new tables of what is good.
And then he gives you this rhapsodic, excited version of it about 10 lines down on 266.
We, however, want to become those we are.
That is what human beings are at their best.
Human beings who are new, unique, incomparable, who give themselves laws, who create themselves.
That's the picture, the new picture.
And so you hear him, and keep your eye open as you read it.
I tried to keep track of them, but I haven't really succeeded.
He talks about creating new suns, new worlds, new gods, new eyes.
That many I found, but I bet there are more too.
And that means finally, that's the whole story about transvaluating all values: is to see the ultimate value as the constantly creating new whatever's.
That's what human beings are good at.
That's what's exciting.
That's what's self-rewarding.
That's what it is to be alive.
I've got time for questions.
If not, I'll go on for another five minutes.
But I think I've said one big chunk of things, so somebody might have something to say about it.
Please stop.
I think that this is such a, well, okay, good.
If you believe in.
Yeah.
Yeah?
Well, I see, because you don't see how radical it is.
The question is, why couldn't you be a free spirit and believe in Christianity?
Well, you wouldn't be inventing new gods, for sure.
Well, worlds, new worlds, and new gods and new values all go together for Nietzsche.
I mean, you can't, if there are any, if there's a human nature, then you haven't really invented new, new, you haven't really become the kind of person who can totally reinvent themselves.
It seems to me within a religion, you've got to have the eyes that see what people in that religion see.
You've got to do what any good person and so forth.
It just goes against the idea that, and another way to put it is, you're not going to find sort of, say, Christianity exciting until it gets boring and then give it up.
And then you have Buddhism for a while until that gets boring.
That's not how religions are.
When you got them, you want to hold on to them.
Ooh, I missed a passage somewhere where he said, why that there's no grief?
Explicitly.
I mean, see, there won't be any, there would be grief if you lost your religion.
You'd be lost in one, you wouldn't have any meaning in any orientation.
Oh, I don't know if I can.
Give me a minute.
I don't know whether I can find the new grief.
Yeah, I got it.
There's no grief, 231.
I don't know how I skipped it.
But so that's another way to understand how the wonder world is different.
So at the bottom of 231, and I'll stop with this.
This is number 289.
Consider how every individual is affected by overall philosophical justification of his way of life.
I don't know where this is going to get us.
He experiences it as a sun that shines essentially for him and bestows warmth.
So having a certain philosophical view is just one more of these sort of grief habits you could have.
He experiences it as a sun that shines for him and bestows warmth, blessing, fertility on him.
It makes him independent of praise and blame, self-sufficient, rich in happiness and goodwill.
Incessantly, it refashions evil into good, leaves all energies to bloom and ripen, and doesn't permit the petty weeds of grief and chagrin and embarrassment, let's say, to come up again.
In the end, one exclaims, how I wish that many such new suns were yet to be created.
Isn't that interesting?
That's the same brief habit story written very large.
So you can have a whole philosophical view, and it will give you all sorts of happiness, and you can just find it wonderful to live in it, and you'll part with it without grief.
Your world won't fall apart.
You will just want a new one, a new philosophy, a new sun that will be created by you, presumably.
He's not emphasizing that, but it's just as he thinks that the polytheistic gods, let me say a word about that, are created by the people who create them, who have them as gods, so he seems to think that these philosophy views can be created by you, and then you can learn to abandon them.
Let me read more of this to myself.
Well, it's all about, okay, let's try this.
We must learn to abandon the arrogant fancy.
The arrogant fancy would be that there was one philosophy that was right, one sign, that S-O-S-U-N.
So we shouldn't, what these people need, people who believe that there's only just one right philosophy, is something, a new, they need new philosophers.
And then it's, he says, there is yet another world to be discovered and more than one.
Embark philosophers ends.
That is, just that's a guess, just again, you see what I mean?
You can have a philosophy, you can live and see things in terms of it, you can find it exciting and gratifying and comforting and warming and so forth, but you shouldn't get stuck with it, because then you would experience grief.
But if you see it as something that's working right then for you, but you will give it up when the time comes and take a new one, that's what philosophers should do, because there's always, again, new worlds to be discovered.
Now I think I've covered all that, so we should stop.
Okay.