Now we're off.
Okay, I like to begin, as I did in the last two movies, with some kind of puzzle at the beginning and try to figure you have to then try in the end, like in Hiroshima, to understand whether she saw anything or didn't, understood anything or didn't.
And in the next one, it's whether Harry Lyme is dead or isn't.
Well, here, the end of the movie is obviously completely puzzling.
Michelle does call Patricia degulas, which gets translated scumbag, which is ridiculous.
It should be translated revolting or disgusting.
And he doesn't say she is.
We'll get to that at the end.
He says it is disgusting.
And the question is, what is he talking about?
It's like his last words.
It seems that it must be that it's because she turned him in to the police that she's disgusting, which would make perfect sense, but not the kind of sense that would make any sense in this movie.
Because he gives her the final friendly secret grimaces, making him, he makes these three funny faces at her, which is certainly not what he would be doing if he was angry at her for turning him in.
But he does say that something's disgusting, so we have a whole movie to go through before the end of the time to figure out what happens in the end.
It happens pretty fast, and the first few times you see it, at least I saw it, I didn't get it.
Okay, so we have to start with Michelle Poichard.
We're going to talk about each of the main characters, each one for quite a while.
Of course, feel free to interrupt.
I'm always interested in, you're all of a kind of video generation that see things faster than I do, and faster maybe than Godard did.
So if you see things that I missed, just tell me.
Okay, to begin with, Michelle seems very attractive, but that's odd because he's just a punk who kills a policeman, steals cars, worst of the either, as far as the movie's concerned, steals money from his ex-girlfriend because she's so trusting that she shows him where her money is, offering him to loan him some.
And as you remember, then when she's putting on her dress, he just steals her money, and then he invites her out to breakfast on her stolen money.
That's all pretty disgusting, one would think.
So why is he so attractive through the whole movie?
This is Belmondo's first movie.
He was a boxer before.
That's what he says at one point in the movie.
He may not be good looking, but he's a good boxer, he says.
Well, what he has is a kind of style.
He's the kind of thing that Nietzsche would admire and that he admires, presumably in bogey.
But he, Michelle Poicard, does everything he does with a kind of flair, openness, cheerfulness, spontaneity, intensity.
That's all a pretty attractive way to act.
And his way of putting it is when he's driving the stolen car, never use the brakes.
And behind him at one moment, a poster says, live dangerously to the end.
It doesn't get translated in the subtitles.
They're busy translating the marquee of the movie theater, which doesn't matter, instead of translating the poster, which is what definitely matters, that it's there.
And in the scenario, how many got the scenario of this?
Anybody?
Well, Clint, I'll have to read you things more than, no, no, you've got it.
Good.
But if anybody's going to talk about it in their paper, they're either going to have to get it or get it from the library.
I take it we have one.
Has anybody looked for it and not found it?
That would be upsetting.
Okay, good.
So it turns out the poster says, live life dangerously, just go boo, to the end.
And so the next attractive thing is that even though he's so intense and won't use the brakes, wants to do things, throws himself into everything, he does it in a way that's cool.
You can contrast him with the sweaty, panicky, serious two cops who are after him, who are equally intense, but utterly uncool.
And he is, or you can contrast him with the factuous, pompous, self-satisfied author that gets interviewed at the airport.
Also, not attractive.
In fact, there's a certain sense in which nobody, I think, in the movie is attractive except Michelle.
That's one reason that you like him so much.
There's nobody around to like more.
I mean, maybe somebody with all of his characteristics who didn't steal cars and steal from their girlfriend would be more attractive, but we don't have anybody like that.
And he's plenty attractive already.
I mean, how many think I'm wrong already?
I mean, do you find him attractive?
How many think he's not attractive?
Okay, well, that's interesting.
I mean, there are some always.
And interestingly enough, some women and some men, but few at least were raising their hands.
And it would be interesting if we had time to figure out sort of from where the people who find him unattractive are coming from.
I mean, I'm going to just assume from the normal cultural morality that says that he's just a bad guy.
And all the things he does are bad.
And killing a policeman is not an attractive thing, let alone.
Again, I think in this movie, the worst thing he does is steal that money from his girlfriend.
But in any case, he has, in the movie, a kind of egoism.
And he does whatever it takes to make him happy.
And he takes whatever he wants.
Remember in the gay science, Nietzsche is saying, uh-oh, I forgot to say, somebody blew their iPod last time?
Or is it the time of the class before this?
Anyway, I have an iPod.
So he, I mean, I'm getting a whole collection of interesting things.
I think that's all I've got for today.
Okay, back to where we were.
So he's, oh, here, Beatrice, do you want?
Okay, now, this egoism is what Nietzsche is talking about on 258.
I want to relate this, of course, to the gay science as much as possible.
And remember, that's the one where he says, Nietzsche says that egoism should have a good conscience.
But the Christians have deprived egoism of its good conscience.
And they deprived people of much cheerfulness, sensitivity, and poisoned it.
So he's got cheerfulness and sensitivity, and he's got the kind of egoism that Nietzsche would like.
But it's a funny kind of interesting egoism.
He does everything just spontaneously for his own happiness and satisfying his desires, but he never thinks about himself.
He's very, very unself-conscious.
I mean, the best way to see that, of course, is to see somebody who's totally narcissistic instead of egoistic.
Of course, who is that?
Who thinks only about himself?
And that's Patricia.
They form this interesting combination on the subject of how they relate to themselves.
But the spontaneity that I can remember, these funny, impulsive things, like when he says that skirt, the girl with the skirt makes him want to go and pick up the skirt, and she says, be my guest.
And so he runs out and does it.
That's pretty charming of him, I think.
And he keeps, and he keeps, and it's more of a theme going on and on in the movie that he keeps inventing his life.
It isn't new worlds, I can't claim that, or new horizons, even, but he certainly does go around inventing his past.
He lives in a sort of vacuum.
There are no details of his real past except that he was an ex, he was a steward on Air France, a fact he never mentions.
The police mention it.
And it's clear that if we knew the facts of his life, they would be utterly uninteresting.
He's just a normal, everyday punk.
Everyday, and any job that he had would be a boring job, and he wouldn't be interested in it anyway.
But in this vacuum, in which he has no interesting past, presumably, and no interesting life in the normal sense of interesting, he invents a whole bunch of glamorous lives.
Remember, his grandfather had a Rolls-Royce, and he didn't look open the hood for 15 years.
There was a time in the Army where his job was slitting the sentry's throats.
He's just come back from being assistant movie director in Nice.
And a thing that won't strike you, but it sort of strikes you if you know about it, he has to stay in her bed or her hotel room anyway, because there's no room for him in the clarage.
And the clarage is the hotel where he always stays when he's in Paris.
The claris is like the rich.
It's a very, very fancy, posh, expensive hotel.
Oh, he also does, he sold used cars in New York.
And his father was a famous clarinetist.
What a bunch, I mean, just an endless bunch of totally incompatible and all of them obviously false stories that he makes up about himself.
If he had really had a famous father or a serious job as assistant director, it would limit his ability to invent this life for himself.
But in the face of relative nothing, he can invent anything.
And now I'm just giving you a list still about him.
He's irreverent.
He's ready to do anything and laugh at anything.
Remember, the free spirit.
I'm saying he's a sort of poor man's free spirit, of course.
And the free spirit laughs at even what is sacred.
Remember the place where he specifically laughs at something sacred?
It's the place where the guy gets killed crossing the street.
And what does he do when they see that the guy is dead?
He crosses himself.
I mean, just a tiny bit of irreverent, irreverent about death and irreverent about religion.
And of course, in a way, the most irreverent thing he does altogether is the way he dies.
He, in effect, refuses to take his own death seriously.
And that's pretty extreme.
We'll get back to that.
And now, the most amazing scene that has to do with not taking something seriously is the scene in the hotel room.
I mean, that makes up almost half the movie.
That was in the original script by Truffaut, one paragraph.
And it just goes on and on and on, and nothing happens in it, really.
Nothing important.
Nobody shows any really serious emotions.
And it's, if you tried to say the what scene in the hotel, is it a joke scene, a love scene, a desire, passion, sex scene?
I don't know.
It's none of those.
It's just a kind of endless play.
And Godard just brings it off brilliantly.
It doesn't look like any other seduction or sex scene or love scene you've ever seen, and yet it's all taking place in her bed.
It is amazing.
And what's and it ends with the radio saying, they don't translate it, work to music, and when the sheets are all spinning around.
And then she reaches out and turns it off.
Then there's one of Godard's usual incomprehensible cuts.
One minute they're in bed, and the next minute he's coming out of the bathroom, and you're not showing any transitional thing.
I mean, I'm just in the background of what I'm saying, and I'll come back to it at the end if there's time, is he's just destroying all the conventions that usually are used in movies to make sense of things.
People go through intermediate steps when they're in bed and then come out of the bathroom.
You see them going in.
Or the beginning of the movie, weren't you very confused?
There was this girl making gestures and there was him looking around and there were boats going by and then so forth.
What was missing was what they call an establishing shot where you could see him and her and how they were related to each other and then you could see him up close and her up close.
But you don't get that.
So you never really know until afterward that she was helping him steal a car.
And Godard is doing all this on purpose.
We'll get back to that.
Okay, so, and now we get to the interesting thing with him and Brief Habits.
He's clearly in an interesting Nietzschean place because he's against eternal love and unconditional commitments.
That is, when she says, let's be like Romeo and Juliet, in effect, he says, she says, I wish we were Romeo and Juliet.
I'll give page numbers in here.
I want to look it up sometime.
So 72, she says, I wish I were Romeo and Juliet.
And Michelle says, oh, la la, what a girlish idea.
And yet, he says, he can't live without her.
Right after that, she says, you see, you said last night in the car you couldn't live without me, but you can.
Romeo couldn't live without Juliet, but you can live, you can, you can.
And he says, no, I can't live without you.
And she says, oh, la la, just a boyish idea.
Well, but what's really going on is it's true he can't live without her.
He is ready to risk his life to stay with her by the end.
But what is it?
Is it an eternal commitment like Romeo and Juliet?
Certainly not.
It's a brief habit.
That is, he's in it right now.
Right now, only sex with her clicks with him, as he tells one of his friends.
That is, right now, she's fascinating to him and exciting.
And though you wonder in a way why he finds her fascinating and exciting, she is in a certain way such a loser.
But that's maybe what's fascinating and exciting.
We have to wait and see that.
But he admits that in a certain way he could live without her.
I mean, it is sort of a brief habit thing.
On 61, when they go through the same thing, she says, I can't do without you, he says.
You can very well, she says.
But I don't want to, he says.
And in the same sentence, look at it, look, a Talbot.
A Talbot.
That's a kind of car I gather.
It's beautiful.
I mean, all in the same speech, in the same sentence.
He's always looking at everything that he finds attractive: the Fost de la Concorde at night, this car that goes by.
I forget what else.
But he's open to anything that's interesting in the world.
But it looks like, for sure, he's got something like a brief habit.
He can't picture, right now, at this point, he can't picture living without her, but he's perfectly clear to him that that's just what's going on at this point.
And now, more important, and I'm sort of building up to the ultimate one, he's got a positive interest in nothingness.
And he likes it.
He's not afraid of death.
He's fascinated by death.
He says he thinks about death constantly.
And even he once pretends to be dead in Patricia's lap.
And I just found out, I was rereading, I'd read it once before, but not lately, in the introduction.
And at one place, Godard, in an interview, I don't know if I'm going to be able to find it again.
I marked it, but I don't know how.
Because I was surprised how much death is supposed to be important to him.
I thought it was sort of a thing.
But Godard makes a big fuss about how he thinks the movie's about it.
Yeah, here it is.
No, no.
Well, anyway, Godard points out that death is always in it.
Michelle says he thinks about death all the time.
There's the guy killed on the street.
There's the policeman killed.
He has other things about death, too.
Well, it doesn't really matter.
It's obvious from just the fact that he says he thinks about death all the time.
And it's close to him throughout the film, and it doesn't frighten him, and it doesn't make his life meaningless.
That's probably the wrong thing.
Of course, it doesn't make his life meaningless because meaning isn't something he's interested in.
And it doesn't make his life uninteresting.
It doesn't make his life not worth living.
I'll put it that way.
And it's interesting if you contrast that with Merceau in The Stranger, which all of you have read, I remember, from when I asked you.
And of course, for Merceau, it's precisely death, the cold wind blowing from the future, as Cameron calls it, which makes everything meaningless.
And it just doesn't have that effect on Michelle Poitard.
He isn't in the meaning business, but he finds death fascinating.
And the fact that nothing has any meaning is good.
That's, again, for the free spirit, an openness to appreciate everything.
By the way, one of the things he notices, he notices lots of things, but just on an aside, sort of, the man who turns him in, when he's sitting in the car in front of the New York Times, looks at him, looks at the newspaper, looks away.
That's Godard.
He put himself in the movie, in case you want to know what he looks like if you play it again on a DVD.
He's following Hitchcock, who always puts himself in some little place in the movie.
But relevant to what we're talking about, Michelle is perfectly ready.
He knows that he's been seen.
He knows that the informer has gone over and told a policeman and that there's people rushing around.
And he doesn't drive off because he's waiting for Patricia.
And he's just totally.
He's bold and he's following his desires.
And right then, he wants to see Patricia.
And the fact that he's been found doesn't affect him.
Let's see where we are now.
So to sum up, Michelle, he's an active nihilist, is what I'm getting at.
I mean, I've been saying he's a free spirit, but an active nihilist is exactly a free spirit who finds, I brought with me, I thought, I'm sure I did.
Here it is.
The definition of an active nihilism, a nihilist is the active nihilist is a sign of increased power of the spirit and all the characteristics that go with it.
And Godard thinks of himself in a way as being this kind of nihilist.
And because of its fits, I'll read it.
In an interview with Godard, he says, the genre of Breathless was such that all was permitted.
Just listen to this with Nietzsche overtones.
That was its nature.
Whatever people might do, all this could be put in the film.
This was even my point of departure.
I said to myself, we just have Hiroshima Monomur, just like you guys.
A certain kind of cinema has just ended, meaning a well-made movie, where every shot is perfectly posed and everything is motivated visually so that no there are no jump cuts and such things as that.
We've j well then, he says, we've just, a certain kind of cinema has just ended.
Well then let's put the period to it.
Let's show that anything goes.
And that's and that's what he's doing.
He's showing in the in making the movie that anything goes.
I mean there are so many strange things that you don't even notice.
But one of them, for instance, is that there are no credits.
You don't know who's you don't know about Belmondo and Gene Seaberg or that Jean-Luc Godard made the movie.
It just plunges into this incomprehensible car stealing scene.
Oh here I found the death thing as I was going through here.
It's in another interview.
Things couldn't go well between them.
He's talking about the American girl and the Frenchman because he thinks about death all the time while she never gives it a thought.
I told myself that if I didn't add this idea to the scenario, the film wouldn't be interesting at all.
The guy is obsessed with death.
He even has pre-sentiments of it.
That's why I shot the scene of the accident when you see the man die on the street.
And I chose the this is this is the only thing that was news to me and I chose the Mozart clarinet concerto.
That's the music at the end when he's gone and was lying there and listening to the the record.
I chose the Mozart clarinet concerto because Mozart wrote it just before he died.
I mean funny thing you can't see in the movie, but that's what he did.
Okay, now where are we?
Yeah, so so I stop with him and with Godard, who's doing who's a free spirit, making a movie for free spirits about a free spirit.
That's all implied in what I've just been saying.
And if you don't wanna if you wanna say anything about it, about him or that, now is the time, because I'm switching to Patricia.
Ah, Beatrice, yeah.
The Nietzsche and Godard inform that they both know their tradition really, really well.
They build on their dance from out of that.
But the Delmanda character didn't know who they were.
That's interesting.
That's true.
It's now if you raise it.
Out of that comes an interesting question.
Does the Nietzschean free spirit have to know about tradition?
I don't know.
Godard is probably maybe less of a free spirit.
Nietzsche does say that he thinks that what's important is not remembering, but forgetting for the free spirit.
And you don't try to remember whether people are guilty or not or accuse them or forgive them.
If they do bad things to you, you just forget it.
You've got better things to worry about.
That's how the free spirit thinks.
So the fact that Bel Nando has no past and Godard has a tradition probably doesn't make any difference inside the movie when you're trying to be Nietzschean or not.
At least that's my claim.
Anything else?
I saw another hand.
Went back there first.
Yeah.
I hope I'm giving perfection, like you can style, because we're not in discussion when you're like because our inbox is balloon, too.
Well, yeah, I think he admires bogey style.
Well, I was going to get to that later, but now we can talk about it.
He certainly doesn't admire anything specific he does, and he doesn't want to have exactly that style, I don't think.
But did anybody know?
I think I may have asked that, this gesture.
Somebody told me that's a bogey gesture, and it must be, though.
I don't remember when I've ever seen it.
Do you know when he is that a is that some?
Yeah, I mean, he does it when he's watching the Bogart picture, and certainly we should say it now or someplace.
You see him staring at something with total devotion, which if there's anything sacred in his life, that would be it.
And lo and behold, it turns out to be that wonderful picture of Bogart, and he stares at it and he makes that special gesture, which I take it, and I think it's going to turn out to be important, has been passed on from Bogart to him and is somehow a sign that he's taking up Bogart's style, only in his own way.
And he knows he is.
He doesn't reflect on it because he never reflects on anything.
But that is his idol.
I don't know whether, I mean, it's funny, I'm not even sure he'd be able to laugh at Bogart, though.
If he's a really good free spirit, he's got to be able to be even to make fun of him.
Yeah.
Well, but both of them also, like Mr.
Bunny, when you beat it, we've all fit Bogart.
What about what's in the Maltese Falcon that you're talking about?
The music is the same?
Ah.
Gee, interesting.
What?
I believe it, yeah, yep.
Oh, okay.
Let's go on, because there's questions to cover.
I'm going on to Patricia Frankini.
I didn't ignore anybody, did I?
I think I saw the hands.
Okay, let's do it.
Well, she's obviously the negative self-death-bying person.
When you look into it, it's really amazing.
I doubt if Godard really thought this out, but you can see that she's negated almost everything.
Her occupation is she's taken up and dropped a whole bunch of occupational roles.
She seems to have repudiated her family, her country.
She's come to Paris to study at the Sorbonne, but she doesn't study.
She's working on a book, she says, but she isn't writing anything.
She wants to be a reporter, and she does go to the press conference, but we don't see any sign that she's writing it up.
Her job, and those are her non-occupations.
Her job is fascinating.
Selling Hero Tribunes on the Champs-Élysées is the least committed job you could have in the world.
You just do it if you feel like it.
You go and buy a bunch of Herald Tribunes at your rate, and you go and sell them at the higher rate.
You don't have to come back the next day.
You don't have any medical insurance.
You don't have to, you know, it's just the minimal job.
And she doesn't even seem to sell any Herald Tribunes except to him, one.
She has got, occupationally, she's totally zero.
Now, and gender-wise, she's very interesting.
I think, though, I'll be interested to see what you think.
She seemingly repudiates her femininity.
She walks with that awkward, unfeminine gait.
I don't know if it's masculine, it's just awkward, and wears her hair cut in that severely short way.
Does that seem unfeminine to you all?
Or, I mean, we've got to remember that this is earlier, too.
I'm afraid we partly this is a problem of what it what people felt in what, the 50s?
When was this movie made?
Late 50s, I think.
Middle, maybe early 50s.
Hmm?
56, is somebody's 66 oh really okay yeah right before the big events of May in 68 okay so I don't so you don't think so and and the fact that she wears his clothes then has no bra I don't know what this what this really means in at that point it seemed to mean somehow shocking to him that she didn't have a bra and he would and he just he's supposed to be immune to being shocked yeah but she well okay so you you don't think she's somehow repudiating being a woman I okay I don't need that I mean if it's all right with me she's certainly got the the occupation thing is negative and a certain aspect of being a woman seems to be something she's not concerned with namely being pregnant she she doesn't seem to care whether she is or isn't she brings it up just to see whether how he's going to feel about it naturally he feels as if it it's her problem but she doesn't seem to be looking for marriage or an abortion or planning to what to do with the baby she just seems to ignore this as a sort of little problem that'll go not even young just forget it so that was that's strange and she seems somehow this is a funny thing repudiate her adulthood by hugging her teddy bear and then I just looked out and discovered that everybody in the audience was hugging their teddy bear and I remembered that my son took his security blanket away to boarding school when he was 15 he still had his security blanket even though he left home.
So, I don't know how many have still their their teddy bear to hug any you're not going to admit it.
Okay.
Anyway, she does, and I I'm going to read that as somehow not wanting to grow up.
So, she's not American, not French, not a student, not a writer, not an adult, maybe not a woman, and so forth.
Michelle calls her a Mar, Michelle calls her a Martian.
I think being a Martian is how he senses that.
And even, and this is very interesting, she wants to repudiate her name.
She says she doesn't want to be called Patricia, she wants to be called Ingrid.
Do you know anything funny about that?
Bogey and Ingrid are part, it seems like Casablanca shows up in all the movies we see in some weird, indirect way.
Godard doesn't make anything of it.
He just mentions it.
So if she had dedicated herself to being Ingrid, the way Bogey is somehow dedicated, I mean, Michelle has somehow dedicated himself to being Bogey, then her life would have been very different.
But she doesn't, she just doesn't know what to do or what to think.
She says, I don't know if I'm unhappy.
She's certainly unhappy.
She's glum all the time or something like that.
Whereas whatever the opposite of cheerful is, she's it.
And glum seems to be the best word I could come up with.
She says, I don't know if I'm unhappy because I'm not free or not free because I'm not happy.
And that's she doesn't, and then she says, I'm thinking of nothing.
I want to think of something, but I can't.
And she seems to be in a grumpy mood because nothing means anything.
Whereas Michelle can fill the void with all kinds of irreverent creativity.
She only complains that meaning is missing, and she feels sort of sorry about it.
And that's about it.
And to put it more sort of philosophically, she's afraid of nothingness.
She sees behind his face that there is nothing, and that really frightens her.
There is, she's right, there is no identity, no fixed commitments, and that's so on page 86, he says, You know, he said, I was afraid, Michelle, I am afraid.
Oh, no, I'm going to read that one later.
This one, she says, I've watched you for 10 minutes, I see nothing, nothing.
I'm not sad, but I'm afraid.
And so she's afraid of nothing.
And then comes this wonderful quote.
I mean, if you weren't sure yet that Godard was writing with sort of Nietzsche in one hand, you get this talk about Faulkner, which is so funny and so relevant.
She says, Do you know William Faulkner?
And he says, No, who's he?
Have you slept with him?
And she says, Of course not.
He's then to hell with him.
Take off your shirt.
And she's, he's, the dialogue is just as amazing reading it as seeing it.
She says, he's a novelist that I like.
Have you read The Wild Palms?
He says, take your jersey off.
And she's listening.
The last sentence is beautiful.
And she reads it in English.
Between grief and nothing, I will take grief.
Between grief and nothingness, I choose grief.
She translates it into French.
And which would you choose?
Well, let's stop for a minute.
You recognize what she should say if she's a passive nihilist.
You recognize anything from Nietzsche?
Nietzsche comes up with this in a way.
I mean, Nietzsche thinks, I think there's even better passages than I could find, but Nietzsche certainly thinks that, where are we?
In Twilight of the Idols on 33, if anybody finds a better quote, I think Nietzsche says somewhere, but I couldn't find it, that we're so addicted to meaning that we'd rather have suffering than give up meaning.
Does that sound familiar?
The best I could find was the bottom of 33 of Twilight.
If we possess a why of life, we can put up with almost any how.
That's pathway there.
I mean, no matter how much we suffer and how much we're miserable, if we understand why our lives are like that, then we're okay.
But I'm sure there's some place where he says people would rather suffer than have a meaningless life.
Yeah.
Yes, that's right.
Well, Faulkner may be in there.
That's true.
And the passage is perfect.
Another comment.
Yeah.
What about it?
I see.
Well, I, I mean, that's when they all say these sort of independent things as they walk around the room at the end after he knows that she's turned him in.
I think that's just his openness.
The contrast with which what she says under the sheet, in the bed, she says, it's strange when I look at your eyes, I just see myself.
That's the difference.
I mean, I think that's just another way of saying.
I mean, you can be an egoist like he is and still want to be, you know, open and involved with conversation with other people.
But to be a narcissist like she is, wherever she looks, she sees herself.
She sees herself in the mirror in a store window, and you see her looking with the same rapt attention as if she was seeing a god, practically, and you wonder, what in the world is she looking at?
It turns out she's looking in a mirror in the store window at herself.
And she pats her stomach.
I don't know whether she thinks she's getting fat or whether she's worried that she's getting pregnant, but that's all you see of that.
But then she's hanging this Renoir picture in the room, and she asks him, Don't you think I look like her?
She selects her paintings, not by the artist, or not by even whether they look good in her room, but whether they look like her.
She is really narcissistic, and I don't have more to say about that, but I do think it's very important to go back to his comment about the Faulkner quote.
She says that she would take grief.
She says, I choose grief.
What would you choose?
And of course, he says, the dialogue is so amazing.
He says, show me your toes.
A woman's toes are most important.
Don't laugh.
No, what would you choose?
She says.
He says, Grief is idiotic.
I choose nothingness.
Not that it's better, but grief is a compromise.
You have to have all or nothing.
That's, you know, again, keep your, don't always accelerate and what, do something, just kaboom.
What's that expression again?
What's the poster?
Action, just, you know, the poster.
Anyway, he's doing this thing again, all or nothing.
It's like never, oh, never step on the brake, and you always, well, I don't remember, but keeping up to the end.
And so that's it.
So he chooses naturally that.
Oh, look, and here it is.
I opened it just from under the sheet.
She says, it's strange.
What?
I see my reflection in your eyes.
That's on page 89.
So he says, oh, it's live dangerously just to the end.
So that's tied up with his no compromises view.
He's not going to grief as a compromise.
He's ready to choose nothing.
And he does in the end choose nothing.
Meanwhile, while he hasn't actually chosen to die yet, he's acting out a fantasy of the fellow who steals money, takes a girl away to Italy.
They support themselves by stealing cars, and finally you get her caught and go to prison together.
And Patricia doesn't have any sort of fantasy like that to guide her life.
She can't think of anything.
She says that at one point.
She says it sort of all over.
The one I happened to mark is at the top of 71, I'd like to think of something, but I can't.
And then they have this discussion with this thing, which I'm going to talk about in a minute.
And she says, why are you, he says, why are you looking?
No, never mind.
It would get ahead of the story.
So she's she does she and is Patricia so afraid if Patricia is so afraid, why does she want a love oh no, where am I?
Okay, now next point.
Her view of freedom is a negative kind of freedom.
She says she wants her independence.
She says, I quote, I want people to leave me alone.
It's a negative kind of freedom.
It there's no no responsibility, no commitment.
And then I it's puzzling if that's true, and I'm sure it is.
Why does she want to love like Romeo and Juliet?
Well, she doesn't really.
And and that'll get clearer as things go on.
As soon as it becomes a question of a real commitment, she is a coward and chickens out.
The translation calls her a chicken.
The French is really just coward.
So when she falls in love with Michelle, then she gets to be afraid of losing her freedom and her sort of nothing.
And she acts on that.
But we're not ready quite for that.
So she doesn't want to take any risks.
She doesn't want to do anything in order to have meaning in her life.
But she can't be a free spirit like Michelle and live dangerously.
She's too weak to live dangerously.
So he keeps telling her over and over, you're a coward.
And when they really do get into, from her point of view, a Romeo and Juliet kind of relation, at that point is where she turns him in.
And I'm just summing her up now.
Nothing has meaning in her world.
Far from finding it exhilarating that nothing has any meaning.
And a chance to be cheerful and creative, she is disgruntled and apathetic.
In a word, what is she?
She's a passive nihilist, of course.
I mean, I don't think Godard even knows how he's got this so beautifully lined up.
And passive nihilism says decline, recession of power, and so forth.
And that's her.
Now, Quail, comments.
We finished Patricia, so it's time for more comments if you've got them.
It's pretty.
Yeah.
Well, only if he, I see, well, no, the question is whether you would choose meaningless or grief.
And he chooses, or is it nothing?
Whichever, meaninglessness or nothing.
It's nothing.
Okay, but nothing is fine with him.
But grief is a compromise, meaning that it's for people who aren't able to go all the way and accept the complete emptiness and meaninglessness of everything.
So he naturally chooses nothing.
He likes, I mean, he's been thinking about death all his life.
That's the big deal, nothing.
But mainly, I tried to say back when I talked about him, the nothingness is what gives him the opportunity to create all these lives and enjoy all these experiences and be observant of everything and so forth, be cheerful and alive, only because he's not sort of tampered by convictions, commitments, moral rules, ambitions, anything.
I don't know if that's a help, but it'll have to do for him a while.
Maybe we can come back to it.
I'm going on.
Okay, now, because we've got to make sure we cover this.
Now we're ready to get to the relation between Michelle and Patricia, which ought to become beginning to become sort of obvious to you.
Why is it that for Michelle, it only clicks with Patricia?
You would think, you might think that he'd hate her.
After all, he says at the very beginning, if you don't like Franch, the sea, the mountains, the big city, go fuck yourself.
That's what it says.
You get stuffed or something, it says in the translation.
And that's on page 35.
But you remember that probably, because that's the first thing he says in the movie.
And Patricia certainly doesn't love any of those things.
So she's utterly unlike him.
But you get a clue as to why it clicks with her if you compare her to this attractive, sincere, good-looking, hard-working, trusting, loving, moral girl that is there at the beginning of the movie, just, I think, to establish the traditional coordinates.
She's just perfect.
She's so beautiful.
She's so nice.
She's so trusting.
She's so generous with her money.
And her job, she doesn't want to be in films because you have to sleep with too many guys.
And she earns an honest living, whatever it is, and she seems to like her work.
And in other words, she's the only traditional, decent, moral person in the movie.
And the last person that Michelle would have any relation to, or who would understand him or care about him.
I don't know why she does care about him.
I think because he's just really kind of handsome hunk.
But I don't know what it is.
We don't need to know.
But whatever it is, she's the only person who is neither an active nor a passive nihilist in the movie.
I mean, I guess.
I mean, the police are people, maybe, and I don't know what to say about them.
But the interesting thing is, again, I hope you're all resisting my sort of mapping this on Nietzsche so much.
But the real trick is one that doesn't dawn on you for the first, I don't know, 15 times you see it.
But sooner or later, you notice a very peculiar thing: that when he's in the room with this girl, who is, so to speak, you might say, the last of the decent people in the marketplace who hasn't heard the news about the desk of God, he says, the camera reveals that on the wall are the first five letters of the word pour croix, which is why.
And he says, what's written there?
Pour qui, she says, but I never finished it.
And she was making it out of cigarette cartons, and she switched to Lucky's, from Nevermind from Galois.
That the important thing, of course, isn't the bank.
What's the important thing?
That she was writing on the wall why, and she didn't finish it.
Remember, if you remember that in Will to Power, the whole story about nihilism is that what does nihilism mean?
The highest values devaluate themselves.
The aim is lacking.
Why finds no answer?
Well, you can't get to the point where why finds no answer.
You're ready to ask about everything.
Why should we do this?
Why are we here?
Why be moral?
Why everything?
And then you either go into the zero slump of Patricia or the happy, exact, cheerful life of Michelle.
But she hasn't gone to the end of asking the why question.
She ran out of cigarette cartons.
But the interesting thing is, I mean, that's a total, I think, reference to the passage I just read.
And that's to say, she's not a passive nihilist or an active nihilist.
She hasn't carried through her thinking that far.
She still accepts the current meaning, the current values, and so forth.
She can't get to the point where the why has no answer.
So now, so no wonder it doesn't click with her.
Ah, yeah, she could, but she isn't.
Obviously, she is.
I go back to my list.
I mean, she's not a free spirit.
She is, well, she's just wonderful in this.
I made this great list about her.
She is hardworking, trusting, loving, has moral principles.
That's why she won't go into the movies, generous, and so forth.
I mean, she just seems to be an utterly decent, old-fashioned human being.
I mean, if you think she's a free spirit, you have to find some evidence somewhere.
She's there to set off the kind of girl, I think, for whom it doesn't click, that Michelle is just not interested in, no matter how nice, no matter how loving, no matter how attractive, against Patricia, who has none of those qualities I just read, but has something that she's asked the why question.
That's my version.
I mean, she got, so to speak, the wrong answer, the weak answer instead of the strong answer.
But let me go on and make my case more.
So Michelle and Patricia are not in the same world.
Sorry, Michelle and that girl who has no name are not in the same world.
Neither Michelle, and Michelle and Patricia are not in that world, her world, the old world.
They are in the after-God is dead world, and they're attracted to each other from the opposite ends of the dimension of nothingness.
You can either take it with courage, cheerfulness, and energy, or with cowardice, disgruntlement, and apathy.
They're like magnets.
The negative and the positive attract each other on the same dimension, but at opposite ends.
Even though she's utterly joyless and lost, she has more in common with Michelle than with the girl who still lives under the old values.
What Michelle likes about Patricia is that she shares his nihilism.
That is, she's more like him than like anyone else in the movie.
And now you can sort of, let's talk about the kind of things they share.
They share a kind of poetry of non-explanations.
There's a kind of poetry where the why is lacking.
You recognize what I'm talking about?
Why are you sad?
Because I'm sad.
Why do you look at me?
Because I look at you.
And all events are explained in terms of that nihilistic poetry, which, in fact, Godard or the scenario writer, I don't know who, says, Michelle says, as if reciting a poem, when she says it's bad to be an informer, he says, this is top of 124.
No, it's normal.
Informers inform, burglars burgle, lovers love.
Look, the Place de la Concorde is so beautiful.
And in other words, and she does it too.
I mean, they both share the nothing ever happens because of anything.
There are no motives.
There's no sort of economic causes.
Burglars don't burgle because they choose to burgle or because they come from families of burglars or because they need milk for their children.
Burglars burgle just because that's what they do.
And that's what she shares with him.
And she also shares with him that all meaningful distinctions are leveled.
So for instance, she says, should I say tou or vous to you?
In French, that's the intimate or the formal.
In German, like do and z.
And you say tou to somebody that you're intimate with and love, or to your children who you're intimate with and love, and you say vou to people you're formal with and polite.
And it's a huge difference in French.
You mess it up, you really mess things up.
And the answer he says is, it doesn't matter, they're equal.
The most extreme might be when he says, I want to make love to you because you're so beautiful, and she said, oh, I'm not beautiful, in 76.
And he says, okay, because you're so ugly.
It doesn't matter.
No distinctions matter.
There are no explanations, and there are no meaningful distinctions, and nothing means anything.
There are no moral guidelines, and so forth and so forth.
What Michelle likes about her is that she sees it.
What he dislikes about her is that she doesn't enjoy it.
That's the fact he says it drives him crazy that she does things by half-measures that destroys his morale.
I couldn't find the quote, but I know it's in here somewhere.
So Michelle enjoys, I'm repeating myself, the nothingness and turns it into poetry.
Patricia just salts and wishes she could think of something positive.
Now, let's see.
I have one here which I think I've sort of jumped ahead and done already, so I'm going to skip it to make sure we've got it in time to do everything.
Okay, we're going to skip to Patricia's encounter with the famous author, the press conference, which is so amazing.
They ask him all these stupid questions and he gives all these stupid answers.
And at one point, he compliments her, which is when a question is asked by a girl with white beautiful hair and a beautiful striped sweater or something like that.
And of course, she loves that because that fits her narcissism.
And she has this rapt expression when the author compliments her.
But now comes the absolutely crucialest thing, I think, for understanding the movie.
She asks him what would be the actually perfect question for somebody who is living in the nothing and doesn't like it.
In effect, how do you get out of meaninglessness?
She says, what is your greatest ambition?
And I hope you remember what he said, because it turns out to be very important, I think.
What does he say to her?
He says, where is it?
What is your greatest ambition in life?
And he says, to become immortal and then to die.
And the important thing is not what he said, but how she takes it.
You get immediately the music, when the Michelle music comes up, you get a perfect front-face picture of her, and she's looking absolutely dazed or stunned or something like that.
I'll read what the directions say.
Michelle's music comes in, she takes off her sunglasses, puts the end of the earpiece in her mouth, and slowly turns to stare straight into the camera.
And that, okay, we don't know yet why that's important, but the way it's set up, it's clearly something important is happening there.
She's either totally unable to understand what happened, or she's got glimmer that somebody's got some understanding about meaning that she has no clue about, but she'd like to know.
But you have to put it aside now.
It's not relevant yet.
But that's when it happens.
Okay, now we've got to go to the next issue.
Anybody want to say anything?
We're still doing okay.
So if you do, you go ahead and say it.
Yeah.
Absolutely identical.
And so is the music.
That's why that's important.
That's why you've got to take seriously what he said to become immortal and then die.
Yes.
But now what that's going to mean when we get there, I'm not ready to say.
The end is so subtle and so interesting and so ambiguous that we don't know yet.
Okay, but we have to know before the end, because it's important for understanding the end, what is her motivation for turning him in, which seems such a strange thing to do.
Well, it turns out it starts, well, first you should remember that, and you don't realize it unless you've seen the film at least once first, that all their kisses have been completely meaningless, sort of pushing their mouths up against each other and rubbing their noses together under when they're in bed together in the hotel room, and when they're, I think, maybe once somewhere else.
I'm sure somewhere else, but I can't remember where.
But where?
Oh, yeah, and she gives him a kiss, that's right, when they first meet and run across the street.
Well, those kisses are non-kisses, that's sure.
And all of a sudden, for reasons you have to help figure out, but I think I know, on page 123, when she reads in the newspaper that he's been married, which isn't important, and he says, I dumped her or she dumped me, I don't remember anymore.
An example of forgetting and leveling that Nietzsche would have liked.
She says, All of a sudden, I love you very much enormously, Michelle.
Now, what's happening?
Well, and Michelle says, How do you feel riding in a stolen car?
And she says, And you when you killed the policeman, and so forth.
What has she discovered?
Well, she's discovered that he's killed a policeman.
Now, why is that so important to her?
That she can tell him that it lets her love him enormously.
That is, though they've never kissed passionately before in the movie house, they do while they're watching the movie.
It's an entirely different kind of kiss because she's now accepting that she loves him enormously.
And what's the point?
Is it the heroism, the risk, the excitement?
No, certainly not.
It's that he has to leave.
She knows now that he won't be able to stay with her in Paris.
And that's good news.
Now, why that's good news?
You can begin to glimmer.
That lets her love him completely, like on the last night before he's going to surely leave.
It's like Yvonne saying people should only be intimate with each other when they know they're going to leave the next day.
That she's got the same view.
So otherwise, it would hamper her negative kind of freedom.
It would demand a commitment from her.
She would risk being hurt.
She says earlier on, I want to love you, and I don't want you to love me.
I want you to love me, and I don't want you to love me.
I want my freedom.
I'm very independent, you know.
86.
A negative kind of independence, of course.
An independence that says that says, in effect, that she doesn't want anything, even a brief habit in her life.
So she panics when she realizes that he's got a plan that actually he could put into effect of going to, that they could go to Italy together.
They're going to have a car, they're going to be given money, and so forth.
At that moment, when he says, Buretti, or whatever his friend is, we're going to get a car, we're going to get money, we're going to go to Italy, she leaves to go call the police.
That's just the worst thing that she could possibly imagine could happen to her.
That she would lose this negative kind of freedom.
She wants him to leave her alone, she says.
She wants people to leave her alone, she says.
I didn't find that quote either, but she does say that.
I thought I had that.
Well, anyway, she says that.
And, of course, you've got to add this, or you can't understand the ending.
She doesn't think he's going to be killed.
She doesn't think he's going to be captured by the police and get life imprisonment.
There isn't capital punishment, friends.
Can you imagine Michelle Clotar with life imprisonment?
I mean, that would be pretty terrible.
But of course, she doesn't expect that.
She expects that he'll leave instantly.
And he just lies there listening to the clarinet quintet.
And then they have this amazing conversation in which they don't talk to each other, but each one sort of says the kind of soliloquy and counterpoint.
But he doesn't leave.
So now that is what happens next?
Well, next is, or you believe that, don't you?
I mean, it's pretty clear with her talk about wanting to be free and not wanting people to depend on her or not wanting any, obviously not wanting any commitments.
It fits her negative kind of nihilism, and it makes perfect sense of what is otherwise incomprehensible, why she would run out and turn him in after just because she says she loves him tremendously.
But it's just because she now admits to him and herself that she loves him, that she has to get rid of him.
But not hurt him.
And that's what she sets out to do by calling the police.
But of course, this isn't how it works out.
Now, it works out, you have to sort of follow everything now, frame by frame, really sort of to follow the plot.
Varudi arrives with the car and the money, the gun, and he doesn't want to take the gun.
And then the police arrive in their car, at which point he reaches over and picks up the gun.
As soon as he picks up the gun, and I think he's supposed to know it, they can kill him because he's self-defense.
Without the gun, they could only arrest him and put him in prison for life.
And he doesn't want to go to prison for life, and he's perfectly happy with dying.
So he picks up the gun, and immediately, Vidado, the police, the frantic, sweaty policeman, shoots him.
And then comes this amazingly beautiful ending, which I've seen maybe 20 times, and it still just seems to me incredibly beautiful.
He does this kind of ballet in which he goes staggering down the street, bouncing off the cars, and the people come out and look in a kind of disinterested way at what's going on.
And finally, he gets to the crosswalk at the end of the street, and he decides to fall down.
It's clear he doesn't want to get out in the street where he'll get squished by a car.
He wants to die on his own terms.
So he throws himself down.
You can see by the way, he puts his feet up in the air.
I mean, he doesn't just collapse.
He falls down intentionally in the crosswalk.
And then, what else?
He does his sort of heroic, bogey death, which is he's in complete control of everything.
From he he falls down dramatically.
He takes a last puff on his cigarette and throws it away dramatically, giving up smoking forever, obviously.
And he then turns to Patricia, who's been following him, and he gives him and she gives him this com beginning of a completely blank look.
But he's not angry at her for turning him in.
And we can see that because he's been looking forward to his death all his life and practicing for it.
Godard understands that.
And he's enjoying this dramatic, so he gives her the three grimaces, or just thanks for getting him killed so nicely.
And that is their secret sign that they're both outside the normal and understand each other, or so he thinks.
And that is, he wants, I said, he doesn't want to keep a straight, put it this way, he doesn't want to keep a straight face even in the face of death.
That's the ultimate seriousness out of which you get a chance to have the ultimate laugh.
And he's having it.
So he turns to her now.
He's just produced a great death, made fun of death and all the sacred things that could go with it.
And he turns to her for what?
For recognition, presumably, for approval.
She ought to give him these grimaces back.
He's dying with cheerfulness and style.
She should at least applaud.
But she can't understand at all this last act of positive nihilism, since she doesn't, since she's afraid of nothing and afraid of death, and she's guilty of having done this to him, even though she didn't intend to do this to him.
So, what does she do?
She looks absolutely blank, stunned and blank, just like she looked when the author said that his aim in life was to become immortal and then die.
So, at that point in the movie, the nihilism that has brought the two of them together pulls them apart.
They're now a passive nihilist confronting an active nihilist, and there's nothing now in a kind of pun that they have in common.
They have, in effect, nothing in common with a capital N.
They both face the nothing after the death of God, but they have nothing in common in the ordinary meaning, in that their way of dealing with the nothing is totally opposed.
And that's now become finally in the course of the movie, in the end that becomes clear.
She doesn't applaud his last great act, and he says, It's revolting, and then closes his eyes.
I'm trying to tell you what I think is revolting.
What's revolting is not her, but that she doesn't understand and applaud his perfectly Nietzschean, Bogartish, active nihilist death.
And she asked the policeman, what did he say?
Well, he, by the way, takes the last tiny bit of control and closes his own eyes.
And then his head falls over.
He's dead.
And then she asked the policeman, what did he say?
And the policeman says, he said, she's disgusting.
Because the policeman, naturally, like you or me, normally, wouldn't understand what in the world he could possibly be disgusted by, except for her turning him in.
But it isn't that.
It's what he said was what she's doing is disgusting.
Or better yet, really, what she's not doing.
is disgusting.
It's that disgusting, by the way, is the same word that way back on page 62, I noticed at this time for the first time watching the movie, and it's totally messed up in the translation, when he sees, when she leaves him to go see the journalist way back, he says, okay, beat it, beat it, you bitch.
But it isn't you, bitch.
It's to Degilas again.
And that is you disgusting person.
And so the word, again, it's important.
It's not a scumbag.
It's not a bitch.
It's something that somehow what she's doing is disgusting.
Then, and now why?
Well, what happens next?
And it isn't over yet.
She looks stunned.
She looks blank.
You can't say she looks sad or shocked or not even shocked, just stunned and blank.
And then she makes the gesture, the bogey gesture.
And you get the same full face picture of her as he says, and you get the same music on the soundtrack.
What's happening there?
Well, is she just looking blank?
Or now you have to ask the same question with the journalist.
When that happens, that somebody says something she can't understand, is it that she just can't understand?
Or is it she's beginning to comprehend some new idea?
What would be the new idea?
Well, the new idea would be that Bogey became immortal and died and passed the gesture on to him, and he is now becoming immortal and dying and passing the gesture on to her, which means the beginning of her transformation into an active nihilist.
I mean, that's one possible reading.
It's totally ambiguous.
Or it means she didn't get it.
But of course, that fact that she makes that gesture makes you think she must have gotten something from him.
And all she could get from him would be to be an active nihilist.
But Godard's not telling you, and that's nice.
He's just, she just turns her back to the camera, and that's it.
You're left with these two possibilities, and you don't know what to think.
At least, I don't know what to think.
If anybody does know what to think, I'm ready to hear.
Yeah.
The Missens Representation actually adds the same thing, like people in the nothingness and saying, like, all this stuff, and this is what it is.
And her teaching is.
Well, I don't see why it would.
I mean, he's certainly saying, I don't think he's saying death is nothing.
He's certainly not saying it's meaningful.
It's an occasion for a free spirit to do a creative and powerful thing.
Death is important, he wouldn't be thinking about it all his life if it was trivial.
It's not trivial at all.
It's how to make the most out of the most you can out of the most nothing there is.
And that's what he did.
Yeah.
Why would he want recognition?
I guess Dyke would say because he cares about her.
Who's the one who said we should talk to each other?
I mean, he's open and he cares.
She's his brief habit.
And he really wants her to, you know, applaud him and appreciate him in his last great act.
That's what I think.
Yeah.
I've got a little confirmed reading down there as a free spirit.
That is cheerfulness, isn't he?
Cheerful?
I mean, he's about what?
But one point, a good point to pick that out.
That's very sensitive.
He says, I'm tired.
I know.
I don't know what to make of that.
So that's why I didn't bring it up.
It seems to me I have two reactions.
One, it seems sort of psychologically, perfectly sensible for him to say it, since he's been fleeing from the police for the whole movie.
But it doesn't seem like the right ontological, the right philosophical thing for him to say.
That's what you're on to.
I mean, it looks like the free spirit would never be sort of spiritually exhausted and ready to sleep.
And so it looks to me like it's sort of plausible in the plot, but not the right thing for him to say.
Of course it is.
That's what I said.
It was a pop punk version of a free spirit.
It's certainly, one way to see it, which I never said before, but I found myself saying a little while back, he's certainly not opening up new worlds.
And that might be the way to put the fact that he's not really a free spirit.
Free spirits don't just do funny things like pick up girls' skirts and so forth.
Free spirits have new suns, new worlds, what are all these things, new whatevers, and he doesn't have a new anything.
So, in a certain way, he's got only sort of half a free spirit.
Yeah, I can say something.
He's always tired, doesn't he?
Yeah, but he doesn't think he's weak and being cleansed.
That's the problem.
I do think it means that he's ready to die, but he's been ready to die all through the movie, and that's why it's a little strange for him to say here he's tired.
Dave's brought up a good question.
I don't really know.
I'm afraid my way of reading it would have to be to say that's, as I said, thought-wise and psychologically, perfectly natural thing for him to be tired and want to sleep.
But it shouldn't be that his sort of, I don't know, cheerfulness and power were running down.
Although, I suppose you could put the two together and say, even a free spirit, after all, gets exhausted after they've been running long enough.
Yeah, he was willing to go to prison with his girlfriend.
You mean in that story about what would happen if he went to Italy or when he does say that?
What does he say?
Let's look, let's look.
No, I don't think he says that, but when this, I'm reading it now, talk about myself.
They don't want to be in love.
She says, Just, it's, I don't, she says, I don't want to be in love with you.
That's why I called the police.
I'm just looking into things and so forth.
Yeah, well, okay, somewhere it says, why aren't you leaving?
Let's see.
She says, I'm independent.
I wish people.
That's what she says.
I wish people would leave me alone.
And then she says, now you're forced to leave.
All this is important to read.
He says, why don't you leave, Michelle?
You mustn't count on me.
Leave, Michelle.
What are you waiting for?
And now he should say something about, yeah, he says, ah, you're right.
Here he says, no, I'm staying.
If any way I feel like going to prison, she says, you're crazy.
Yes, no one will talk to me.
I'll look at the walls.
You see, you said that.
I don't know.
They say funny things to each other.
And then he says, oh, shit, Baratti, and he runs out.
The car is arriving.
Just when they're reaching some kind of understanding, I guess, about it's okay for him to go to prison.
And then that goes, you're right.
That goes with him saying he's tired.
That doesn't seem like the proper free spirit attitude.
Well, I'm just going to say that he'd rather die than go to prison.
He is ready to go to prison.
Maybe that's okay.
Maybe he can even be cheerful in prison.
I just don't know.
But I can't leave it out, but I don't know what to do with it.
He and then you.
Yeah.
Yes, you don't feel, and that's both of you are on the right track.
I said something wrong in the sense that I said that he knew that he didn't want to go to prison and for life, that he would prefer to be shot.
I think if you sort of ask him, he might know that.
But he doesn't have it.
He doesn't think that because it's somehow a kind of afterthought that he picks up.
It's not clear why he picks up the gun.
It's certainly, but it isn't as if he picks it up in order to have a shootout with the police.
He just looks like somehow he just doesn't think.
He just picks it up.
That's what you think?
That's how I picture it in the movie.
Okay, well, so, but that isn't a big disaster for me.
I mean, I think that what he does is get shot, and that's, and he doesn't mind getting shot.
In fact, it turns out to be an opportunity.
Yeah, we got one more minute.
I saw a hand over here.
Yeah, last comment.
Good, good, I like it.
He says, because clear it up the fact that he lived on impulse, and then we could end it with, and why does he pick up the gun?
Because people who see guns lying on the street pick up guns.
It's sort of, don't give it, don't ask for a why at that point.
Okay.