And now, so problem, the whole issue of the teleological suspension of the ethical is the phenomenon can be summed up in one clear problem.
And that is, once you have some absolute source of meaning in your life, thanks a lot, then you have also a kind of an authority in your life that you have to obey, even if it goes against what is normally understood as the right thing to do.
Now, the sort of caricature of that, but it's just so clear and simple that it's something we could begin with.
You all had it once, right?
Never.
Ah.
Well, yeah, I'm just going to read it then when we get to it.
Don't worry about it.
And it's on the website.
I'm very surprised.
I thought I handed it out on the back side of the revised syllabus.
Does that sound familiar to anybody?
Just a hallucination.
Okay.
Hmm.
What?
Pascal.
It wasn't on, no, it wasn't on the Pascal things.
You're right.
That was the first syllabus.
There was a revised syllabus, which only changed the times of the movie, so it doesn't matter.
But then I thought I had Huckleberry Finn.
I know I've got it in my computer, but I guess I didn't ever give it.
Out.
That's okay.
What I need, I can easily read.
So let's.
So, sir, a simplest example of the teleological suspension of the ethical, just utterly, utterly too simple to take seriously, and it's not supposed to be taken very seriously, is in Shakespeare's Much Ado About Nothing, where Benedict loves Beatrice, and Beatrice demands that Benedict kill Claudio.
How many know the play, any of you?
And in effect, she says, I don't like Claudio, and if you love me, then you'll do what I tell you to do, and I tell you to kill Claudio.
And the idea is, if you really got an unconditional commitment to Beatrice, there, then if Beatrice requires it, you'd better do it.
It's the Knights and Ladies story in a kind of comic version.
But of course, it needn't be comic.
I mean, it turns out to be comic because Claudio doesn't have to go through with the murder.
But the point is, it could become terrible.
And of course, it does become terrible in the case of Abraham and Isaac.
And so now, Abraham and Isaac's story, which never fit too well with the unconditional commitment, defining relation, and so forth, because it was so weird that his defining relation was to his son, and it was so weird that somehow something commanded him to destroy the defining relation.
It was a complete craziness.
But this time, it's pretty simple.
As Kierkegaard puts it, the ethical is just in Isaac.
That is, Isaac, you shouldn't kill people, and even more, not your own children.
So, Isaac is, well, on 88, he just says, in effect, Isaac is the ethical.
Now, that's sort of confusing.
So, I better tell you right now what the confusion is so you can be unconfused.
Most people, oddly enough, who write about this and read about it, don't even notice how confusing it is.
But if you're teaching it, at least in reading it my way, it seems it's a little bit weird.
Because what happens is first, Isaac is an example of the object of an unconditional commitment, and all this problem about the sword hanging over the head of the beloved, and the land of the princess is brought in in connection with Abraham's relation to Isaac.
And then, Isaac switches around and is a kind of instance of the ethical, namely, he wants to kill Isaac, and it's against the law to kill.
But so, let me just do it the way I was going to do it.
Show you first, even though it's not in your reading, on page 54, the clearest place where Isaac is really presented as if he was the object of Abraham defining commitment.
That Abraham is, Abraham is who he is, gets his identity and his meaning through his relation to Isaac.
It's not important, but just to show you how different that Isaac is than the one in the problem.
So here's the Isaac of the preamble from the heart, namely the unconditional commitment character, about 15 lines down on 54.
Abraham believed, he believed he would become old in his land, honored among his people, blessed in his kin, eternally remembered in Isaac, the dearest in his life.
So Isaac is the one who gives meaning to Abraham's life, just like the beloved.
And that's fine.
But that's a different issue than on 88 when we're told about Isaac the following at the end of the big middle paragraph: insofar as the universal was there, the universal is the same as the ethical, because the ethical, you should get used to this, is universal in the sense that if it's wrong to kill, then it's wrong for everybody, everywhere, all the time.
I mean, at least let's say if it's wrong to kill when nobody's threatening you, and you know, you could make some qualifications for wars and stuff.
But maybe, or if it's wrong to lie, everything else being equal, complications again, it applies to everybody, everywhere, all of the time.
What's right is just simply right, and what's wrong is simply wrong.
That's how the ethics works.
And then you bring in qualifications for the situation, but basically, the rules and principles are universal.
So when he says, insofar as the universal was present, the universal here would be thou shalt not kill, at all, it was latent in Isaac, concealed as it were in Isaac's lines, and it, if the universal, would cry out with Isaac's mouth, don't do it, you're destroying everything.
That is, you're breaking the law, you're becoming a bad person, don't kill me, it's unethical to do it.
Now, it roughly, and for years I believed this and taught it for slightly simpler.
I thought all of the defining commitment stuff is in the preamble from the heart, and all the ethical stuff is in problems 1, 2, and 3.
And that's right, except for some smart student who students are always helpful, but sometimes I wish they wouldn't discover these things, discovers that on page 60, which is the preamble from the heart, there is one mention of Isaac as the ethical, about 15 lines down.
The ethical expression for what Abraham did is that he was willing to murder Isaac, and so forth.
I think that's all I want to read.
That, I think, belongs in problem one.
Let's see if I need any more.
Well, we start a little further up, about ten lines down.
If one hadn't the courage to think this thought, to say that Abraham was a murderer, then surely it's better to acquire that courage than to waste time on undeserved speeches of praise.
So, there for a moment, the issue of the unethicalness of killing Isaac comes up.
You see how different the issue is, whether you somehow lose, it's so complicated if you kill him, but anyway, the loss of Isaac as Abraham's meaning is one thing, and the killing of Isaac as breaking the law is another.
And we're switching to the killing of Isaac as breaking the law.
Now, it might help, and it might confuse more, I don't know which, to think why is Kierkegaard doing this?
Well, because in his relation to Regina, the two are mixed up together.
The fact is, one, he can't have Regina for some reason we don't know, the way the lad can't have the princess, and that is, it's got to do with the vulnerability of a commitment to another person.
He claiming he's completely defined in terms of Regina and claiming that somehow or other he can't marry her.
Now, but he's also breaking his engagement to Regina.
And that's the anti-ethical.
I take it in 1850 in Copenhagen, engagements were big deals.
They were like super promises.
So now he's breaking his super promise to Regina, and that puts him out against the ethical.
So he's got both these problems on his mind when he flees to Berlin, and he sees both these problems, therefore, in the Abraham-Isaac story.
But the important thing is, and now we're going to stick to that.
This was all sort of try to get you to just focus on the phenomenon.
The phenomenon and its philosophical implications is what we care about.
The rest is all just sort of confusion and gossip.
But the issue is clear.
The issue is: what's the relation of your unconditional commitment to where it looks like you are required to make an exception of yourself, and you are defined uniquely as an individual, and you're called to do your own unique individual thing, and that seems to be higher than the ethical, whose principle is something like: never make an exception of yourself.
Always do what any good, rational, I guess, whatever, you could put different things in there, but whatever anybody who understands what's right and wrong would do, you would do.
Remember, I said in the very first lecture, from the ethical point of view, the Greek point of view, every good, all the good people are exactly the same because they're all in the same situation, would do the same thing, namely the right thing.
And in the Hebrew picture, every unique individual has their own unique calling, and it makes them, and this is Kierkegaard's term, an exception, or the exception, he calls them sometimes.
Anybody who becomes an individual, in Kierkegaard's sense of individual, by following their calling, is an exception.
And that's just another way of saying what I said in the first sentence of what I've been talking about.
They are called by their unconditional commitment to go to do whatever that commitment requires, even if it looks from the point of view of ethics, as wrong.
In Abraham's case, murder.
As Kierkegaard's case, breaking a promise.
So now I'm going to tell it to you in abstract form, probably easier, really, once you get used to it.
We're going to read the first paragraph, or half of it, on page 83, which is the beginning of problem one.
Where he's going to explain the teleological suspension of the ethical.
Okay, all of this stuff now should sound like what I've just been saying, only in philosophical language now.
The ethical, as such, is the universal, and as the universal, it applies to everyone, which can be put another point, which can be put from another point of view by saying it applies at every moment.
It rests imminently in itself and has nothing outside itself as this telos, but is itself the telos for everything outside.
I'll explain that in a minute.
And when that is taken up into it, it has no further to go.
That's a long, complicated way of saying that whatever is right is something you should do just because it's the right thing to do.
Not because, if you, let's try telling the truth.
You could tell the truth because people would like you, or because people would trust you, or because it would be good for business, or because somebody might catch you if you don't.
Those are all what Kant would call hypothetical reasons for doing something.
That is, if you want to be liked, tell the truth.
If you want to succeed in business, tell the truth.
But the ethical principle says simply, tell the truth.
Even if you lose your friends and fail in business and bad things happen to you, the ethical command is just tell the truth.
Kant has a famous name for this.
He calls it a categorical imperative.
That means an imperative means you just do it.
And categorial means for Kant, it's just there's no other reason to do it than just because it's the thing you have to do.
Whereas a hypothetical imperative, which is a Kant other term, means if you want such and such, then do such and such.
Okay, so Kierkegaard is just saying that where the ethical is concerned, it's the highest goal.
There's no further away to go, as he puts it.
You can't say why you should be ethical.
You're just required by your conscience or by your reason.
Different philosophers have different views, by the Bible, by the natural law.
There have been a dozen possibilities, but they all tell you what you have to do just because it's the right thing.
So that means its telos or goal is itself.
That's just this funny way of putting it.
Seen as the immediate, now we're going to get the good old lower and higher immediacy talk.
Seen as the immediate, no more than sensate and psychic being.
Oh, comes another whole story.
Just take my word for it.
Put instead of single individual the particular.
I'll explain why in a minute.
The particular is the particular that has its telos in the universal.
And the particular's ethical task is always to express himself in this, to abrogate his particularity so as to become the universal.
Now, that's good.
It's that getting the individual in there.
This isn't about individuals as exceptions and so forth in the big deal sense.
I'll call it a capital I individual, where Kierkegaard said he wanted to carved on his tombstone that he was an individual, and where the individual is an exception and has a calling.
And I have to prepare you for this.
This is very hard to read.
I hate to have to do this to you, but no, if there was any translator who understood this, I would have told, you know, had you buy that translation.
There's only, apparently, only, I've checked this out with Danish people whose natural language is Danish, and it seems there is only one word in Danish, which does a double job, and we have two words for them in English, thank goodness.
And I think I may have already said this once, because when I talked about Kierkegaard wanting to be an individual, but remember, I'm pretty sure I said a particular is any, we could say individual thing, but it would be a funny thing to say.
This is a particular, your dog is a particular, you can carve on your dog's tombstone.
I remember saying, here lies a particular, but you can't say on your dog's tombstone, here lies an individual in the sense that Kierkegaard uses it, or here's an individual.
That's only maybe this is an individual, depending on whether I've got a calling and whether I define myself in terms of it.
And what's the problem?
Well, the translator has no idea what's going on in the book, so he has no idea which translation to use at any given point.
So he just throws in single individual when he feels that the source sentence structure or avoiding repetition makes it nice.
Or he throws in particular or he throws in just plain individual at random.
So there's so and that's that you can't say the single individual, that is the one who's done an unconditional commitment is the particular that has its telos in the universal.
See, that's just exactly what it's wrong.
The particular has its telos in the universal.
Now I have to explain what that means.
The particular is not only the lectern and your dog, but it's you insofar as you are just another entity or organism or person.
I think person would be all right.
Persons, just plain persons are particulars.
And that's because, let's go and look at children.
I mean, that's maybe the way to see it.
Children are in lower immediacy because they are always making exceptions of themselves, but not in any fancy way of having a calling, but because they go in for immediate satisfactions and they go after whatever they desire.
And everybody begins as a particular with their own impulses and desires and moods and so forth.
That's lower immediacy.
And we all start out as particulars.
Only unlike dogs and lecterns and so forth, we can get to be individuals.
But we have to go through, and now you have this chart where you have to go through mediation, but you don't have to have the chart in front of you.
And now, a new way to put the chart is that you have to go from lower immediacy to mediation.
You can also say you have to go from being a particular to subsuming yourself under the universal.
That means you have to stop being a child, constantly making exceptions and just trying to get the biggest piece of cake.
And you've got to understand that there are general principles governing human behavior, and you've got to get rid of this sort of selfish, one-sided way of looking at things that all people begin with, and do what any right-thinking person does.
That's that funny sense.
Let me just read it again now: seen as an immediate, no more than sensate and psychic being, that means having feelings and ideas in their head.
Why did we put the child?
I ever thought of putting it that way.
That's sort of not, I mean, that's a little too specific, but it certainly helps understanding.
Get rid of single individual and just put child.
The child is the particular that has its telos in the universal, and the child's ethical task is to express himself in this, to abrogate his particularity, to get over that selfish point of view, so as to become the universal.
And now let's just switch to particular again.
As soon as the particular wants to assert himself in his particularity in opposition to the universal, he sins, and only by recognizing this can he again reconcile himself with the universal.
Okay, that's all we need for the moment.
And I'm just catching up with where I am.
Okay, now the next question is: why is the ethical important?
Why, I mean, it's true that your conscience sort of commands you to be ethical and your religion does and so forth.
But you might want to say, what sort of role does it play in human life, and why does everybody really want to be ethical?
Well, from Kierkegaard's point of view, and I think he gets it from Hegel, he puts it on page 103.
He puts it also in a very fancy Hegel talk.
I don't know which to go first.
I think I better do it 97.
I'm going to tell it to you first in a literal way and then in a metaphorical way, and then maybe you don't need to hear it any other way.
In the ethical view of life, then the paragraph that begins on 97.
In the ethical view of life, then it is the particular's task to divest himself of the determinant of interiority.
That's a new one.
So, lower immediacy and particularity is also now going to be called interiority.
And that means, get the feel for this, the interior are your moods, your desires, your own subjective perspective.
And you're supposed to get over your interiority and give it expression in the exterior.
That means find a way of expressing what is universal and everybody can understand it, instead of just having your own peculiar, kinky, idiosyncratic take on things.
And now, when the individual shrinks from doing so, whenever he wants to stay inside, to slip back into the inner determinants, and then there's this nice feeling or mood.
You get a hint of what he's talking about there.
He commits an offense, he's in a state of temptation.
Okay, let's now let's read the more literary version of the same thing.
What I'm trying to say is, well, what's to be gained from getting from the interior to the exterior?
Well, it's intelligibility.
You are able to explain to yourself and everybody else what you're doing and why you're doing it in a way that you can't as long as you're just following your impulses.
And that's the attraction of the ethical.
That's what the Greek philosophers understood, that there was a way of acting that you could understand yourself and everybody else could understand you because what you were doing was what everybody saw to be the right thing, or that you could explain to be the right thing.
So here's how he puts it in this nice form.
In the middle of 103, starting about this third sentence, about five lines down in that big paragraph.
Someone who believes it is a simple enough matter to be the individual.
That really is.
You could put a capital I there if you want.
The individual can always be certain that he's not a knight of faith.
For stragglers and vagrant geniuses are not men of faith.
Faith, that is, and those are the lower immediacy people.
Faith Knight knows that it is glorious to belong to the universal.
Now comes this big metaphor.
This is, think about this when you want to see why the ethical is attractive.
He knows that it's beautiful and benign to be the particular who translates himself into the universal.
The one who, so to speak, makes a clear and elegant edition of himself.
That's how he gets from the interior to the exterior.
As immaculate as possible and readable by all.
He knows it is refreshing to become intelligible to oneself in the universal, so that he understands the universal and everyone who understands him understands the universal through him in turn, and both rejoice in the security of the universal.
That's all fine.
Then, in more general talk, if there has to be some shared public moral vocabulary about what's right and wrong and worthy and unworthy, and then when there is, people can communicate what they're doing and what they should be doing, and people can blame them or approve of them and so forth.
Now, there's something that happens, I think, between problem one and two, which is relevant for us.
Problem one is really Kantian.
It just says there is a universal, like, don't kill, don't lie, and so forth.
And it applies, he said, remember, everywhere all the time.
But really, we don't believe that anymore.
We've seen cultures in which there are so many different varieties, and cultures in which perhaps the best thing you can do is be a clever liar and get away with it, or cultures in which everybody, I mean, I'm not sure there really is such a culture, but supposedly there's a culture called the IC, in which everybody is constantly trying to outwit everybody else.
And supposedly, when they see a child crawling toward the fire, instead of rushing to help the child, they all laugh to see the child get burned.
I don't know whether there could be such a culture, but let's suppose in that culture you could get credit for how well you managed to set up traps for people and so forth.
But the point is, having seen this diversity of what counts as good and worthy, and maybe even you can't talk about anymore what's right, because what's right, I think Kant is correct about it, is universal.
If there is anything right, everybody's got to do it.
But there's local goods.
What's good for the Greeks isn't the same as what's good for the Hebrews, and isn't the same as what's good for the Athenians, isn't the same as what's good for the Spartans.
And now comes problem two.
Problem two makes a kind of Hegelian move and switches, instead of talking about the universal, it talks about the inner and outer and about intelligibility.
And that means that as long as there's a shared moral language of discriminating the good from the bad, the worthy from the unworthy, in your peer group, that's all you need in order to become clear, intelligible to yourself and everybody else.
I mean, I think of my, I got my example from Charles Taylor, a philosopher who likes to think and write about these things.
He talks about how a bunch of bikers have their own values and what it is to be tough, for instance, and cruel and so forth.
And it turns out that what it could be that to be manly and tough is the good thing, and to be girlish and weak is a bad thing.
But they all understand what's worthy and not worthy.
And they all can justify what they did by saying, well, if he did that, he would have been a sissy.
And everybody says, yeah, that's, or he didn't do that, and he was a sissy, and then he gets condemned.
You can see it on every level.
You can see it on the level of the Vikers, or you can see it in what I said at the very first lecture, where I think I said, for the Greeks, the big moral contrast or ethical contrast was heroes and slaves, or heroes and heroes and slavish types.
And that's utterly different than the medieval.
Did I talk about this as the difference between saints and sinners?
I thought I did.
Good.
Okay, so that's just another example.
Heroes are independent, and they don't need any help.
They don't need any God.
They're like gods to the people who need them.
And the same heroes, if they were existing in medieval times, and they are in Dante's Inferno, show up in hell because they are rebellious.
They've taken over the, instead of being meek creators, the meek have inherited the earth, as the Bible says.
The meek who, for the Greek point of view, were slavish, are now the good ones up in paradise.
And the ones who were tough and independent and not at all meek, but proud, are at the bottom of the inferno.
There's nothing worse than pride.
Achilles had lots of pride, and nobody blamed him for it.
So you get the point.
But it doesn't matter as far as inner and outer is concerned.
They are all getting rid of their particularity, their moods, their whims, and all trying to be either heroic and proud or trying to be meek and saintly.
And everybody understands what they're trying to do and blames them when they fail at it and praises them when they succeed at it.
And they understand what they're trying to do.
They're making this clear edition of themselves.
So you don't need to do this Kantian universal right story.
For the intelligibility of it, it's enough that there's a shared sense of what's good, of what's worthy, of what people should be doing and not doing.
That's enough to get you a sense of what you ought to do and you ought to do, and that's what matters.
That matters when you try to justify yourself to yourself and to everybody else.
And that's a 97, and I read it already.
It's how you're going to get outside of these inner determinants of feeling, mood, and so forth.
And now back to 83.
He says it in these different places over and over, but some places better than others.
Now, I'm going to go on where I left off last time.
So it's the individual's task to become the universal.
And now we can say, well, whenever you see the universal, you only need to realize it means universal relative to the group of people whose vocabulary and sense of worthiness you grew up in and share.
It's that, so the bikers will do, but there has to be some shared sense of what's worthy.
Now, and then I'm going to go back to where I am now.
As soon as the notice in a single individual wrong again, you can either say person or child or particular or whatever helps you understand that.
I guess I like this child just for a change.
As soon as the child wants to assert himself in his particularity in direct opposition to the universal, which means what one does, he sins, and only by recognizing this can he again reconcile himself with the universal.
Whenever, having entered the universal, the child feels an urge to assert his particularity, he's in a state of temptation from which he can extricate himself only by surrendering his particularity to the universal in repentance.
He's got to admit he's wrong.
Okay, that now I could stop with that for a minute because that's as far, that's the first step.
Do you get that?
I mean, we haven't got any problem yet.
Well, what are we doing in problem one and problem two?
Well, I sort of told you in the first minute what the problem is going to be.
How many see having now that I said all this, what's the big problem he's going to have to head into?
Somebody say it just so I can be sure.
Yeah.
Ethical, but if you have the right.
So here you've got this whole story about the ethical, how important it is, how it grounds intelligibility, how it makes you transparent, how it gets you from the inner to the outer, from lower immediacy to the universal in mediation.
Everything would be fine, and you could just stick with that if only we had just the Greek culture.
But we've got also the Hebraic Christian culture, which is telling us, do your according, even though it makes you an exception and puts you outside the universal.
And now we're going to, Abraham's going to turn out to be, of course, the extreme case of that.
And we have to see what's happening there.
How can this, well, let's just do it in Kierkegaard's way.
To begin with, I just want to, yeah, I need to fill in one thing.
Yeah.
Kierkegaard is the main one who sees the conflict between the Hebrew Christian, on the one hand, with individuals becoming unique and exceptions when they've got their calling, and the power of the universal to make you intelligible to yourself and everybody else so you can just know what to do and everybody could see what's the right thing to do and you can tell when you did something wrong and how you have to make up for it.
Kierkegaard believes in both of them.
And I just want to run through something which I won't ever get a chance to talk about again.
What makes him particularly interesting to me anyway is that the other existentialists and people generally think existentialists in general, but Kierkegaard is after all the superexistentialists.
He defined what he called existential thinking.
And he's the one who brought the, remember the Hebraic Christian way of looking at things crash into the Greek one and sort of worked out Pascal's view that the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob is not the God of the philosophers.
Kierkegaard didn't just dump the philosophical Greek perspective.
So I just want to mention that.
When you get to Nietzsche, you'll see that for Nietzsche, the ethical is not a good thing.
It's just, it is just a means to an end.
It makes you stronger.
It's a necessary stage to go through when you sort of outgrow being a child.
But when you really get to be a highest-level human being, you leave the ethical behind.
In some ways, that's true in Kierkegaard too.
Why am I...
Ah, but in Kierkegaard, you see that the ethical was a necessarily valuable stage.
And when you leave it behind in Nietzsche, you leave it behind in a way that you sort of look down on it as something that only weak people need.
But I don't want to go into these.
I just want you to know.
Heidegger thinks that the ethical is the voice of conformism.
It just tells you what one does.
It doesn't tell you what's right or what's good.
Your conscience is just, it's a kind of modern, I guess, Freudian view.
Your superego is just whatever everybody in your peer group tells you, but that doesn't give it any real authority.
Sartre, how many of you, anybody know The Flies, the play, The Flies of Sartre?
Well, in The Flies, Zeus says that he uses the ethical to keep people enslaved because then they, as long as they believe in these religious guidelines, they don't do individual and rebellious things.
And all that is ways of saying, oh, and I forgot Dostoevsky.
How peculiar.
Well, Dostoevsky thinks, you'll see when you get to the brothers, that philosophers and philosophy is sick, literally sick.
I mean, it's some kind of pathology that he wants to understand, how all these philosophers are running around, particularly in the West.
And Russia is generally free from this kind of disease.
But even there, it has somewhat taken root.
Now, only Kierkegaard has this idea that everybody needs to go through critical reflection to get rid of lower immediacy.
And it's not something that's sick or weak or makes you subservient or anything like that.
Even when you've got a defining commitment, you still remain completely indebted to the ethical.
And in a certain way, you still respect and are called upon to respect.
And that means for Kierkegaard there is this big collision if it turns out that your unconditional commitment requires you to go against the ethical.
You can't just say, well, I grew the ethical.
I don't have to think about it anymore.
Or it's only for weak and sick people.
No, the ethical is really unconditional command on you.
It does apply.
And so you get in Kierkegaard a whole.
Now we're in the new problem.
How can you respect the ethical as in a certain way the highest thing people can do, and yet bring in the unconditional commitment as the highest thing people can do?
And of course, the answer is it's going to be what?
What's his word for what happens when this collision occurs?
Do you know yet?
You shouldn't really.
So wait till we get there.
He's got a name for the feeling you get when these things collide.
Does anybody recognize it?
What?
No, no, not despair.
That's an important feeling, all right?
That's when, let's just review it, the way you're living your life makes it impossible that you were ever happy or you ever could be, like the woman in Hiroshima Manamur.
But we go back to that in the last lecture.
Don't think about that now.
Now, the word is anguish.
Every once in a while, and you'll hear about it now.
Anguish is the experience of the collision between these two worlds.
I read this once.
That's why you do know it, but I didn't make a fuss about it.
And it's not in your reading, which helps you not know about it.
But I read it.
Where is it?
Only he who knows anguish can experience bliss.
Maybe I can't find it.
Where is the life?
In the lives of the spirit, there's...
Ah, here it is.
It is in your reading on 57.
Right in the middle of the page.
Only one who knows anguish finds rest.
But what anguish is exactly is what we're going to get into now.
Yeah.
I mean, even if you like what it is, kind of area, I mean those were the answers, so they kind of things that they always break down in the hypotheticals if you just work on you're unjust for society with opinions of God.
And so there are these reasons for doing this opinion that others do exactly.
And then you combine that to society with the individual, then the individual will also have a reason.
Yeah, I do, but it's not quite right.
I don't know how to say why I don't think it is until I go on.
And then see if you think that I've answered you.
It's interesting what he's saying, that there's going to be a conflict of reasons between the reasons to do something that the person with an unconditional commitment has and the universal reasons or the Hegelian more local peer group reasons.
And that's true, sort of.
But Kierkegaard's got a more radical problem than that.
That wouldn't, that I don't think would give you anguish.
That might just give you perplexity.
What you want is something like two absolutely grounded and I like the word respect the ethical, grounded and sort of respectable claims on you.
So let me go on and you'll see how that comes out very quickly.
So we need, I think I just read this, but I'm not sure, so I'll read it again.
No, I didn't.
Let me one more round now of the Hegel part on 97.
I'm just trying to give you a feeling now of what's good, no, where the problem comes in.
So, we want to get rid of the determinants of mood and so forth.
Okay.
Now, now comes the new part.
The paradox of faith is this, that there is an interiority that's incommensurable with the exterior.
Now, notice, just I hope you realize that this is now, what's the paradox?
It's let me say, I'll say it in these versions, and then you see if you can recognize what it was last week.
But it's the same thing.
Okay, there is not identical with the, there is a new, sorry, there is an interiority which, it should be stressed, is not identical with the first, that of the child.
That's like me in there, but it is a new interiority.
This is not to be overlooked.
Recent philosophy has allowed itself without ado to substitute the immediate for faith.
Well, what is this new interiority?
You recognize it under a different description?
Exactly.
This is now another name for higher immediacy.
There is something that is above the universal and the ethical that you get to after you've made the movements of reflection and mediation and rationality.
And that's what he wants, that's what he's going to talk about now.
And so, let me go on.
If one does, and you can't substitute the immediate for faith, that is, his big enemy here, I have to explain to you, is Hegel, who says Christian faith is just another kind of superstition.
It's a very high-level superstition.
It's a kind of deep superstition.
And when Hegel comes along, he can explain the philosophical and theological meaning behind these biblical stories of God becoming man and people performing miracles and stuff.
That's just lower immediacy.
That's the kind of thing simple people believe.
But faith.
So faith is kind of lower immediacy, Kierkegaard thinks, but Christianity is mediated into philosophy.
That's Hegel's big job, to show the philosophical truth in it.
Now, Kierkegaard thinks that's just terribly wrong.
That's to get the whole Judeo-Christian tradition mishmashed into the Greek.
It just continues.
Hegel, remember, I put it on the board, is the last of the philosophers, starting with Plato, and then there's Aristotle, then there's St.
Thomas Aquinas, and then there's Descartes, and then there's Kant, and all of them, and then there was Hegel.
And they're all trying to put the Judeo-Christian thing into Greek terms, and thereby always losing it.
And the last, and they always get an enemy.
So Pascal, so Pascal, Descartes gives rise to Pascal denying the God of the philosophers is the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.
And then, jumping ahead, Hegel gives rise to Kierkegaard.
The one that Kant gives rise to is a guy named Haman, but he's so obscure that it doesn't do any good to, Kant was such a heavy, nobody stood up to him.
To this day, they haven't managed to stand up to him.
And then Hegel gives rise to Kierkegaard, and what Kierkegaard rejects in Hegel is to claim that Christian faith is lower immediacy, but it can be mediated into Hegelian philosophy.
So he goes on, he says, let me go on.
Recent philosophy, that's Hegel, has allowed itself without ado to substitute the immediate for faith.
That is, they stick faith down along with moods and superstitions and so forth.
If one does that, it is ridiculous to deny that faith has existed through all ages.
That is, there's always been plenty of lower immediacy.
Faith in such cases keeps fairly ordinary company.
And there's a great list here of lower immediacy.
It belongs with feeling, mood, idiosyncrasy, hysteria, and the rest.
Insofar, so far, philosophy is right to say one should not stop at that, should not stop at lower immediacy.
But there is nothing to warrant philosophy speaking in this manner, that in this manner.
Wait, what's happening?
So, philosophy is right to say one shouldn't stop at that, these lower things, hysteria, mood, feeling.
But there is nothing to warrant philosophy speaking in this manner.
That is, that there is something higher than faith.
No, I can't read any more of it.
It doesn't help.
It's not clear.
But anyway, I hope you get it.
What's happening is that faith isn't something you can subsume philosophically, like Hegel, and say faith is a part of lower immediacy.
It's just superstition.
And you have to outgrow it and go through the ethical and the philosophical.
Then you get something.
But you don't get higher immediacy, you get just get higher philosophy, which finally, that's Hegel, supposedly captures all you need.
And Kierkegaard's big thing is: no, there's something higher.
And so, at the bottom of 97, then faith paradox is this: that the individual with a capital I is higher than the universal, that the individual determines his relation to the universal through his relation to the absolute, not his relation to the absolute through his relation to the universal.
Enough, I think, for a moment.
Let me fill you in first.
Okay, well, then I let you go.
I feel I lost you, sort of there.
That's why I worry.
So, anybody want to say anything?
Probably I lost you because nobody's had a chance to say anything.
And so, are you with it?
What I need to now is to tell you, but once this is clear, sort of how, and I'm still answering him too, how Kierkegaard sees this clash between the individual and the universal as something much more serious than anybody has ever thought it was before.
Yeah.
Good question.
Can this kind of, I'll say it repeat, repeat it for the podcast.
Couldn't somebody's understanding of right and wrong be determined by their unconditional commitment?
No, but I haven't really explained that.
Let me see where to begin.
I mean, it's part of the notion of your calling or your unconditional commitment that it's just for you and it's something that you can't explain in the terms of the shared peer group culture.
One, I'll give you sort of bits of it.
Remember when we talked about the defining commitment in the romantic love story, that the one you love isn't sort of objectively lovable.
It isn't as if you can give reasons why you love them so that everybody ought to love them because they are the wittiest and the sexiest and the smartest and so forth.
Then you wouldn't really be loving them.
You'd be just loving a type.
And the idea is that any kind of commitment is unique.
But you're forcing me to say something interesting, which I don't know if I could have said it before, but it's just exactly what Skirpigard's thinking about.
I've got to try to answer in this.
It isn't that an unconditional commitment needs to go against the ethical.
You might reconcile your unconditional commitment with the ethical.
So when I use Martin Luther King as an example, I'm always feeling uneasy because Martin Luther King's unconditional commitment is intelligible.
He can explain it to everybody, and he uses the Christian shared understanding of the good and the justice understanding and the democracy and so forth.
But, and this is the move I haven't made clearly, but I'll make it now.
The unconditional commitment could cause you to go against the ethical.
That is, in answer to you, it might be that you could reconcile it with your peer group's values.
But, and this, it's always got in it the possibility of suspending the ethical.
That means it's always got in it the possibility that it will call you to do something that is not ethical.
And Kierkegaard is interested in that.
He's interested in the frame of mind of a person whose unconditional commitment is forcing them, and this is the crucial thing, to do something that is unintelligible, that they can't explain to themselves or anybody else.
You exactly force me to that.
He doesn't care about the fact that sometimes it will go your way.
What he cares about is that it could possibly happen that somebody could be called to do something which, from their own point of view, was completely unethical and immoral, and called to do it by their unconditional commitment.
Now, now I think the reason that he and he have both not seen it is because they're right.
I haven't said it clearly enough yet.
What I haven't done is given you the phenomenon.
So, I'm going to do that.
No more talks about Kant and Hegel.
Let's talk about what it's like to experience something like this.
So, my, I mean, and that's how you have to read these books, remember.
This crazy idea of Abraham being ready to kill his son and thereby become a murderer, and that he is both knows that he's a murderer and at the same time knows that this is the thing he has to do.
First, let me read it in terms of Abraham, but then I'm going to give you real examples in real life because that's the only way you'll understand it.
So, what we want is a place where an Abraham talks to himself.
He has to say to himself, because it's the only language he's got, that he's a murderer.
Help me find it.
And that's when the crunch comes, and when Abraham looks like something absolutely incomprehensible.
Okay, well, right after the beautiful, elegant edition on 103, I'm going to go on.
He knows it is beautiful to be born in the particular with the universal as his home, his friendly abode, which receives him straight away with open arms when he wishes to stay there.
That is when he goes from being a particular to being universal.
But he also knows that higher up there winds a lonely path, narrow and steep.
He knows it's terrible to be born in solitude outside the universal, to walk without meeting a traveler.
He knows very well where he is and how he's related to men.
Humanly speaking, he is insane and cannot make himself understood by anyone.
And yet, insane is the mildest expression for him.
Now, I just want the place where he just nails it and says, whenever Abraham tries to say to himself what he's doing, he can't say anything to himself about what he's doing, except that he's a murderer, because that's the.
Here I am, at the top of 95.
So Abraham's story contains a teleological suspension of the ethical.
Let's start a little before, at the bottom of 94.
And now I return to Abraham.
In the time before the outcome, either Abraham was a murderer every minute or we stay with the paradox and so forth.
So Abraham's story contains a teleological suspension of the ethical.
See, it's not just an ethical that's higher or that's based on his understanding of what is best for his peer group.
It's a suspension of the ethical, meaning the ethical is no longer the highest thing.
There is something higher.
He has, as the individual, become higher than the universal.
This is the paradox which cannot be mediated.
How he got into it is just as inexplicable as how he stayed in it.
If this is not how it is with Abraham, then it is not even a tragic healer, but a murderer.
And why isn't he a murderer?
Oh, well, I've got to find a place.
You guys should help me, but I don't know why I can't just find it.
I'll look at my notes in a minute, but that seems like a desperate thing to do.
I have to be able to just see it.
See, what I want to find is when Kierkegaard says, and he's got to say it, that when Abraham talks to himself and tries to make intelligible what he's doing, he's only got the shared ethical language.
And the shared ethical language says you're a murderer.
What page?
39?
89?
89.
Okay.
I owe you great thanks if that's where it is.
And I don't know how I keep missing it.
Well, that's close because it says Abraham cannot be mediated at the top.
He cannot speak.
The moment he speaks, he expresses the universal.
Does it say the murderer?
That's the right thing, all right.
But does it say it later down or somewhere?
But that's right.
When he speaks, he has to keep silent because if he asks himself, well, what are you doing?
He can only say that he's a murderer.
If I can't find it right now, it doesn't matter.
I say it's on 95 or on 103.
Let's look and see.
Now, we did 95, and it wasn't there.
And now I want to go 103, top of 102.
Yes, I guess so.
And there he is, and remains a murderer.
Okay, that's better than anyone I found, and I'm going to mark it.
But I thought there was one in which it says when he talks to himself, he can only say.
I mean, it's implied in everything that we've read.
But I thought I would find a place where he just said it outright, and I haven't found it yet.
Okay, we know that he's a murderer, that he's insane, that he can't speak, because if he said anything to himself, he'd be a murderer.
Okay, what I want to do now, because I feel otherwise I will lose you, is what's the phenomenon?
Is this just sort of psychological, theological, science fiction or something?
Do people ever get in the position in which what's calling them to do something is something they feel that it's the most right thing they could ever do, the best thing that makes their life worth living, and that it is the most awful thing that they're just totally despicable if they do it.
Well, I think there's an easy example, and I think it's fascinating because it may even be a true example.
But think now what it would be like to be a homosexual in 1850 in Copenhagen, which Kierkegaard may well have been.
Nobody knows why he couldn't marry Regina.
He wrote notes about it in his journal and called it the thorn in his flesh that prevented it, and he tore out those pages and burned them or something.
But he did show up dressed up like a dandy in the intermissions of operas.
He was very weird.
But in any case, suppose he was gay, and suppose, just I don't know if there's any, there's no evidence for this, that he loved some guy.
Let's call him John.
Now, Kierkegaard is then exactly in the position of Abraham.
That is, the best thing he can do is be with this guy, and it is, and what does he have to say to himself if he uses any language?
It's despicable, it's unnatural, it's depraved, it's disgusting, it's whatever.
He has a whole lot of words he can use to describe what he's doing, but they're all awful.
They're all, nobody would do such a thing, and here he is doing it.
And that's the situation that really can happen to people.
It happens to us that we're looking at it from the point of view of Berkeley in 2000-something after gay liberation and all that.
It isn't a problem anymore.
But it was a problem even when 50 years ago, when I was in high school and graduate school, it was a big deal whether people came out or kept secret this depraved and disgusting side of their lives.
And now you can see why Kierkegaard thinks that's important, whether it was in his life or not.
There is a possible situation in which, for the people who are in it, the ethical comes up, crash against their calling, their sense of what's the most important, meaningful thing in their life that has the highest authority in their life.
And then they both have authority.
It isn't as if, and that's why I say it's stronger than what he said.
It isn't as if just that there's two different reasons going on.
There's only one reason, the ethical reason, which said this is depraved and unnatural, disgusting, pervert, you're a pervert.
And there is the feeling that this is the best thing I ever did.
Okay, I've got another one now.
And I used to go on about what it would be like to be a child raised by the Nazis who wanted to save a Jew.
But I think now, and then maybe you could tell the same story, I'm sure, in some form about suicide bombers and how somebody who could, maybe somebody could be called to be a suicide bomber and at the same time know that that made them a murderer.
I don't know.
But the best one, somebody sent me one day, last time I gave it, that's the greatness of podcasts.
Nobody had ever told me this in our own American tradition, in what might be, some people think the best American novel ever.
I think second place to Moby Dick.
But anyway, a good one, and that's Huckleberry Finn.
How many of you read Huckleberry Finn?
You recognize what I'm talking about as the suspension of the ethical?
Jim does it.
You don't have to be Abraham or a Kierkegaard.
So I'm going to read it.
It's about whether he's going to turn Jim in or not.
And he starts to turn him in, and then he lies to some slave hunters and sends them away.
And then I'm going to read two quotes from him.
They went off and got aboard the raft, and I got aboard the raft feeling bad and low because I knowed very well I had done wrong.
And I see it weren't no use for me to try to learn to do right.
A body that don't get started right when he's a little, when he's little, ain't got no show.
When the pinch comes, there ain't nothing to back him up.
And so he gets beat.
Then I thought a minute and I says to myself, hold on.
Suppose you've done the right thing and given Jim up.
Would you felt better about what you do now?
No, says I.
I'd feel bad.
I'd feel just the same way I do now.
I mean, this is about anguish.
This is about the fact that he's caught between knowing that whatever he does, he's done something terrible.
If he turns Jim in, it would be terrible.
And he knows that.
And then he realizes, I mean, first he knows that if he lies to protect Jim, it's terrible because that makes him, well, I guess a very, very, very bad thing, a slave protector.
Or if he gives Jim in, it's bad.
So here he tries it again.
After writing a letter to Mrs.
Watson that he's got her possession, namely Jim, I took it up and I held it, that's the letter betraying Jim, in my hand.
I was a trembling because I got to decide forever betwixt two things and I knowed it.
I studied a minute.
I sort of hold my breath and then I said to myself, all right then, I'll go to hell, and tore it up.
That's like Abraham saying, okay, then I'm a murderer.
It was awful thoughts, awful words, but they were said, and I let them stay said, and that's it.
So, okay, so there, I mean, it's great that it's there because it's not, that just shows that it's something that can happen.
Of course, again, we're looking back from the fact that now we don't think it's a big problem because we don't think people should turn in slaves and have slaves and so forth.
But you'd have to find something now.
But if you found something now, I don't know what it would be.
If anybody does, they can write an A-plus paper.
It would have to be something that we all agree is so bad that it's unintelligible it could ever become good.
That's what it would be like if somebody was in it now.
And yet somebody was doing it because they couldn't help but feel that it was the best thing they ever did.
Now, it gets very interesting at this point.
But now it's time.
I'm going to not do that part.
I'm going to stick to this.
But I'll tell you what's interesting.
I'm going to start with it next time.
You will want to ask yourself, but if you did find one like it, how could you tell whether they were just crazy?
Well, I can't.
I have to go on with this.
So, I mean, it isn't as if just any crazy will do is an example.
You can't take the shining and say the Jack Nicholson character who's been reading Kierkegaard and is setting out to kill his son is doing this.
But the question is, why not?
Or there's another movie I mentioned called Bigger Than Life.
These are movies you should take out and watch where the guy has been reading Kierkegaard again and sets out to kill his son.
This happens apparently in the best of families every once in a while.
But there's got to be, Kierkegaard says, some kind of criteria that you can tell a knight of faith from a crazy.
And I'm not going to tell you what it is, although in a certain sense I have told you what it is, but I haven't, I'm not going to tell you in the sense in which I've already told you.
So I'm going to go back for the last five minutes, though, and I'll start, you think about it, and I'll start next time with what he calls the criteria.
If you're reading carefully, you'll see a point where he says, well, we've got to give some criteria so we can tell the knights of faith from the loonies.
Okay, let's see now.
So where are we?
Well, Greek philosophical categories have no way to distinguish unconditional commitment from sin.
No way to distinguish faith from sin.
Oh, that's interesting.
Yeah, maybe I should, I'm going to say that till next time, too.
So the Greek conflict is sort of out in the open in Kierkegaard, where it never was in the history of the culture up to then.
Although people had always been stuck in these two worlds, mostly they didn't notice it.
They thought they lived in one coherent world.
Now, let's do one more thing in the next five minutes, and I won't be coming back to that.
And of course, he says, if you really understand this, it'll keep you awake at night because you will have this terrible thing that some people will, and maybe you will, be called upon to do things which go directly against the ethical the way Abraham was.
And over here's the middle of 60 is a place sort of close to what I was looking for.
Abraham was willing to murder Isaac.
But the point is that Abraham has to say to himself that he's a murderer.
That's the homosexual example.
He has to say to himself that he's a pervert.
And notice that Huck says, I'm going to hell.
I'm a bad person.
And he doesn't, he can't, there's no way outside of that.
He has no way of denying that.
He asked if he really believes it.
Okay, but I want to do the other because I don't want to go back to it.
And that's the tragic hero.
Because the tragic hero is really what he invented.
You back there.
Sort of.
A tragic hero manages to do a deed which, it turns out, can be reconciled, where his commitment is a kind of commitment which has a kind of universal instead of an individual component in it, which puts him in tune with the universal instead of requiring him to go against the universe.
What would that be like?
Well, that's like the tragic hero.
The story of Agamemnon comes in here, then Kierkegaard tells it.
And the story of Agamemnon is that, and I have been, how many know what happens with Agamemnon and Ephigenia?
Okay, not very many.
I can end with that, and then I'll start with the next.
Oh, but I'll tell you the story.
This is from, it's in the Orestea, I guess is the main place it is.
But it's one of the Greek myths that is important.
So when Helen runs off with this attractive stranger, Paris, I can't resist saying because what she does is in a certain sense all right.
Aphrodite shines on her, and when Aphrodite shines on anything, the situation becomes purely erotic.
And this so that she ran off and left her husband and child when Paris came to stay overnight at their house, at their palace.
And the interesting thing is, in Homer, nobody blames her because moods are like gods and you're supposed to do them.
But that's for another, that's my other course.
Let's stick to this one.
She runs off with Paris.
Agamemnon, the brother of the, no, no, Agamemnon.
Menelaus is married to Helen.
Helen runs off with Paris.
Agamemnon is the brother of Menelaus.
And Agamemnon has sworn to protect his brother, and they've sworn brotherly truce, like a brotherly oath to help each other.
So it looks like now Menelaus, or Agamemnon, has to run off and help Menelaus get Helen back.
And when he organizes, and he's the commander-in-chief now, Agamemnon, he organizes all his forces, and they get as far as an island out a little way from, where are they, in Ithaca?
Yeah, in Ithaca.
And they, and all of a sudden, there's no wind, and they're stuck.
And for days and days, they're stuck.
And the prophet comes and says, unless you kill your daughter Ephigenia, your men will be stuck there forever.
And they're beginning to get sick, and they're beginning to get hungry.
And so he's got a big problem.
And then he sees that he's got to kill Ephigenia.
And he also loves her.
And the way Kierkegaard puts it, she's his favorite daughter and all that.
And so he's in sort of the situation of Abraham killing Isaac, except, and he does it.
He kills the daughter.
And instead of everybody thinking that he's a murderer, or he thinking that he's a murderer, everybody thinks, including him, that what he did was intelligible.
He subsumed one ethical, namely, or two, maybe, don't kill, and secondly, it's your duty to love and protect your children under a higher ethical, do your duty as king.
And his duty was to get the, as commander-in-chief, to get those troops off the island and over to Troy to get Helen back.
And everybody celebrates the fact that his unconditional commitment was to be king, which is a universal role, and it called him to do the ethical thing, namely to kill Ephigenia, and he did it.
I'll say one more thing because it's so timely.
Nobody knows except me, and now you will know, why in the world the prophet required Agamemnon to kill his daughter in order to get his troops off to Troy.
I had a colleague, he died here about six months ago, who understood that.
He wrote a book called Agamemnon and Other Losers, but he explained what it was.
The answer is: what the Prophet understands is that if you're going to send other people's children off to die in the war, you have to be ready to send your own children off to die in the war.
Bush wants the young people to go off and die in Iraq, then if he had children of draftable age, they'd have to be drafted.
So Agamemnon has to, in effect, show that he's willing to sacrifice his child to have the right to ask all the other citizens to sacrifice their children.
And when he does it, it shows that he's ready to sacrifice his child for promoting the war as commander-in-chief and so forth, then they get off the island and everything comes out all right.
And what's the moral of this?
Tragic heroes go to subsume one ethical under another.
That's their way of they don't suspend the ethical.
They just suspend the one ethical, love, take care of your daughter, under a higher ethical, do your job as king.
And that's utterly different.
And then they become completely intelligible.
That's utterly different than what Abraham does and what Vierkegaard, if he's homosexual, does and what Huck does.
They subsume the whole ethical under something which is unintelligible from the point of view of that ethical and there's no other point of view.
And that's the paradox and that's the anguish.
Okay, now we're ready for the next stage.