It's probably the most important and interesting episode in the book and the most fun lecture to give.
It's, remember, we had just gotten up to the issue of miracles.
And as usual, the well, and sort of, I said this, and I don't want to repeat it except just very briefly.
If Dostoevsky is going to existentialize miracles, then he's got to explain it in terms of human experience.
And it's got to not be, as philosophers like to say, spooky.
It's not got to be something that's outside of the, that contravenes the laws of physics and chemistry.
And yet, it's got to be something that isn't part of the everyday natural world, or it wouldn't be a miracle.
So it's pretty hard to figure out whether there's any space in there for something which captures the human, something about human existence, that's why I call it existentialized, captures something about human existence that it makes sense to call a miracle.
And it's something that only Christianity has brought to the world.
And you have to, and now Dostas is going to try to do it.
Now, the other part of the sort of preparation for this is the question left from the Grand Inquisitor, where all of these or most of these existentialized issues are already posed but not answered, is the question: can people live without miracles when there's some big crisis in their lives?
That's on 290.
You're going to be running around in around 290 from now on.
So, this is about two-thirds of the way down, where the Grand Inquisitor says, Is the nature of men such that they can reject miracles?
And at the great moments of their lives, the moments of their deepest, most agonizing spiritual difficulties, cling only to the free verdict of the heart?
Well, we're going to find out whether people can.
We're going to find out by looking at somebody who is the best person in the book, namely Adayasha, and see whether he can get along without a miracle when there's a spiritual crisis in his life.
And this is already happening on 380.
It turns out that Dosama's body is beginning to decompose and to smell bad, and the monks are taking this as a kind of negative miracle.
That is, it's a sign that there's something wrong because the body isn't just decomposing normally, but too quickly.
And that's the scandal.
And the question, and the I think I did.
I already talk about this.
Did I ask you whether you think after reading it that this is a negative miracle, or is it just a natural thing, as in the middle of 378 the narrator says?
Or is it some kind of positive miracle?
I'll just repeat briefly that there's lots of stuff being written about what it means that Father Zosima's body is decomposed.
I mean, there's a lot of gossip in the monasteries, but the gossip is still going on in the secondary literature.
What does it tell us that the body of Zosima is stinking, as Rakedin says?
And you'll see later in the book.
How many have managed to finish it over vacation now?
Or managed to finish it, whatever.
Okay, well, it doesn't give away the plot to say that Elusha dies, and Elusha's body remains absolutely pure and doesn't smell at all.
So people say, gee, what is there wrong with Zosima?
Write about Elusha.
Well, if you look into it, you discover that the windows were closed.
I won't read it, but on 378 it talks about that.
There are no flowers.
It talks a lot about the flowers, the windows being open around Elusha's coffin.
The elders are not washed when they die.
That's just a traditional thing.
He mentions that on right off on 375, three lines down.
As is well known, the bodies of dead monks and hermits are not washed.
And it was a warm autumn day, which you'll learn in the next chapter when Alyasha runs out of the monastery into the weather.
Well, given that the windows are closed, there are no flowers, the body is not washed, and it's a warm autumn day, do you think it's a positive miracle or a negative miracle or just something natural?
Pretty easy, I hope.
A no-brainer is supposed to be.
It's just something natural.
It might happen to anybody's body under those conditions.
And that's what you're supposed to think, because you're not supposed to expect a miracle to be something that goes against the laws of physics and chemistry by either condemning somebody by their body rotting too fast or giving any credit to anybody because their body isn't decomposing.
And it's just a wrong way to think about it.
That's a magical kind of miracle.
And the whole point is, if Dostoevsky is going to deal with it, he's going to deal with it in an entirely different way.
He's not going to make it a miracle that goes against the laws of physics and chemistry.
It's that Zosima's body stinks because of the laws of physics and chemistry.
That's how it is.
It doesn't mean anything.
That's the first thing to know.
But now back to the important question.
How does Alyasha feel about the fact that Zosima's body is, Zosima is not performing a miracle?
And then on the middle of 378, it gives him a terrible shock.
It brought a crisis, middle of 378, brought a crisis and turning point to his spiritual development, giving a shock to his intellect, which finally strengthened it for the rest of his life and gave it a definite aim.
We haven't got to that yet.
But already we've got to the point where we can see, and it's clearer on 389, that Alyasha absolutely needs a miracle in order to keep his faith in Zosima.
So the answer: can people, really good people, deep spiritual people, sort of strong people like Alyasha, live in the face of moral spiritual crises without any miracle and keep their faith?
The answer is no.
The Alyasha people, the Grand Inquisitor is right, people need miracles.
What he's wrong about is that you just manufacture them by making all paces that appear on veils and so forth in the Catholic Church.
That's not what Dostoevsky wants, that they do need miracles.
Now, and so now what's going to happen?
Well, what's going to happen is Alyasha is going into a kind of decline starting on 389.
All kinds of bad things are happening to him.
And they're happening to him.
And Dostoevsky is always so brilliantly saying about three or four different things at once.
Dostoevsky is telling you how much Alyasha's love is wrapped up in Zosima.
And the fact that Zosima isn't performing miracles is, let's see.
And the way his love is wrapped up in Zosima is such that when Zosima doesn't perform miracles, then Alyasha is going to lose sort of the object of his defining love.
So, this is, I'll make it clearer in a minute, on 389, two-thirds down.
The fact is that all the love that lay concealed in his pure young heart for everyone and everything had for the past year been concentrated, and perhaps wrongly so, and indeed wrongly so, on one being, his beloved elders, and so forth and so forth.
And it's true that his elder had for so long been accepted by him as his ideal that all his young strength and energy could not but turn toward the ideal, even to the forgetting at that moment of everyone and everything, when his ideal elder is dying or dead, I guess, at this point.
Then he remembered afterwards, I'm still on 389, how on that terrible day, the day of the body decomposed, he had entirely forgotten his brother Dimitri, about whom he had been worried, and so forth.
So he's oh, now remember, we've seen that Ivan says, I'm not my brother's keeper, and Smerzhikov says, Why should I know about and care about what Dimitri is doing?
And now even Alyasha isn't caring about Dmitry.
That's very bad.
And I've been saying he needs miracles to keep from losing his faith because all of his love is wrapped up in Zosima.
Zosima ought to be a super being, a super spiritual being, and that ought to be shown by miracles.
And it's not happening.
But it's tricky because these lines at the bottom of 389 make it look like I'm wrong, but I'm not.
And you'll see in a minute.
It was not miracles he needed, the narrator says, but only the higher justice, which had been, in his belief, outraged by the blow that has so suddenly and cruelly wounded his heart.
That's decomposition.
And what was the higher justice?
Well, the higher justice was that if Zosima is really a sort of spiritual star, I mean, a saint, then he shouldn't decompose.
And what does it signify that this justice looked for by Alyasha took the form of miracles to be wrought immediately by the ashes of his adored elder?
Why?
And so forth and so forth.
Let me skip a little, but it was justice, justice he thirsts for, not miracles.
Well, that doesn't really make any sense.
Rightly.
I mean, the narrator is sort of inside Alyasha, and he's telling us what Alyasha really wanted was a miracle.
But he puts, Alyasha is putting it in a very strange way.
He's putting it by saying he demands justice.
Why is he putting it in this mysteriously strange way?
Do you know?
Who thinks in terms of sort of whether we should accept or not the world, in terms of whether the world is just or not?
Ivan.
He's corrupted by Yvonne.
And you can see that at the top of 391.
Well, let me read the middle of 390 first.
Even had there been no miracles, had there been nothing marvelous, why this indignity, why this humiliation, this premature decay, the excess of nature, as the spiteful monk said.
In other words, he's not understanding none of them are, that this is just perfectly natural given the windows and the washing and so forth.
And he's seeing it through the conversation with Yvonne.
Remember, in the background is Dostoevsky constantly showing you how different, how people influence and corrupt and help each other.
And Yvonne has corrupted him.
So the top of 390.
I will not forget, however, forget to mention something strange, which for a time came to the surface of Alyasha's mind at this fatal moment.
This new something was the harassing impression left by the conversation with Yvonne, which now persistently haunted Alyasha.
At this moment, it haunted him.
Well, it was not that something of fundamental, elemental, so to speak, faith of his soul, it's not that the faith of his soul had been shaken.
He loved his God and firmly believed in him, though he was suddenly murmuring against him.
Remember, Yvonne says, I believe in God, or at least it doesn't matter whether you believe in God.
The question is whether you accept his world.
And now he have, you know, faith, and Alyasha is beginning to lose his.
A vague but tormenting and evil impression left by his conversation with Yvonne the day before revived again in his soul and seemed forcing its way to the surface.
So Yvonne has fed him up for having this rebellion reaction to the decomposition of Zosima, which is a special case of the general principle.
When you're in a spiritual crisis, you need miracles.
And Alyasha is in a spiritual crisis because his beloved monk is dying, has died, and is decomposing, and he needs a miracle, and he isn't getting it.
At that moment, he's very close to losing his faith.
And guess who arrives on the scene?
Exactly at that moment.
On 391.
It was dusk when Rakitin, crossing the pine grove from the hermitage to the monastery, suddenly noticed Alyasha lying downward on the ground under a tree and so forth.
He went up and called him.
So Alyasha has thrown himself on the ground in despair, really, that this person whom he loves and who's the unconditional commitment of his life isn't being recognized by the universe or by God as he should be.
And now comes this conversation with Rakitin to just to say, again, remind you that Rakitin is the existentialized devil.
He behaves, he behaves in the world the way the devil, in sort of Christian mythology, from Dostoevsky's point of view, believes that namely, the devil is going around in the world, undermining people's faith.
He shows up when they're about to lose their faith, and instead of strengthening their faith, contributes to undermining it.
That's just what Rakitin is now going to do.
On 392, he says at the top, can you be so upset because your old man has begun to stink?
You don't mean you believed he was going to work miracles, exclaimed Rakitin.
And then he's really upset.
He says, I believe, I believe, I want to believe, cried Alyasha.
And then Rakitin says, Damn it all.
Why no schoolboy of 13 believes in that now?
And there, so now you're angry with God, you're rebelling against him.
See, he recognizes that it's the rebellion of like Ivan.
And now look what happens in the middle.
I'm not rebelling against my God.
I simply don't accept his world.
Alyasha suddenly smiled a forced smile.
He's being taken over by Yvonne, sort of challenging, challenging, channeling Yvonne at this point.
And now Rakitin sees that he's got a chance to really turn him against God altogether.
And then he begins his temptations.
Let me just make sure I am where I want to be.
Yeah.
So, anybody want to say anything?
I don't like it when I just go on and on, but I must admit, I can't think of anything anybody could say at this point, does he?
As he is laying it out even more clearly, he's going to hit you over the head with this whole miracle story, absolutely, so that I don't see any alternative interpretation.
So let's go on and if you do, challenge it, please.
So, what does he say?
Well, he says at the bottom of 392, Rakitin says, I've got some sausage in my pocket.
And it must be, I think it's lint.
It's something that he shouldn't be eating sausage.
And Alyasha says, give me some.
And he says, what?
You're going to eat it?
It's a regular mutiny.
The rebellion, of course.
And he said, Would you like some vodka?
I suppose vodka's going too far for you.
You know, the devil is tempting him step by step.
And he says, Give me some vodka, too.
You surprise me, Alyasha.
Rakitin looked at him in amazement.
So at the bottom of 393, he pulls the ultimate thing.
He's going to really run Alyasha.
He knows that Alyasha has a Karamatsov.
It seems practically genetic.
He lusts after Grushenka.
So does old Karamatsov.
Everybody but Ivan.
But so, anyway, so at the bottom of 393, Rakitin says, let's go to Grushenka's.
Will you come?
And Alyasha says, yeah, let's go to Grushenka's.
So he answers calmly, and he's off.
And it turns out that Grushenka has bribed Rakitin to bring Alyasha because she wants to seduce him.
At the end of the next paragraph, his object, namely, it's interesting.
We want to know, you want to make sure that Rakitin's the devil?
Well, read the last bit of that chapter.
His, Rakitin's object in this case was twofold.
First, a revengeful desire to see the downfall of the righteous.
Well, that's just a perfectly demonic, evil, and it's the essence of the evil notion.
Instead of supporting the righteous, he wants to bring them down.
And Alyasha's fall from saint to sinner, that's what he wants.
See, only the devil wants that.
Everybody else would like everybody who were sinners to become saints and help them do it.
That's what Alyasha does, because Alyasha is an angel.
As you see many times, if you watch for it, Alyasha is always described as an angel.
And in the second place, Rakitin had a certain material gain in view.
Yeah.
Well, yes, Grushenka has bribed him, told him he'd get a reward if he brings Alyasha to her house.
So, and if Alyasha doesn't get a miracle, he's going to lose his faith, and Rakitin's going to help him do it.
I think I've read everything that's important.
Yeah, 392.
Yeah, I just catching up.
Okay, we're so far.
Now I'm at a stopping point.
Namely, like a scene shift, the next thing they arrive at Grushenka's.
And that's when Dostoevsky's going to pull off his amazing coup.
So they arrive at Grushenka's.
Now we have to switch and talk about what state of mind Grushenka is in.
She is having a kind of fit of excitement and mixture of joy and anger because, and now you need to know a little bit about what happened to her on 395, a third of the way down, there were rumors that she had been at 17, betrayed by someone, some sort of officer, and immediately afterwards abandoned by him.
The officer had gone away and married, while Grushenka had been left in poverty and disgrace.
And that's, and that officer, that Polish officer, the wife has died, and he's coming back and calling for Grushenka.
And she is alternately sort of humiliated and outraged, he's just whistling for her like a dog, and happy that he's going to, he's ready to marry her.
And she's in a state of great excitement about all.
That's what we're hearing about at this point.
And just at the bottom of 397, she's so excited, her face was pale, her lips and eyes hot, and she was restlessly tapping her arm and so forth.
He's all upset.
She doesn't know what to do in the face of this.
The middle of 402, she says, My officer is coming, Rakita.
My officer is coming.
I heard he was coming.
Did he see so near?
He's at Muckrow right now.
He'll send a messenger from there.
So he wrote, I got a letter from him today.
I'm expecting the messenger any minute.
So she's that's her optimistic, I mean, hopeful view.
But she's got, she's got this problem that she doesn't, she doesn't know whether she will or and go to him with a knife or like a dog, because she doesn't know whether her she wants to revenge herself against him for what he did to her when she was 17 or whether she's going to come when he calls her because he's going to make her an honest woman at this point.
That this is, she says it on 408, about two-thirds of the way down.
It took my breath away.
Then I suddenly thought, if he comes and whistles to me, I'll creep back to him like a beaten dog.
And then she says at the bottom of the page, perhaps I'll take a knife with me today.
I can't make up my mind.
And a little above the bottom, before you came in, she says to Alyasha, I was lying here waiting, brooding, deciding my whole future life, and you can never know what was in my heart.
Although she's pretty well told him now what was in her heart.
These two alternatives.
And it's important to realize, which isn't very hard, that these are two destructive alternatives.
I mean, there's nothing, nothing good can happen to her.
If she goes to him like a dog, she'll feel humiliated all the rest of her life with no sense of her own value.
And if she goes to him with a knife, she goes to Siberia as a murderer.
So she and she doesn't know, there's no way out.
She's in a kind of trap.
And at that point, I've jumped ahead to tell you what's going on.
What really happens back at 401, as soon as they come in, she jumps onto Alyasha's lap, and she's interested in, looks like she's busy trying to seduce him on 401.
Where did she jump into his lap?
Let's see.
I think I just lost what it is.
401.
I've got 401 in front of me, but I'm not sure.
Oh, yeah, there it is.
Okay, we're a third of the way down.
Rakitin says his elder stinks, and she says, What?
You're talking nonsense.
And let me sit on your knee, Alyasha, like this.
He suddenly got up and laughing nestled like a kitten on his knee with her right arm about his neck.
I'll cheer you up, my pious boy.
You'll let me sit on your knee.
You won't be angry.
If you tell me, I'll get off.
Now comes one of the crucial paragraphs.
How is Alyasha going to take this?
As a Karamatsov, he's sort of lusting for her.
And as somebody who is scared of anything that has to do with sex, he's afraid of her.
And here she is sitting on his lap.
Okay, well, here's what happens.
Alyasha didn't speak.
He sat afraid to move.
He heard her words.
If you tell me, I'll get off.
But there was nothing in his heart, such as Rakitin watching him might have expected.
The grief in his heart swallowed up every sensation that might have been aroused.
And if only he could have thought clearly at that moment, he would have realized that he had now the strongest armor to protect him from every lust and temptation.
Yet, in spite of the vague irresponsiveness of his spiritual condition and sorrow that overwhelmed him, he couldn't help wondering at a new and strange sensation in his heart.
Do you know what that is?
What's happening to him?
Well, I think I wrote on the board once in some other connection, though I don't remember why, two crucial words to understand this: Eros, and what he's been feeling, erotic, agape, the Greek word for Christian love, for what gets translated charity, but that's not good anymore, so we just say agape love.
He's feeling the kind of love that he had for Zosima and that Zosima has for everybody.
And it's described here very briefly: a strange new sensation in his heart.
This woman, I'm reading back on 401, this dreadful woman had no terror for him now, none of that terror that stirred in him at the passing thought of women.
On the contrary, this woman, dreaded above all women, sitting now on his knee, holding him in her arms, aroused him a quite different, unexpected, peculiar feeling, the feeling of the intensest and purest interest without a trace of fear.
Some other translations say curiosity instead of interest.
That's definitely bad.
I don't know the Russian, but you Russians listening to me, I have them out there.
Let me know, but I'm sure that that's the right thing.
The purest interest is the agape, not a desire for anything.
Eros is desire.
Desire for something that you lack, but want.
This is love as overflowing goodness held for, and not something you want.
Okay, so now we've got the and Dalyach is sitting there, sort of too terrified, was too terrified to look at Krushchenka, but and but now he's got no eros.
It's all this new experience of agape that he's feeling.
Comments, anybody yet?
Okay, you sure?
Okay, okay, I'm going on.
He's got this unselfish, disinterested interestedness.
And that's what in this book is called active love.
Zothima is a kind of specialist in active love.
And now it's as if Zothama has sort of contributed to Alyasha, who's caught it.
So he's got it too now, active love.
And Alyasha, and it turns out, now we need another move.
Alyasha has been responsible for Grushenka's constant sense of worthlessness and humiliation, which is what she feels all the time.
And how could he be causing it?
Not now, but in the past.
Well, you want to say something?
That's right, exactly.
He's so attracted by her that he's afraid even to look at her.
I think I told you maybe Marilyn Monroe wanted to play.
You've got to think of sort of Grushenka looking sort of like Marilyn Monroe with a dark wig, at least that's how I think of it.
And he can't resist her, so he can't look at her.
But when he doesn't look at her, she understands that as he's disgusted by her.
Where does that happen?
On the middle of 403.
Rakitin is thinking, you know, that now she's going to seduce him, and she says, No, this is different.
I love Alyasha in a different way.
It's true, Alyasha.
I had designs on you because I'm a horrid, violent creature, but at other times I've looked upon you, Alyasha, as my conscience.
I kept thinking, how anyone like that must despise a nasty thing like me?
And then she says about him lowering his eyes, I have to find that.
Did anybody see that?
If he doesn't look at her, I thought I'd mark it.
Hmm.
I don't know where it is.
But it's true that he casts his eyes down.
We ought to be able to find that.
Surely somebody will find it if I just look for it.
No, maybe it's going to come up later.
It's true.
Anyway, and he, the important thing is that by not looking at her, he's making her worse because he's making her feel worthless and humiliated as she says that he had even, he disdains her so much.
And now let's see where we are.
He couldn't look at her.
Well, I've got 407.
Let's see if I say that in 407.
Yeah, here we are, in the middle of 407.
I wanted to ruin you, Alyasha.
That's the holy truth.
I quite meant to.
I wanted so much that I bribed Rakitin.
You knew nothing about it, Alyasha.
You turned away from me if you passed me on the street.
You dropped your eyes.
And I've looked at you a hundred times before today, and I began asking everyone about you.
Your face haunted my heart.
He despises me, I thought.
He won't even look at me.
So that's her typical Dostoevsky thing.
The source of most bad actions are people feeling humiliated and disdained.
And if you loved them instead, you could cure them of what's making them make bad actions.
She's being bad with Alyasha, or wanted to be, seduce him, and humiliate him because she thinks that he's humiliated her.
And then, but, of course, everything gets turned around.
And she tells us that he's an angel.
Now we have to find that.
He says, why didn't you come before you, but you angel?
It's all in such funny order.
Help me find that now.
We have to go back because it happens before that.
We're back on 403.
He thinks he despises me.
And then.
And she has transformed Alyasha.
I'll read that while we're at it, the bottom of 404.
He says, She pities me.
I came here to find a wicked soul.
I felt drawn to evil because I was base and evil myself.
This is Alyasha talking.
And I found a true sister.
I found a treasure, a loving heart.
She had pity on me just now.
Gushenka, I'm speaking of you.
You've raised my soul from the depth.
So they've sort of turned agape on each other.
And now she tells the story of the onion, which we're going to talk about next time.
But I really want to find when she calls him an angel.
Nobody's found it.
They are.
Bottom of 411.
You never know whether anything's going to turn up.
Why didn't you come before, you angel?
She fell on her knees before Alyasha.
I've been waiting all my life for someone like you.
I knew that someone like you would come and forgive me.
I believe that nasty as I am, someone would really love me, not with a lustful love.
That's the crucial, that's her experience of his turning his agape love on her.
And he is an angel.
And she affirms him, and he affirms her.
And now that she's got self-respect, she's got a new option.
She doesn't have to go back humiliated or revengeful, neither like a dog nor with a knife.
But she can go back with sort of hope and joy and look over this Polish guy and see whether she wants to spend her life with him or not.
And Alyacha says she won't take a knife with her, the middle of 409.
He sees that she's been transformed.
He says, after five years of torment, as soon as anyone says a word from the heart to her, that's the agape, it makes her forget everything, forgive everything.
The man who wronged her has come back.
He sends for her and she forgives him everything and hurries to meet him and she won't take a knife with her.
So she's not going with a knife.
She's not going like a dog.
And that's now what's happened there.
Well, it's because the love that he had focused, perhaps mistakenly, and Dostoevsky thinks really mistakenly, because it leads him to forget Dmitry, is now free, thanks to the fact that she is taken pity on Alyasha.
And the love that he had all directed toward Zosima is now freed up so he can turn it on to other people.
He didn't help anybody or love anybody, if you look in the book, until Zosima died and he went to Grushenka.
And Rakitin, and Dostia is constantly putting, if you want to know what's really going on, pay attention to the person who would be most critical of what was really going on and see what he thinks.
So it's Rakitin's view of all this, which is getting it right.
So on 409, Rakitin says, a third of the way down, so you are so primed up with your elders' teaching last night that now you have let it off on me.
Rakitin, Alyasha tries to love Rakitin.
It doesn't work.
He says, Alyasha, man of God.
Rakitin said, with a smile of hatred.
But in fact, it didn't work when he turned it off on Rakitin.
But when he sort of, how's Rakitin let it off, this love onto Grushenka?
It did work.
It did transform her.
So now where are we?
They've had this reciprocal agape situation.
And what has happened?
Well, that agape love, which comes from Zosima, has done something which you have to describe in the right way.
It's created out of nothing a third alternative, which is not destructive for Grushenka, who's up to then had been in this kind of trap of contemplating two destructive alternatives, the knife and the dog.
A new alternative is there, namely, she goes back with joy and neither like a knife or with a life or like a dog, and she just decides on after looking him over what to do with the hole.
And she's saying she's flying to a new life, as she puts it at the two-thirds down on 4:12.
Now, now comes what just happened.
Well, Dostoevsky's going to put it in the mouth of the devil, what just happened?
Do you know what just happened?
This creation out of nothing, of a positive possibility where there are only negative possibilities, where a soul was saved by being looked at with a God they love.
What's the name for that?
A miracle has happened.
But less you don't notice it, and I certainly wouldn't have, and you probably wouldn't have, Dostoevsky will, of course, hit you over the head with it.
And here it is at the bottom of 4:13.
Ratiaton says, So you saved the sinner, he laughed spitefully, you turned the Magdalene into the true path, driven out the seven devils, eh?
So you see, the miracles you were looking for just now have come to pass.
Well, that's pretty clear.
He needed miracles.
He couldn't keep his faith without miracles.
He got a miracle, namely the saving of Grushenka.
He's now okay.
He's been saved by rebound, so to speak.
And all of this is part of this miracle, this love that he loaded up from Zosima, which he now turned on Grushenka.
And so the saintliness of Zosima is ratified by this miracle.
But it isn't quite nailed down yet because it's pretty tenuous, the relation of this miracle to Zosima.
Remember, Zosima, Alyasha doesn't need just any old miracle.
He has to have a miracle performed by Zosima if it's going to justify his love, or which is Ivan's way of putting it, if it's going to, let's say, confirm and strengthen his faith.
So Dostoevsky's going to hit you over the head a few more times.
Again, very clearly, it's Zosima's love that performs these miracles, which don't abrogate the laws of nature, but nonetheless produce these amazing transformations.
And when he goes back to the monastery, he discovers the following thing.
But let me just say one more thing, and then I will get to that.
Right after that miracle story, Rakitin at the bottom of the page behaves like a devil again.
He says, Damnation take you all and each of you, he cried.
Why the devil did I take you to Grushenka?
Well, I mean, that's just Rakitin over and over naming you that he's the devil.
But now, what happens when he gets to Father Zosima?
Then we get more miracle talk.
The important thing is that I'm amazed I don't have it here written down.
If I don't, I will have to find it anyway.
It's a question of the first miracle.
Well, when he gets back to the monastery, okay, I don't have it written down, but I know where it is.
So they've opened the windows.
The smell got so strong that they finally did that.
But that's not what's important.
He began on the top of 415 listening to what Father Piasy was reading.
And what was Father Piasi reading?
If you want to be covered over the head again, the story of the first miracle, of the fish and the wine at Canaan, where Jesus goes at this wedding and there's not enough fish to go around, and he fixes it so there's plenty.
There was this great story in the New Yorker about a year ago about this, where this girl who's following around Jesus, because she's a kind of Jesus groupie, has written in her notebook, and Jesus did this wonderful thing.
He invented canopates, kind of little, you know, little things with a little dab of fish on each one.
So the fish went far and fed everybody.
That is the wrong way to think about the miracle, but it's pretty funny.
But what happens really is, Jesus, and this is important, just breaks the laws of physics and chemistry.
He doesn't invent little fish sandwiches.
He makes a whole lot of fish where there was only a little, and a whole lot of wine where there was only a little.
That's because that was the first miracle.
It was understood by the people at the time, at least, as doing what miracles are supposed to do, break the laws of physics and chemistry.
But it's clear that what was the important thing about that miracle, its miracleness, so to speak, is directly related to what happened with Grushenka.
It's just that things have gone on so that you can't have that kind of miracle anymore that violates the laws.
What you can have is, instead, existentialized miracles.
So you get a story connecting the first miracle with the bread and wine miracle to the current miracle, the latest one, saving Grushenka.
And you get it also relating Zosima into the story with Grushenka.
Now, all that's happening when he goes back on page 415.
So he's reading the story about the marriage and so forth.
And when they wanted more wine in italics, then they got wine, and he's thinking, that's wonderful, they're happy, and everybody's glad I'm just skimming.
And that's the first miracle.
And so then, okay, now it gets directly related to Zosima in 4:17.
And he's having this vision.
Zosima's dead, but he's having a vision of what's happening.
Zosima's talking to him.
So the feast of Canaan turns into at the top of 4:17, Zosima talking.
Yes, my son, I'm called to call and bidden.
He heard a soft voice saying, Why have you hidden yourself?
Come and join us.
It was the voice of Father Zosima, and it must be he since he called him.
The elder took Alyasha by the hand and raised him from his knees and so forth.
He's invited to the feast of Canaan.
The first miracle is being linked with the latest miracle.
It's clear that they're both miracles.
One is the earlier kind of miracle, but the latest one is the existentialized miracle.
And they're all traced these miracles, the second one that is, is traced to Zosima.
And now, I can't tell you why it's important that the elder takes Alyasha by the hand, but there is something called the apostolic succession of bishops, in which in a magical way, it was thought that the bishop, that Jesus gave agate love to Peter, who passes it on to all the bishops.
And only the Catholic Church is in this succession.
It's the big fight between the Catholic Church and the Episcopal Church that sometime in history, time of Henry VIII, maybe I'm not good on history, that they lost touch with the apostolic succession.
Now, of course, that's too magical.
Gostoevsky doesn't care about how laying on the hands passed on this love from bishop to bishop.
The way to pass on love is to love people.
But I wondered when I read it, we better, and I followed it because you'll see that Markle also puts his hand on Zosima at a certain point and says, go live for me.
And now I wondered how Zosima is going to pass this on to Alyasha.
Well, he does.
And on 4:17, when he takes Alyasha by the hand and raises him, it's like in Star Trek, where Spock has this thing he has to pass on to, and you wonder, I forget which Star Trek it is, how he manages to pass it on.
And they look at the picture, and yes, yes, he does just touch whoever it is.
I think it's the doctor.
But anyway, that's, again, the magical kind.
But this was just the fact, important that at this crucial moment in this vision, he gets this connection with Zosima.
Now, I think we've got as far as we need to get with that, but I want to make sure.
Well, there's one puzzle which I can't answer.
Well, in 317, I'll just say it briefly because I want to make sure we have enough time for what's going to happen next.
But there's this funny fact, which I'm going to, one of the Alex, who knows whose natural language is Russian, his first language is Russian, is going to help me to understand the following thing.
When he's talking to Zosima, Zosima says in the middle of the page, the end of that big paragraph, begin your work, dear one.
Begin it, gentle one.
Do you see our son?
Do you see him?
S-O-N.
Well, in another translation, it's S-U-N.
Well, that looks like a big difference, where one of them seems to be Jesus, a son with a capital S, the Son of God, and the other one seems to be an astronomical shining body.
My guess is that there is some Russian word that means something like, in English we say, somebody was the light of my life.
I think that's what this word is trying to do.
It's trying to bring together the Jesus story with the story that there can be other people, like Zosima is the light of Alyasha's life.
And if you've got to Markle, how many of you read the Markle part?
Presumably you have.
We're going to talk about it next time.
Zosima's brother, who passes on this love, is the light of Zosima's life.
These are, by the way, remember these mysterious fingers that point Zosima to the monastery and point Alyasha, so to speak, out of the monastery?
That's all the channeled love of Markle.
But put that off for the time being.
So, what you get is that there's something like this, that Zosima is passing on this love, which was charged up when Alyasha loved him with Agape love, to Alyasha, who is going to pass it on, we don't know yet how, into the world.
But so much for that.
That's the next stopping point.
I think, let me just look.
Yeah, the next, that's.
So, anybody want to say anything about that?
Yeah.
Hooray.
I didn't hear the question very well.
Is there a personal situation?
My own personal me?
Yeah.
One has it.
Oh, that's a terrific question because you are exactly, how does it feel to get this love, to get in touch with the light, which is the light of agape, and have it shine on you and through you?
How would that feel?
That's your question?
Is that that I changed it?
Yes.
Okay, how nice.
The next page is the answer.
You asked exactly the right question.
Exactly.
At the bottom of 4:17.
And it starts out, let's start with the paragraph before the end.
Something glowed in Alyosha's heart, something filled it until it ached.
Tears of rapture rose from his soul.
He stretched out his hands, uttered a cry, and woke up.
Now, this has been a vision that he's had.
But this vision is crucial because it ties the first miracle to the latest miracle, and it ties them both to Zosima, and it sort of reinforces the argument that the point that Dossia is making.
But now comes a whole new point, her point.
And what does Alyasha experience at this point?
Okay, let's see.
Alyasha didn't listen to the reading, and he went up to the coffin and so forth, and he gazed for a minute in the coffin, and now comes the crucial thing.
We've got to read almost every word of the rest of the chapter.
It's very beautiful.
Dostoevsky at his most amazing, and it's absolutely central to the book, literally central to the book, if you look at it.
I mean, I think Dostoevsky thinks architectonically, that is, if he thinks if it's the most important thing in the book, it ought to be in the middle of the book.
And it is.
Okay, and what happens?
I'm going to read things.
He did not stop on the steps either, but went quickly down, his soul overflowing with rapture, learning for freedom, space, and openness.
Well, that's already interesting.
Dostoevsky, and it's so moving when you're reading it, because Dostoevsky, you realize later, has kept you sort of cooped up in a world in which everybody is in everybody's face in these hot rooms and monks and inns and so forth, that you don't feel nature, you don't feel openness, but he is now yearning for freedom, space, and openness.
And the sort of the, if you see it as a movie, as I always do when I read these things, it goes into cinema scope, big super cinema scope, and it goes into color.
You haven't heard anything about color, but you're about to hear about color.
I'll read some more.
The vault of heaven, full of the soft shining stars, stretched vast and fathomless above him.
The Milky Way ran in two pale streams from zenith to the horizon.
The white towers and the golden, that's a color, domes enfolded the earth.
The white tower against the sapphire sky.
The autumn flowers, that's how we know it was a warm autumn, in the garden were slumbering.
The silence of the earth seemed to melt into the silence of the heavens.
The mystery of earth was one with the mystery of the stars.
If anybody's trying to track mystery, there's a clue, and I don't know what it means, that this is called a mystery.
But now, let me see if I'm just keeping up here.
Okay, so now we're in this total openness, and he's about to have the sort of the religious experience that she wants.
But there's lots happening.
He threw himself on the ground in despair at the beginning of this lecture, remember?
And now he's going to throw himself on the ground in a new appreciation of something absolutely solid that supports him and so forth.
It's somehow, this is where the earthy switches from being a bad thing, dirty, to being a good thing, something that sort of supports you and sustains you and that you should love.
And this is kind of an aside, but this is what happens next.
Galiasha stood and gazed.
Then he threw himself on the earth.
Maybe you could distinguish the earth from the ground in Russia.
He fell on the ground.
That was the dirty ground.
And now he's embracing the earth.
Russian consultant, please check.
He could not have told why he longed so irresistibly to kiss it, but he kissed it weeping and watering it with his tears, and he vowed to love it, to love it forever and ever.
We've got to come back later to the forever.
Water the earth with the tears of your joy and love those tears.
His elder words echoed in his soul.
Why was he weeping?
Okay, now comes the crucialest paragraph in the book.
If you're asking, sort of like her question, what's the experience?
And the bigger question that goes with it, what is the sort of truth about the spiritual nature of the universe?
What is, in effect, God for Dostoevsky is coming up in the next paragraph.
So praise yourself.
Oh, in his rapture, he was weeping over those stars which were shining to him from the abyss of space, and he was not ashamed of the ecstasy.
There seemed to be threads from all those innumerable worlds of God linking his soul to them, and his soul was trembling all over in contrast with other worlds.
Now, God turns out to be something like the field of connectedness of everything to everything.
Zosima says it's like an ocean.
I'll read you that passage in a minute.
But the basic experience, that's sort of the general field of agape love, and also the field of everybody being responsible for everybody.
Everybody is connected to everybody, whether they know it or not.
But when they experience it, like Alyasha did with Rushenka, it's a transforming thing.
Because that's, so I was going to say, as near as you come and getting in touch with God, but that's the wrong way to put it.
That is existentialized God in Dostoevsky.
There is no supreme being.
There isn't any God the Father.
The universe has interconnected, and us being in touch with everything is the sort of sacredness of everything.
If it may help you to see this, if you remember that for Kierkegaard, God is that all things are possible.
Remember, a sort of atmosphere, not an object.
These people are getting rid of a certain conception of God as a superbeing and making God into some kind of field of experience in which certain kinds of experiences become possible that aren't possible just in the natural world.
This is all supernatural, but it's not against the laws of physics and chemistry.
But it's certainly supernatural that there's an ocean of love and everything is connected to everything and we're part of it.
And when we find out, then we experience this love.
Let's go on.
He longed to forgive everyone and for everything and to beg forgiveness and for all men.
And others are praying for me too, echoed in his soul.
And with every instant, well, I think I have to stop there to say more about that yet.
And then I'll read the last part.
Okay, now let's see where we are.
So there are these threads connecting to other worlds.
I think that's on 366.
I don't see it on 366.
Oh, I see, yes.
The section there is called Contact with Other Worlds.
I'm worrying about what are these other worlds that God is connecting everybody to.
And the and I think what's what's going on is you have to remember that where two people are gathered together, there is a world of living love, as Osimus says.
I think we have to find that.
Because otherwise, just all these worlds, you don't know what they are.
They're sort of any group of loving people.
Now I have to find it.
It's part of the Osima story.
Probably I've written it down here.
Maybe if I just go on, I'll find it.
367.
Yeah.
Does anybody know where?
I mean, I want to see it just because.
Oh, here it is, 370.
Right.
Through four lines down.
And if two of you are gathered together, then there is a whole world of love, of living love.
That's the agape again.
Embrace each other tenderly and praise God, for if only in you two, his truth has been fulfilled.
That is, connectedness of people to people.
Even if there's only two people connected, like again, Aliasha and Gushenka, the perfect example, each loving the other one and saving the other one, then, and all those connected worlds are connected in some way that people can move from one to another or they can recognize each other.
I don't really quite know how.
But it's all like an ocean, he says.
And that's what I want to read now.
367, yeah, at the bottom.
This is Osima talking of what he learned from Markle.
My brother asked the birds to forgive him.
That sounds senseless, but it was right.
For all is like an ocean.
All is flowing and blending.
A touch at one place sets up a movement at another, at the other end of the earth.
See, this is the interconnectedness story again.
It may be senseless to beg forgiveness of the birds, but they are a little happier.
And children and animals are happier if you yourself are noble and so forth.
It's all like an ocean, I tell you.
Then, and so forth, that's enough.
And yeah, okay, now 370.
I'm just explaining the talk of other worlds.
Okay, I got the people gathered together.
If God is now, now, now for the rest of the time, and I just have enough time, I'd have to tell you sort of abstract philosophical, theological things about what's happening.
I started to tell you that.
That there's no God the Father, there is no being, individual being, that you're supposed to be praying to.
In fact, if there was some super individual being that was completely satisfying, that had agape love for you, and you had agape love for him, it would get you out of this connectedness into this just two.
It's the danger that you see between Zosima and Alyosha, where Alyosha gets too wrapped up in Zosima.
If there were a super god, everybody would be too wrapped up in the super god.
I mean, you're going to not really understand this unless you take Philosophy 7 and read Dante.
Dante is the extreme of this version of there being a supreme being.
And have I mentioned this before?
Dante loves Beatrice with unconditional commitment.
Dante's involved in politics in Florence, Italy, up to his neck.
But when he finally sees God, the Supreme Being, he forgets Florence.
He forgets Beatrice.
He just stares into this incredible radiance.
Haven't I said that?
Okay, I think I did once.
And the last line of the Divine Comedy is: Dante says, My will became one with the will that moved the sun and the other stars.
That's exactly the view.
Whoa, get this microphone back on.
I think I can do it.
That's exactly the view that people like Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky want to get rid of.
In my way of talking, that's the Christian taking over Platonic Greek or Aristotelian Greek beliefs about this Supreme Being.
It's not, for Dostoevsky, it's not like that.
It's that there is this connectedness of everything is the bottom line.
And it would only get in the way if there was a Supreme Being, because what's most important is the connectedness of everything to everything.
And I've just tried to say that.
We're going to get, where is it now?
Just a second.
I went to a lot of trouble to collect a certain.
Here they are.
Okay.
Now, there's a certain interesting loose end, but let me make sure that I've got where I want to be.
Then I'll tell you about it.
Okay, we got to the contact with other worlds and the ocean and so forth.
Now, there is a certain symbol of the connectedness of everything, which is a very dangerous symbol.
And it's fascinating what happens in here.
Plato, who's got this Supreme Being, which he calls the good, says that the good makes a kind of light in which everybody can see everybody and see everything, but even better would be to look at the source of the light.
So he tells a story about how the sun shines and makes everything visible and intelligible.
And then he tells this further story about how when you get really spiritual and religious, you can turn your eyes to the sun.
That's what Dante's got.
That's the Greek move in Plato.
That's the move that Dostoevsky's not going to make.
But how he resists it is so interesting.
And maybe I'm making this all up now.
You have to consider the possibility that it's too clever by half.
But I think it must be something that he's doing, whether he knows he's doing it or not.
We're back to the puzzle I set you.
Why are the slanting rays of the sun so important?
Remember way back on page 17 when he's being squeezed by his mother, who's screaming and holding him up to the icon?
What does he remember?
None of that, or barely that.
The thing he remembers most are the slanting rays of the sun.
On 17, he remembered one still summer evening, an open window, the slanting rays of the sun.
He recalled this most vividly of all.
Now, why would he say that?
Well, you have a clue?
Don't tell me yet.
But I mean, I'm going to show you all the places where whenever anybody gets in touch with the ultimate spiritual reality, it's by way of the slanting rays of the sun.
So let's, I spent some time this morning finding, I think, all of them, but if you find any more, let me know.
On 27, see, if there was only one mention of the slanting ray there, I would just say, okay, so that's the most important in that particular experience.
Don't make a big deal out of it.
But I want to make a big deal out of it.
But if I had to get the right to make a big deal out of it, I better find a lot of places where it happens.
Well, page 27, remember, I've read this already.
What gets him into the monastery are the slanting rays of the sun again.
The three lines down.
Perhaps his memories of childhood brought back monastery.
Perhaps the slanting sunlight, the holy image, and so forth and so forth.
But there's that slanting sunlight.
Okay, and again on 329, here's Markle talking.
No, this is Osima remembering on the middle of 329.
I remember I went into his room when there was no one else there.
It was a bright evening.
The sun was setting.
The whole room was lighted up.
He beckoned me, and I went up to him.
This is the passing on of Agape.
And he put his hands on my shoulders and looked into my face lovingly, and he said, Run and play now for me.
So just as the baptism of Alyasha was this together experience, and there were those slanting rays.
So here is the passing on of love for Markle, and there are those slanting rays.
And on 3:30, Zosima says what he thinks about the sunset.
What's he talking about here at the bottom?
I remember first being moved to the devotional feast.
It was a fine day.
I remember today.
This is how Zosima got into religion.
Yeah, he's telling you the important memories in his life.
And now, the bottom paragraph.
He says, My mother took me to Mass.
I don't remember where my brother was at the time.
And now comes the usual.
It was a fine day, and I remember as though I saw it now, how the incense rose from the censer and floated softly upwards.
And overhead in the cupola, mingled in rising waves with the sunlight that streamed in from the little windows, those are the slanting rays of the sun again, not the sun.
You beginning to see what's happening?
You never see the S-U-N, the sun, any more than you ever see God and Jesus, or at least God.
Or yeah, you never see, never mind that.
I mean, it's complicated because you see Marvel.
But you don't see the Supreme Being.
You see the light of the Sun all the time.
So it happens again on 332.
That must be where Zosima says what I want.
Yes.
Two-thirds of the way down, Zosima says, I bless the rising sun as before, my heart sings to it.
Now, why not the sun at noon?
Plato loves the sun at noon.
Even Nietzsche loves the sun at noon.
Dostoevsky only likes the sun when it's on the horizon and all you see are the rays.
He says, But I now love its setting, its long slanting rays.
You just put slanting rays into Google, you find all these quotes.
I just tried it.
And that's probably all of them.
But sometimes you find quotes, if you do that, where they're called God's rays, and that's fine.
But now, what's going on there?
Well, I think, I mean, again, it sounds too clever by half, and I don't know whether Dostoevsky knows it consciously, but I think I made a case that somehow every time you're in touch with the ocean of love, and agape love is happening, the slanting rays of the sun are there.
It's not the sun.
Well, that is to say that it's the field of light, not the object.
Don't look at the sun.
If you're living in the world, I mean, when I read Augustine, he's another one of the, of course, Greek-influenced ones who looks at the sun.
So Augustine thinks you live in this dark world, but up here is the Supreme Being, and Zap, you get that experience, and then you are saved.
Dostoevsky, I think, thinks then you're doomed.
You don't get the connectedness right.
But when you get the connectedness right, then you have the rays and the light without the sun.
That's the existentializing move about God.
Now, I want to say one more thing just a second about that.
Oh, yeah, it's the slanting rays.
I really haven't talked about the slanting rays.
Why the slanting rays?
Because that is the interconnectedness.
I mean, instead of all of it going up like that, it's all the rays are going in all directions, slanting into each other.
That's the picture Dostoevsky has of the ocean of interconnectedness of everything.
Now, I think, let's see.
So, God's this field of involvement.
Now, we've got to just look one more back to, where's this religious experience that I was talking about?
Tell me what page.
I want to go back to the one I was reading where he runs out.
Hell, you all must know.
I'm not supposed to know.
Here we are, 418.
I'd have to read what's 419 now.
We're still sort of answering her question: What's the experience?
So far, the experience is that you love the earth, then you water it with your tears, you feel an openness and a total connection to all the worlds of God.
That is everywhere where anybody is loving anybody, you're loving them too, and they're loving you too in some very general way.
And what does that do to him?
The top of 419.
He felt clearly and as if it were tangibly that something firm and unshakable as the vault of heaven had entered into his soul.
It was as though some idea, that's a bad thing.
Let's hope the Russian doesn't say that.
Check on it.
I think this isn't where it needs to be, though.
Okay, so it shouldn't be idea.
It should be something more else, some notion or something.
Some notion had seized the sovereignty of his mind, and it was for all of his life and forever and ever.
Now, what's the forever that's happening to him?
You recognize it?
Kierkegaard has it too.
They don't read each other, but they both somehow know that when you existentialize our spiritual tradition, you get rid of the Supreme Being, and you get rid of the eternity up here that Augustine and Dante think they get into.
And what do you get instead of this eternity?
Remember?
You get the eternal in time.
You get the moment of unconditional commitment.
The instant that Kierkegaard talks about.
The instant which is, instead of the moment, when you point up there, it's the moment in time which is going to determine your whole future as having it and your whole past as lacking it.
Thus, yes, he's got the whole, the same picture.
Only he, instead of saying that it's unconditional for him, it's always some other kind of moment of total human connectedness.
His mother and the icon, the German doctor with the nuts thing, saying the baptism over him.
And you don't even need one other person.
Alyasha is falling on the ground in connection with everything.
He's got the experience of, that's your, then back to her question.
That's the experience of God.
That's the ultimate experience.
That's why it's in the middle of the book.
Everybody's in it.
But if you don't experience that you're in it, you're in despair, you're suffering.
But if you get it, he calls it the word to change it.
And that's your touch, that's what it is to be in touch with eternity, existentialized.
Oh, now we've got all the pieces, I think.
Okay, yes.
I believe that's exactly what I want.
Yeah, now, we've answered everything that we started with.
Of course, you need a miracle if in a crisis, the Grand Inquisitor is right, but it's not going to be a miracle.
And you can't believe just freely, like Jesus says.
Even Alyasha, the hero of the book, can't keep his faith without a miracle.
There are miracles.
They are always miracles of saving people through agape love.
We saw one with Grushenka.
Keaton says it's a miracle.
And once you've seen that kind of miracle, you then will be able to see the have the ultimate experience of being in touch with everybody at this level of the way the universe is set up.
And that's it.
Now, what we need for next time is, okay, that's how it happened to Alyasha.
But somebody has to be the original person who got in touch with the universe, the ocean of love, and told people about it and showed them, point again, showed people what it's like to live once you're in touch with that ocean of love.
And who is that, of course, just repeating?
That's Markle.
Markle goes crazy, and in his craziness, his brain fever that he gets from his tuberculosis, he gets a vision that is the vision of the connectedness and shows people how to live in it, shows them the God they love.
I mean, so Markle is Jesus.
Jesus was the one, according to this.
Now, this is demagicalized Satan and demagicalized incarnation.
This love gets embodied in Markle, who shows it to everybody.
Or will he really only show it to Zosima?
Shows it to Alyasha, who now is in a position to leave the monastery and show it to everybody.
Ah, somebody's going to say something.
Say something.
Ah, I hadn't thought about it.
Where's Markle?
Early on, isn't it?
Markle is in the remembering of Zosima.
You're already past what you have to read for next time.
I hate to tell you this.
Yeah.
This is the existentializing of the afterlife, too.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Okay, yes.
Beatrice asked a very important question.
Zosima contradicts a lot of what I've said.
Zosima even talks platonic, like, I couldn't find it in her, but I think he talks about sort of the supreme being.
And he talks about a kind of eternity that you get after you die.
Gosima is not existentialized.
He hasn't left the monastery.
He's still talking Christian symbols about the existential experience.
It's only when you leave the monastery that you don't need those symbols anymore.
The way Alyasha ran out of the monastery and got in touch with this field, the ocean of love, Dosima hasn't done that.
Zosima can't do that.
So don't let it upset you, but mark it, because it's interesting.
See if you can see how far Zosima is still in the traditional Greek infiltrated experiences and how much Zosima's out of it.
I don't have a clear answer to that.
That'd be a good paper topic.
Add it to the paper topic.
Okay, that's it.