Alyasha said, Alyasha has this terrific religious experience, spiritual experience in the middle of the book.
After he sees that Father Zosima has indeed performed a miracle by creating his love, which he then turns on Grushenka, and that creates a miracle for her, giving her a new option for acting, which is creative instead of destructive.
Thanks a lot.
And then, Alyasha has the last comment by Dostoevsky is the transition I want to make.
We were on 419 last time, and the experience is over.
The last thing he says about it is, it sees the sovereignty of his mind for his life and forever.
I don't know if I said it last time, but I'll say it again.
For the Russian people listening who send me helpful comments every once in a while, it's too bad he says some idea sees the sovereignty of his mind.
It would be nice if the Russian word was something like a conviction or a notion or something.
An idea is too abstract.
What sees him is a whole sense of what it is to be a human being in touch with all the other, all the other human beings, all the other worlds of God, that is, all the other people who love each other everywhere.
And the final thing is something later.
I finished this last time.
I just summed it up.
The one step on 419 that was after last time and begins this time is someone visited my soul in that hour, he used to say afterwards, with implicit faith.
Now that's interesting and strange, because the normal way to hear that would be the someone would be Jesus, I suppose.
God the Father doesn't go around visiting people's souls, but it isn't.
It's someone else.
And it's the same someone that points the way into the monastery for the mysterious visitor on 358.
I mentioned it already.
The last thing he says, these final, these funny last things that Dostoevsky puts in, on 358, it says, I left the town, I entered, by God's grace, I entered upon the safe and blessed path, following the unseen finger that guided me so clearly to it.
Period.
Because then he talks about Michiel.
But Michiel is not the unseen finger.
The unseen finger is, you know, I think we talked about it, this sort of suddenly love explodes into the mind of Zosima as he's about to enter this duel.
Who gave him the capacity for that mystical kind of total connected love that he suddenly experiences?
His brother Markle.
And he gave it to him by actually touching him and looking into his eyes and telling him to go out and live it.
Let's see if I can open to that right away, where he tells him that.
Yes, the middle of 329.
I went into his room.
I read it already, this quote in connection with the sun.
Of course, when one of these amazingly important religious experiences, when getting in touch with the connectedness of everything and getting therefore agape love charged up in you, so there's always the sun rays.
He beckoned me, he put his hands on my shoulders and looked into my face lovingly, and then he said, run and play now, enjoy life for me too.
That's the moment that he gives him, he passes on to him this sort of supernatural, but not against science, but not normal nature either, agape experience.
And I think I said it, but I'll say it one more time: that this is the existentializing of a not very interesting Christian notion, but it's something Dostoevsky's interested in: the passing on of the power to save people from Jesus to Peter and then to all the bishops from there on.
All they have their laying on of hands.
And Dostoevsky is saying, but that's just magic that you could pass this thing on by just laying your hands.
But it gets passed on by these emotional experiences that stay in the memory of the people.
So Alyasha's memory of his mother holding him up to the icon, Dimitri's memory of the German doctor giving him the pound of nuts.
And now we get another one, Markle's memory, which he says a lot he doesn't remember, but boy, does he remember this, this moment when he sort of connects with his brother and the vision that his brother has of the love.
So now we have to just look at Markle.
It should be clear, I hope, that Markle is the existentialized, unmagical, unmythical, but also normal, because not anti-science.
Since science and religion are having such a fight these days, I want to keep saying Dostoevsky's got an answer.
Don't go around arguing about whether Christianity or any other religion, but this is Christianity, is compatible with science.
That only comes in if you think of Christianity in this magical way.
But if you think of it in what is its existential meaning, what does it mean for human beings and how does it change the way they live?
That's not a question for physics and chemistry, nor for neuroscience.
Somebody came up afterwards and said, but now we know how it happens in the brain.
Keep your eyes open later in the book, when, believe it or not, Gostovsky, who thinks of everything, has Rakitin talking to Dmitry about neurons, which have just been discovered, and saying, Well, now we know neurons do it.
You don't have to feel guilt, and you don't have to feel repentance, and you don't get redeemed.
We know all now that that's all caused by neurons.
And Alyasha's response is: if you'll keep your eye open for it, is not to answer Dimitri, but simply to ignore him.
Meaning, in effect, that's just irrelevant.
The causal basis of agape love is fine, and certainly something goes on in the brain when you experience it.
But there is also an existential meaning to it, and science can't deal with that meaning.
But science doesn't refute the meaning, nor do the neurons.
So now, Markle is going to be the existentialized version of the incarnation.
The incarnation, meaning, you know, incarnate has to do with body, the word, namely the logos of the universe, becomes flesh in Jesus.
And what is that now?
But all that is so strange.
Dostoevsky's got the job of saying, well, what does it really look like?
Well, what he's going to do is sort of restage the original Christian sort of events as they would happen right now in order to capture what existential experience was going on.
So the incarnate, every, I think he thinks that there can be a plurality of incarnations.
Markle is one of them.
Jesus was the first one, and therefore very important, because without somebody starting this, there wouldn't have been anybody else doing it.
And what is the this?
Well, the incarnation means the embodiment of God.
Now, if God is the connectedness of everything with everything, what would it be to embody that?
Well, look at Markle.
It would be to feel in touch with the birds and the bees and the people and his mother and the animals and feel overwhelmed with joy about it and so forth.
And so he exhibits, in effect, that everybody's connected and how everybody's connected and what to do about the fact that everybody's connected.
That makes his story a story.
It's the incarnation.
And now I will jump to what I want to do next.
So he reveals, I just said what I need to say about that.
And how does he talk?
Well, he tells you all these things on 326 and 327.
By the way, it may or may not be important.
I think maybe it's because Markle is so important that on 326 it looks like Markle combines all the three brothers.
Zostima says of him on 326 that he did well at school, and we know that he reminds him of Alyasha.
He looks like Alyasha at the bottom of 324.
Alyasha seems to me so like him spiritually that many times I've taken him for that young man.
So he's sort of reincarnated.
He's the incarnation and then he's reincarnated in Alyasha.
That is, Alyasha is going to also embody the love and the connectedness.
And he's like Yvonne.
And this is more important to us, that he's corrupted by philosophy.
So about 10 lines down on 326, he did well at school and so forth.
Six months before his death, when he was 17, he made friends with a political exile who had been banished from Moscow to our town for free thinking.
That's sort of anti-religious secular thinking.
And led a solitary existence.
This man was a scholar who gained distinction in philosophy.
That's always a bad sign.
Yvonne is a philosopher, or does what presumably natural philosophy, sort of philosophy of science.
This guy does social philosophy, what will become something like Marxism.
And all that's the wrong way to go, Dostoevsky thinks.
But it has a corrupting effect on Markle.
And that's important.
So the next paragraph.
It was the beginning of Lent, and Markle would not fast.
He was rude and laughed at it.
That's all silly, and there is no God, he said, horrifying my mother and the servants, too.
Well, that doesn't seem a very Jesus-like thing for him to do, does it?
I mean, that he's saying there is no God and laughing at the people who are religious.
Well, that's one way that Dostoevsky deviates from the tradition.
I mean, he's enough of a thinker on his own that he's not going to just tell you everything that the Russian Orthodox Church tells you.
And he's got this theory, which I told you once already, and since time is running out, I'm just going to remind you that unless these saving people have already had some experience which shows them what it is to be brutal and evil and selfish and so forth, they can't understand the other, the suffering of others and the tendency of others to sin.
So, Zosima, remember, was in the army and was so brutal that he slapped his orderly so hard in the face that he was covered with blood.
And then he, at that moment, having experienced that, he suddenly remembers Markle and throws himself on the ground, or I think he does.
Anyway, certainly experiences that he never will do anything like that again.
And even Markle has to have at least an understanding of what it would be to laugh at religion.
But it doesn't last long.
He gets tuberculosis and he's got galloping consumption, the doctor says, and he's going to die very soon.
And as soon as he does, he gets a lot of, presumably has a high fever.
The doctor says later he has a fever.
And again, that's something that happens in his brain.
Directly.
We don't care whether he has a fever or not.
I mean, because he has a high fever, he begins to have these sort of visions that he wouldn't have if he wasn't in a certain way going crazy.
Remember, the doctors also say the mysterious visitor had gone crazy, only they think it's some problem with his heart.
And again, Dostoevsky doesn't care that maybe there is a problem with his neurons because of his high fever.
The question is whether he sees whether that enables him to see something real about the universe that people normally don't see because their brain has sort of got too simple and solid a grip on ordinary reality.
So he's going crazy with his high fever and sees things that other people don't see, but they're not just his imagination.
And you know that because they have this amazing effect on people.
Markle has an effect on Saseva and gets him to give up the duel and points, he's the finger that points him into the monastery.
And Zosima has an amazing effect on Alyasha, which points him out of the monastery into the world.
And all of this may well be the result of brain fever, but it doesn't matter.
It's true in the sense that it counts, that it makes things happen, very important things happen.
It saves Grushenka, for instance.
So let's look at the middle of 327.
A marvelous change passed over him.
His spirit seemed transformed.
He was transformed.
He was transformed from a normal, selfish, philosophical, atheistic, secular guy into even more than a saint, into somebody who brings the agape-connected love into the world and exhibits it.
That's how he's transformed.
So, and now what does he do?
When they try to do their religious things, the old nurse would come in and say, Let me light the lamp before the holy image, my dear.
Before this, he would have allowed it, would not have allowed it, and would have blown it out.
Light it, light it, dear nurse.
I was a wretch to have prevented you from doing it before, he says.
Now he says sort of the existentializing thing.
He says, You pray when you light the lamp, and I pray when I see you.
So we're praying to the same God.
Meaning, it isn't the sort of magical thing of lighting the lamp or not lighting the lamp, but what lighting the lamp means.
And it means to her some devotional thing, and it means to him that he's happy that she's doing the devotional thing.
And that's now he's in this religious dimension, and he says to his mother at the bottom of the page, life is paradise, and we are all in paradise, but we refuse to see it.
If we would, we would be in heaven on earth the next day.
That's important because, and we'll come back to it, for him, Markle, and presumably Dostoevsky thinks for primitive Christianity before it got mixed up with philosophy and Greek thinking, it wasn't that heaven was someplace else in another world, higher and better and different than this one.
Heaven is this world, if you understand it right and relate to it right in this kind of totally loving way.
The same thing, remember, what Deer Kierkegaard says about the afterlife.
He says that, well, maybe there's an afterlife and maybe there isn't.
But what's important is whether you can experience bliss in this life.
Anything short of that, anything that says that this life you can't really be fulfilled, but there's another life in which you can, is already giving away much too much.
That says, well, this world is a terrible world.
We're just stuck in it.
And you can't understand anymore why God created it and thought it was good.
The Augustine has a problem with that.
He thinks the world is terrible.
It's always luring you away from this direct relation to God that I drew on the board.
And the point is, this world is not terrible.
It's not luring you away from a direct vision and experience of God.
This world is the experience of God, of the connectedness.
Okay, so he sees that.
And he says, at the bottom of 327, dear ones, he would say, What have I done that you should love me?
How can you love anyone like me?
How was I to not know I did not appreciate it before?
Now comes an important sense.
You're always supposed to be looking, remember, for where Dostoevsky is going to sort of hit you over the head and say, I've just existentialized the incarnation.
I've restaged the original church and Jesus' original experience.
And how does it happen?
How does he tell you?
Well, it's the bottom of 327.
Those of you who aren't steeped in Christian tradition won't recognize this.
Some of you will.
When the servants came in to him, he would say, Dear kind people, why are you doing so much for me?
Do I deserve to be waited on?
If it were God's will for me to live, I would wait on you, for all men should wait on one another.
You recognize, I mean, that's what Jesus says when he washes or wipes the feet of Mary Magdalene.
Not being Christian myself, I don't know it by heart.
But I know that he's telling you, sort of, he's in a way, Mark is now plagiarizing Jesus or talking just like Jesus, talking literally what Jesus was saying.
And that's important, just so Dostoevsky gets you to realize, gee, I've heard that somewhere before.
Yeah, yeah, of course.
That's a direct quote from the New Testament.
So, and it goes on, Mother, darling, there must be servants and masters, but if so, I will be the servant of my servants.
And another thing, everyone is sinned against all men, and everyone more than I.
Well, that's, I don't think that's, I don't think that's something Jesus ever says.
I mean, that's the thing that Dostoevsky teaches anything.
Not only are we all connected in a positive way by agake love, but we're all connected in a negative way of hurting other people and doing things that make other people worse, even when we don't know it.
That's the thing that Zosima makes such a fuss about.
And then the doctor says at the bottom of 327, your son cannot last long, the doctor told my mother, the disease is affecting his brain.
Well, I said, yeah, the disease is affecting his brain.
So what?
That doesn't mean that he isn't having a sort of a repeat of the original experience of Jesus.
And that's what's important for Dostoevsky here, to get that experience.
Now, let me see where I am.
So he's transformed from cynical socialist into the dimension of love.
I think I read that already.
And he never goes back on his way of he never goes back to fasting and lighting the lamps and so forth.
He doesn't go, and I'll explain why in a minute, but you have to notice, he never talks really Christian talk.
He never says, yes, the icon is where you should be praying, nurse, and I'm going to pray to the icon too.
He says, you pray to the icon, and I'll appreciate the fact that you're being devoted and praying to the icon.
He's not demythologizing or demagicalizing.
He's pre-magicalizing.
That is, here's an understanding of this kind of love before it got put into the symbols and language and rituals of Christianity, which is the first thing that happens in the church or in the Christian community.
And it's before it gets made into a church.
And it's before it gets Platonized.
He's just, and so he never says any sort of, as far as I know, if you find places that contradict it, let me know.
He doesn't say anything specifically, magically gospel, New Testament-like.
He says we're all servants of servants, but that's not magical.
That's this experience of interconnectedness.
He's got that.
What he hasn't got is a way of talking about it.
Now, that turns out to be important because if you want to ask yourself what happened to Markle, why did, why does, how do I put it, the two people who have the experience of the connectedness before Zosima has it, go crazy and die.
That is the mysterious visitor and now Markle.
Why does that have to happen?
And that is really tied up with why did Jesus have to die in an existentialized way?
The idea is that this experience is so overpowering, so absolutely against everyday human nature of selfishness and protectedness and wanting other people to be your servants and not you theirs and everything.
The whole way everyday life is organized and the whole way we can think about it and make sense of it is contradicted by this experience.
I mean, take the extreme case that we should love the birds and the animals and ask forgiveness.
That's crazy.
Nothing in our experience suggests that we should do it or why we should do it or what good it would do to do it or what bad it would do not to do it.
It's just an amazingly contradictory experience.
And that's so that you can't live in this normal world once you see it.
That's the moral.
And so it looks like craziness once you see it because you can't really make, you can't explain to anybody what's going on.
You can't relate to the people except in this way that they can't understand, which is this overwhelming love.
So you end up, that is, at least in our existentialized way, Markle, the incarnation, the God-man is in our book, Jesus in our book, will definitely have to go crazy and die.
He doesn't have to get crucified.
Crucified is another issue.
Dimitri gets crucified.
Dimitri, Dostoevsky sort of divides up the various parts of being an incarnation.
I'm not going to get time to talk about Dimitri, so I'll just say it right now.
Notice how Dimitri keeps talking about suffering and being crucified.
And you will see that Dostoevsky is hitting you over the head to watch the way Dimitri suffers, because his suffering is the kind of suffering that is Christian suffering, which will lead to joy in the end.
And there's a whole story to be said about that.
And anybody who wants to write about Dimitri and crucifixion can, that is, suffering, can do it.
But Dostoevsky doesn't, he separates them on purpose.
There's the joy of getting in touch with this love, and then there's how to deal with getting in touch with your guilt for having caused very bad things in the world, more than you even realize.
So now I'm going back to here.
So he's got this pure love now, and he's got this extreme Christian vision.
I'm just wanting to make sure I've read the passages I want, yeah, that we're in paradise and we don't see it.
And that he's got brain fever.
That's where we are, at the bottom of 3.28.
And anybody who experiences this pure kind of love must go crazy.
The idiot, too, another one of the Jesus figures in the book, Dostoevsky's book, The Idiot, goes crazy.
It just happens.
You just can't cope with it.
So the question becomes: how come they can experience this love at all, given that they're selfish people like everybody else, and now they've experienced this total love?
And the answer is, well, they can't really live that way.
I'm just repeating myself.
They have no precedent for it, no language, no practices, no institutions, no way of making sense of it.
They just experience this connectedness, and that makes them stop being normal, sane human beings.
And Dostoevsky's way of describing that is they just look crazy.
And so now he's going off and looking crazy.
That's where we have to see what's next.
Then he talks about loving the birds and the animals at the bottom of 367.
And you should pray to the birds.
Consumed by an all-embracing love in a sort of transport.
You see, he's just sort of, this is sort of his madness, just a typical.
If somebody starts talking like that and thinking like that, they look crazy.
You're consumed in an all-embracing love, in a sort of transport.
You would pray that they too would forgive you, the animals.
Treasure that ecstasy, however senseless it may seem to men.
You see that?
I mean, that's another way of saying, I'm experiencing something that if you experienced it, you should think it's a wonderful thing to experience it, even though it seems to you and everybody else crazy.
And that's as far as we get with that.
Michael dies and so forth.
So, well, how then do these existentialized Jesus figures who are even crazier than Jesus?
I don't think Jesus ever asked the birds for forgiveness.
But these people who don't read the Bible, don't use the symbols from the Bible, don't sort of restrict agape love to other people the way the Bible does, how do they ever get into being sort of stable and sane Christians?
And that's the next thing we have to talk about.
Let me see now.
I want to make sure we got everything.
Yeah.
Now, so I've now convinced you, I hope, or done my best, that if you have this experience, you seem crazy to yourself, and you seem crazy to everybody else, and in a certain sense, you are crazy.
And then what happens?
Well, I already said what you need is a language, sort of rituals, shared experiences, institutions that make this intelligible and bring it under control so you're not in this sort of mind-blowing, literally mind-blowing state all the time.
And what is that?
Well, that's the church.
The church takes this crazy experience and tames it and makes it intelligible by writing the Bible, for instance, the New Testament.
They're all busy trying to explain it.
Paul's trying his way, and John is trying his way, and none of them have got it very clear.
It turns out, if you look at the Bible carefully, some of them think there's a Trinity, some of them think there's a duality about God, some of them think there's only one.
And it's all mixed up.
But gradually, there are people who are called church fathers who work hard to straighten it all out.
And they form, they write credos that state the things you have to believe if you're a Christian, and so forth.
And that, now I want to give you the overall picture.
That's the second stage of Dostoevsky's three-stage story about how the world is going to be saved.
We've done the first stage, but I just didn't name it.
The first stage is primitive Christianity before it has a language, before it has a church, before it knows what it's doing.
And we just did that.
Markle is primitive Christianity at stage one.
Who would be the next stage in our book?
Zosima, yes.
The next stage is to institutionalize it.
They withdraw from the world because the world is too worldly and secular for them.
It can't support this kind of love and craziness.
You can't go around on the street falling on your knees at the beggars and saying you're worse than they are and you're very sorry that you're so evil.
Anyway, it's all crazy.
You can't go around talking to all the animals all the time.
They'll certainly lock you up.
But anyway, by the time you fix it, you make it into a shared way of life.
And you withdraw from these people in the world who can't understand you and think you're crazy.
And you find a language in which you're not crazy anymore because you can understand each other and confess and love each other and so forth.
And that is stage two.
So we have to look at stage two, because that's where most of the book takes place.
So when Markle's love gets stored up in Zosima, when it finally breaks out in Zosima, when he feels terrible about what he did to his orderly and throws away his gun at the duel and says, look, the world is beautiful and everybody should love everybody.
When that happens, then Marko has pointed the way to the monastery, Zosima says.
That's Zosima's kind of, I don't know, poetic or magical or Christian way of saying that thanks to having been loved by his brother and seeing his brother exhibit this kind of love, he is drawn to go into this institution where the love is preserved.
And I think maybe that's on 329.
I mean, I don't want to snow.
No, that's when he passes it on.
So let me go further.
So that's the apostolic succession, and Marko is in it.
And Zosima receive a kind of ordination from Markle.
That's when Marko puts his hands on him, and Alyasha receives it from Zosima.
I'll just mention that, but I'm going to go back to talking about Zosima.
But I gave you a wrong example in 85.
I said that in the dream, Zosima blesses Alyasha.
But even before the dream, in real life, at the top of 85, it says, Father Zosima raised his hand to bless him.
So, Zosima, that's when Zosima passes it on.
But let's go back.
Now we hear Zosima was an almost savage creature.
He strikes his orderly.
That's on 336 and 339.
I won't read them.
He goes to the duel.
He refuses to shoot.
And then we better read what happens, what he says on 342, because he's channeling, in effect, Markle at that point.
It suddenly dawns on him.
It takes him over.
340.
Oh, I'm looking in the wrong place.
Yeah, he says, this should sound familiar, top of 342.
Gentlemen, I cried, suddenly, speaking straight from my heart, look around you with the gifts of God, the clear air, the pure air, the tendergrass, the birds.
Nature is beautiful and sinless.
Only we have sinned, and we don't understand that life is heaven, that's here and now in the world, this paradise.
We have only to understand that, and it will at once be fulfilled in all its beauty, and we shall embrace each other and weep.
So that's Osima getting the stage one primitive Christian experience.
But instead of going crazy from getting the stage one experience, which sounds pretty crazy there, he goes in the monastery where it's not crazy.
And that's that.
So now we get to stage two.
And now we get something on 367.
Oh, he's telling them more about how everything is connected and so forth.
He still holds that.
But he holds it now in its Christianized language and in the institution of elders where people understand each other and don't have to go crazy.
Now, I'm just summing up what I wrote here.
Those who receive this ecstatic Christian experience, not yet Christian experience, have to institutionalize it and make it livable.
And that's what the elders and the people in the monastery do.
They start, it starts already when the New Testament tries to make sense of it.
And in the monastery, they've got a whole ritual for doing with it, dealing with it.
But it's in the second stage, and this is the next important point, they are corrupted by philosophy.
This is not an important thing to Dostoevsky.
I don't even know if he thinks about it.
But Zosima not only talks in Christian terms about the afterlife and how God is watching you and how you should pray to Him, he says this to the old woman whose son has died, for instance, does it several times.
But the worst thing he says is on 368, two-thirds down.
It's interesting, just because if you aren't tuned into the stuff I'm telling you, you think, well, Zosima knows the truth, and Zosima says this, this must be what Dostoevsky believes.
Well, this is what Dostoevsky believes, stage two Christianity is about.
But that doesn't mean that he believes that that's the last word.
That's a necessary stage to go through to try to put it into philosophical terms.
But it doesn't really work.
And now here's where you can see it going wrong at the two-thirds of down on 368.
Zosima says, on earth indeed, we are, as it were, astray.
Is that a markle sentiment?
Or even a Zothima sentiment when he first gets hit with a Markle Lammy that somehow on earth we're astray.
Were it not for the precious image of Christ before us, we'd be undone altogether and lost.
Well, if you translate that so that it means markle, it's true.
But he gives it a philosophical slant.
He says, much on earth is hidden, and so forth and so forth, but we've got a mystical sense of our living bond with the other world.
Now comes the problem with the higher heavenly world.
Where's the problem?
Is there a higher heavenly world that we're connected to?
It's here.
It's now.
Good.
Okay.
Yes.
We are in paradise.
We are in heaven here and now if we could only see it.
That's the right thing to say.
But Markle, sorry, but Zosima is part of the church, and the church got sort of trying hard to make sense of all this, turned it into this platonic story, that there's a better world.
So let me go on there.
The higher heavenly world and the roots of our thoughts and feeling are not here, but in other worlds.
That's why the philosophers say that we can't understand the reality of things on earth.
Very bad, very bad.
It's true that the philosophers can't understand the reality of things on earth, but that shows that they're wrong, not that we should believe it.
Now, I wouldn't harp on this so much, but there was such a funny thing that happened.
About a few times back when I gave this course, the new translation of the brothers had just come out.
And it was considered just the hottest thing, the best translation.
And I happened to be, and I was looking at the footnotes.
I just want to read you this to caution you that just because something's printed in a book doesn't mean that you should believe it.
Here's a footnote to that very passage, the passage where Zosima goes most wrong in giving a philosophical, platonic, otherworldly interpretation of this new form of life, which is what Markle and found.
And even Zosima lives, but he doesn't understand it very well.
Footnote says, where he says, much on earth is, what's the phrase?
Where was I again?
I have to go back to it.
368.
Much on earth is hidden from us, but we have the sense of the other world, the higher heavenly world.
It seems to me you can make up your own mind.
I say that's where Zosima goes wrong.
That's a sort of a hint of where the second stage of Christianity goes wrong.
It doesn't understand that the Christianity coming from Marko and Jesus is going to save this world.
Well, look at this footnote.
Like that one.
He says, Victor Terius, I've never explained who that is.
Obviously, some paper the Spanish translator has read.
Victor Terius rightly considers the passage from here to the end of the chapter to be the master key to the philosophical interpretation and the structure of the brothers Karamazov.
It's 180 degrees wrong, but it's interesting.
And why it's wrong, it's because this guy, whoever it is, is sort of falls for the way Greek philosophy about there being another world, a better world, and what Augustine fell for.
By the way, Augustine, when I keep criticizing him, though he's a saint in our Roman Catholic world, the Russian Orthodox don't make Augustine a saint.
I think that's terrific and to their credit.
And I think it's the same point.
I mean, that's Augustine talk, so to speak.
And Augustine is certainly part of the second stage, but it's not the part of the second stage that gets things right.
It's a part of the second stage that gets it wrong.
You've got to think.
If you wanted, here's another way to put it.
What would be the third stage?
The third stage might be sort of leaving this world to go to the better one when you die or by meditation or however, get out of this sinful, suffering world to paradise.
That would be the mistake.
And so, and what was I starting to say?
Wait a minute.
I have lost my own way of why I decided to say it.
That would be the mistake.
And it is in here.
I'll find myself in a second.
So we don't want to go to a better spiritual world.
We've got to get in touch with the connectedness now.
Well, I don't know what I was going to say, but I'm going to find it in a minute.
It's okay.
Well, let's look.
I mean, I guess the way to say it isn't what I was going to say, but maybe you remember what I was going to say.
It's the monastery, remember, is the safe path, as Osima says.
The safe path is the one that saves you from craziness, makes it all sensible, makes it into respectable philosophy that any sensible maybe person can understand, and takes all the mystery and overwhelmingness out of it.
But it has to go in the monastery for that period.
Oh, I knew what I was going to say.
I knew it would come back to me.
So, what would be the third stage?
If the monastery one is a necessary stage, because otherwise they'd be crazy.
But it's a necessary stage that makes it so sensible that it's not crazy anymore, but it's not, it's lost the point.
Yeah?
The government, you church, the use of the environment.
Exactly.
But never mind, like the monastery, because you leave behind.
You want to say something?
Okay.
You leave behind the language, the rituals, the Bible talk, and you go out in the world and you existentialize the whole thing into something not secular, because that would be against the spiritual, but something worldly, something that can happen here.
And that's the third stage.
The third stage is that Christianity is going to go out into the world.
Now, how it does it, you ought to be able partly to figure out.
Let's go through it.
What do you have to do to get out of stage two and into stage three?
What does Osima do with Alyasha?
He sends him out of the monastery for good.
He says, your place is not here.
You've got to get in the world.
He doesn't even say, I used to think it said somewhere, when you get old, you can come back here.
But it doesn't, I don't think.
I can't find that passage.
It vanished in my reading.
Osima, I will have to read it.
It says, you've got to get out of the monastery and get married and stay out of the monastery when you're not going to be a monk and so forth.
But let me see if I've got the passages now.
This is how you go from stage one to stage two.
That is, I don't know why that's in it.
327.
Well, I don't know.
I read this, I think, already, but I see myself saying it again.
I did read when Markle says life is paradise and we're in paradise, only we don't see it, and so forth.
That's what you've got to get out of the monastery to experience.
Yeah.
So Father Chai on page 388, he says when that's where I got it.
380 is he says you'll come back again.
But Zosima, I think, says you won't come back again.
But I think that's interesting.
That's how I got the idea that he would come back.
Well, maybe he will come back.
I think he will come back.
So let's find out.
What does Zason say?
We have to find out now what Zosima says.
So it is like angry because Zosima's body is smelling and Father Days and he would still come back.
Like, he does come back.
He comes back after the religious experience.
Then he maybe leaves.
Let's find the place where Zosima sends him out.
You guys are helping me get clear about something that I have never been quite clear about.
So let's see.
The monks, they retire from the world to keep their faith.
I'm going to sort of lead up to where we are.
And now we want to know how they get out of there.
But I want to read you, this is my favorite quote for what the monks do in the second stage on 359, that top paragraph about halfway down.
Meanwhile, in their solitude, they keep the image of Christ fair and undefiled in the purity of God's truth from the time of the fathers of old.
Those are the church fathers making sense of this.
The apostles and the martyrs.
And when the time comes, they will show it to the tottering creeds of the world.
That is the great thought.
That is the star that will rise out of the east.
That points you from stage two to stage three.
Now, how now I'm going to go on and see what when, and now we get to stage three.
So he's told to leave the monastery on page 84.
We have to read how he's told.
Okay, here we go.
Middle 84.
This is the kind of thing you have to take risks when you teach or when you write papers.
I mean, you have to go out on a limb with a hypothesis, and then sometimes you get it right, and sometimes you get it wrong.
When you get it wrong, you learn from your mistakes.
I'm about to find out whether I hallucinated this.
When it's God's will to call me, leave the monastery.
Go away for good.
Aha, that's what I remembered.
What is it?
This is not the place.
This is not your place for the time.
I bless you to the great service in the world.
It's ambiguous, isn't it?
First he says, go away for good, and then he says, well, this isn't the time for you to be here.
Somebody's confused.
I don't know whether it's Dostoevsky or whether I am or something deep is going on.
Yours will be a long pilgrimage, and you will have to take a wife, too, which is Lisa, of course.
You will have much to bear before you come back.
There will be much to do.
Aha.
So he's coming back.
And who says that?
Zosima says it.
Zosima just says, go away for good, and then he says something about what happens when you come back.
Boy.
But I have trust in you, and so I send you forth.
Christ is with you.
See, that's Christian talk.
Alexa is not going to talk that way.
Do you not abandon him?
He'll not abandon you.
You will see great sorrow, and in that sorrow you will bring happiness.
And the remember why words and so forth.
Wow.
Well, either, I mean, I don't know what to say.
I mean, I like it.
I like it better if he didn't ever came.
It doesn't fit the three stages, which I'm sure is very important in the book.
That when you leave the monastery, you leave the safe path.
Why would he ever come back to the safe path?
I mean, as long as he's alive, he's got to be helping people.
He's got to be playing his role as an angel to fight the devil, which is always there fighting for people's souls, as in the chart I gave you.
So, I don't know what to say.
Come and tell me in office hours if you know, or tell me right now, even better.
Well, I think that's the right feeling.
I think that that's sort of you have to put the two together somehow.
One, that as long as he's sort of active and so forth, it's not, he shouldn't be in the monastery and he has to leave it for good.
That's the first thing.
But when he's really old and, so to speak, retires, in the sense that he just hasn't got the strength anymore to go traveling around and blasting people with agape, then he can come back here.
It sort of mixes it in a way that I don't like.
I mean, because you really want to say that once you've brought this love out into the world, I guess you have to say, well, the monastery is no longer the safe path, but it's the retirement home.
It's become a retirement home.
That's exactly what you were saying, and exactly the only way to think of it.
I mean, it's not doing its job anymore of being the preserver of the Christian message, because you'd better go out in the real world now with the Christian message.
But it is just incidentally a place where you could go to rest when you're really, really done your work.
I haven't anything more to say.
I'm convinced that it's no longer doing its monastery job once Alyasha leaves.
And in that sense, he leaves for good.
Whether it's doing some kind of humane retirement job, I have no, I see that he must go ahead, help me.
Okay, well, good, help me by changing the subject.
In what sense, I kind of retake the universal and express your religiousness to the universal beings.
Ah, but that's good, but it's wrong in an interesting way.
He never thinks that you spread the love by philosophical means, by preaching, by telling somebody something that's a universal kind of truth, any more than he believes anymore in the universal church.
But it's good because the question would then be, well, what does he do?
Well, Dostoevsky saves a lot of important things for the last few pages of the book, which we'll get to two or three times from here.
One of them is what replaces the church and how it goes out into the world.
And he's going to show you how it is.
He's set up a lot of little pieces of it.
What do you actually do if you want to start transforming the world so that the state will become the church, which is the right thing that must happen.
Another, remember, you want to be a Christian socialist.
You've got to transform the people from being selfish people.
You can't just establish socialism by declaring people should share things.
You've got to turn people into the kind of beings that love each other and do share things.
And how do you do that?
Not by preaching philosophy, for sure.
So you look like you want to say something more.
What I want to say is that what says his decision to go into the monastery and getting away from the world Christiana's phrase teach, a resignation for the Christian aspect of love, you know.
Well, it good, good, good.
Well, it's a kind of resignation.
It's better not to relate it to Kierkegaard because that's such a special thing, infinite resignation.
You've got to have a defining commitment and all that stuff, like in Hiroshima Monomore.
It is a kind of resignation.
It's a kind of resignation which says we can't transform the world, we monks.
Well, the most we can do is keep the image alive till the conditions are right for transforming the world, and then it'll go out in the world.
And now I'm back to where I am talking about this.
The conditions are right, and Alyasha goes out into the world, and he and two things are clear that you've got to keep your eyes open for when you read.
He doesn't perform any miracles until he leaves.
I mean, he leaves, well, he sort of comes back for his clothes, maybe, or something.
But when he runs out of the monastery and throws himself on the ground, he's ready to perform the first miracle on Grushenka.
And he performs lots more saving miracles.
He's the angel of the book.
Everybody, he helps everybody at some point or another, and they all call him an angel.
And that's when he is no longer on the safe path, which is a kind of resignation, and he's actually doing it, which is certainly not a kind of resignation.
And it's so much, resignation makes it sound too pessimistic.
Father Zosima is joyful because he knows that they've kept alive this experience and this message by making it safe, but they've at least kept it alive.
And he's very ambivalent about it.
Maybe that ambivalence is related to whether he should come back to the Alyasha should come back to the monastery or not.
He's ambivalent about it in that he thinks that it's a good thing that they retired and kept this alive.
But he also knows that it's a kind of cop-out because it's a safe path, and he should feel guilty about having done it.
So he feels a combination of being joyful to be there in the loving community, which is preserving Agape love.
He feels joyful about that, but he feels resigned or sad that he's not going to see the promised land, so to speak, to talk Bible talk like Moses does and Martin Luther King does.
To see the promised land is to go out and turn the world into paradise.
He can't do that.
He knows he can.
You can call it resignation if you want, as long as you say that he leads a joyful life, too.
Okay, let me go on because it gets clearer what happens with Alyasha, which is so nice.
So he's sending him out into the world on 84.
On 85, I don't know what's happening.
That's when Zosima just blesses him to do it.
And he will now, okay, now let's see.
Eventually, Dostoevsky believe that Christianity in this existentialized form will take over all of Russia and from there the entire world.
But it won't be Christianity as we know it after 2,000 years of institutionalized Christianity.
It'll be Markle's truth.
It'll be this ecstatic experience of the world here and now as paradise.
So we don't want to say that it ever gets secularized, remember I said, but it gets existentialized.
This unrational, supernatural experience of agape gets, well, at first it gets sheltered by the monastery, stage two, and then it gets expressed in a way that is worldly.
I need a word for it, you'll see why.
Not secular.
That's the opposite of spiritual.
It's spiritual, but it's worldly.
It's not withdrawn from the world.
So we're going to see that now.
He looks completely worldly when he leaves.
I mean, that's the way to see.
Alyosha is not transformed because he's already been transformed when he threw himself on the ground.
He's, I don't know, sort of demonasteryized, demonked.
On the bottom of 202, or the two-thirds down on 202, the boys tease him for being a monk in silk trousers.
I have to say that only so you can appreciate.
Dostoevsky says it, I think, so you can appreciate what he looks like when he leaves on 616.
Doesn't matter if you made it there, although if you don't hurry and read it over the coming weekend, I'm going to tell you the plot.
You're going to have to discover who the murderer is and so forth.
But here we are.
This won't give away anything.
On 6.16, Alyosha looks different now.
Just the beginning of the second paragraph.
We may note here that Alyasha's appearance had undergone a complete change since we saw him last.
He had abandoned his cassock, that's this robe-like thing he was wearing, whatever it was.
He's now wearing a well-cut coat, a soft brown hat, and his hair is cropped short.
Obviously, monks had long hair.
All this was very becoming, and he looked quite handsome.
Now, it's all very nice.
That's the new Alyasha in the world.
And that new Alyasha performs lots of miracles.
I wonder if Zosima ever performed any miracle.
I'm not sure that he does because he stays in the monastery.
And I think if you don't go out in the world, maybe you can't perform them.
Keep your eyes open for that, too.
So now, let's see where we are.
Okay, now we've got something that's not normally possible for normal human beings, and that is being part of this flow of agape love.
Like an ocean, I can talk in water metaphors, it flows into the world through Markle or Jesus.
It flows into the world first through Jesus, and so to speak, again through Markle.
It's sort of not only the incarnation, but a re-incarnation, you could say, with Markle.
The love flows into the world.
And now the question is: how does it sort of go from person to person?
How do they get in touch with this flow of love?
And that gets us to the onion chain.
The onion chain is the first part of the story for him in a way, the first part of the story of how it's going to go out into the world.
But it told in terms of a parable on 405.
It's brilliant that Dostoevsky finds this funny story to make his point.
Where is the onion story?
405.
Okay, I'm going to read you the whole onion story.
Now you should have the chart in front of you.
I just turned the onion story into a chart for this book.
But first, I'll read the story.
I'll read it fast because we've got not much time because you've got it in front of you.
Once upon a time, there was a peasant woman, a wicked woman.
She died and didn't do a single good deed.
The devils plunged her into a lake of fire.
So her guardian angel, everyone has a devil and a guardian angel, demagicalized.
On both sides of it, I do it in two ways.
But the onion chain one is what you want, which is the succession of love to Alyasha.
Then chart two is what happens when it hits Alyasha.
Then everybody gets into it in a different way.
So let's, I'm reading it still.
So the guardian angel comes and wonders what good deed, and she's given away an onion, so they start pulling her out with an onion.
And if you pull her out, God says she can come to paradise.
The angel ran to the woman and held out the onion, and he was pulling her out, but she was a very wicked woman, and she began kicking all the others.
I'm the one to be pulled out, not you.
It's my onion, not yours.
As soon as she said that, the onion broke, and she fell back into the lake, and is burning there to this day.
Well, Alyasha's the woman, but Alyasha isn't a selfish, bad woman, and he doesn't take all the people off.
He's pulled out, and everybody else is pulled out by holding on to him.
That's the parable version.
Now, in the chart, you can see, chart, onion, chain one.
There's God, which is the field of connectedness.
There's Marsha, the Markle incarnates it.
Well, Zosima is really the onion.
I'm sorry, I got it wrong.
I once realized.
Zosima is the onion.
He's the one who is enabling Alyasha to be pulled out.
And Zosima pulls Alyasha out.
By the way, does Zosima have one S or two?
In our book, it has two, but everywhere in my charts, it has one.
Is it open to two different ways of spelling?
Or is it just dyslexic?
Russian consultants, how do you spell Zosima?
We will find out.
So now we get to Alyasha.
So Alyasha connects with everybody.
And you can just run through it.
I don't think you've gotten near enough the end of the book.
How many of you have read Yvonne's encounter with the devil?
Well, you guys know, anyway, that Alyasha comes in and saves Yvonne from going completely crazy.
And Yvonne says, so you come in just in time, you came flying down to rescue me, and he saves him.
But he doesn't save him completely.
That's why he's in brackets.
Yvonne is in bad shape by the end of the book.
And he doesn't save Lisa completely.
She's in brackets on my chart.
He certainly counteracts the bad Yvonne influence, but he can't really help her.
He does save Kalya, you don't know that yet, Ilusha, the boys, Dimitri, and we've seen already how he saves Grushenka.
Now, when he saves them, now you turn over the chart, you see something that isn't in the parable of the onion, except in that one sentence, that there was a guardian angel.
But there's not only a guardian angel, there's a devil trying to bring about the destruction of all of these people.
I once heard on the radio when I used to listen to the radio, always some, before the program I wanted, which I don't remember, there was some sort of evangelical program, and the guy ended by saying, and the devil still goes through the world, seeking to corrupt the souls of men.
And I think, gee, people still believe that.
Well, Dostoevsky believes it, but he believes it in an existentialized way.
I don't know what the preacher on the radio meant.
There is, notice now, there's always somebody corrupting.
You've got Markle, there's God, the ocean of love, and there's that socialist philosophy friend.
And the socialist philosophy friend makes him say to his mother, remember God, there is many God, and I won't pray to the icons, corrupts him for a while, but God wins out in Markle.
And then Zosima, it's the army that turns him into a brute.
And Markle wins out in Zosima when he has this sudden transformation at the duel.
And Zosima gives this love to Alyasha, and now you get all these pairs in which we saw Rakitin and Ivan corrupting Alyasha, and the angel saving Alyasha's Zosima.
And we see thus, Alyasha, saving Grushenka.
Well, we see Alyasha corrupting Grushenka and saving Grushenka.
That's why there's so true arrows from him.
Remember?
Because people at the bottom, below Grushenka, Alyasha is the devil one.
It's his not looking at Grushenka, remember, that makes her humiliated and drives her to despair.
But there's the Alyasha who looks at her with the purest interest, which saves her.
You don't know all the fight around Dimitri yet.
Alyasha is trying to save Dmitry.
Ivan and Rakitin are trying to corrupt Dimitri.
Ivan is trying to, I can't even tell you what.
Rakitin is telling him about neurons.
And Dimitri says he's going to go to Siberia and become the angel for the Siberian prisoners.
Ivan, we can't say much about yet, nor Lisa.
You have to sort of figure it out from here on.
But the little chart at the bottom there is: the angel is always the one above, and the devil is always the one below.
And what I want to say is the whole structure of the book is, as that chart is supposed to show, is not always the angel and devil fighting for the soul of man.
Ooh, I just remembered.
Look at this.
Remember what Dimitri says?
Dimitri says, 121, God and the devil are fighting there, meaning the soul of man.
God and the devil are fighting there, and the battlefield is the heart of man.
That's the heart, that's what this is about, the battlefield for the heart of each person.
Now let's see where we are.
We still have time, which is good.
I want to see.
So there's the onion story.
Looks, I have to go back now and it jumped ahead.
Ah, look at that.
I was just going to cite the Dimitri thing.
So let's just review again.
And what does the angel do?
It always loves the person.
It's usually Alyasha, always in this book.
I guess the angel is Alyasha.
Loves the other person.
And by giving them this kind of confidence, he gets them over their humiliation.
People are always humiliating other people, in Dostoevsky, and then that makes them able to love themselves and to love others and to come out of the selfish world, the hell of isolation, to talk like the mysterious visitor into the world of love.
And Dimitri sees all that.
Another way to put it, the angel is always there, sort of affirming the good side of the self when you think about it in the two books.
If you think about it as having lackey, and what's the other side?
What is Ivan the view that they're either lackey or lofty?
That's it, yeah.
Anyway, so insofar as there is a good and a bad side to the self, which is very tricky because depending on how you define it, but if you've got a good and bad side, your view of the self, then you really have a good and bad side because you're the self that you've got a view of.
Then the angel, whether the devil tries to bring out the lackey side and the angel tries to bring out the lofty side, or whatever it is that's leading you to despair and to give up on love and give up on your fellow human beings, that the devil reinforces that.
Saw that with Rakitin when he was despairing because of Zasima.
And when you see it with Grushenka, when Rakitin brings Alyasha to Grushenka to bring out the worst in her to get her to seduce Alyasha.
And the other side is always trying, the angel is always trying to bring out the good side and reinforce the person and save them from despair.
And that's what the chart is about.
And Alyasha does it to everybody in the book except Lisa and Yvonne.
And maybe he'll do it later with Lisa because he's going to marry her.
And there's one sentence that says that Yvonne lived to become a nice person.
I think I cited it once.
You'll see it when you go by.
It says, years later, Yvonne considered the moment when he was down.
Blow everybody's mind.
When he sees, okay, when he, so, so Yvonne will be saved too.
There are people who won't be saved.
And I think I just want to mention it now.
On my chart, there are no angels and devils fighting for two people.
And one of them is Rakitin, because he's not a person.
He's only got this ambition to see the fall of everybody.
He is a demythologized devil.
And who's the other person, sort of semi-person, that Alyasha doesn't try to save?
And nobody's fighting over the solo.
It's Merzhikov, because he's no person at all.
He's got no self.
He lost his self when he was told that he grew from the mildew in the bathhouse, which he never remembered.
Remember all that?
So it's important then, that you really have to be sort of pathological or kind of physiological to be outside of this self that has these two sides and having the, what's it's the Madonna and Sodom sides.
I just want to remind you of them in which there's always a side that the angel needs to sort of support and the other side the devil needs to bring down.
I have to say something here that I skipped somewhere.
I don't know where I should have put it, but maybe I should put it right here.
Maybe I do put it right here.
Let me look.
Probably.
So I'm just thinking about Lisa.
What happens with Lisa is when, you know, she is sadomasochistic.
She slams the door on her finger and watches the blood.
She dreams of seeing the child crucified and eating compote while watching it.
She plays this game of dreaming of the devils coming at her while she's in her bed and then just at the last minute making the sign of the cross and chasing them away.
And what's interesting is, here it's 674.
Can Alyasha help her?
What's her problem?
This is all very strange stuff.
And on the top 674, is Alyasha still a monk or does she just think he's a monk at this point?
I don't know.
You're a monk, she says.
He's talking about how everybody wants to kill their father.
This is the part Freud liked a lot.
But that's not what we want to talk about here.
What we want to talk about is she says, I had a funny dream.
I dreamt of devils.
It's night, and I'm in my room with a candle, and the devils come and they want to grab me, and they're just about to grab me, and I make the sign of a cross, and they draw back, but they don't go away.
They stand in the corner waiting, and suddenly I have a frightful longing to revile God aloud.
And so I begin, and then they come crowding back to me, delighted, and grab me again.
And I cross myself again.
It's awful fun.
It takes one's breath away.
And that's already amazing, weird Dostoevsky.
But the next line is even more amazing.
First, let's ask: I mean, what's the dark side of Alyasha that would enable him to understand and help Lisa?
And the answer to everybody's amazement, at least mine, is Alyasha says, I've had that dream too.
What?
Reviling God and playing with the devils?
Really?
cried Lisa, surprised.
Alyasha, don't laugh.
It's awfully important.
Did two people have the same dream?
It seems they can.
Alyasha, I tell you, it's awfully important, Lisa went on in amazement.
It's not the dream that's important, it's having the same dream and so forth.
So it's very important that he has this dark side which enables him to empathize with her and help her.
So even to be an angel, remember to be able to save anybody, you've got to have a dark side.
And we know Sauson was in the army, and we know the mysterious visitor was a murderer.
We know what else.
We know what, but there's another one, too, right?
One of the saving people.
Anyway, so, yeah.
What about Jesus?
Ah, well, that's there.
We have to have another course and read The Idiot.
The Idiot is about Jesus.
And as I read The Idiot, nobody else reads it this way that I know of.
The idiot is supposed to be Jesus.
And after The Idiot's been in the world and been relating to people for a while, he drives one of them to suicide, and another one goes crazy.
He creates a complete mess, the idiot.
And that's because he's perfectly good.
He has no dark side.
Now, so Dostoevsky thinks Jesus must have a dark side, and we just don't know about it.
And that Alyasha has this dark side is really mysterious.
If anybody could cast a lot of light on it, they should write a paper about it.
I think, when you ask yourself, what makes Lisa a spiritual double of Alyasha?
And it seems, this is just my first guess, but some of you will understand this better than me just because you can sort of try and see how far I got and maybe go further.
I mean, I think that they both, remember, Alyasha can't stand hearing the dirty words that his schoolmates shout in his ears.
He hasn't integrated his sensuality.
That's why he came.
It's beginning to be integrated because he can look at Grushenka now without getting upset.
But in general, Alyasha's sort of earthy side is very undeveloped and unintegrated.
And Lisa must have the same thing.
She has these very dangerous desires.
She desires that Ivan come and beat her up or rape her or something, and he doesn't.
And then Alyasha said, she says, I don't want to go find the passage, but she says, I wanted him to, and then the thing goes dot, dot, dot.
I mean, what you couldn't write probably in Russia at that time.
But it's clear that she wanted him to do something to her qua-masochist and him asatus, because Alyasha said afterwards, he did an honorable thing.
He just left.
He didn't take advantage of her.
But anyway, so all I can think of is that Alyasha and Lisa have some big deal problem with their sensuality, which they misunderstand, this is the crucial part, as some devilish part of themselves.
And as long as they do and sort of play with it that way, they are not going to be able to integrate it.
And of course, somehow, some way, probably the way they love each other, they're going to have to be able to do that.
I just find that an interesting sort of loose end that must have been for the second volume that we can only make up.
We've got another minute to make it up.
You want to go ahead.
He's already given it up.
That's interesting.
Let's look.
What tense does he say?
I have that dream or I've had that dream.
It's interesting to look.
He says, I had the same dream too.
Uh-huh.
So, okay.
We can believe that maybe he's made more progress at getting out of it.
We haven't seen, and one of them maybe is the relation to Grushenka.
He's seen that he doesn't have to look at women with lustfulness, but his agape sort of trumps that.
And maybe then he's already got that in his past, so he can help Lisa somehow learn to put it in her past.
That's what you're thinking.
Is that right?
Yeah, that was there in the Rakitan thing, but he overcame it.
I agree with you.
He doesn't have that dream anymore, probably.
But I'm back to what I was saying.
He just hasn't finished the job of explaining how he's going to deal with Lisa.
But one thing is fascinating.
Try to figure out what it is that makes them existential doubles.
And it's got something to do with not integrating the dark side.
That's all I had.
But start playing with integrating the dark side and then not integrating it and then doing it.
Let's stop with that.
We'll go on to the next issue next time.