And now that's the perfect transition to what I want to talk about, because that's where we are about resisting it.
Well, I have to do another thing before two things before I get there.
Remember, I'll remind you that we're going to get to the point where the Knight of Resignation has all kinds of possible free maneuvers to make to resist getting into this vulnerable situation.
But two things.
One, you may have noticed, and I just sort of thought that he was going to bring it up.
That's why it flashed in my mind.
And I'm happy he didn't.
And I shouldn't probably.
But just you must be sort of uneasy about how this maps on the Abraham-Isaac story.
And I'm not talking about God and Abraham and commands to kill Isaac at all.
That's because I, one, first, I think that's not a big deal issue in the preamble.
It's a big deal issue in the ethical why Abraham's trying to kill Isaac and why that's a good thing or a bad thing and what and so forth.
That's important.
But don't my feeling about this is get the phenomena straight first.
Find the revealing experience.
Go through all those nine different characteristics of it, for instance, and then, and I, by that way, I promised somebody that I would put the nine characteristics on a handout.
And then I discovered I had filled this handout.
So you'll have another handout next time in which I put down those nine characteristics of a defining commitment.
But when just when, and so get a good grip on the phenomenon before and its implications before you try to make sense of everything in the book.
Sooner or later, we're going to have to ask whether the Abraham-Isaac story really works very well with the Regina story and works very well with the defining commitment story and so forth.
But it is confusing and dizzying, and the best thing is just not to worry about it yet.
Yeah, Beatrice.
Yes, I keep putting the handouts on the webpage.
I haven't put the nine, I don't know whether I put the nine features yet, but I will.
Yes, if you don't get it here, but there were enough here, weren't there?
Did we run out?
I do have the hands out from last time.
But you always can find them and print them, but they're theirs last time.
Anybody, who needs the handout from last time about the Greek versus the Hebrew?
Just put your hands up.
Okay, now I'm back to things I want to talk about.
And here goes.
I have to get some interesting issue out of the way before we can discuss what the main subject for today is, all the various moves of resignation and why they don't work.
But before that, I want to discuss a special one that you really have to get off the table, or you won't understand anything else.
So let's review first.
So you've got an unconditional commitment.
And to make your life fully meaningful, it's got to be for something finite and temporal that gives you not only an identity, but day-to-day meaning in your life.
But if it's concrete enough to give you day-by-day meaning, then it's vulnerable.
Remember my example.
I mean, if Martin Luther King just thinks that justice ought to come to the black people sometime, and he gives sermons on that and so forth, then that isn't enough to get him out of bed in the morning if it's a cold, rainy day.
It doesn't matter what he does.
Sooner or later, God will get justice for the black people.
That's not a commitment that's finite and temporal enough.
He has to think justice for these people in the United States now, before I die, that is.
And if he has that, then he knows what he has to do every minute when he gets up out of bed.
He has to get up out of bed and plant his peace marches, rain or shine.
But it's that thing of making it finite and temporal so that every moment he has something meaningful to do in his life, which also makes it vulnerable.
If it's safe enough to not be vulnerable, it's empty enough and general enough and formal enough not to make everything meaningful.
My other example is in the old days, the committed, the communists who were committed to the ultimate triumph of the proletariat, but not necessarily their proletariat in their country and not necessarily now.
That isn't enough.
And if you're really committed to a revolution right now in your country, that's very vulnerable.
Okay, so that's the first thing.
And so Kierkegaard thinks that through a defining commitment to something finite and temporal, then you get an eternal lifelong commitment, and that gives you German a life full meaning.
And another way that it's vulnerable and dangerous is it might require you to die for it.
We said that you might die, the cause or the other person might die, all kinds of bad things could happen.
And is there any way of keeping meaning and keeping this strong kind of meaning and identity in your life and not be vulnerable?
And the answer is going to be no.
There are lots of moves in the philosophies of the world and the religions of the world and specific moves in the history of the West trying to have this thing that I said, one student asked me at the end, not last time, but time before, but isn't there some way to keep the meaning and not have the vulnerability?
And the answer is no, from Kierkegaard's point of view.
And in the world of the spirit, you have to have the risk in order to have the fulfillment.
One strange way he puts it is on 57, where he's talking about how in the world of the spirit, everything is you get what you deserve, so to speak.
And a little below the middle of 57.
Only one who knows anguish finds rest.
Only one who draws the knife gets Isaac.
That means, roughly, anyone, only those who live in the realization that all their life and their meaning and their identity and everything is not under their control, and yet it could be taken away at any moment, only they can have a full life.
That's getting the bread, of having a fulfilling life.
So only those who take the risk get the bliss and the eternal life, meaning the forever in their life, which can't be reinterpreted and gives them a sense, makes their life worth living, you could say.
And now comes, I had to say all that in order to say, but what about the people who believe in an afterlife?
Some of you, I presume, Christians certainly have for a long time.
And Kierkegaard's a Christian, you might think that you would think, I mean, after all, if you're a Christian theologian are completely, fanatically Lutheran.
And yet, he doesn't believe in the afterlife.
And if he, because if he did, of course, he wouldn't be having all these problems.
You could just say, well, we'll meet in the next life, so don't worry so much about the fact that you've lost your Beatrice in this life.
And that's how Dante has it.
Beatrice is always around.
Beatrice comes back to help Dante, even though she died, because she's been there all the time in eternity.
But the crucial passage is on 53, which is before your reading, but it's so important that we have to go back and read it.
The bottom of 53.
This is Kierkegaard making a move.
He doesn't say there isn't any afterlife.
You'll see the same move in Dostoevsky.
He's going to say that whether or not there's an afterlife isn't going to help us any with the existential problems involved in living a full time in this life.
And here's how he says it: But Abraham had faith.
He had faith for this life.
Yes, had his faith been for a future life, he would indeed have been, it would have indeed been easy to cast everything aside and hasten out of this world to which he did not belong or go join your loved one in eternity, that kind of eternity, not eternity in time, but eternity out of time.
But Abraham's faith was not of that kind, if there is such, for faith like that is not really faith, but only its remotest possibility.
That means it has a sense that somehow you ought to be able to be vulnerable and safe at the same time, but it doesn't really understand.
A faith that has some inkling of its object at the very edge of its field of vision.
Somehow, that's getting the bread.
Somehow, if you did it right, you could have a life that took on vulnerability and was secure at the same time.
And they realize that, these people who believe in the afterlife, but they think that it can only happen later.
So now let's go on.
So they have an inkling of this kind of bliss, but they remain separated from it by a yawning abyss in which despair plays its pranks.
And dominant stop with that, I think, just a second.
Yes.
And what that means, why are they in despair?
It looks like they should be happy if they believe that there's an afterlife.
They're in despair in that they have given up hope that they could be completely fulfilled and have a completely life worth living, have a commitment to what's finite and temporal that makes every day important.
They've given all that up and said, well, in this life, no, you can't do that.
It's unfortunate but not very good life.
But in the next life, that's going to be all fixed.
And that's despair because this is the main life you've got right now.
And if you go through it all, thinking that you can't have meaning and fulfillment now, you're in a kind of despair, even if you think that later you can.
That's his view about that.
And that means that, so that way of getting a fulfillment by that belief, you've got to just cancel when you read Kierkegaard.
There's a necessary connection for Kierkegaard between unconditional commitments, which are necessary for a meaningful life, and riskiness and vulnerability.
And you can't, there's no way to dodge it.
And all religions try to dodge it.
I think I said maybe Buddhism says non-attachment.
I had this, all kinds of, all mystical views are not facing the need for something finite and temporal.
I had this weird experience when I was teaching this long ago when I first came out here, and there was a big TM movement was very strong, and I had several very high-level TM people in the course, and they convinced me I had to go and listen to the sort of speech of the people and join TM.
How many know what transcendental meditation is?
I trust you've all seen some reference to it somewhere.
Anyway, and I did it, and I thought it was interesting.
And then we saw a video of Maharisha Yoga, the man who's Baha'i, who's the founder of this way of doing meditation and so forth.
And he said his whole speech was sitting there holding a rose and saying, if you follow my way of life, you can have the happiness without the thorns, you could have the rose, which is the happiness without the thorns.
You could have the bliss without the suffering and the anguish and the vulnerability.
And I thought that was just so absolutely wrong.
I was teaching Kierkegaard that when we went around the room and they asked each one what we got out of this, and everybody said, oh, isn't it wonderful, isn't this wonderful possibility?
And I said, if the devil himself came back and gave this talk, he would say just that, because he would be undermining Western civilization.
Namely, that detachment and innerness and so forth is not what we're here for.
Now, maybe it is what other cultures are here for.
Remember, you are what custom makes you.
But Kierkegaard certainly thinks that 2,000 years of Judeo-Christian custom has made us into people who need to have the thorns in order to have the rose.
So that's what it is.
But back to what I was saying, but all traditional philosophers make some kind of move that makes meaning safe.
And now we have to look at them, all of them, because they're all interesting.
And Kierkegaard mentions all of them at various points in this opening introduction, but not, of course, in any systematic way, because that's not how Kierkegaard writes, particularly when he's upset in Berlin thinking about Regina.
He can write in a much more step-by-step style, but not here.
So anyway, here we go.
Here are the modes of defense.
All of these are defenses against the vulnerability of making an unconditional commitment.
And the first one is simply to avoid commitments of that, unconditional commitments.
Then you just don't have a defining relation.
You don't concentrate the whole content of your life into a single wish.
What have I got here?
Just a second.
How to avoid the risk.
Oh, well, I see.
Well, first he's going to say what you don't do.
But the knight of faith has it.
I'm not sure this is the best way to explain it, but I wrote it down this way, and I'm going to follow it because I may have known what I was doing when I wrote it down this way.
So the top, the knight has the strength to concentrate the whole of his life's content and the meaning of reality into a single wish.
And then comes the sentence I was wanting to quote.
If a person lacks this concentration, this focus, his soul is disintegrated from the start.
This is the lowest level.
This is lower immediacy.
Lower immediacy is so sort of disintegrated and distracted that they don't even focus enough to get an unconditional commitment.
And they never come to make the movement to do the unconditional commitment.
He, we're talking about this lowest level person, will act prudently in life like those capitalists who invest their capital in every kind of security so that they gain on the one what they lose on the other.
In short, he's not a knight.
So the second, so the first stage is lacking a defining commitment at all, and that means not being a knight at all.
And I just want to say one more thing about it.
The translation is bad at the top of 72.
And even if you don't notice it, it sort of throws you off.
You see anything wrong with concentrating the meaning of reality into a single wish?
Wish is the wrong word.
Martin Luther King didn't sit around thinking, wishing that justice would come to the black people.
Or the lover doesn't, Dante didn't sit around wishing that Beatrice would always be there in the flesh, so to speak, with him.
What they really are trying to say, what Fierga's trying to say is, in a single commitment.
And there is another translation which says, in, let's see, what does it say?
Into a single heart's desire.
That must be the sort of Valentine way to describe this romantic commitment.
But it's not a wish.
Heart's desire is supposed to point at something much deeper.
But this character doesn't have that.
They are dispersed and they have backup lovers and backup callings.
How many have seen a movie Shampoo, which was around once?
It's a good movie.
What's interesting about shampoo, though, nobody ever says it, is that everybody has sort of backup lovers in case something goes wrong with their current relationship and backup jobs in case something goes wrong with their current vocation.
It all happens in LA and it seems to be, according to this movie, something about an LA way of life.
And those are the people who are lower natures, as he says on 6, oh, sorry, on 72, about 10 lines down in the first full paragraph.
That means two-thirds of the way down on the page.
He says, only lower natures forget themselves and become something new.
I read this last time.
The butterfly forgets itself.
The caterpillar can forget that it was a caterpillar when it's a butterfly.
Deeper natures never forget themselves and become something else.
Okay, so basically, the lower, so the there's in lower immediacy, you're not an eye, and you don't have this problem, but you don't have any self either.
Yeah.
Okay, and what and probably, but I don't know yet.
I have to read where we are.
Where is, okay, here I see, I'm going to skim it.
The paragraph that begins, faith is therefore.
Yeah, let me look at it.
Just to start explaining as we go, an aesthetic emotion is some kind of excitement, like an infatuation.
And aesthetic is another name for the lowest level in Hegel.
I don't know if it's on the chart that way.
I doubt it.
But aesthetic for him means, no, we don't have it there.
But it means, yes, we do.
Under Kierkegaard, at least, there is something called aesthetic.
It's a kind of lower immediacy.
It's in the feeling business.
Aesthetic has to do with feeling.
That's why anesthetic means not feeling.
And now it's lucrative.
So it's not, and that's the immediate, you notice that inclination of the heart.
But that's not the paradox of existence at all.
Now, let's look at the young girl.
If you just have a kind of simple faith that everything will turn out all right, in childlike simplicity and innocence, you haven't got it.
You haven't got it because, why?
Because you're missing the vulnerability.
You don't see the sword hanging every minute over the head of the beloved in love as if it's the surest thing of all, which is what he says about the knight of faith.
You don't see the sword hanging over the head at all.
You're just in total shock, like Regina probably was when this nice bourgeois kid or young man, well, just suddenly broke her engagement and ran off to Berlin.
I mean, that wasn't even conceivable.
It hadn't bothered her that that could happen.
So that's just a nicer version rather than the capitalists of somebody who hasn't faced up to the problem at all and therefore doesn't really have an unconditional commitment at all.
She has a crush on somebody and she doesn't know, or he has a crush on somebody, and he doesn't know, doesn't even think about the fact that there's any risk involved.
So, okay, so now let's see.
So, there are many strategies for people who are not lower natures.
And now we're going to get those.
Philosophers obviously get you to some kind of mediation which is not lower immediacy and is safe.
And there seem to be three different kinds of philosophical ways of making a move that makes things safe.
The Greek philosopher, in effect, and this is surprising, forgets the whole thing, forms a defining relation, and then life goes on, and he decides that, really, well, that wasn't really important after all.
And the interesting thing is, Kierkegaard thinks that that requires a certain concentration.
That is, these aren't just, these philosophers don't just forget it, or like the young girl, never saw the problem, or like the people in shampoo thought that you could make backups of yourself in the situation and not have to face it.
These people make the big deal effort of breaking themselves out of any such commitment, stopping it before it grabs them.
And this is what he's talking about on 72.
So the knight makes the movement, the first full paragraph, but what movement?
Does he want to forget the whole thing?
Because in that too, there's a kind of concentration.
No, the knight doesn't concentrate, can contradict himself, and it would be a contradiction to forget your whole life's content and still be the same.
You recognize that.
If it's a defining relation, you can't just forget it, because it makes you the person that you are.
Well, what would it be like to forget it?
Well, how many, any of you read the symposium, Plato's symposium?
Well, it's always interesting because the symposium is a very, very Greek take on romantic love, among other things.
There is a story in the symposium about that all people were round once, and then they got cut in half, and they all go around feeling very wounded and miserable, looking for their other half.
When they find their other half, they hold on to them and hug them and don't want to leave them and so forth.
It sounds just, it's a lovely story of romantic love, except that it's told by the comic, it's supposed to be funny.
It's told by Aristophanes, who thinks it's a joke.
And that's very characteristic of this whole approach.
So what does Plato think you should do?
Well, he thinks that you should start by loving some particular beautiful body and then understand that after all, beautiful bodies are lots of them around.
And why just get stuck with this one?
So you love all beautiful bodies.
And then you realize that inside these beautiful bodies are beautiful souls.
You love one beautiful soul, but then you realize there are others around, so you love all of them.
And then you realize, well, what's going on here?
I really love beauty of bodies and souls.
And that's, and once you see that, and you can contemplate pure beauty, Plato thinks.
I never have understood what that would look like or how to do it.
But anyway, he thinks when you finally contemplate the beautiful, then you see that all of these attachments to particular beautiful souls and beautiful bodies in all sorts of combinations were petty things.
That's the important thing.
You leave them behind.
That's what the forgetting of the whole thing.
You see that all the individual relationships were of small account.
And in other words, nothing was really lost.
The individual was never really important.
There's never been any suffering.
There's just been better and better and better, that is safer and safer and safer fulfillments.
That's what the symposium tells you.
Now, then I'm going to, the next, that's number one.
That's the Greek philosopher, Plato, Symposium.
Now, there's another one which I can't talk about yet.
That would be the tragic hero.
You will read about the tragic hero and Agamemnon.
That's not in your reading yet, is it?
I don't think so, right?
It's in Problem 1, right?
Okay, so we won't talk about that.
But there's another one which is just fascinating.
And if this, to get a full feeling of what's going on in Kierkegaard and how much he's repudiating the whole sort of mixed mishmash of the Jewish, well, that is Hebrew, Christian, and Greek, which is what happened when they started trying to put the Christian into, the Judeo-Christian, into Greek categories.
And I said that Augustine is the first really, really brilliant attempt to do it.
And Augustine is a Platonist of sorts, but he's also been somehow transformed by Christianity so that he's not really able to be a normal sort of Platonist.
And how it changes him, I'm going to read you passages because he has a beautiful story of a defining commitment and what happens to it.
So for the Greek philosopher, it turns out the individual was never significant.
What really was desired was always the universal, safe, secure ideal of the beautiful.
But from the Christian philosopher, namely Augustine, he sees both that loving an individual would be too risky, and yet, he sees somehow that it's more important than Plato says.
He never looks back and says it was just trivial.
And how this goes, I'm going to read you passages from the Confessions.
This happens to be the edition happily translated by somebody named Pine Coffin.
And so I'm going to read that.
Starting on 77 of this, that you won't want to read this.
I just want you to read it because I want to read it because it's got this nice phenomenology of defining commitments and then draws from a describing a kind of Christian commitment.
He ends up drawing a kind of Greek Plato conclusion.
And how it happens is interesting.
So on 77 of this translation, where do we get?
Why do we start with that?
Why, I don't know, but I'm doing it in a funny order, so I'm switching to my order.
The description of his relation to this friend is, before we had reached the end of the first year of friendship that was sweeter to me than all the joys of life as I lived in, you took him from the world.
That's the problem.
But starting with this, they were so close to each other, they never left each other's side.
They were completely dependent on each other.
They were always happy when they were together.
And he describes this beautiful relationship.
And then this friend dies.
And then what happens is the kind of grief that comes, which I keep talking about, which is why you don't want to let yourself get into this situation, where everything in the world becomes meaningless.
He says, My heart grew somber with grief, and wherever I looked, I saw only death.
And where else?
Let's see.
I wondered that other men should live when he was dead, for I had loved him as though he would never die.
I wondered that he should die and I remain alive, for I was his second self.
But now the second self isn't a joke anymore, as it was in the symposium, and that they're sticking together all the time.
It's this kind of romantic love, except it comes out quite differently.
So now everything has made sorrow for him, for the grief I felt for the loss of my friend had struck so essentially into my innermost heart, simply because I had poured out my soul upon him like water upon sand, loving a man who was mortal as though he would never die.
That is, he was treating, and everybody does, he was treating this love, which was vulnerable, as if it was the surest thing of all, and letting himself get more and more involved in it.
And that is exactly what the Knight of Faith is going to do.
But Augustine thinks that it shows that he's done something wrong.
He says, Blessed are those who love...
Now, where do I have to.
The moral is, now, this is the moral of all this bad experience he's had.
Blessed are those who love you, O God, and love their friends in you and their enemies for your sake.
They alone, this is the crucial thing, will never lose those who are dear to them.
For they love them in one who is never lost, in God.
So the finite temporal part of the relationship is not important.
It goes away.
Let me see now if I want to read more.
No, I think that's fine.
Now you've got in it.
The fact that he understands how important this love is, and he understands how dangerous and vulnerable it is.
And he makes this move where he never says that his love of his friend was a petty thing.
That's the crucial difference between him and the symposium.
It's clear that he always loves and remembers his friend.
But he should have loved only the eternal meaning of the relationship, right?
He should have loved the friend in God.
And then it would have been safe.
And so it's not wrong to think that the friend is important.
It's absolutely crucial the way he describes it.
He understands this kind of commitment to the friend completely.
But he thinks that the right way to do it, so as to not suffer, is to love the friend.
And again, the way I can put it to make some sense of it to myself is love the meaning of their relationship.
Love the happiness they had together.
But and don't get hooked on the actual presence of the friend.
Otherwise, bad, bad things will happen to you, namely total grief and suffering.
And so in the end, he says, I guess, did I read this?
I'm not sure.
Yeah, I think I did already.
I was to make sure I read what I wanted.
Yeah, that the friend is in God and never lost in God.
That's the crucial conclusion.
And he never mentions the friend again in the confession.
That's sort of Plato-like, that once you get beyond it, you don't have to think about it.
But it's not Plato-like to say that it's a petty thing.
It was that's the Christian.
You see what I mean?
The Greek part has made him think that he can love his friend in God and get out of the spatiotemporal and out of the risk.
And the Christian part has made him describe this relation to the friend, not as just one beautiful body among many, and not as one beautiful soul among the many, but an absolutely essential experience in his life, which he will never forget.
He will always preserve the significance of it in God, but not in this world.
Yeah.
It's exactly the same step as Dante's taking with Beatrice.
I think.
Let me see.
She's his savior.
She's dead.
He's loved her.
Yes, that's it.
Good.
And Beatrice, and Beatrice tells him so.
Beatrice says, It's funny.
We wish you could read the Divine Comedy because Dante's got enough of this Judeo-Christian sense of the real embodiment.
Because the first thing he does when he sees Beatrice, who shows up in the Divine Comedy, in the, I can't resist telling you, I don't think I did.
Dante, in the middle of the divine comedy, there's a procession in which all the books of the Old Testament walk by.
And then there's, and then there's the four gospel writers going by, and then there's a kind of chariot in which somebody is there, just covered up, so you can't see them.
And the angels are flying over this chariot, singing, Blessed is he who comes.
And then the person in the chariot throws off this covering.
Who would be in the chariot in the middle of history, led up to by the Old Testament and leading the New Testament with angels overhead?
Who could that be?
It's got to be Jesus, of course.
But it isn't.
It's Beatrice.
And the first thing she does after throwing this off is scold him forever paying attention to any other women and for getting upset when she died when he should have remained faithful to her the meaning of the relationship.
And Dante goes through the same thing.
And the first thing he does when he sees her is to remember how beautiful her legs were.
And then gets all hot thinking about him.
And she scolds him for that.
It's all very interesting.
So then he stops paying attention to her legs and starts paying attention to her smile, which is better.
And the angels overhead say, isn't that nice?
And finally, finally, he gets totally just hypnotized looking into her eyes.
And what he sees in her eyes is the symbol of the God-man, of Jesus.
So again, I mean, twice in the middle of the poem, he tells you, Beatrice is my Savior.
And then remember, I said he was going to write a poem about his girlfriend like nobody ever did before, and he sure does.
And then, and that's what's her point, but then, in the end, Beatrice starts, from the beginning of reappearing, Beatrice said, You never should have cared about my body, you never should have cared about the finite and the temporal to talk like Kierkegaard.
You should, we should have loved each other in God.
And in the end, they just both are staring at God, and they don't even, they give one last smile to each other, they never look at each other again for eternity.
And that's when the Greek wipes out the Christian, just as it does in Augustine.
Yeah.
That's for a bit larger than that.
Ah, uh-ha.
Good.
Good, good.
So, let me give you sort of, you realize, I hope, but if you don't, I better tell you.
I mean, the reason, the literary reason he's writing about resignation is that the book is being written by Johannes de Salentio, who is a knight of resignation.
And this is just, this doesn't answer your question yet.
And the reason he's writing about it at all in the world is because he's going into resignation in the face of having, for some reason he never explains, not being able to marry Beatrice like the lad couldn't get the princess.
And why is he talking so much about resignation?
Because he wants to tell you how important it is to have a commitment and how tempting it is to have a resignation, and how relatively easy it is to have resignation compared to what everybody could have if they had faith and were strong enough, which is being a knight of faith.
And he keeps saying, I don't really understand the night of faith.
I can't do the night of faith.
The best I can do is resignation.
Now, so my direct answer to you is he's writing about resignation because that's the best thing you can do short of being a very, very difficult character, namely the knight of faith who somehow keeps the meaning and the vulnerability because you can't get rid of it as resignation tries to do.
And when Kierkegaard, somebody asked me after class last time, what's Kierkegaard's unconditional commitment?
Obviously, not, Regina.
And it's relevant here.
Kierkegaard thought that it was his destiny to make Christianity very hard and to show people how hard it was and to fight the Lutheran church, which had made it so easy that you could be born a Christian and born a Lutheran without having to do anything at all except just be born in Denmark.
And he tried to become a martyr to this.
He wrote this, I told you the last book, I think I told you, call it Attack on Christendom, in which he said that the Lutheran church was part of the, was the worst scandal and problem because it was making it easy and therefore impossible to be a Christian, because being a Christian is very hard.
And this is part of what's very hard to be a knight of faith.
The reward is terrific, but it's very hard.
And I told somebody this at the end, which they thought was sort of interesting, so I'll tell you too.
When Kierkegaard wrote this attack on Christendom, I think he was in his 50s, wasn't he?
Well, even that young.
He was 42.
He did his job.
Since nobody would make him a martyr, the church wasn't going to burn him or hang him, he just died.
Fell down on the street with a disease that nobody could particularly diagnose and just died, done his job.
David wrote a book about Kierkegaard.
That's always struck me as absolutely amazing.
You go ahead.
So, your conscience or this, how are you know, not a desire?
Right.
I mean, uh the I'm trying to think about this.
I mean, being aware of these kinds of resignation, uh, I think he thinks the consciousness is important because you can be aware of the kind of resignation you've got when he tells you about it.
You can say, oh, that's just like me.
And then you can and then he tells you also that this kind of resignation is despair because you can't get the finite and the temporal.
And I think that's supposed to sort of help you.
You can't then willfully become a knight of faith, but you can sort of, I think, lose your attachment to and enjoyment of.
It's very interesting, very interesting.
It'll be a knight of resignation.
In every stage which you could be in, the aesthetic stage, which we mentioned of feeling, or the ethical stage where you try to do the job of being a good husband or wife and do your civic duties and get your meaning out of that, or even the stage of resignation.
There's always two ways it looks.
It looks like it's making your life work for the people in it.
And it looks like for the people who've already seen that it's despair and gone on, that it's a trap and your life isn't really working.
So he writes his books in a very peculiar way, which he calls indirect discourse.
First, he writes a book about the aesthetic stage of enjoyment, keeping all your possibilities open.
We've heard about that already.
And it's written from somebody, from the point of view of somebody who thinks it's a great thing to be in the aesthetic.
But you can see on the margins that this guy is in despair.
He's suffering from a lot of melancholy, and he gets more and more unhappy as the book goes on.
And then the ethical, the next stage is the ethical.
Judge William, who's a husband and a judge, the perfectly sort of ethical type, and it looks like that's the solution to everything.
That's how to lead a full life.
But then you begin to read around the margin and toward the end, that he's in despair, seen from an even higher stage.
So it's always, so now I'm trying to say that.
So his picture of it is you help somebody see that what they think is the right way to live and it's working, that it's not working, by showing them both that they identify with the aesthetic or the ethical, and then they get to the end of the book and they're discovering, if they're a very sensitive reader, the breakdown.
I think it's really brilliant on his part.
That's all he can do.
And then it'll either drive you to have an experience of leaping into the next sphere, as he calls these spheres of existence, the aesthetic, the ethical, the religious, and when it does, you will be in the next sphere.
You can't really choose to do it.
It's much deeper than that.
It's like reading him would be a kind of therapy.
I think that's what he thinks.
Okay, good question.
I saw another hand while I was talking to him.
Beatrice, yes.
That's right.
That's yeah, in fact, that is the punchline.
I said it early just because I had to say it.
But yes, that's right.
The middle of 73 is as close as you ever.
Well, sorry, no, let's wait for a minute, Beatrice, because that is it.
But there's a stage or two in between.
And then ask your question or say what you want to say.
Because we're still, let's see now.
We've gotten, there's the hero and the bourgeois way of life, and we're skipping over them.
We've now gotten a kind of Christian way of becoming a knight of resignation.
Let's see now.
I'm just reading now, this is just to lead up to the best way of trying to make resignation work, the highest kind of resignation.
So remember, somehow all these ways, like the one we just read, of finally, never mind making the meaning of it, that's not happened yet.
We've got all these people like Augustine and Dante so far.
And that's not enough to have your sort of, love each other in God.
We want some kind, we Judeo-Christians need that somehow the full meaning of our life has to make our life worthwhile, to give us bliss.
We have to live fully in the finite and the temporal.
So then, is there some way, and that means, I hear having italics, but that means the more meaning, the more vulnerability.
That's sort of a slogan that I had in the back of my mind at the beginning of the lecture.
I mean, that's the danger.
I mean, but it's not a danger you can avoid.
The way things are set up, the more deeply you get involved, the more risky it is, and the more meaningful everything is.
And so the question becomes: is there a way of making a defining commitment and yet be safe and not vulnerable?
And that's the what that's now what we get next.
And that's, I'm trying to think, is it Dante or is it, I don't know how I exactly later, but that's what's going on at the bottom of 72.
And it's an important thing, starting about 20 lines from the bottom.
Only lower natures forget themselves and become something new.
We've read that, skipping a little.
Deeper natures never forget themselves and never become something other than they were.
So the knight will remember everything.
This is the night of resignation.
But the memory is precisely the pain.
And yet his infinite resignation is reconciled with existence.
In his infinite resignation, he's reconciled with existence.
His love for the princess would take on for him the expression of eternal love, would acquire a religious character, be transfigured into a love for the eternal being.
Notice Augustine and Dante are doing this.
They're turning their love of love for the other one in God.
And that means, in a way, forgetting the other person in a certain way, as ever having to, Dante never has to never smile through Beatrice again, and Augustine never mentions his friend again.
They've turned it into an eternal love.
It's transfigured into a love for the eternal being, which although it denied fulfillment, still reconciles him once more in the eternal consciousness of his love's validity in the eternal form that no reality can take from it.
That is, you bring out the true meaning of the love.
There's echoes of Plato still in here.
That what's really important is that it's love.
And the highest kind of love is love of God.
And one way to put this is, Beatrice or the friend of Augustine has become the way that you get to the truth.
In the Gospel of John, John says Jesus is the truth and the way.
And what's happening in these Greek-influenced Christians who've got too much Plato and Aristotle in them, they can't really understand loving Beatrice as the truth.
That would be the truth is subjectivity.
That would be Beatrice as the object of infinite commitment and so forth.
They can understand Beatrice as leading them to see that they really love God.
That's the medieval Christian Beatrice Dante solution.
And there's so they've got a notion now of the love's validity in an eternal form.
I think that means what was really important about the love was that it was loving and not that it was about a finite temporal person.
And so love turns out to be a way to get to loving God and loving God is safe.
He has to turn his attention away from finite temporal Beatrice and so forth.
Okay, now there's one further stage, and this is where Beatrice's question came in: that we don't think that the highest is love of God, transforming this love into love of God.
What we've got is something like a secular version of that, which is transforming the love into an idealized version of the love, in which you love the significance of it, the meaning of it, the beauty of it, of that love with that person.
You remember them, and you remember how great it was to be with them, and so forth.
That's the move of resignation that we're going to talk about.
And then I can give you particular examples.
Where's the page, Beatrice?
That's what I thought.
72.
Let me.
Oh, well, 72, well, no, then 72, it's the one I just read then, and it's not all got all gone all the way.
Yes, that's what you want.
Exactly.
This is about 20 lines down.
This is the modern romantic way of having, I've been promising and promising this.
How can you have this love and the invulnerable?
The answers, and this is all in very important preparation for the movie.
That's why I'm stressing it so much.
And what do you gain and what do you lose?
Well, we haven't talked about what you lose, but what you gain is you've got the whole marvelous, beautiful memory of this experience.
And nothing can take that away from you.
And that makes you who you are.
You are still the lover of Mary, though Mary's gone now, died or left.
But you still have a definition.
And you still have, in some way, a meaningful world.
But of course, there's something missing.
You don't wake up every morning knowing what you have to do, as you did if you were the lover of X or the leader of something.
But you just contemplate the significance that you were that.
I mean, if Martin Luther King had lost because the people didn't come to the peace march, he can still remember being the leader, preaching it, hoping for it, having a vision of it, and so forth.
So this is what he's saying on 73.
He keeps his love.
Where do we start?
Yeah, about 15 lines down.
He's too proud to want to let the whole content of his life be a fleeting affair of the moment.
I mean, in a certain way, that's, of course, what Plato did in the symposium.
He keeps this love young and it grows with him in years and beauty.
And on the other hand, he has no need, has no finite occasion for its growth.
For the moment he made the movement, the princess is lost.
He needs none of this erotic titillation of the nerves at the sight of the loved one, etc.
Nor does he need in a finite sense to be making his farewell, for his memory of her is an eternal one.
And skipping a little, he has grasped the deep secret that even in loving another, one should be sufficient unto oneself.
That is, you can have this love, it can define you, but it can't hurt you because you're not dependent on the actual existence, presence of the other person.
So you've got the best of all worlds, it would seem.
And a little more on the next page about infinite resignation.
And that's being, and now I have to make clear.
That's what it is finally to be a knight of infinite resignation.
That's the highest kind.
And all these others were sort of failed nights of infinite resignation.
They didn't really bring it off.
They didn't keep the individuality and the absolute importance of the other person who's there all the time, day and night, in a funny kind of, what, fake temporality.
I mean, they're always present to think about, and it's you think about them more than where you really are.
Let me just read a passage, and then somebody wants to say something.
Okay, where are we now?
74, this first full paragraph.
In infinite resignation, there is peace and repose.
Anyone who wants it, who has not debased himself by what is still worse than being too proud, belittling himself, never mind that.
Just skip the parentheses, the dashes.
So anyone who wants it who has not debased himself can discipline himself into making this movement, which in its pain reconciles one with existence.
And that's Kierkegaard who did that with Regina.
And that's the writer of this book, Johannes de Salentio, has done that.
There is, again, skipping down, in infinite resignation, there is peace, repose, and consolation in pain.
And there's some stuff at the top of the page, which is a problem that I don't think.
Now, remind me, if you want, that what I say, what I haven't said it yet, but I'm going to say something that contradicts the top of 74 and knocked down Kierkegaard's grade a bit for having made a mistake.
But I'm not ready to wipe that mistake away a little later, or you'll get confused.
If you don't understand why he says what he says at the top of 74, that shows you're really understanding the book.
Go ahead.
I couldn't hear you well enough, and probably neither could the people in in the podcast world.
Say it again louder.
How about love defines but you think that you live in the even lost being hurt?
Yes, exactly.
You depend on the world, and that's the nice thing.
You can't get hurt if you depend on it in sense of the memory of it, the meaning of it, the fact that it's the most important thing in your life, that it tells you who you are.
You're the lover of Mary who lost Mary.
But that's still a very defining, very meaningful way to be.
And that's how you can do it.
Be sufficient under yourself and you can't get hurt.
And that's the moment of resignation.
Yeah.
Oh boy.
And how?
But it really, that's the whole next lecture.
But basically, the Knight of Faith sees the sword hanging over the head of the beloved and gets more and more involved with the finite, embodied, present love all the time.
So the Knight of that's the interesting thing.
The Knight of Faith has the actual person there or the cause or whatever.
And the fulfillment and the fun and the romantic situations and the sexual pleasures and all that, the Knight of Faith has all of that.
And knows that it's vulnerable, but doesn't sort of put all their defenses into keeping from being hurt, but puts all their energy into getting more and more involved.
And just as I'm saying it now, you're supposed to be thinking, but that's a crazy thing to do.
Why would anybody get themselves in the situation of getting more and more involved, knowing that that could at any moment lead them to be terribly hurt, like Augustine when his friend died?
Why not take the safer one, the infinite resignation, where you get everything but the actual finite embodied person.
You get all the meaning of the relationship, and isn't the meaning what really matters?
Well, Kierkegaard wants to both say that's very attractive.
That's as near as you can get to having the relationship and being safe, but it's not good enough because, and now I could just ask you and you will know the answer.
Why is infinite resignation?
Let's find a quote.
I read them already, but now you're in a position to see what they mean.
Darn.
I'm going to find some.
Maybe.
I want to find about the pain in the relation.
Is that 75?
It's right around there.
Bottom of 75.
When he lists the joy and the pain that goes with being a knight of resignation, he does it every once in a while.
He says at the middle of 74 in the infinite resignation, there's peace and repose.
But he also says when he says the whole thing, and there's suffering.
Just help me find that one.
73 at the bottom.
Okay.
I don't see it there.
Where do you see it?
Oh, yeah.
I don't see it yet, but I see you're right.
Where on 73?
Oh, 72, no wonder I can't see it.
And I don't see it yet.
Now what's wrong with me?
Okay, I see.
No, I want to talk about the pain.
Where is the pain?
The very bottom.
Reconcile.
And denied his fulfillment.
That's Sparta we were talking about.
Reconcile him in the eternal consciousness of his love's validity that no reality can take from him.
I still don't see the pain.
Okay.
Ah, got it.
Yeah, that's the right quote, all right.
Deeper natures never forget themselves and never become something other than they were, so the night will remember everything.
That's this wonderful relationship, remembering it.
That the memory is precisely the pain, and yet in his infinite resignation, he is reconciled with existence.
I mean, he understands that he's got as much as you can hope to get, and he's got all that meaning, and he just has to take the pain along with it.
And that's it.
Okay, yeah.
Okay.
Well, maybe if she finds more.
I guess after a little higher.
Yeah, stop, stop.
That's the quote.
That's a mistake, I think.
But that's what you're about to say.
Yes, it's wrong.
Now, remember, I said, if you think that the top of page 74 doesn't make sense and is the wrong thing to say, you're really understanding it.
Congratulations.
I can't make any sense out of it.
But to say how wrong it is and why it's obviously why he's led to make the mistake, the mistake, I can't be too mysterious, is where I have to skip a big jump, which I'll just do right now, and then we'll come back to it.
I mean, we have to get to what he says that makes he can't, it shows that he can't say that.
So, where we go.
He's safe.
Right?
Absolutely.
But there's a stronger place than that, what he's saying, which I could want to find.
And then, because people won't see very well yet what you're seeing, how it's contradicted, unless I go further.
So, let me start this: the downside, I'll still have time.
The downside of resignation.
We talked about the pain, but now let's get the pain clear.
So, you're self-sufficient, so that you're never fully joyful.
Aha, if I'd only paid attention to my markings, I have a page for this too.
Let's see if it's better or worse than the pages you guys got.
On page 63, he says, At the bottom, I am happy and satisfied.
That this is the night of resignation talking, of course, that my happiness is not faith, and compared with that, it's indeed unhappy.
That's all.
That's just another way, it's no better, no worse than you're saying that it's joyful, that it's always sad and suffering at the same time.
And now comes the point that's going to lead to his problem.
And he says that if that there's something wrong with the night of resignation, in that if the night of resignation got the loved one back, he wouldn't know what to do with him or her.
You see why that's the stage to getting where you are?
And why would that be?
Well, he's resigned himself to making the whole of the finite, temporal, embodied other person irrelevant and said, What's really important is the meaning of this relationship.
Right now, suppose the other person comes back.
Let's just fill it out.
He's gotten used to living without the other person.
Then the other person is not essential, in fact, it seems sort of awkward to have this person around.
And why is it so awkward?
Well, if you don't get attached to them, then they're sort of a stranger in your house.
But if you do get attached to them, you're back where you started with the problem.
Because if their bodily presence is important and fulfilling and thrilling and all that, then you're going to get more and more involved.
Then you're going to get more and more hurt.
And so the person who's done the movement of resignation doesn't want this other person around because they're either just a bother or worse, they're a temptation.
So you would get into the anxiety all over again.
And if you're a kind of Christian, even Augustine can't resist getting hooked on beautiful things.
After he's managed to get unhooked from ever having a friend or any other human being so close, he says that he can't resist the attraction of the incense.
He loves the smell.
Then he starts saying how much he loves the stained glass windows and the light and so forth.
There is just this tendency to get to find the finite and temporal beautiful, wonderful, and so forth.
And that's a big risk for the night of resignation.
So, and on 65, you hear about it again.
So, the loved one can only be in the way.
And where do we find that?
On 65, at the end of the top paragraph, my behavior would have vitiated the whole story.
Never mind that part.
Or I would have been at a loss if I got Isaac back.
In this case, Kierkegaard saying, I'd be at a loss if I got Regina back.
What Abraham found the easiest of all would be for me hard.
I'm explaining why it's hard.
The other person is either a temptation or just an annoyance.
To find joy again in Isaac.
For he who, with all the infinity of his soul, on his own account and with his own responsibility, has made the infinite movement and can do no more, that person keeps Isaac with pain.
So you just write, Kierkegaard, if he got Regina back, could only keep Regina with pains, right?
And then you turn to the page that I said was just hopeless, but you could see why he would write it, because it's so, it's an expression of such sort of longing at the top of 74.
And this is a message to Regina, but it contradicts the previous message, namely, that I'm a knight of resignation, and I'm afraid now I could never know what to do with you if I got you back, because he says, and this is sort of advice to her, she too will keep her love young and sound.
She too will have overcome her agony, even though she does not, as the song says, lie at her Lord's side.
These two will then be united to each other in all eternity with such a strict, pre-established harmony.
Now, soft, so far, so good.
It's like Dante and Beatrice.
She understands that she's never going to go to bed with them anymore.
She understands that.
And she understands that they can still remain true to each other in their sense of the meaning of the relationship.
And then he blows it.
He says, so the two will be suited to each other in all eternity.
Fine.
With such a strict, tempoed, pre-established harmony that were, now comes the trouble, some moment to come, a moment in which they nevertheless not concern finitely, for in the finite world they would grow old.
Were such a moment to come, which allowed their love its expression in time, then they would be in a position to begin precisely where they would have begun had they been united from the beginning.
Now, what's the now complaint?
Yeah, don't forget me, keep desiring me.
Maybe if everything works out, we'll just get back together again.
And you can get to experience, it wouldn't be lower immediacy because that would be butterflies losing their essence.
No, no, no.
He says, if we've got this right relation to the ideal version of our love, then if we could ever get back together in the real world and in temporality, we could begin just where we left off, bodily and day by day, loving each other.
Yeah, well, it could be, but it also could be higher immediacy because the Knight of Faith also has the other person finite and temporal day to day.
What he's really trying to do is get a bit of the goodies of the Knight of Faith, which we haven't got to yet, who gets more and more involved and keeps the finite and temporal.
He wants to run away where it's safe, keeping in mind the ideal of the relationship and keeping open the possibility of getting back together.
Now that's okay, but it can't go along with him saying that he doesn't know how he would ever be able to take the princess back, and that he doesn't understand how Abraham could ever take Isaac back.
And I just told you why, because once you take them back, you're sort of starting on a step on an escalator, which will get you into the same trouble again.
You'll either just have them sort of like a ghost in your house because you can't really care about the finite temporal side of them, or you'll start really appreciating the fact that they're together.
You're together, finite and temporal, every day embodied together, and you're off on the big risk again.
Because if that either it's not important at all what the person is actually like and what the person is actually doing, because all you need is the ideal, and then you're okay, or it's very important what the other person is actually like at every moment, right here and now, at which point it's a risk because they might stop being here and now.
And he's trying to have it both ways.
The philosophical Kierkegaard, not I mean, not in the bad sense of philosophy.
I mean, the Kierkegaard who's thinking out this position of infinite resignation and seeing the advantages and the disadvantages, has a view that one of the big disadvantages when you give this person up and make their ideal crucial, you can't take them back.
And the Kierkegaard who's sitting in Berlin, wishing he was at home with Regina in Copenhagen, is making a mistake.
Yeah.
But you mean the second round you maybe could get a chance.
I think I see what you're saying, I think, but I think it won't work because that's this business of you don't get another chance in Kierkegaard.
If you make the movement of resignation, you actually deny, like Plato and Augustine, that the real person being there is significant, and that's what makes it safe.
And you don't get another chance.
You're saying, well, maybe the next time they get together, he can be a knight of faith.
He can really manage to stay in the finite and temporal.
But yeah, yeah, wait till next time.
I think you're thinking ahead of where we are.
Yeah.
Well, this is supposed to be a kind of theoretical book.
I mean, you shouldn't literally contradict himself in a bad sense, saying, let me just repeat it so you can see it, and then let's forget it.
It's just the only place in the whole book that I know that he makes a mistake.
He's saying the knight of resignation can't ever take the loved one back because they can't stand vulnerability, and the only way to get rid of vulnerability is to make the meaning of the relation all that matters.
He can't say that and say at the same time, and the great thing about the knight of resignation is if the girl ever comes back, he can begin with her right where he left off.
I mean, he wouldn't want her to come back, he just said.
And the right thing to say is the first thing, and he says it over and over, that you can't take the, when you make the knight of resignation, you leave the finite and temporal for good.
That's it.
Okay, I'm going to, next time we'll talk about the knight of faith who does something entirely different and much more amazing.