So there are sort of three parts to today's lecture.
One is we're finishing something which we haven't really finished, which is various ways of living if you're a free spirit or on the way to getting to be a free spirit.
And then there's a whole thing I have to talk about on nihilism before you see the movie.
And that's what you've got in the will to power handout.
And that's the next thing I have to talk about.
As long as I finish those two, that's all that I really have to talk about, because then you'll be ready to see Breathless on Thursday.
But if I finish them before time is up, I'm going to start discussing the various comparisons between the three people because we only have one concluding lecture to put everything together.
And I don't want to waste any time.
Okay, here we go.
So we've seen three ways of life, which if you're a Nietzschean, you would say healthy ways of life that people can have.
And certainly they're all possible.
And they aren't incompatible.
You can have them all.
So you have brief habits.
And we've done that.
I don't want to go back over it.
So we've done control and use the dark, conflicting impulses that you've got.
Use them in some productive way.
I'm sorry that we don't have it on the handout because I said last time, I just found it.
And now it was too late to put it on the handout, which is now on the website, by the way, the handout being the will to power.
But this nice quote from the will to power, which I read last time, sums up the way you should deal with your dark side according to Nietzsche.
I mean, remember that in Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard, there are ways to get the finite, temporal, embodied, sensuous side spiritualized and sublimated in some way.
That's not Nietzsche's view.
He says the highest thing is dominating the passions, not their weakening or extirpation.
The greater the dominating power of a will, the more freedom may the passions be allowed.
The passions are this dark side instinct, lower immediacy.
The great man is great owing to the free play and scope of his desires and to the yet greater power that he knows how to, the greater power that knows how to press these magnificent monsters into service.
The magnificent monsters are all these impulses, the dark side that everybody has, and that every philosophy has some story about how to deal with them.
Well, Nietzsche's is original, as everything is with Nietzsche.
Deal with them by keeping them under control, but don't try to get rid of them.
They're your way, one of your most important ways of being in constant impulsive involvement in the world.
Okay, we did that one.
Now comes another one, which we've already done, but it's this quote, which is actually in the movie.
So I wanted to put it in.
I think I wrote the page numbers wrong, but I can reconstruct it.
But I want to make sure that I really am wrong.
Yeah, I wrote it at Will to Power 228, but it's really gay science 228.
Yes, I read this bottom 228, but as I said then, and I'll say it again, the live dangerously comes up on a poster in the background in one of the scenes in the movie.
It's one of the evidences, if you need any evidence, that this really is a Nietzschean movie.
And it says at the bottom of 228, for believe me, the secret for harvesting from existence the greatest fruitfulness and the greatest enjoyment is to live dangerously.
Build your city on the slopes of Vesuvius.
Send your ships into uncharted seas.
Live in war with your peers and yourselves.
And then this line is really the relevant line.
Be robbers and conquerors if you can't be rulers and possessors.
That is better to be an outlaw than not to have your own power and your own activity.
Okay, that's so far.
That's all review.
Now, there's one more important way to lead a healthy life.
And we have, and it's an interesting one.
And it's a Gay Science 232.
And it's just another interesting Nietzschean idea that I don't know anybody else who has it, and it's worth looking into.
The middle of 232.
One thing is needful, to give style to one's character.
And by the way, this is also relevant to the movie.
You'll see.
To give style to one's character, a great and rare art is practiced by those who survey all the strengths and weaknesses of their nature and fit them into an artistic pattern until every one of them appears as art and reason and even weakness delights the eye.
Here a large mass of second nature has been added, there a piece of original nature has been removed, both through long practice and daily work.
Here the ugly could not be removed, that could not be removed, is concealed.
There it's been interpreted and made sublime.
Much that is vague and so forth, I think we can skip that.
In the end, when the work is finished, it becomes evident how the constraint of a single taste governed and formed everything, large and small.
Whether this taste was good or bad is less important than one might suppose if only it was a single state.
It will be the strong and dominant natures that enjoy their finest gaiety and such constraint under a law of their own.
So you impose, you don't get anybody imposing any order on you.
You impose this kind of order on yourself.
It's another version of just as you impose order on your impulses so that they don't just go off in all directions, but you don't squash them either.
The control story, here you impose order on your looks and on your tastes and on your ways of behaving until they all give you a single style.
And what's interesting about the style, you notice all these proposals about how to live are not traditional ones.
They're not about how to find meaning in your life, how to make your activity intelligible so you can explain it to yourself and justify it to other people.
They aren't stories about how to make what you do into universal principles.
They break with all of that.
And there isn't any content that's being proposed, any particular ethical principles.
Nature doesn't believe in any particular ethical principles.
And it isn't supposed to be giving your life meaning.
It gives your life something aesthetic, like a painting.
But it's something admirable that you have this style unified and as beautiful as you can make it.
And there are two different kinds of styles, at least.
They're generic styles, like the style of the 50s or the style of New York.
But what Nietzsche is interested in is obviously individual styles.
Again, it's not universal, it's not even shared.
Each person can give their life their own unique style.
Like there's a unique Bogart style and Bogie in all of his different movies.
That's what makes a movie star.
They don't really merge into the characters they perform, the old Hollywood movie stars.
They were always themselves in whatever movie they were in.
And if occasionally they got off that, it didn't work out very well.
So there is certainly a Bogart style.
And Nietzsche wants to substitute this notion of individual style for any notion of universal meaning.
Whereas acting, you might think you have to do what is intelligible and everybody understands and justifies the normal ethical, the normal mediation.
You don't have to mediate a style.
The more individual it is, the better.
And everybody can appreciate it.
They don't have to understand it.
That's not what you do with styles.
So, and you praise people for, and artists, for unique styles.
Artists are his highest form of human being.
Artists are more like free spirits in the sense that they create new worlds and they create themselves.
They create their style.
And that's all fine.
Now, then I got into a puzzle, which I'm surprised it took me so long to figure out.
But I used to think until last time after class that there was some kind of conflict between whether you make your life a work of art, which is a fixed style, which covers every aspect of your life and presumably remains the same through all your life, and you spend your time perspecting it.
How does that relate to the brief habits, which you're constantly changing?
Well, I thought that was a problem.
But then one of the people in the class explained to me, and once you see it, it seems perfectly obvious, and I don't know why I didn't see it.
You can have a whole series of brief habits, all in the style of whatever your style is.
There doesn't have to be any conflict.
The brief habits are the content, so to speak, and they change completely, whether it's cities or people or ideas or whatever.
But your way of taking them up and doing them for a while when they're a brief habit is always your way.
And I can't describe it anymore than to say it's your way.
I mean, Bogey does it his way, presumably, if he has brief habits.
And that's good.
Brief habits for Bogart would be like being in all sorts of different movies.
But he can be in different movies.
He could be a detective.
He could be a criminal.
He could be a lover.
He could be a soldier.
But it's always in his same style.
Okay, so that that's that's the story for...
Now that's the fourth one, the fourth way of having a healthy life.
Yeah, Beatrice.
And what about?
Oh, it is, it is, but it is and it isn't.
I mean, that's a good question.
Why isn't an unconditional commitment to your style?
Well, that's I sort of answered that without meaning to when I said that it has no content.
It isn't like justice for the black people or loving Beatrice.
It's just a style.
It can any content.
You can love Beatrice or you can love a guy instead if you're a guy.
Or you can just love your work and know other people.
You can do anything and have an unconditional commitment to it in the style because the style has not got any content.
You can't have an unconditional commitment to being being in having bogey style.
Bogey's got to have a commitment to something if he's going to be an I don't know if he's if he is a you know a Kierkegaardian individual but if he were a Kierkegaardian individual then we'd have to find out well who does he love or what cause is he devoted to or is he maybe acting could be his commitment but acting isn't his style okay yeah ah ah well that's an interesting question too where does style come from after the cataclysm well the answer is something like that what's nice about style is it's not affected by the cataclysm that's a terrific question because I would never have thought of saying this but that's what's interesting about it I mean it's not in the meaning business you did there is no why you have it and no way to to justify it.
And if all the the, see, there's I mean I should jump to the to the nihilism thing for a minute, because after the cataclysm, I'll get to the more details.
The why has no, me finds no answer.
He says, what does nihilism mean?
The highest values devaluate themselves, the aim is lacking, why finds no answer.
There is no question about the why of a style, neither where it came from, nor why this style is better than that style.
It's not in the ethical business.
So after the cataclysm, the free spirits will still be around.
They're having a good time, being cheerful, and cultivating their styles.
Does that help?
You look worried.
I thought that was a terrific answer.
Well, that's interesting, too.
That's a tough one.
I'll tell you how it comes up.
I mean, how much does your style depend upon other people?
Well, in a certain sense, not, because you can have any style that you can imagine no matter what everybody else thinks.
However, and your point is right, so you can't really imagine having the style of a, I don't know, a Native American buffalo hunter or something, whatever style they had, if the whole society is gone now and doesn't support that kind of style.
So your style is limited by what your current culture can support.
And yet, it's not limited in the way sort of meanings are.
It's not that some styles which you can understand thanks to your culture are bad.
Any style you can understand, you can have it.
I mean, understand is the wrong word.
No, never mind.
Admire.
Any style that you can admire, and that means any style offered up by your culture as a possibility which you can admire, you can have.
Now, I'll tell you why that's interesting and relevant.
How many have heard of Michel Foucault?
I don't know whether his name has, oh boy, he's gotten to, gotten to lots of people.
When he was here last, he filled Zellerbach, 2,000 people and had people beating on the door when he was lecturing.
Sure, he's a.
One of the last things he said was that you should make your life a work of art.
He was always a Nietzschean, but he just hadn't used that aspect of Nietzsche.
He was doing what Nietzsche called genealogy, we're not going to, which is tracing where our beliefs come from, which is not what we're talking about.
But when he said make your life a work of art, then a kind of discussion among us Foucault people, of which I was one at that point, wondered, well, to what extent does that mean that it's something you can just do on your own no matter what?
And to what extent does that mean that you're dependent on what is possible in your culture?
And I think the answer is you get an answer from aesthetics.
To what extent can a painter paint in any style?
Well, certainly any style that's already admirable, they can.
It'd be sort of boring if somebody started painting in Rembrandt style, if they could.
But the main thing is the artists are inventing new styles.
And that's so you can't say that they sort of have a spectrum of styles available from the culture, and they will pick one.
But you can't say that they can just invent any old style.
You can't invent the style of, say, Mozart if you haven't gone through Bach, and you can't get to Beethoven if you don't go through Mozart and Haydn and so forth.
There's certain ways that music or painting or any architecture, any art form develops that it only allows certain new things, although you can't have a list of the new things that allows until some artist comes along and creates some new thing.
So, okay, so it's who asked this question?
You, yeah.
So it's interesting.
It's both very independent of the culture, more than any sort of ethical principles are.
And it's not totally independent of the culture.
You're on something, you're on the right track.
Yeah, Beatrice.
Rendering the old form in content?
Yes, I think so.
I think that's absolutely right.
And I think that he wants that because he wants to get at something that is not universal and doesn't have to be understood.
It just has to be appreciated.
And style is appreciated, but it doesn't have a content.
Yeah, I think it's supposed to be split.
Because I think you could, I don't know.
I mean, you can't, it's a puzzle, really, if you start thinking about it.
Can you just do any old thing in any old style?
I wouldn't think so.
So they have some kind of tenuous relation.
You can't, what, let's think about it.
Let's we've got bogey style as our example.
Can you can bogey play a priest in a movie?
That does seem like your gears get split if you try to picture that.
That just doesn't seem to work.
So there is some kind of relation to what sort of thing you can, what sort of content you can do with that style.
I don't think you can play a serial killer either.
I mean, there are certain things, certain contents that just don't go with certain styles.
That's all interesting.
I don't know what else to say about it.
It's a typical Nietzsche thing.
It raises a whole lot of questions that you could think about.
Yeah.
The Nietzsche wouldn't want that.
I think he wants to exclude certain content.
Well, yeah, he will include, well, style ought to include, exclude certain things.
Yeah.
Well, yes, if you it excludes living so as to be like everybody else, trying to be respectable, trying to be attractive, having the official smile of the people in the United States now, and which you which everybody puts on when anybody takes a picture of them.
That is certainly not the kind of style he would admire.
So I guess maybe you have to add at least this.
It has to be your unique style.
You can't just be imitating.
You can do an interesting individual variation, which is your own unique style and some style, and artists do that.
By the way, one more thing.
Does Bogey make a gesture like this in his movies?
I've been told he does.
I don't remember ever seeing that.
You've got to realize when you see this movie that this is a bogey gesture.
And when you see it, try to figure out if you've seen him do that in any movie.
I don't remember.
Where were we?
Yeah, oh, you're full of good questions.
Yeah.
Sometimes they're like, I have to.
Well, maybe.
I don't know.
I think having one unified style sort of precludes having others.
If you read the thing and you put pieces of yourself, get rid of some and cover up others and bring out others and work at transcribing.
I suppose you've got a weird way of smiling.
You can work at getting rid of it.
But once you've done all that work, do you likely get another style in which you change completely all the things that you're trying to change?
You make a whole different job of constructing yourself.
You're throwing out the old one.
It looks like you got one for life, not because styles have to be for life, like unconditional commitments.
It's just that if you put a lot of work into one, it's unlikely you're going to throw it away and put a lot of work into another, though you could.
Again, all these are good questions.
It would have been a good paper topic, but not an exam paper topic.
So we'll have to save it for some other course.
Anything else?
Yeah, Beatrice, this is really full of questions today.
What?
No, he wants it to be unified.
Well, it is mono something, but it's not the wrong, I mean, it's a mono that's all right.
Just like an unconditional commitment, sort of.
Well, not quite.
Well, it's not a brief habit either.
See, he's really found something interesting.
It's not a brief habit because as we just said, it's takes too much work in it to be throwing it out every once in a while and getting bored with it.
You should be constantly improving it.
So it's not a brief habit.
It's not an unconditional commitment.
It's not that you eternally have to play this style.
If you really want to scrap it all and start again and have your face made over and your voice change your voice, you can do it.
People do it.
People change their sex and become totally different with different styles.
That's a lot of work.
So, but that it should be unified.
You know, that sounds like an old virtue.
And I think, I don't know what to say, except that Nietzsche admits the positive value of unity provided it's imposed in a controlled way by the will on everything about you.
That's what happened with the controlling all his impulses controlled in one unified self that's always just about to come apart, but always some part of it else or other gets control and keeps it from falling apart.
So his picture is a unified style in which all the tendencies that you notice, as you fix one of them and you find some other tendency in you you want to fix, then get into that style.
This movement toward a unity is not a kind of resting place.
It's not peace.
It's not harmony.
It's not having finally arrived at a stable view.
But it should sort of gain control or struggle to gain control of every aspect of how you talk and how you walk and how you write and how you know how you sleep.
I don't know if that can come under style.
Now I doubt it.
But anyway, okay, you're looking unhappy, Carl.
About what I'm saying?
Okay.
Anything else?
Okay, well then we're going to change the subject altogether.
I had no idea it was such an interesting subject.
We're going to go to the will to power piece, which is in front of you because it's about nihilism yeah what extra are they still going around as have we used them all up anybody got an extra one hmm we used them all up are there are there people who don't have it that want it oh dear I didn't make enough I then can you sort of share it with somebody who's near you if you've got one and because it is important to have it in front of you okay now yeah yes yes it's not just for today that's why you won't you can you can give it away because it's it's posted online it's if you go where did I put this URL just now oh yeah it's on the it's on the it's on the paper at the end of the paper topics is the URL where this is posted and I know it's there because I just put it there so so don't worry about giving it away to somebody who needs one and sharing it with somebody because they are you can print one you get when you get home now the from now on we're talking about nihilism because nihilism is certainly what's going on in breathless and we've got to understand what nihilism is by the way since it's sort of on my mind I'll just tell you something that's going to happen quite a little while from now have you got do you realize this business of on the same page that everybody's going to see ang Li's the ice storm.
Has that been announced yet?
You know, there's always something that everybody is supposed to, every freshman, anyways.
But how many freshmen here?
Well, you will soon hear and soon get informed about this.
Ang Li is going to actually talk.
How many seen the ice storm?
It's probably a little before your time.
It's a terrific movie.
It's going to be shown all around, and Ang Lui is going to be here to discuss it.
And I just tell you, because you won't be in front of me for the time it happens, it's a nihilism movie.
It fits right in with this.
And the whole subject of the movie is that.
Nobody knows what to do or why.
Okay.
And keep your eyes open for it.
Do take it in.
It's a really good movie.
Now, here we go.
We start with nihilism by explaining, of course, but I haven't said it in so many words.
Nihilism is a problem for our culture.
The people in Bali don't have to worry about it.
And nor the Homeric Greeks, nor even the Athenian Greeks.
But why is it a problem for our culture and only for our culture?
I mean, it could be another one, but it seems to be only ours.
And that's because, remember, because our culture has become meaning addicts, as I called it.
This is so important for Nietzsche.
And again, when I read it before, I couldn't tell whether he thinks our culture or all cultures, but I think he thinks our culture, though he doesn't say it.
But here we are at the bottom of 75.
Gradually, man, I want to say Western man, and I bet he does too, has become a fantastic animal that has to fulfill one more condition of existence than any other animal.
Western man has to believe, to know from time to time, why he exists.
His race cannot flourish.
Well, maybe he means all human beings.
I can't believe it, though, because why would it happen sort of simultaneously in the Bushman in New Guinea and to the polytheists in Japan?
I'm going to do it my way.
Anyway, he has to understand why his race, that is, us in the West, cannot flourish without a periodic thrust in life, or trust in life, without faith in reason to live.
Boy, I really find this amazing.
Again and again, the human race will decree from time to time there is a thing in which it is absolutely henceforth forbidden to laugh.
And that's the reason they've all become meaning.
Well, that's a funny, that's a thing I'm very surprised at because Nietzsche has such a sense of history and how the human animal has no nature and gets all sorts of natures depending on where you happen to grow up and in what culture.
Why should he believe that the human race, all of them, people, somehow innate in them, is that they have a need for meaning when he knows that they don't really have a need for meaning because they can become free spirits.
Or another way to put it, he doesn't believe it's sort of genetic determination that they have a need for meaning.
How come they all have a need for meaning?
Let me think about it here.
And remember the business about people, human beings don't have any fixed horizons like animals.
It makes us like an animal.
And it says, here's this race of animals, you can call human beings, which have to have meaning in order to exist.
And then you wouldn't understand how they gradually became that kind of animal.
That would seem to happen differently at different times in different cultures.
I give up.
I've never noticed it.
Now that I've noticed it, I don't know how to deal with it.
You look like you might have a view about how to deal with it.
Do you?
Well, you need what test it?
Ah, oh, you take one.
Yeah, we need, you need it.
Oh, but that's not the text.
I see, no, no, that's not the text I was reading, though.
I'm reading the gay science right now.
I'm reading Gay Science 75.
I'm setting up the text of the will to power.
Anyway, the will, I mean, all I can say is we're running into lots of interesting problems.
Nietzsche is full of interesting problems.
I don't know what he's doing there, but I know that I could fix it.
All I have to do is say the Western X, and you've got it.
I don't even think for him the Homeric Greeks have yet become believers that they have to have meaning.
They've got to have wonder.
They've got to have the sacred.
They've got to have something at which you can't laugh.
But to call it meaning is to make it in a, is to distinguish it from wonder.
That seems to me just the wrong way to go.
Yeah.
I wonder if you're trying to distinguish between meaning and purpose.
Purpose.
Well, I'm not distinguishing between meaning and purpose.
I see, let's think about that.
Man, all human beings have to have a sense of purpose.
They have to have.
You think that's what he's talking about?
He wants to know why he exists.
His race cannot flourish without a periodic trust in life, without faith, in reason in life.
Let me think about it.
Well, for one thing, we know that the free spirit doesn't need that.
So it can't be something that human beings just have.
So how come all over, all human beings develop a sense that they have to know why they exist?
I don't know if the Bali people know why they exist.
They've got other things to worry about, that the gods are coming all the time.
Every day is a religious holiday.
It's all wonderful, and you have to keep all the ritual and all the flowers.
They don't have time to worry about why they exist.
It just isn't a sensible question, I think.
So I'm still puzzled.
Yeah.
All these things have all tendencies that impose their Nietzsche thinking everybody imposes their interpretation.
It seems to me somehow that should include wonder.
I mean, these terms all need to be defined more clearly than I'm defining them.
Everybody interpretational.
See, they can think of it as full of gods, for instance.
And they can think of themselves as, well, maybe their purpose is then worshiping those gods.
Then that could be the meaning in their life.
I'm just thinking out loud.
So they all have the meaning that they should be interpreted for sort of satisfying their gods.
Of course, do they all have gods?
Do those gods all demand satisfaction?
I don't know.
Again, I'm going to do my simplified version of it, but I'm glad you're all raising.
This is what it is to do philosophy and read hard books like Nietzsche, raising the right kind of interesting questions.
A sub-truth, which I'm going to stick to, is that in the West, we have a strong demand to understand sort of what the universe is for, what we're here for, and we somehow got it at some point in our history.
And I don't know if Nietzsche thinks the Homeric Greeks already had it.
I doubt it.
I can't believe that he thinks that they have become the kind of fantastic animal that he doesn't like, because he thinks they're terrific.
So I'm confused.
But I'm going to stick to my story.
We in the West, thanks to the Athenian Greeks, thanks to the Hebrews, who told us exactly what it all meant and where we fitted it and what we were supposed to do, have become meaning addicts, and that's enough to get us into nihilism.
And that's another way to put the problem.
If everybody's a meaning addict, why isn't everybody a nihilist?
And he's clear that nihilism is a modern, recent thing, and only in the West.
So I'm lost.
But as I say, I'm not really lost because I've got my minimal interpretation.
Just add in the West that it all makes sense.
At some point in the history of the West, after the Homeric Greeks, and by the time of Plato, everybody had been given an answer to why we're here and what we're supposed to do, and an answer that is based on God and some sort of reason and is true for everybody and gives your life meaning and purpose.
And that's all he needs to make the point about nihilism.
Okay?
It's this passage which I don't like.
I mean, I don't know where else he says anything like this.
Hey, well, you guys keep your interested in more Nietzsche.
If you come across passages in which he tells us more about whether he thinks all human beings are fantastic animals who can't get along without meaning, or whether he tells us more about why he thinks it comes around in our culture now and only in our culture.
See, in our culture, God is dead.
And that seems to be a very, very peculiar feature of our culture.
Where we once, see, and in our culture, I'm getting more and more convinced that I can't agree with Nietzsche on page 75.
We know that in our culture, everything has been built into this God, and everything has been explained in terms of it.
That's why it's a cataclysm.
If that God comes down, everything comes down.
So, and we're the only culture who's got that.
We're the only culture who, he says, that it's the greatest kind of catastrophe and the greatest overcoming that ever happened in history.
That means we're the only culture who are so committed to meaning that we find meaning, we demand meaning and purpose in everything and build it all into this religious structure, such that if that religious structure becomes unbelievable, everything collapses and we get nihilism.
But it's clear that that only happens, it's never happened, he says, never happened in any other culture.
So, okay, so I'm sticking to my line.
Anyone want to quarrel with it?
Let's not.
Okay, quarrel with it.
Jason, what?
Nihilism is not the highest value.
The highest values devaluate themselves.
I mean, wouldn't that apply to everyone?
Yes, that's true, but it's but there's more to nihilism than that.
If that was all, it was nihilism, but then I just answered what you just said before you said it.
But not only do the highest values devaluate themselves, but in nihilism, everything is built into those highest values.
So when they devaluate themselves, everything devaluates themselves.
Then you've got real nihilism.
I mean, maybe there's kind of partial nihilism where some god or other gets killed off or discredited, but not everything.
Now I'm going to read this because this is very important to us.
And we've got to get it read before you see the movie.
So I'm going to go to where I am keeping track of what I'm talking about.
So we get a definition of nihilism on the second page.
I'm going to start with that and then sort of back up and fill it in.
I read it already.
It's so straight on.
The number two, right, at the top, spring 87.
So what does nihilism mean?
That the highest values devaluate themselves.
The aim is lacking.
Why finds no response?
So you'd expect in a nihilistic culture, there'd be no answer to why people love people, betray people, help people, and so forth and so forth.
Okay, and then from there, we're going to go to the front page.
And I've got to read a whole lot because he lays out more clearly than any place else exactly all that's involved in nihilism.
And there's sort of four components.
So, first, the nihilism is a psychological state which has to be reached first.
Now, where that's number one component.
When we sought a meaning in all events, you see, sought a meaning in all events.
That's why everything collapses.
That is a meaning that is not there.
So, the seeker eventually becomes discouraged.
Nihilism is the recognition of the long waste of strength, the in vain, the insecurity to recover and regain composure, composed here.
Being ashamed in front of oneself as one was deceived oneself for too long.
See, this is all very Western.
This does not happen in Japan or Bali.
This meaning could have been the fulfillment of some highest ethical canon in all events, the moral world, order.
Now he's listing the meaning, which is helpful.
Those of you who had some other philosophy courses will recognize some of them.
There could be fulfillment, that's Greek, that's Aristotle, that is the meaning to get as much fulfillment out of life as possible.
It could be the moral order, that's Kant, that you obey the moral law, or the growth of love and harmony in the intercourse of beings, that could be Dostoevsky, or the gradual approximation of a state of universal happiness.
That's uh utilitarian.
That's the wo the one where he says only the English love happiness 'cause they invented the utilitarianism that something is good if it if it gives you the greatest happiness to the greatest number of people.
Or it could be the development towards a state of universal annihilation.
That is really amazing.
I took me a while, I was sort of stunned to think what would that be?
Well, it would be one like one of these suicide cults, like the people in Jonestown, which is a little before your time now, but you've probably heard of it, where they somehow got themselves into the idea that they should all commit suicide and put poison in their Kool-Aid.
And I don't know how many hundred people, does anybody know, who died in John?
Seven hundred, that's and that seems to be their the meaning in their world was to get out of this world as quickly as possible when they had a suicide cult.
Any and any goal at least constitutes some meaning.
What all these notions have in common is that something is to be achieved through the process.
And now one realizes that becoming aims at nothing and achieves nothing.
Okay, that's the first stage.
Yeah.
Universal annihilation.
A philosopher.
I doubt it.
I don't know.
I mean in a way Schopenhauer w would wanted everybody to be able to commit suicide.
I don't really he didn't exactly propose they do it, but I don't know why they didn't why they don't do it.
I guess it's because the will to life is strong, so strong in them that they can't do it.
But if they could, they it probably Schopenhauer.
And that would be good for Nietzsche because he would have Schopenhauer sort of looking over his shoulder.
That was his guru until he it turned Nietzsche is so much into the will to life and the importance of life and the way life is constantly outgrowing and expanding and joyful because Schopenhauer was so much his teacher, in effect, was so much against life when he said it was all misery and suffering, and the quicker you could get out of it, the better.
And he lo he liked the Buddhist Schopenhauer.
Nietzsche turned against the Buddhists when he went to this life-involvement business.
Okay, number two.
Nihilism as a psychological state is reached secondly when one has posited a totality, a systematization, indeed, any organization in which all events and underneath all events, organization in all events and underneath all events, and a soul that longs to admire and revere has wallowed in the idea of some supreme form of domination and administration.
That's the supreme being.
I mean, that's when you get a religion in which there is one supreme being administering and creating and overseeing everything.
And again, that seems so ununiversal.
I mean, that's very Western, one supreme being.
That's only the Judeo-Christian-Muslim bunch there.
Where else do you get supreme beings?
Not in Buddhism, not in polytheism, nowhere else.
So it looks like it's us.
So let's go into three.
Nihilism, psychological state, the third and last form.
Given these two insights, that becoming has no goal and that underneath all, all becoming, there is no grand unity in which an individual could immerse himself completely as in an element of supreme value, an escape remains to pass sentence on this whole world of becoming as a deception and invent a world beyond it, a true world.
As soon as man finds out how that world is fabricated, the true world, from his own psychological needs and how he has absolutely no right to it, the last form of nihilism comes into being.
It includes disbelief in any metaphysical world and forbids itself any belief in the true world.
The true world would be Plato, the good, or whatever philosopher you happen to like who has his view of what the world is.
That's the most highly worked out form of avoiding nihilism.
But then what happens at the bottom?
What has happened at bottom?
Question mark.
The feeling of valuelessness was reached with the realization that the overall character of existence may not be interpreted by means of the concept of aim, the concept of unity, or the concept of truth.
Existence has no goal or end.
Any comprehensive unity in the plurality of events is lacking.
The character of existence is not true.
It's false.
One simply lacks any reason for convincing oneself that there is a true world.
Briefly, the categories of aim and unity and being, which we use to project some value into the world, we pull out again, and the world looks valueless.
That's so clear.
He thinks that we have projected all this meaning because we, Western fanatical, fantastical animals, have gotten to expect so much meaning and projected so much meaning that if we then realize, because we're always trying to be honest with ourselves, we realize that we just projected all that because we really needed all that, we take it out, and then everything collapses.
So now I'm keeping track of where I am.
Let's see.
So then you get the extremist kind of nihilism, radical nihilism.
That's right after what does nihilism mean unto?
Radical nihilism is the conviction of an absolute untenability of existence when it comes to the highest values one recognizes, plus the realization that we lack the least right to posit beyond or an in itself of things that might be divine or morality incarnate.
I mean, that is, any kind of supreme being.
This realization is a consequence of the cultivation of truthfulness.
You see, that's what I said when I said you try to be honest about your desires and honest about the world.
The church, I just remind you, the church with its sort of highly sophisticated notion of confession has gotten very critical and skeptical about desires and knows that you can't mistake your desires for what's really there.
Physics, I didn't do the story about physics, but physics gets very good at telling us what's really there.
And physics tells us, according to Nietzsche, what's really there is just a chaos with no direction that has anything to do with us.
And the combination, because we really want the truth, leads us to see that we can't believe in any religion anymore, any meaning anymore, any goal, any purpose, any aim.
That's radical nihilism.
And then what?
Well, that flips over into cheerfulness.
Just as remember, right after the death of God, the name of the next section is the meaning of our cheerfulness.
Well, the cheerfulness is here in number 14, a little below the middle.
Values and their changes are related, and why are we cheerful?
Well, because we can increase our power.
Values and their changes are related to increases in power of those positing the values.
Positing means we make up the value.
We can decide that what's valuable is, let's say, saving the earth and the environment.
Now, there's nothing in the universe that says they need to save the earth, or the universe doesn't care a bit about the earth, and there's nobody around to care about the earth, and the earth doesn't seem to be going in the direction of saving itself and so forth.
But we can make it a value, and we can dedicate ourselves to reversing global warming and so forth.
And when we do, that's good.
That increases our power.
I mean, we have the power to set goals and purposes and to pursue them, as long as we understand that they're ours and not that they're not by to ourselves, that the goals and purposes are somehow built into us or into reality.
So that's the positive cheerful nihilism.
So he's gone now.
The measure of unbelief, of permitted freedom of the spirit, as an expression of the increase in power.
So the greatest overcoming is when the whole world collapses.
And the greatest convalescence is when the free spirit comes along and deals with this whole collapse by just freely choosing what to care as purpose and then doing it.
Now, of course, that might be an impossible idea.
I think it is an impossible idea.
I don't see how anything that you just sort of arbitrarily choose is going to have any authority and power to motivate you.
And I think Nietzsche would just say that that shows about me that I'm sick and not a free spirit.
If I were a free spirit, I'd understand that I can posit anything I please, that it'll make me stronger, and what more would anybody want than to sort of make up values and then pursue them?
So I'm back now and we're still reading under number 14.
Nihilism, an ideal of the highest degree of powerfulness of the spirit, the over-richest life, partly destructive, partly ironic.
So that's the free spirit again.
The free spirit has this power.
The free spirit is sort of over-rich, that is, so overflowing in liveliness and in brief habits, in making life a work of art, in living dangerously, all of that.
That's this over-rich life, and it's partly destructive.
Why is it destructive?
Well, it's destroying all the complacency of the people in the marketplace who haven't heard that God is dead.
Then that's all got to be destroyed.
And that's okay with Nietzsche.
And it's partly ironic.
That's because it can laugh at anything sacred.
Remember that every culture has declared that there's something, some God, some moral principle, some ethical norm, some purpose which is sacred and which you can't laugh at.
And the free spirit can make fun of and laugh at anything, and that's the ironic side of it.
Okay, and now we're just about ready to, as far as the movie is concerned, just put in the last, the bottom of page two.
I'm not going to tell you why it's important.
I'm just going to give you a clue that it's very important.
So nihilism is ambiguous.
First, I'm going to start with B.
Nihilism has decline, recession of the power of the spirit.
That's what he calls.
Then, but there's also, A, nihilism is a sign of increased power of the spirit, active nihilism.
That's free spirits.
So nihilism is totally ambiguous, as he says.
It isn't necessarily a bad thing.
In fact, it's a very, very good thing.
It's what the free spirits appreciate, what makes them cheerful, what gives them plenty to do, positing values all over the place, and going out on always inventing new worlds, new eyes, new suns, new whatever.
We try to, as you read it, keep a list of how many new things Nietzsche thinks people can invent.
That's nihilism, too.
But that's active nihilism.
That says we don't have, there's no why, no purpose outside of us, but we will give ourselves whys and purposes to act on.
And then we'll do them for a while, like brief habits, and then we can drop them and give ourselves some other purpose and act on them.
What more could you want?
That makes you very powerful.
That makes you feel very alive.
That if you're doing it well, it'll fill you with excitement and wonder.
And that's the new health that comes after the collapse.
Okay, that's all you need to know to appreciate Breathless and understand it, as nobody, as far as I know, has understood it.
I don't know why.
It seems to me as clear as could possibly be what's going on in there.
But you'll have to think about it for yourself, and we'll see it Thursday and talk about it on the following Tuesday.
And you should be sure and be here at 3:35 to see the beginning.
Though if you don't, if you aren't, don't feel bad.
Nothing important happens.
It's all beautifully done and extremely fun.
But nothing important happens in the first 10 or 15 minutes.
And then from then on, everything is dictated.
You're looking puzzled.
You don't think that's true?
You don't think something important happens?
Only.
I see.
Oh, a lot of important things about how movies are made happen.
It's a totally new world movies.
No?
I don't think so.
We're going to have lots of debates about the next lecture.
I can hear that.
But, oh, how many know Breathless?
I've seen it very recently.
How far into the movie, how many minutes into the movie, does he visit his old girlfriend?
Try to get money for her.
Ten minutes, maybe?
Something like that.
Anyway, when you get there, don't feel bad.
You haven't missed anything.
You need to understand the plot.
And there is a plot.
I mean, whether Beatrice is right that it's somehow not important and taken back, or whether I'm right and think that this plot is exactly the right plot, and there is a lot to argue about.
Okay, now I'm not going to send you all home.
That would be a bad idea, given that we've got only, where's my notebook?
I mean, I don't want to be wrong about this, or I will send you all, but I'm pretty sure.
Okay, we're going to show Breathless Thursday.
We're going to have a discussion of Breathless on Tuesday, and we're going to wrap up our comparison to these three people.
I'm going to tell you what existentialism is because everybody tells me I should tell them what existentialism is.
I don't think that's very important, but if you want to know, you come and I'll try to tell you.
But in the meantime, I'm going to switch now to one of the ways that Nietzsche and Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard all have a certain view in common, a very important view, namely that they all make a mistake that Nietzsche calls reversing causality.
I'm sorry, yeah, that was totally wrong.
They all, that is Kierkegaard, Dostoevsky, and Nietzsche, don't make Lady, but everybody else does.
So we have to understand what that, why Nietzsche is saying that, and how it shows up in Kierkegaard and in Dostoevsky.
So one of the, I'm not going to hit it head on.
The first thing he talks about is that, and they all would agree, is that religion isn't a matter of beliefs, but it's a way of acting.
You can see that.
I mean, it's all over the place.
I mean, it isn't important whether Alyasha believes that there's a connection.
You could believe it and not do anything about it.
Or you could be constantly doing a thing, responding to this connectedness without noticing or reflecting on the fact that it's happening to you.
As far as I know, Alyasha doesn't even have any beliefs.
Do we know anything that Alyasha believes?
I guess.
No, I mean, I was going to say he believes that he performed a miracle with Grushenka, but he didn't say that.
Rakitin said he performed a miracle.
I mean, he feels he did.
It's just not something he has to think about and believe.
And if you believe that everything's connected to everything, but you don't do anything about it, that won't do either.
I'm just remembering something very, very funny.
It won't seem so funny to you because you won't be able to see it.
I was studying in Lou Vince, studying Husserl, and Husserl papers are all in the archives of the Franciscan monks who saved the Husserl notes from the Nazis.
And the head of the Franciscan monks was Father von Breda, a very nice, fun-loving monk who was, and they were all in their brown cowls and their sandals and their rope belts and everything.
And the Husserl archives was on the top floor.
And one day some poor dog wandered into the Husserl archives.
And Father van Breda kicked the dog down the stairs.
He says, that's a Franciscan who may well believe that you should love all the birds and the animals the way Franciscans do.
They're like Markle followers, but he certainly didn't practice it.
And then I noticed that, and this is the funniest part of all, when he would go in the courtyard, all the birds would fly in the other direction.
I mean, he says, this is just, this is exactly what you, but he probably believed all this, but he just didn't have anything to do with how he behaved.
Okay.
What?
He was preaching.
He was.
Why'd you say that?
Oh, yeah, but he preached what nice things, I suppose.
I think he was teaching the dog how to behave better, not to go around and get in the Husserl archives.
Okay, so here I'm going back to where I was.
I suddenly transport myself into the happy days with Father Van Breda.
Let's see now.
Okay, so religion is not a matter of belief on 163 of the Antichrist.
He's saying.
Okay, so, and let me see where I am.
Oh, I'm trying to say too many things at once.
So, where do I see that it's a spontaneous religion?
Is not a matter of beliefs?
Oh, I see.
About 15 lines down on 163: genuine primitive Christianity will be possible at all times.
Not a belief, but a doing.
Well, you remember, Kierkegaard is trying to get back into what he thought the early Christians were before they got philosophy mixed into them.
Dostoevsky with Markle is trying to get back to what he thinks the early Christians were.
And they're not trying to understand what the early Christians believe, but the way, particularly Dostoevsky with Markle, but the way they acted.
And they act spontaneously, they do the right thing.
So, reading a little further, not a belief, but a doing, above all, a not doing of many things, of being a different being.
States of consciousness, beliefs of any kind, holding something to be true, for example, are a matter of complete indifference and of the fifth rank compared with the value of the instincts.
To speak more strictly, the whole concept of spiritual causality is false.
That means, remember, instincts for him means doing something just spontaneously.
It means a good kind of lower immediacy.
And there's just no place in this for doing things on reflection because you decided that was the right thing for a Christian to do.
And it means that you just spontaneously help your neighbor when your neighbor needs you.
That's what it's about.
You don't have to believe anything to do that.
You don't have to be conscious that that's what you ought to be doing or anything like that.
You just naturally do it.
And that's how Nietzsche thinks the early Christian community was.
But of course, it didn't last very long.
Nietzsche thinks it was over before it got started.
And I think probably Kierkegaard and particularly Dostoevsky think it lasted a while, but they all agreed with that.
And now what's the reverse causality?
Well, the reverse causality is the thought that several things.
Here's the simplest one: that somehow believing something to be true can affect your sort of spiritual situation.
By that I mean believing something like there is a Creator God, Christ died for our sins, God loves us, that if you believe that, you will be reborn, able to love, etc., etc.
You're certainly mistaken.
It isn't your beliefs don't cause you to feel this love and this rebirth, like Dimitri feels and so forth.
It's on the contrary, your experience of the love and your experience of this rebirth and coming out positive transformation of suffering and all that.
That's what causes you to have beliefs, if you happen to have any beliefs at all, but it doesn't matter whether you have any beliefs or not.
They are completely irrelevant.
Okay, that's, but there's a much more interesting story than that.
And it's more, you can see it better in Dostoevsky than you can see it in Kierkegaard.
So let's look at Dostoevsky.
In a way, Dostoevsky, oh, I didn't read you the reverse causality quote, which I better read you just because I didn't make it up on page 64.
I don't see it on 64.
It must be very nearby.
Well, it says in so many words that it's a mistake of reverse psychology.
And it's in italics, reverse causality.
I misspoke.
Whoa.
Well, maybe it's an ear in 64.
I just, oh, no.
Just let me look for a minute in the vicinity.
Keep your eye open.
We're very near where I am.
I swear there's in the reverse.
This reverses the causality.
Well, maybe I'm getting this line.
It's me that says reverses the causality, but the line is at the top of 64.
It has to be this.
Morality and religion fall entirely under the psychology of error.
In every single case, cause is mistaken for effect.
That's enough.
That is the reversing causality.
That's more important than believing something saving your soul.
Because now it's a kind of philosophical thesis.
The thesis is that cause is mistaken for effect.
Now, think of it in terms of the big experience of love in the middle of the brothers' karamatsa.
Now, cause is mistaken for effect is the real cause that you are connected to everything is your experience of being connected to everything.
That's the ground level, so to speak, experience.
And you can then, that you can take as an effect.
You can say, because God created all these worlds as interconnected, you feel this experience of interconnection.
That's the mistake.
What Dostoevsky thinks and what Nietzsche thinks is, you feel the experience of interconnection.
That's just basic.
And it doesn't help and it doesn't add anything, and it really just confuses things to bring in God as having created this connectedness of everything.
Dostoevsky never says that.
Never says that Alyasha had any beliefs about the connectedness of everything at all.
That's the first point we were making.
But secondly, Dostoevsky doesn't say from his own point of view, aha, now we know what God is.
God is the connectedness of everything.
He's not the cause of the connected.
He didn't produce the connectedness.
Just as Kierkegaard, now we can see in Kierkegaard, says, God is that all things are possible.
That doesn't make a God, which then makes all things possible.
God is that all things are possible.
And what's interesting is this is a very, very important move.
Nietzsche is giving it a funny name, and you have to hardly, I can hardly get it myself when I look at the top of 64.
But when you say the cause is taken as effect, you're really getting rid of the making an object and cause that you don't need behind the religious phenomena which we're trying to describe.
So God doesn't cause the soul that's isolated to be in hell.
Being isolated just is being in hell, and so forth and so forth.
In other words, what Nietzsche calls getting the order of cause and effect wrong is what Dostoevsky is trying to correct by existentializing.
Because his existentializing always takes away any sort of supreme being doing anything that you don't need and focuses on the experience and what people do when they have that experience, which is what you do need.
So that's why this whole thing is important to see how these three people all share some very deep idea.
They use very fancy terminology, which you don't have to know, but it might come in handy at cocktail parties or something.
They are all against onto theology.
That's Heidegger jargon.
Onto theology is just that there's a supreme being behind it all.
The onto is being, and the theology is the science of God as the supreme being.
That's what has to be crossed out.
That's what came in from Plato and from metaphysics and partly and partly from the Old Testament.
But the part that the really clear version of it is coming out of the Greeks.
And they are naming this is just, let me give you one more example.
Then I'll let you say something.
I mean, what's on my mind right now is what isn't something that they talk about very much, but I'm writing about it.
But it's interesting.
People who think they have a calling.
They have a calling, meaning that they sense when they're doing what they need to be doing and that they must be doing, and they sense when they're deviating from it.
So Martin Luther King knew he had a calling.
Luther, who's behind all this calling talk more than anybody, knew that he had to stand up against the Catholic Church, which was a pretty amazing thing to do since the Catholic Church controlled everything and all intelligibility at the time that Luther was around.
And the interesting thing is, what these guys are saying is you can have a calling without a caller.
That is, you can have a sense of what you have to do.
You can have a sense when you're doing it and feeling that you're on the beam.
You can have a sense when you're failing to do it and you're off the beam.
But you don't need, so to speak, a beamer, a light shine, something that shines this beam on you.
You just need that experience.
And so that's, to me, right now, that's the most interesting one because in a recent book, Charles Taylor, who's a religious Catholic and a very good philosopher, goes from having a calling to getting his belief in a supreme being that's doing the calling.
Well, these three people would certainly want to say, block that move.
You don't need it.
Now, you want to say something?
What?
Just want to kind of feed back into the last question about chaos?
What Nietzsche would say about chaos?
Is that what you're asking?
Is God, I mean, for Nietzsche.
Yeah.
Well, I think you're asking an interesting question.
So, yeah, God is, for Kierkegaard.
God is that all things are possible, not an object, not onto theology.
And for Dostoevsky, God is that all these worlds are connected, the worlds of love.
Now, for Nietzsche, what do you want to say?
That it's all chaos.
That's right.
But of course, for Nietzsche, he's not sort of opposing any wrong interpretation as far as whether anything created the chaos.
And he's not saying it's all chaos, but we don't need a supreme being to create the chaos, because nobody ever bothered to think that there was a supreme being.
But you're right in the sense that the bottom line for Nietzsche that does the same job as God is interconnectedness, or God is that all things are possible, is something like the universe is chaos, and there is no purpose, no why, and so forth.
There's a long list I didn't assign, I don't think, where he says the universe is not an organism, it's not a machine, it's not, I forget, it goes on and on about all the things the universe isn't, and then he just says it's chaos.
Okay, so but he's not, but he didn't, it isn't as if he's correcting somebody who got the causality wrong.
He's just, you see what I mean?
Okay, how are we doing?
Well, we've got some time.
And did I see any other hand?
Yeah, Beatrice.
First, you said you have a calling?
Is the situation of it?
Yeah, well, I mean, the way I try to describe it, when I talk to people who claim to have callings, which is what I was doing lately, it's, and Charles Taylor being one of them, that they have a sense that they're feeling that they are in a kind of bliss.
Their life is as full as it can be.
And I think Nietzsche won't like that, because I think they might think their life is as meaningful as it can be.
But whatever it is, they feel that they're doing something right, and that it's absolutely necessary for them to do that, no matter what havoc it might make, as it did in the case of Luther.
And they have another sense that even though they think they're doing something right, they're not doing something right, and they better shape up.
And prophets, all prophets have that, and Martin Luther King must have had it.
But you can be a much lesser version of it.
Any creative person, anybody who's sort of opening up new worlds will have that sense when they're doing it right and when they're doing what they have to do, being who they are.
So Kierkegaard's got it.
When you've got an unconditional commitment, you don't get this unconditional commitment by, see if this works.
Well, he doesn't spell it out.
You feel it, remember, twining about every ligament of your consciousness, and you feel that you can't tear it out or you'll lose yourself.
That's how it is in Kierkegaard.
But it's the same thing.
It's an experience of something that's binding you.
And you're letting yourself be bound.
And that's going to become who you are.
It is becoming who you are.
That's what it is to have a calling.
But we shouldn't be talking about callings.
We should be stopping.
Let me just be sure where I am, and we will.
Okay, you can go.
I have to figure out where I am.