Because I had a discussion with the TAs who want to make Holly Martin a tragic hero, but I don't.
But let's see.
Calloway for me is a tragic hero because he's sort of funny.
What does a tragic hero do?
He has a role, and that gives him a duty which is universal.
That is, anybody with that role ought to do such and such.
And what he does is intelligible because he does what his role requires.
His role is to keep people from getting hurt.
And he does that.
And so far, that's already sort of getting him into the ethical.
But then this is trickier.
There are two things a tragic hero can do, I think.
Subordinate a lower ethical to a higher ethical.
So you can read Agamemnon as having a duty of a father to love his and take care of his daughter, but he subordinates that because it's his duty as king to take care of his troops.
Or you could read a tragic hero as putting mediation above immediacy.
Then you would say, well, he's a tragic hero because, Agamemnon is, because he puts his love for his daughter, which is a strong feeling, but it's still lower immediacy.
I mean, we're assuming he hasn't got an unconditional commitment to his daughter, but he feels strongly about her.
He puts that below his duty as policeman.
And now, but we haven't, oh, sorry, I shouldn't have said policeman.
That's Agamemnon.
But now we switch to Calloway.
Calloway does his duty as policeman, and he does it.
It's not a big deal, but it's moving.
When Pain is killed, I think it's supposed to be clear that he cares a lot for Pain.
And they've really been together a long time, and they really like each other, respect each other.
Because he drops everything and goes to Pain's body and tries to revive him or cry over him.
I don't know what he's doing exactly.
But whatever he's doing, he suddenly realizes that his duty and his role of keeping people from getting hurt requires that he drop pain and run after Holly, who's done another stupid thing and is running down the sewers, exposing himself to be shot.
So that's my conclusion.
He's a tragic hero who subordinates either a lower ethical, which I don't see what the lower ethical would be.
It might be something like take care of your subordinates or something, but I don't think that's important.
He subordinates a lower something, either lower immediacy or lower ethical, to what's important, his role, which is a recognized role and which is intelligible to everybody, and it's clear that he does the right thing when he drops pain and runs after Holly.
How's that?
Does that answer you?
Are you satisfied?
Okay.
No follow-up?
Why would he not be a knight of resignation?
Because I don't think he's got an unconditional commitment to anybody.
I say not to pain.
That would be odd.
You have to see what I mean.
Okay, good.
Yes.
White is white.
Okay, Holly, yeah, this is where it got interesting in office hours discussing this.
Holly is clearly meant to be a fool, as Hannah tells him he is, and he's not sensible.
I meant to mention this, when names are so important, you get a sort of the names get emphasized.
And at one point, Callaway says something, something, be sensible, Martins.
And Holly Martin says, I haven't got a sensible name, Callaway.
He's not sensible.
What he does is not intelligible.
There is no universal role for vigilantes who go about deciding on their own what's right and wrong and going around sort of cleaning up without without judicial procedures or anything.
He's a loner.
He's the lone sheriff of Santa Fe.
Isn't that the name of the book?
Uh-huh, great.
So he, and there is no such thing as role of loan sheriff, I think.
We can recognize it as something people do, but it's not something that comes with a certain bunch of duties, which we respect, and so forth.
That's why I don't think Holly is, Holly shouldn't be anything respectable.
Holly is just a very foolish, naive, dangerous person.
He's just as much a villain, or more, more, I think, in the way the book works, than Harry Lyme.
Though Harry Lyme's killed a lot of people off stage, kids offstage, which is pretty serious.
All the people on stage get killed by some influence or other of Holly.
And in general, there is a look of melancholy that goes across Harry Lyme's face.
And when Holly asks him, what do you believe?
He says he believes in God.
And I think he does.
I think he believes in God and that he's a sinner and that he can't help being selfish and that he's going to go to hell and that that's pretty awful.
The awfulest thing that can happen to somebody who has made their own interests and their own desires the you can't say sort of defining thing in their life, I think, because I think that's too empty as to say I'm defined by my desires.
And my desires are changing all the time.
And I don't change my identity every time my desires change the way I do every time, if there is a time that my unconditional commitment changes.
Okay, more.
I'm always ready to talk about the third man.
I love the third man.
But I'm ready also, and I think I like it that you're not saying anything more, because I really want to go on and do the brothers.
But before I do, I want to look at four pages that I marked as something that I might want to say.
Oh, yeah, I wanted to say a few quick things that I didn't think came across clear enough.
That maybe you all understand this, that to be a knight of faith and to be a human being who is totally fulfilled and in bliss and so forth is at the same time to be in anguish.
That's the whole point of this peculiar religion that's so unlike Buddhism or any other religion, I suppose, because Buddhism is the only one I really know a little about.
But anyway, the idea of the Greek kind of religions, and Buddhism may have influenced Plato, is to get happiness by getting rid of suffering, by getting rid of the contradiction.
Whereas starting with, well, really starting with Jesus, Pascal would say, but starting by being recognized by Pascal anyway, there's something absolutely special about Christianity.
It recognizes the contradictoriness of the self, and it recognizes that you can't have bliss without anguish.
They just go together.
Was that clear?
How many thought I was clear already, and I'm wasting my breath?
Well, then it was worth saying.
How many thought it wasn't clear already, and they've been enlightened?
Hardly worth saying.
But anyway, I'm happy to see that you can raise your hand.
You can move your arms.
Let's see now.
What else is here?
And the question about somebody asked, these are good questions that come up in office hours.
Can you fall back into despair once you've been out of despair?
I think not.
I think, I mean, to get out of despair, you have to have been in despair and saved by having a defining commitment in a way that nothing could ever take it away from you.
That second clause is the important thing.
Once you've got a defining relation, you might lose it, and that might lead you to despair, like the French woman.
But if you've got a defining relation and faith, then you will always have a new Isaac, and you will always somehow have a new ethic, although you can't picture what that could mean in either case.
But the point is, in the world of the spirit, nothing bad can happen to you if you've got faith.
That's the divine comedy.
The good wins out always, and the bad loses, always.
And once you've got faith and an unconditional commitment, and therefore are out of despair, you're always out.
And it's related to a phrase of Paul's, which I find interesting in the Bible, saying, Paul, of being a slave to righteousness.
I think that that means when you're in the right relation to unconditional commitment and to the field of all things are possible, nothing can get you out of it.
I'm not sure that's right.
I put that as a challenge.
I can't quote any Kierkegaard that says it.
Okay, I think that might be it.
Yeah, okay, yeah.
I don't think you can tell from the outside.
For instance, if we hadn't seen the French woman give her moan of utter sadness and know the whole context in which that happened in the movie, if we had just sort of walked in and seen her, we wouldn't have recognized that as despair, unless we were Kierkegaard or Dostoevsky, some very sensitive person.
I mean, there is something about the glide of a person with infinite resignation, which, if you were sensitive, you could see it.
And you know, if you read Kierkegaard that all knights of infinite resignation are in despair.
So you, in principle, could recognize them, I think.
But most of the time, I think, you couldn't.
And lots of the time, they don't even know they're in despair.
So it isn't as if, I mean, I can't say to Beatrice, well, they don't, you can't recognize them, but they at least know.
No, they don't know.
And we're back to that again.
All of you are in despair, and very few of you know it.
Not all of you, almost all of you are in despair.
Some of you may be Knights of Faith sitting out there.
And the Knights of Faith know it because they're in anguish and bliss at the same time.
But lots of you are in despair, and you don't know it.
But when you finally do get pushed into despair by, you will know that you always were, because there's only one way that a human life can work, and that is by having an infinite unconditional commitment, which gets together the finite and the infinite and the temporal and the eternal and the possible and necessary and does it in a way in the field of faith, in the field of all things are possible, and thereby is out of, is in bliss and in anguish.
Okay, that's it.
I'm ready to go to the brothers.
You're ready to go to the brothers.
How many have been reading the brothers?
Oh, wow, well, that's sure we should go to the brothers.
Absolutely, right away.
I'm happy we're there.
Okay.
Everybody's with me.
Now, I'm going to tell you some background things, which you probably have figured out for yourself, but it just helps to make them clear.
You've surely figured out for yourself, all the brothers are very young.
They're pretty much your age, maybe a little older, in their early 20s.
And that, but something else you may begin to notice.
How many of you have read other Russian novels?
How many have read War and Peace?
But a lot of you have read Crime and Punishment.
How many have read Crime and Punishment?
Okay.
Well, you know in Russian novels that characters have so many names that it's hard to keep track.
That's why I gave you the name chart.
That is, but I'm going to tell you something that isn't something you can't see from the chart.
That is, to begin with, let's just, I once had the inspiration, I think, to say to myself and to you that it isn't just Russian novels where everybody has so many names you can hardly keep track.
American novels have it too.
It's just we're so used to it that we don't even notice that characters can have something like five or six different, very different names, and we know that they're all the same.
Here's my example.
This guy, Mr.
Smith, is William, Bill, Billy, Will, and Willie, at least.
And I probably left some out.
Now, what's important is, one, to see that when you read it, you have no trouble as they come around recognizing that William, oddly enough, is the same person as Bill.
I'm always amazed the way that John is the same person as Jack, but I finally gotten used to it.
That's right, isn't it?
I think so.
But you get used to it.
But the one thing I'm going to tell you that you don't notice, and my chart doesn't tell you either, is that it's important what of these many names the person is called.
That is, it's important to know who call that some people are call that you call this.
Who calls, well, my favorite example is, in this case, Charlie.
Charlie Brown is called Charlie by everybody.
When one day the girl who cares a lot about him, I forget what her name is, calls him Charles, it's just an amazing shock to everybody.
And the same goes on here.
It's very, you've got to be tuned in to which names are being used for these people.
Now, for instance, Mitya is, how many know?
Dimitri.
Dimitri is Mitya, and people call Dimitri Mitya about half the time, meaning that he's sort of on friendly relations with half the people and sort of more impersonal relations with the other half.
Now, that's not at all true of Alexei.
Who is Alexei?
It's harder for you to even know.
Alyosha.
But practically nobody calls him Alexei.
The narrator maybe.
But all the people in the book are on friendly terms with him, and so everybody calls him Alexei.
Can you think of which brother nobody calls by a nickname?
Almost nobody?
I finally found occasional.
Yvonne.
Yep, the narrator always calls him Yvonne.
Everybody calls him Yvonne.
One person calls him Vanka, and that is his father, old Karamatsov.
And way late in the book, there's a song about Vanka, which, if you don't recognize that that's really a song about Yvonne, you miss something very important that's happening, which I missed for years, because how should you know that that Vanka song is taken to heart by Yvonne when he hears it?
So let's see now.
We've done Dmitry Alexei Yvonne.
Seems to me somebody's missing.
Well, there are two people missing.
Old Terematsov, I forget what they call him.
Who do they, what's it?
Does he have a first name?
I just made it up.
What?
Fedor, of course.
So, and he's called, and Freud was very interested in the fact that old Terevatsov is called, that the father, because Fedor Dostoevsky is also called Theodore.
And you might want to ask yourself, what is it?
Why is Dostoevsky giving this villain in the book his own name?
But I don't have any interesting answer to that.
I don't think Freud did either.
But there is probably something going on there.
So, and finally, well, let's go through one more: Shmerdikov.
I'm pretty sure Smershikov doesn't have any nickname.
Or Shmerdyakov is his nickname, I think, more likely.
I just don't know why.
But since he's practically not human, nobody has, I mean, the distinction, nobody has an intimately friendly relation to him or a formal relation to him.
They more or less treat him like what he is, a lackey, and they have whatever you have relation to your valet and your lackey.
Okay, I think I've covered them, but I just want to scan it now.
Let's see.
Yeah, okay.
And now to the big deal things: the self.
The amazing fact is that Dostoevsky has exactly the same view of the self as Kierkegaard.
I don't know how they both got it.
I think they both probably, almost surely, read Pascal.
And it's sort of in Pascal.
I mean, that there are the self with contradictory factors and the factors that give you something to be proud of and something to be ashamed of in Pascal.
But I really am amazed that, and I think maybe, maybe, maybe somebody way over in the podcast world, who knows where in Russia or someplace, will be able to send me an email telling me why, how it could happen that this very complicated idea should show up in these two different people who almost surely didn't read each other's work.
But we're going to read it.
But you won't see any reference to the self in the brothers, so you may well think that I'm leading you astray.
What's the word for the self in this book?
Yes, if you've got it in your hand, haven't you?
The heart, exactly.
You'll see before the end of today, maybe, that it's clear as can be that one of the characters says the heart is contradictory and it's too broad, and I have it narrower, and so forth and so forth.
And in the heart, there is, there's no special, you can call it heart or self, whatever you want.
It's something or other that's at the center of what it is to be a human being.
And another thing, as in Kierkegaard, but it's clearer in Dostoevsky, because Kierkegaard just says it, but Dostoevsky shows it, that there are these ways of relating to yourself.
The way it's harder to say that your heart relates to itself, but somehow what it is to be a self, what kind of heart you have, funny way to think, is now, and this is the important thing, which is the right one, which is the good way, go back to Kierkegaard talk, that the self relates to the self.
Well, Kierkegaard's got an answer.
It's relating to itself by relating to another and having an unconditional commitment for that other, and that only that way can you get all the factors together.
That's what he says.
The Dostoevsky shows you four different ways of relating to the self, because there are four Karamatsovs.
That is, they're the three sons and the father.
They're really four and a half Karamatsovs, counting Smerzhikov, but I don't think he has a heart.
But in any case, Dostoevsky shows you the right way to relate to yourself, the self should relate to yourself by showing you various ways of doing it.
That is, we see how Alyasha relates to himself, how Ivan does, how Dmitri does, how old Karamatsov does, and we see which ones work.
That is, the only test isn't sort of a Bible telling you, or reason telling you, or nature telling you, or Kierkegaard telling you.
Dostoevsky wants you to just see these lives and see for yourself which ones lead to joy and bliss and which ones lead to despair and madness.
And when you see that, you will understand which is the wrong way, which is the right way to go.
I'm not sure that it's easy to choose something as deep as this.
It may be that it takes some kind of grace to go the right way.
Nobody in the book chooses their way of being a self.
They start with it when the book begins.
But one thing is sure: how you should relate yourself to yourself depends, is shown by what becomes of you.
So you've got to watch and see in the book what becomes of all these people.
There's really eight of them.
Why do I say there's eight of them instead of four of them?
Well, I'll show you in a minute, but I can tell you a general principle already, which, insofar as I've read books about the brothers, which I have read very few, and I would be happy when I say things if people would tell me, again, out there in the big world, whether somebody's already said that and I should give them credit, or whether somebody said the opposite and I should make clear to warn you that they're wrong.
In any case, there are eight of them.
And that's because subtly, you don't even notice it the first four or five times you read it, if you can live that long.
For every Karamatsov, there is a double, an existential double.
And the existential double has exactly the same stand on the self as the brother.
And even the old father, which is what I'm going to start with, has his existential double.
So we're going to start with that in a minute.
But let me see first.
So I went back to what I said of reading my notes.
You have to be aware of which orientation each of the brothers has so that you can learn from which one works and which one leads to madness and suffering and perhaps suicide.
Okay.
Or one more way, I just like to keep saying this because it's important.
In existential philosophy, a view of how to live isn't tested by argument, of any sort, but by action.
You commit yourself to it and act on it, and then you see how you come out.
Every one of them is an extreme version of the position they're in, and something extreme happens to them, which is a comment on that way of being, way of existing, if you want to say existential.
Okay, now, one more thing in background, and then we'll get to old Feodor.
All the Taramatsaws are related to each other in interesting ways, and Dostoevsky thinks heredity is very important.
So in the history of the family chapter, we learn that old Terematsov, the father, has two wives, so that the brothers have different mothers.
Dimitri's mother is Adelaide, and his personality is related to hers.
Remember, she's hot-headed and impulsive and passionate and also strong and beats up, beats up old Taramatsov.
And people choose professions, by the way, which of course fit their heredity and their stand on the self, too.
What profession has Dmitry got?
Yeah, soldier.
He's in the army.
He had a tough, strong, aggressive mother, and he's tough and strong and aggressive too.
Now, what's really much more interesting is that Yvonne and Alyasha have the same mother, Sophia.
Sophia is a kind of religious person, very weak and meek.
I'm going to say not weak.
She's weak too, but that's not important.
Meek.
And she is has, to my amazement, and you learn something new every time you read this.
I didn't ever notice before she has the kind of mental condition that she experiences devils.
I wrote that in the back of my book because I was so surprised.
I'll tell you why I'm so surprised in a minute.
You'll be surprised too.
On page 11, in the middle of the page, in the end, this unhappy Sophia, kept in terror from her childhood, fell into that kind of nervous disease which is most frequently found in peasant women who are said to be possessed by the devil.
I say that it's amazing because guess what?
Both Alyasha and Yvonne are confronted by the devil.
Dimitri couldn't be further, devils wouldn't be interested in Dmitri, and Dimitri's not interested in devils.
But Sophia is in this religious dimension, and she is a kind of perfectly Christian person, but perfectly Christian people can, and even Alyasha does, have a confrontation with the devil.
You'll see that, but that's a long way away.
So let's go back to where I am.
So here we got two brothers.
What in the world do they have in common?
Yvonne, you'll see, but you know already, is an intellectual.
I don't know about you, but let's find out.
When I read it, I identified with Yvonne.
He was my favorite character.
He went to the university.
He had a job to support himself.
He was on work study.
He studied philosophy and science, would be called natural philosophy in those days.
But maybe you didn't.
How many identify with Ivan?
Okay, that's interesting.
How many, you may not read it far enough to know yet.
How many identify with Dimitri?
See, Dimitri's furthest from us.
Okay, I thought so too.
Well, how many identify with Alyasha?
Ah, well, that's nice.
You're onto something I wasn't onto when I was reading it.
So, okay, so, but we don't understand yet what Yvonne and Alyasha have in common.
What they have in common is something that I can't really explain.
I can only, I don't even know if I can find a name for it.
I'll explain it when I get there.
Well, roughly, each in their own way is concerned with purity.
But what purity means to Yvonne and what purity means to Alyasha are totally different.
And yet, they go back to this, this mother.
Purity is certainly not on Dimitri's mind, nor on his mother's mind as she beats up old Feodor.
So Dmitri certainly couldn't be the brother of either of those two brothers without having, they're introducing a different wife.
Yeah.
Ivan and Alyosha.
Yeah, well, I think that's right, but I think there's a deeper thing.
But I don't disagree about that, but I'm not in a position to tell you the deeper thing yet.
And I can't think of any reason to disagree about you, because Dmitry is certainly confused a lot.
And there's no other candidate for clarity of thinking, but those two, I grant you.
And that's fine.
I suppose Zasima, but he doesn't count as a Karamatsov.
Okay, let's go on.
So now I'm going to talk about them.
And in the order, I think, at least I never thought about what order I'm doing it in, but we'll see whether I do it right.
I would like to talk about them in the order that Kierkegaard talks about, the various ways that the self relates to itself.
So if I did that, who would be the first one that I should talk about?
Well, let's discuss.
What's the first way that the self relates to itself?
Lower immediacy, somebody says.
Spiritlessness, Kierkegaard says.
Not even despair, but something lower than despair.
And who could, which of the four Karamatsovs could that be?
Oh, Theodore, absolutely.
So let's look at the now I have an interesting problem, but it's only temporary.
Somebody has my copy of the lecture notes, which have the page numbers that I need as I talk about it.
You have them?
Okay, good.
I'll trade.
Thank you.
No, no, no, no.
I can see why you think that.
But no, we've got to find mine where I've written in the page numbers because I don't want to rail at this, but I really am annoyed.
Every time I teach it, I get a new book comes out.
No, it's a different one.
No, no, that's Kierkegaard.
Every time I teach it, a new book comes out, and they manage to make a new introduction, and that changes the page numbers.
So somebody somewhere must have a copy of my lecture notes in which the page numbers are there.
Oh, thank goodness.
I would really go crazy if I didn't have them.
I spent two hours copying page numbers from this, which is exactly the same book, except that it's in this.
And they've reset the type even so that the lines aren't at the same places on the page.
They've done everything to make it impossible to use this one when you're teaching the brothers, and that's nice.
They made you all buy it.
But it's not nice at all if you've got your page numbers and you have to rewrite them all in each book.
I'm going to find one that stays constant.
But then it won't be small.
I don't know what I'm going to do.
So it looks like we start on page 19 when we're talking about Karamatsa.
And I remember.
You start on page 3 when you're in this book, 19 in this book.
Okay, here we are.
Starting on page 3, right at the beginning, we hear about him about 10 lines down, that he was a person fairly frequently to be met with, despicable, vicious man, and at the same time, senseless.
And in another translation, muddled.
Now, I don't think either one of those are quite right.
And I wish my Russian people were here, but I trust they will hear this in podcasts.
I don't know.
It may be the same Russian word that's being translated senseless and muddled.
And I don't know the Russian word, but I want to translate it distracted.
Because he's not at all senseless.
He's a very successful businessman, quite rich, and he's very good at selling and buying property and getting people to give him sort of mortgages, which they then default on and so forth.
So I don't think he's senseless.
And I don't think he's muddled in the sense that he's able to carry on fancy theological conversations with Yvonne and friendly sort of, almost sort of religious conversations with Alyasha.
And he's very clever in a selfish sort of way.
But he is distracted by a distracted, and that's Pascal's word.
And now what does Pascal use it for?
If you went back at your notes, you would see that for Pascal, people distract themselves from recognizing their miserable human condition and the fact that they're going to go to hell if they don't shape up.
And then they do things like, you know, remember, play games and hunt and dance.
And they would certainly play computer games if they had them.
And these are all, and those are all ways to avoid thinking about their existential condition.
And that's the word you should have in there where it says that he was senseless.
And so he's got these sharp business practices just to show you.
Once I went through marking up this book, I might as well show off.
The bottom of 21, he gets good security and he makes people pay their debts and so forth.
But now comes the new part, the bottom of 21.
I want to read this.
And this is part of his distraction.
Of late, he looked somehow bloated and seemed more irresponsible, even more uneven and sunken into a sort of incoherence.
He used to begin one thing and go on with another as though he were letting himself go altogether.
He was more and more frequently drunk.
That's not senselessness or muddledness.
He's trying not to think about something.
And we have to figure out what he's trying not to think about.
In drunkenness, money making, women chasing and so forth, what is he avoiding?
Well, he's not actually conscious of having a self.
He's not aware of a contradiction.
He's not aware that he's in despair.
But all that is there in the way he behaves.
So, and you see it in two places at least, on page six, a great revealing story at the end of the first chapter.
How what happens when Adelaide, the first wife, dies?
She died at the end of the first paragraph quite suddenly in a garret, according to one story of typhus, or another version had it of starvation.
Now, that seems like an innocuous sentence, but that's a very relatively important sentence because it requires me to point out that the Bhagavad-Chernatsov is supposedly written by somebody not too bright who lives in the town where all this took place.
It's got what technically people call sometimes an obtuse narrator, which means that you have to sort of see through what the narrator says to what's really going on.
Now, it could be very important.
There are books, whole books, that are written just that way, and that's the game.
But Dostoevsky's not very interested in this game because after a few chapters, the obtuse narrator sort of fades out, and Dostoevsky takes over and begins to describe stuff that the narrator could never know, what people were thinking and what was going on in some other town and so forth.
But when this obtuse narrator is being obtuse and narrating, he's got this idea that people, that there's only one cause for things.
So either she died of typhus or she died of starvation.
But why not both?
I mean, you could die, maybe very technically, you'd have to say, well, finally, what does the coroner's report say?
But it's clear that this is sort of a kind of condition of being badly nourished on your own.
Now, that's a minimal one, but it turns out that it gets maximum in the next paragraph.
What gets maximum is the peculiar quality of the narrator to talk as if people couldn't have contradictory impulses.
They either do something for this reason or that reason.
Whereas Dostoevsky is constantly smuggling in that people always have contradictory impulses and usually do things for at least two contradictory reasons.
He talks about that in his notebooks about double motives.
So he's invented an obtruse narrator who sees these double motives but doesn't really understand them.
Now the next paragraph, that happens.
He says, this is what the narrator says.
Fedor Karamatsov was drunk when he heard of his wife's death.
And the story is that he ran into the street and began shouting with joy, raising his hands to heaven, Lord, now let us thou thy servant depart in peace.
But others say he wept without restraint, like a little child, so much so that people were sorry for him in spite of the repulsion he aroused.
It's quite possible that both versions were true, that he rejoiced at his release and at the same time wept for her who released him.
So he's sort of there, he sort of sees that there might be two motives, but he doesn't see that they're sort of opposed motives because he says, as a general rule, people, even the wicked, are much more naive and simple-hearted than we suppose, and we ourselves are too.
Now, if you see the funny conclusion, he sees that old Karamatsov is not naive and simple-hearted, that he sort of hates his wife and loves his wife, and then he concludes somehow that they are.
And that's typical of him, even when he sees the people acting out of double motives, he thinks that it's simple and that somehow he doesn't understand what Dostoevsky very much believes and understands.
People are just full of contradictory impulses because they've got a contradictory self and it comes out in all these ways.
So, anyway, there he is.
And now, what else have we got?
I've got to find out where we are.
Oh, here we are.
On 21 and 22, I'm just giving you a picture of old Terematsov still.
We have time.
You know, he's letting himself go and getting drunk.
I've got that already.
Okay, we're going to go to another place in a minute, but first I will bring you up to the date there.
We're seeing that old Terematsov has very sort of down-to-earth and bad impulses, and even somehow good impulses, and that he sort of gives into them at random or to it both at once.
What we hear about often is the earthly and the lofty impulses.
That's one of the ways that the factors are described.
You've got to get used to the fact, obviously, that the factors aren't going to be called infinite and finite, temporal, and eternal, causable, and necessary.
The factors are called all sorts of other things.
And lofty and lackey opposition is one of the oppositions.
You can see it on the chart.
Different characters have different ways of describing the oppositions, but they're always sort of, you could say roughly, heavenly and earthly impulses.
Now we want to go to the place where it comes out most clearly what old Terematsov is trying to hide.
There are other places in here which I couldn't find in the time I had to redo all the pages, but the most important one is on 45.
When they're in Zosima's room and they're having this kind of psychodrama in which everybody sort of is freaking out, and at the middle of 45, it's Theodore's turn to freak out, and he says, that's why I'm a buffoon.
It's from great shame, great Elter, from shame.
It's simply oversensitiveness, which makes me rowdy.
If I had only been sure that everyone would accept me as the kindest and wisest of men, oh Lord, what a good man I would have been.
Teacher, he fell suddenly on his knees.
What must I do to gain eternal life?
So it looks like he's been what he stays drunk and confused and muddled, if you will like, and diverts himself is that he really does worry about eternal life.
There are other quotes, keep your eyes open for them.
I didn't have time to find them, where he asks at dinner whether there is hell and he worries about that.
But let's go on with these.
But notice in the next line, the narrator says, it was difficult even now to decide whether he was joking or really moved.
Was he joking or was he really moved?
Both, absolutely.
It's clear that he cares a lot about eternal life and he can't face that it's a serious and tries to make it an unserious issue just because he's so scared and it's so serious.
And Zosima says to him at the bottom of paragraph, above all, don't lie to yourself.
The man who lies can't distinguish truth and so forth.
And having no respect, he ceases to love and so forth and so forth.
And he admits he's been lying in the middle of 46.
I've been lying, lying my whole life long, every day of it, he says.
But finally, I thought there was more to this, but I better find it.
No, I guess that's all there.
And I couldn't find the places, I got millions of page numbers, something like five different sets of page numbers for five different books, but I couldn't find the places where, particularly when he's talking to Alyasha at dinner and so forth, he gets overcome by fright.
So anyway, it's clear enough that he wants not to think about whether he's leading a life that is going to take him to heaven or hell.
That is, he doesn't have it, whether he's going to lead a life that ultimately leads to despair and misery or whether he's going to be able to shape up.
He just doesn't want to face that.
So he stays in this stupor.
Now, now I get to make the other interesting point I want to make.
And it's surprising.
And again, it takes a while to notice it.
He has a metaphysical, or I guess their existential double.
Somebody else who, always a woman, if it's because they're the sort of man-woman dyads.
So a woman who is in a continual state of dithering confusion.
Can you recognize that?
She also has an interview with Zosima, and there's something very similar in what she does and says, and what he says to her.
Okay, well, it's Mrs.
Holokoff of all things.
I mean, she's a society lady and not drunk and not rich and not, and in every kind of obvious way, not at all like old Karamatsov.
But it turns out that she's got exactly the same kind of strategy of covering up what's going on with her.
This is on 48, we hear about her, that she's there, and she's a woman of rank.
That's all I need from that page.
But on 49, up, oh, 59, okay, on 59, we hear a long thing about her.
And she's starting to tell her story to Zosima at the end of the middle paragraph.
I'm suffering.
Forgive me, forgive me, I'm suffering.
And in a rush of emotion, she clasps her hands before him.
You are suffering from what are you suffering?
I suffer from lack of faith.
Lack of faith in God.
Oh, no, I dare not even think of that.
But life after death is such an enigma, and no one can solve it.
You're a healer.
You're deeply immersed in the human soul, and so forth and so forth.
The thought of life beyond the grave fills me with anguish, with terror.
And it does old Karamatsov, too, if I could only find the passages.
Keep your eyes open.
But it does.
I don't know to whom to appeal and have not dared to all my life.
And now I am bold enough to ask you, oh God, what will you think of me now?
See anything strange in that outburst?
She claims to be worrying about whether there's an afterlife and the state of her eternal soul, and what she's worrying about is whether she's making a fool of herself or not.
And Vasa immediately says that.
Don't worry about my opinion of you, said Father Zasima.
I believe in the sincerity of your suffering.
And that's one, she is sincerely suffering.
Two, she's so kind of diverted by her social role and so forth that she can't just seriously talk to him about it.
And he tries to tell her, you know, to shape up and pay attention.
And she goes on telling you, telling him about all of her love and her love for Lisa, her daughter, and so forth.
But it's clear that she, and you'll see it more and more if you keep your eye on her, is having the same kind of problem he is.
She's really worried about the right relation of the self to the self and whether that's going to take you, never mind whether, they all say it in terms of afterlife, but of course it means whether that's going to give you a fulfilled and blissful life or whether that's going to give you misery and despair.
But they're worried about it, but they keep being distracted.
They want to be distracted.
And she's constantly distracted in a kind of dither over her daughter and her dither over herself, but never really focusing.
I'm worried about the fact that everybody's sitting here looking at me not nicely, but nobody's saying anything.
I understand in a way that it's not very controversial what I'm saying.
I'm just telling you what the book is saying.
Nobody has any comments they want to make to help me say more about these people or happen to know the page numbers where we find out more about these people.
Well, okay, I'm going to go on.
I'm tempted to go back to this one.
I wonder if that's probably suicidal, but let me just see if I could find out.
I want to find out more about old Karamatsov.
I don't find it in a minute.
I give it.
Oh, yeah, here's a good one.
But now I can't tell you where it is, except that it's in the chapter, The Sensualists, the book, Three, The Sensualists, Chapter One, about one page in, but it's a good example.
At the bottom of the page, no, it won't be at the bottom of your page, but they managed to fix it, so you can't tell where we are.
But it says, corrupt and often cruel in his lust, like a poisonous insect, Fedor Karamatsov was sometimes in moments of drunkenness overcome by superstitious terror and a moral convulsion, which took an almost physical form.
My soul simply quakes in my throat at those times, he used to say.
And skipping a little, one who had seen all his vices and knew his secrets, but was ready in his devotion to overlook everything, not to oppose him, and above all, not to reproach him for so-and-so and so-and-so.
He's looking for such a person to defend him from whom?
From somebody unknown, the terrible and dangerous.
And that's so that I just want to give you another exam example so you won't so you'll believe me that old Karamatsov is the not willing to have a self, not not willing to face up to being a self.
Okay, and now we go on to let's see if I'm doing it in the right order.
We want somebody to let's see if you remember.
Help you all wake up.
Here's a contest.
So the first relation of the self to the self is that it tries to forget the problem, that it has to take a stand and it will go to hell or heaven, depending on what stand it takes.
Now, what's the next form of despair?
That wasn't even really despair.
What's the first form of real despair?
You must have it.
Somebody has it in their hand, obviously.
So read it.
It's at the top, that little thing at the top.
It's in despair, not willing to be a self.
Can remember what that is?
That's a despair of a negative relation, negative R2.
Negative R2 is the self relates it to itself by denying half the self.
I'm not really a body, just a mind.
Or I'm not really a mind, just a body.
Or I'm not really infinite, just a finite, or vice versa.
So who's now, and this is harder, and you may not have read far enough to know, which of the brothers is in the despair of not wanting to have the self he's got, but to get rid of?
It's probably too early to ask.
Okay, let's.
Alexi, no, he's not.
Alexey, no, he's not in despair about anything.
Or do you mean Yvonne?
No.
Oh, no, no, no.
He hasn't even had trouble.
Why are you saying this?
I'm interested.
We're talking about Alexei, Alyasha.
Oh, I see.
I see.
Yes, when he's with Dzosima, he's very much almost in tears because they're behaving so badly.
I know what you mean now.
But that's.
But he doesn't, you know, when he's with old Karamatsov, they get along fine.
And Karamatsov, old Karamatsov says, you're the only one who doesn't despise me.
It's interesting, by the way, in case I forget to say it.
There's so much subtle detail.
Ivan, who's an intellectual, despises old Karamatsov.
But Dmitri, who's a kind of passionate person, what's his word for it?
Not disgust, but it's like contempt.
I don't know.
Now I'd have to go back and look.
Maybe it's Yvonne who has contempt for old Karamatsov and Dmitry to despise him.
They've all got, they all dislike Karamatsov and got a different kind of emotion against him, except Alyasha, who accepts him and affirms him, and that makes him a nicer person when Alyasha's around.
But it's true that Alyasha on 44 of your book is, as she says, embarrassed by the way his family is behaving at the about ten lines down.
Alyasha stood with hanging head on the verge of tears.
What seemed to him strangest of all was that his brother, Yvonne, on whom he had rested his hopes and on whom he had influen, and who alone had such influence on his father that he could have stopped him, sat quite unmoved with downcast eyes, apparently waiting with interest to see how it would end, as though he had nothing to do with it.
That's a very important speech about Yvonne.
It doesn't much matter that Alyosha is upset about it.
It's just that's only, you know, he's upset about it because he's so concerned that everybody should be loved and appreciated.
What's interesting is what it shows about Yvonne.
It shows about Yvonne that he thinks of himself as a kind of observer of everything.
He's not involved.
He's not responsible.
It's not part of his family that's cracking up.
He's just there as a witness, or as we might say, an eyewitness.
Why am I making a sort of joke about or a pun or something about his being an eyewitness observer?
You know?
You remember how he earns his living when he's a student?
It's important.
Yeah, we'll get there.
So first I have to back up, and I think, I've got to go look anyway.
Well, it's about Sophia.
And I think I've read enough about Sophia.
I don't really need any more.
No, so we can go to Yvonne.
I was just making sure we had his mother.
So they are so different, Yvonne and Alyosha, that even old Taramatso forgets that they're brothers.
But they have the same saintly mother, and each one of them is seeking purity, but in a very different way.
And each one of them has a problem with devils, which Dmitri does not have.
So let's look at Yvonne now.
He is a self-made man, and we're now going to do some Dostoevsky sort of psychology.
That is, he's very, he understands that people's early childhood experiences are very formative of their personality.
And he thinks that they can be absolutely decisive.
We'll see that later.
But already Yvonne is trying to be independent.
That's why he's supporting himself at the university and not asking his father for money.
And why is he trying so hard to be independent?
Well, because he felt that he was dependent on others, the relatives that he'd been sent to when his mother died, and he resents that.
The interesting thing we'll get back to is that Alyasha is also completely dependent on some relatives or other.
And his reaction is entirely different.
He just lets himself be taken care of by anybody.
He's perfectly happy to be housed and fed and loved and whatever by anybody who wants to take care of him.
Whereas Yvonne doesn't want any dependence on anybody.
So he's self-sufficient.
And he doesn't, whereas Dimitri wants money from his father and always wants more money from his father, Yvonne doesn't want that at all.
And now it turns out that, of course, what looks admirable about Yvonne, and what I always thought was admirable when I read this part of the book, is, from a Christian point of view, pride.
I mean, who's right?
Alyasha, who loves everybody and assumes that everybody's going to love him, and who would give any beggar or anybody who needed anything, whatever he had, and assume that if he goes around and needs a place to sleep or needs food, somebody will give it to him.
Dostoevsky is so clever.
So I think it's too clever to be something in his mind.
I think that he just writes out of this deep understanding of all these characters.
But you'll discover that you know always where Dmitry is staying and who's feeding and where he's getting his food, and where Ivan is staying and how he supports himself.
You never find, you never, never even, Dostoevsky or the narrator never even bothers to tell you where Alyasha got the nice clothes he got when he left the monastery, where he's sleeping.
At one point, he feels hungry and he takes a roll out of his pocket and eats it, but I have no, we have no idea.
Somebody gave it to him.
Maybe when he goes by the bakery, they give him food.
Anyway, with Yvonne, it's pride.
That is, he wants to be self-sufficient.
He's not a Christian saint like Alyasha's on the way to being.
He's a Greek hero, that is, in his mind.
He's the one who has enough power to take care of themselves.
And he has, here I wrote it down, contempt for his father.
Ah, I wrote down, Dimitri has loathing for his father.
That's nice.
Contempt is an intellectual way of hating some, despising somebody.
And loathing is the sort of visceral way of having a very negative relation.
So now he's going on, and he has contempt for his father.
And Miyazov, who's a kind of observer of things, who gets things right generally, though he is an intellectual and likes Europe, which is a bad sign for Dostoevsky.
Did I say Dmitri?
Ooh, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, what did I say about Dmitri?
He is what?
Loathing.
Wait, I'm saying, no, I mean Dmitri.
Ivan has contempt for his father.
Dimitri has loathing for his father.
That's the point.
And Alyasha has love for his father.
despicable as he is, the old guy, and almost sort of saves him by way of that love, but not quite because he's.
But Miyazov says on page 15 of your book, about two-thirds down, he's proud, he used to say.
I'm just reading it because I marked it.
And he takes on this job to be self-sufficient.
And he hates, in the middle of 13, being on other people's charity.
And while I'm at it, and at the bottom of the page, he was forced to support himself all the time he was studying.
Well, he was forced to do it in the sense that he wasn't going to, he was forced to do it by the fact that he wouldn't let anybody help him do it.
It isn't clear that old Karamatsov wouldn't give him money if he asked for it.
He gives Dmitri some money.
But anyway, he doesn't want anybody to help him.
So he has a job.
But just to fill you in on 13, he has a brilliant and unusual aptitude for learning, like all of us.
That's again why I identified with him.
I said, ah, yes, he's going to go to a good, goes to a good university.
He entered a university and so forth.
But now comes the really revealing thing.
What job does he take to support himself?
I wouldn't be harping on this so much if it isn't going to turn out to be very important later.
So, at the top of 14.
However, that may have been, Ivonne was by no means despondent and succeeded in getting work, at first giving lessons and afterwards getting paragraphs on street incidents into the newspapers under the signature of eyewitness.
Remember, I just said he was behaving as if he was an eyewitness to the freak out in Zosima's cell.
In general, he behaves as if he's an eyewitness to the world.
Dostoevsky is absolutely brilliant to get in that job.
People are doing things that they're very involved in.
Lovers are quarreling or kissing, and people are stealing apples and chasing them.
And you can imagine the kind of little stories he writes, little stories that are little dramas.
But they're not his drama.
He just stands back and writes about them.
And that's his way of being in the world.
His way of being in the world is just to be an eyewitness.
And you'll see how important that is.
I'm just curious, how many have got up to the part where, wait, let me think a minute.
How do you describe it?
No, I can't describe it without going into too much trouble.
But you'll see him putting himself in the position.
Oh, yeah, the part where he's talking to Alyasha in the tavern about giving back his ticket to the world.
Have you got to that yet?
Not yet.
Okay, well, then we won't talk about that yet.
So he's a detached spectator.
He's of life.
And when things are happening, he's observing and taking notes on them.
So, and Alyasha, of course, couldn't just stand there and observe what was going on in the cell.
He's completely upset.
I think I already read that line, but I'll just go back to see if.
Yes, that was what I read: where Yvonne is sitting there as if this isn't his business, it isn't his family, it's just an event.
Where Alyasha is on the verge of tears.
And you get the hint already that Dostoevsky thinks that this kind of self-sufficient detachment that Yvonne has is a bad way to behave.
But just how bad it is as a way to behave isn't clear yet.
I mean, it's about as bad a way to behave as you can get in Dostoevsky's world.
And he's an intellectual.
That's not bad.
Dostoevsky doesn't mind intellectuals.
And so where are we?
But it's interesting, and it's in a way bad, that what he's doing is philosophy.
And why is that bad?
Well, because philosophy is a kind of observing of everything.
If you do philosophy, you sort of step back and reflect on other people and your own life and current events and all from a detached way, at least if you're doing Greek philosophy.
And Yvonne is like a Greek philosopher.
At one point, Miyazov says about him, he has his idea, where Plato always was talking about the ideas.
So Yvonne is a kind of philosopher, a kind of Platonist, which means he's chosen the intellectual, detached, objective capacity of the self.
And he's dumped or rejected the involved, emotional aspect of himself.
And now we're getting close to remember that the issue.
So, what's his relation to the self?
Well, it's a relation that wants to deny half of it.
It's in despair at failing to get rid of half the self, the trying.
Because we will see, you've got to keep all this in mind.
Well, you have to ask yourself, well, okay, so Yvonne wants to get rid of the evolved, emotional, impulsive, sort of lower immediacy, however you want to describe it, side of himself.
Can he do it?
And what happens when he tries to do it?
Those are all things that are going to go on hundreds and hundreds of pages from where you are, so I can't say more about them yet.
So, where am I then?
He has, they say, some goal.
And he's got some question that he doesn't know how to answer.
Let's go to the Zosima thing.
I didn't find all these page numbers because I didn't have time.
And it's going to be a lifetime job.
But I want to go to the place where Zostima says something to Yvonne about Yvonne having, help me find it, about Yvonne having a kind of goal which is hard to achieve.
We have to get into the Zosima section.
Where is it in this book?
Somebody tell me.
Somebody must know.
What?
About 40.
Okay, now in there somewhere around 40, you find when Zosima starts talking to Yvonne, and it may be at another time, in a different time in his monk's quarters.
I doubt it, though.
I bet it's in here.
Well, if it were, I wouldn't see it.
That's the trouble, because I didn't have time to move all my marks to the next page.
Zosima says to him, you are seeking a certain goal which is very hard to find and achieve.
And the question is, will you achieve it or not?
And Yvonne is sort of struck by this question, because he sees that he sees that this is, that Zosima has, of course, understood his kind of self.
Well, I'm going to go on to one more thing just so that you can get used to it.
That is, Yvonne is seeking a kind of perfection and a kind of purity, which is a Greek Platonic kind of purity.
That is, he's trying to get rid of everything lackey-like, lower, immediate-like, and so forth in himself.
And he can't do that.
And Zosima sees that he can't do it.
I wonder if I can find this spot.
Let's just see if it's on page 70.
No, I'm not going to find it.
I can come back to it next time.
I want to find I do know how to find that I want to leave you with as a kind of cousin.
I'll come back next time to the question of the two kinds of purity: the kind that Alyosha is trying to find and the kind of Von is trying to get.
I'll tell you roughly so you can keep your eyes open for it.
German has two words for purity: one is cleanliness, Reinheit in German.
I can write it on the board next time.
And the other is purity, which is in German Lauterke.
But what I want to say is, cleanliness purity is getting out all the dirt.
It's what the cleaners do, Rheinegung in German.
They clean out the dirt.
Yvonne wants to clean out everything that's dirt in himself, everything that's imperfect, everything that gets him involved with the world.
And he wants to be this perfect ideal spectator, like God and like a philosopher.
And Ayasha wants to be pure.
That means he wants to get rid of all the impulses which he considers dirty and demeaning and selfish and so forth.
And he wants to transform them into loving impulses.
And Zosima says you can do that.
That's part of the Christian hope.
You could be reborn pure.
But the difference is that we're back to Yvonne.
Yvonne is trying to get rid of half of himself.
He's not trying to take it over and purify it.
But now we're back to this mystery of how they come from the same mother.
They come from the same mother because, as I said, in general, sort of, I don't know what word, cleaning up your act, no, that's too much Reinheit.
Purifying yourself, that's too much purity.
We don't have one word that I know of.
But in general, they're two versions of if anybody finds the word, come and tell me in office hours or send me an email.
But it's going to have to have cleaning and purifying as two utterly different versions of it.
Okay.
Now, I want to give, but here's the puzzle I want to give you while there are four minutes left.
I just want to read you who is the next person?
That's what I want to stop to help you think about w before we get together again.
Who's the next despair con?
Well, it's the despair of trying to get the two parts of the self together on your own.
Now, by elimination, really, if that isn't Yvonne and it isn't Alyosha, that's got to be Dimitri.
Now, let me read you the description of Dimitri on 73 when he comes onto the scene.
And then we'll stop.
Dimitri, young man of 28, of medium height and agreeable appearance, looked older than he was.
He was muscular and strong, yet there was something not healthy about his face, which was rather thin.
His large eyes had an expression of determination, and yet there was a vague look in them, too.
At the bottom, something sullen in his eyes.
People who saw something sullen in his eyes were startled by his sudden laugh.
Then, at the top of 74, a certain strained look in his face was easy to understand at that moment.
And then at the end of that paragraph, the prosecutor says he is of unstable and unbalanced mind.
What is the characteristic of that description of Yvonne as he comes on the screen?
So it comes on the stage or whatever.
Well, he seems to be old and yet young, determined and yet vague, sullen and yet laughing, and so forth.
Contradictions.
Who said it?
Okay, yes.
He's a bundle of contradictions.
And that's exactly what he's going to turn out to be.
He's a self trying to get himself together, and he can't get himself together, and that's messing up his life.
And just one more, just two minutes on 120 of your book.
He says, in so many words, that he's an insect and an angel.
And he says at the middle of 120, I'm an insect, Alyasha, and we Karamatsovs are insects.
But beauty is terrible, skipping a little.
Here the boundaries meet.
All contradictions exist side by side.
And then he says at the bottom of 120, man is broad, too broad, I'd have him narrower.
So Ivan is, and knows he is, a kind of walking contradiction of angel and insect.
You can see it on the self-chart.
And he wants to keep, he wants to somehow keep all that.
He doesn't want to throw any of it out, but he wants to get it together, and he can't get it together.
And so he's in bad shape.
Okay, now you keep reading, and I will keep marking up passages.