The truth chapter is, I think, hard because there's so many interesting things going on in it.
And Heidegger's really gave whole courses on logic and on the c and involving the correspondence theory of truth.
And whole courses on truth, I think.
And now he's got them all condensed into a a few pages.
How many pages?
I don't know exactly here.
Four.
Twenty-five pages.
That's pretty condensed.
But so let's and then there's a whole lot of misunderstanding about these chapters out there.
Probably because they're so condensed.
People think that Heidegger somehow rejects the correspondence theory of truth.
He doesn't think that when I say there I'm leaning on a lectern, that that somehow corresponds to the fact that I'm leaning on a lectern, and that he doesn't reject the correspondence theory of truth.
He wants to fix it.
He thinks there's something wrong with the correspondence theory of truth that the whole tradition has come up with and worked out.
But he thinks that there is a way in which truth does, is correspondence, everyday ontic truth is correspondence.
And he's going to try to give you the phenomenology of that and then show you why the theory of the correspondence theory of truth doesn't work.
And then he's going to introduce an even more primordial understanding of truth.
This is all the outline for today.
And then, and the primordial understanding is unconcealedness or disclosing, which has been around all the time, but now it's going to be called primordial truth.
And finally, he's got to give you a story, which I may not get to today, of, well, if primordial truth is disclosing, something must be closed.
Or if it's uncovering, somehow everything that you can say truths about must somehow, to begin with, be covered up.
So he has to tell you a lot about untruth and the covered, the necessary structural covered upness of experience.
So that then you'll understand why primordial truth has to be uncovering.
If I cover all that today, that will be just fine.
So now to start with, the critique of the traditional theory of truth as agreement or correspondence, which means the correspondence, and this is the part that's going to turn out to be wrong, the correspondence of representations, that is, propositions, beliefs, assertions with states of affairs in the world.
That version of correspondence is what he's going to criticize.
But to start with, truth with correspondence is okay if you think of it in the way that Heidegger does, that somebody who holds a belief or makes an assertion succeeds in directing his or her thoughts or words or beliefs in a way that captures the way things are in themselves.
We're going to go over that.
That's a kind of correspondence view about truth, which is just fine.
It's pointing out things as they are in themselves.
That's the notion of takes takes the notion of correspondence and agreement and turns it into a notion of uncovering, though it isn't denying it, it's just making clearer what is really involved in making true assertions.
So on 261, we're now going to be running around 261 for quite a while.
So there he says, and I'm just explaining this sort of condensed thing right below, above 219 in the margin, that paragraph.
To say that an assertion is true signifies that it uncovers the entity that it's about.
It covers the entity it's about as that entity is in itself.
Such an assertion points out, lets the entity be seen, that is, that's apophensis, I presume.
It's an apophantic assertion, which means it lets the entity be seen in its uncoveredness.
The being true of the assertion must be understood as being uncovering.
That is, the activity of making the assertion is the activity of uncovering.
That's what then enables you to have an assertion that lets the entity be seen.
So the being true of the assertion is, I think it'd be better if it was, it was, is to be uncovering.
Being there with a capital B and all that makes that seem sort of incomprehensible.
So he's saying what makes it true is that it uncovers, makes the assertion true.
Thus, truth has by no means the structure of an agreement between knowing and the object in the sense of a likening of one entity, the subject, to another, the object.
So now we have to sort of stop for a minute and understand.
Some lights just go on.
And understand that what's going on here.
So what I'm skipping ahead because I decided I should say something that I wanted to say later right now.
What's being repudiated or denied or blocked in this is that this agreement amounts to something inner in the mind agreeing with or being similar to, in some way connecting with, something outer in the external world.
That is, if you think that way, you do what Heidegger calls slipping in a representation in the story that you're just hearing about making an assertion that points out something as it is in itself.
He talks about this on 260, the slipping in of an assertion, and I'll explain that.
But I want to see the whole correspondence theory is some version of the subject-object view.
So naturally, Heidegger's going to take it on and try to fix it by getting the subject-objectness out of it and preserving the revealing of something side of it.
But he's talking on so about eight lines from the bottom of 260.
The asserting, which merely represents, is related in a sense that is its own to the picture on the wall.
We'll get back to the picture on the wall.
Let me just skip the sentence.
Any interpretation in which something else that is between the assertion and the picture in this case, any interpretation in which something else is here slipped in as what one supposedly has in mind in an assertion, that assertion that represents belies the phenomenal facts of the case as to that about which the assertion gets made.
Asserting is a way of being towards the thing itself that is.
That's the summing up of what I just said, that I wanted to relate it to the inner-outer talk.
In fact, even more, because I feel that after all this time in the course, you must feel at home, sort of at least, with the subject-object enemy, which is the Cartesianism, which is always around, and you must feel at home as to sort of what's going to be done with it.
It's always going to be transformed into some kind of skillful coping or skillful dealing story and something about the background.
So that's going to happen to truth, too.
It's going to end up to have to do with skillful dealing in the background, but we're not ready quite for that.
So look at 258, where he's talking about this at the bottom, four lines from the bottom, and clarifying the truth relation.
We must notice also what's peculiar to the terms of this relation with regards to what to do, to what do intellectus and re agree?
That is the mind and the thing.
That's the intellectus and the re.
That's just the medieval way of putting it.
So, and the idea is that there's correspondence or agreement.
And how do they correspond or agree?
In their kind of being and in their essential content, do they give us anything at all with regard to which they can agree?
If it is along some water because I knew, having just had a cold, that I would start coughing.
Oh, I stopped coughing.
Because if it's impossible for intellectus and re to be equal because they're not of the same species, are they then perhaps similar?
But knowledge is still supposed to give the thing just as it is, and so forth.
So if you think about it, you can't understand how a proposition or a statement, an assertion, or something in your mind like a belief can correspond to or be similar to a state of affairs or a thing with properties in the world.
That's just, if you're so used to it, it sounds like it's perfectly all right.
But Heidegger thinks it's perfectly incomprehensible.
He says a little further, I'm still at the top of 259.
In what way is this relation possible as a relation between intellectus and re?
From these questions, it becomes plain that to clarify the structure of truth, it's not enough to presuppose the relational totality.
We must go back and inquire into the context of being to provide support for this totality.
Well, the context of being, I think he means the understanding of subjects and objects.
We have to go back to the inner-outer, and then from there, get a new story about being, namely, again, something to do with dealing and something to do with background, that will make us able to understand what corresponds to what and how that works.
So and now I'm back to 261.
I backed up there to give you his running start for that, what we read on 261.
So Heidegger's going to give you a phenomenologic, a kind of phenomenological description of a true assertion that relates to the world.
He's going to give you two, in fact.
He's going to give you a story about how assertions in general relate to the world.
And then he's going to give you an example of how a particular person relates, a particular assertion made by some particular person relates to some particular something in the world.
So starting with the general claim on 261 I think I just read that.
Yeah.
Okay.
What I was going to read again is that just this general statement that it's a question of uncovering and so forth.
That's not, there's nothing more I have to say about that.
And that's not really phenomenological.
I don't know why I said it was.
I guess, I'm trying to see if what if anywhere.
Maybe at the top of 261 is something like the phenomenological description of the way assertions work in general.
Let's try it.
Second line.
What comes up for confirmation is that this entity is pointed out by the asserting.
I think you don't need all of that by the being in which the assertion is made, which is.
So it's pointed out by the assertion.
If I went back and that's what I found in the translation.
Let me try again then.
What comes up for confirmation is that this entity is pointed out by the assertion as the assertion in its role as being towards what is put forward in the assertion.
Thus, what is to be confirmed is that such being uncovers the entity toward which it is, which gets demonstrated, what gets demonstrated is the being and covering of the assertion.
Skipping a sentence.
The entity itself, which one has in mind, shows itself just as it is in itself.
That is to say, it shows that it in itself sameness is just as it gets pointed out in the assertion as being, just as it gets uncovered as being.
Yeah, all that is a general description of the phenomena of making true assertions about things.
And then again, just I'll bore you with this, but you've got to keep, you always have to know the view that's being rejected.
And since the view that's being rejected here, the correspondence view, is something so obvious to everybody in our Cartesian time, that I've got to keep pointing out that that is, he's rejecting the next sentence.
Representations do not get compared, either among themselves or in relation to the real thing.
What is to be demonstrated is not an agreement of knowing with its object, still less of the psychical with the physical, but neither is it an agreement between contents of consciousness among themselves.
That is, it's not a correspondence theory, and he just throws in it's not a coherence theory either, where truth is something where that fits in with all the rest of what you already believe.
Okay, now the interesting, more fun thing is his example.
Now he's going to give you, just say, okay, look at the phenomena.
And I brought in a paragraph from the metaphysical foundations of logic on page 125.
It's not something you're likely to want to go back and look at because it's something very similar to what's in here.
But it's fun because it's a course.
So here he is in the classroom, like us.
And he says, if someone here in the classroom, you can just, I'll just be him, channel him.
If someone here in the classroom makes the assertion, the board is green, it says black here, but we have to bring it up to context.
The board is green and does so in the immediately given context of a question and answer, to what are we then directed in interpreting the assertion?
The assertion, namely, the board is green.
Perhaps, now he's going to give you a lot of wrong answers.
Perhaps to the phonetic articulation or to the representation which the assertion makes and for which the uttered sounds are signs.
No, rather we are directed to the board itself here on the wall, and precisely in perceiving this board, or rather in making the board present in thinking about it, and in nothing else, we participate in and repeat the making of the assertion.
That which gives itself immediately in the assertion is that about which it asserts.
That's again, don't slip anything in.
If I make the assertion that the board is green, then my assertion refers directly to the board.
It isn't, there's no need to have any other entity in looking.
And if there is another entity slipped in, then of course you'd never be able to understand how that entity corresponds to or agrees with the blackboard.
So you better not slip another entity in.
There's something sort of, I don't know, worrying about you all.
This seems so strange or something or so obvious.
Anybody have any questions or problems?
Maybe this represents, maybe your looks, is a look of concentration and not of something else.
Yes.
Oh, well, yes, I thought I'd said it already, but it doesn't.
What I'm slipping in, if I do it wrong, is a mental something called intentional content if you're Searle or called an OEMA if you're Husserl.
Something in the mind, in my mind, which agrees with and corresponds to something there, namely the green board.
That's what you're slipping in, because all you really got is the assertion, the board is green, and there it is, the board is green, and you don't need anything else.
And then, moreover, if you tried to use anything else, it wouldn't work anyway.
There's nothing that can get you from, if you think that you need something to get you from what's inside your mind to what's out there in the world, you're lost.
That's the inner-outer story.
And the inner-outer story, we just got so used to it, it doesn't bother us anymore.
But it bothers Heidegger that we don't understand that at all.
So, what we do understand, just the simple phenomenon, it's no puzzle, it's not it's that I can say these things to you and we can all see the blackboard and that it's green.
That's I think I'm glad you asked.
I mean, you're looking unsatisfied, however.
That's interesting.
You're not.
You're just traumatized.
Okay.
Anything else?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
That's right.
Exactly.
It indicates or points out, you could say.
He doesn't use those terms, but it points out the board as it is, yes.
Confirmation signifies the entity showing itself in its self-sayness.
That was part of that.
It seems so obvious I don't know.
I mean, that I am telling the truth.
That's confirmation.
It depends on the entity, namely the green blackboard, showing itself as a green blackboard.
That's just sort of, there's nothing puzzling about it, I don't think.
But if you can make me puzzle, I'll be happy.
Yeah, that yeah, showing itself as green.
That's all.
I mean, it's just showing itself as it is.
Now, that's going to turn out to be much more problematic than I'm letting on right now, because he's going to start telling you a story about the picture although behind me is crooked in a minute.
And that, I think, raises very interesting issues.
But for the time being, I don't see anything problematic about that.
It'd have to be a really weird situation if all the light in the room was green and the blackboard was really white or something, and somebody was questioning the truth of my assertion by saying that the blackboard isn't green, then we'd have a problem.
But since everybody's seeing the blackboard is green and I'm saying it's green, that's just the basic phenomena.
I don't see a problem.
Oh, that it's self-sameness.
The truth isn't it, the truth isn't.
Yeah, but its self-sameness isn't the truth part.
It's that my assertion points it out as it is in itself.
It would be a coherence theory of truth if somehow I wasn't, I mean, if the truth belongs to the pointing out, and there's no place for a coherence theory.
Now, and the self-sameness is just a way of saying it's green.
It doesn't take, it doesn't have to cohere with anything else to be green.
It has to cohere with itself to be green, but that doesn't really add anything, I don't think.
Yeah.
Well, what if they were?
Then they wouldn't see it.
Then would my assertion become untrue?
That would be interesting.
I'm pointing it out as green, and nobody sees it as green.
Huh.
I've got to think about that.
I think, oh boy, I like that.
That's hard.
It's like something I was going to talk about in about an hour, about whether Newtonian laws are true before and after Newton's around to point them out, particularly before, let's talk.
And because I want to say, and Heidegger, you've got to keep close to common sense, otherwise you're almost surely getting it wrong.
The blackboard is green whether we're all colorblind or not.
It turns out that that's the first thing you've got to preserve.
So I'll remind you and I'll go back to the Newtonian thing.
If nobody's pointing out gravity is pulling things down in Athens, because Newton hasn't been around yet, Heidegger says, then you can't say that there's anybody making any true statements about falling things at that point.
However, because he's perfectly sensible, he says, nonetheless, it's true that things are obeying the laws of gravity already and all the time, if Newton is telling the truth.
It's just that, I got to be careful.
And I've got to use different words than true.
Things are obeying Newton's laws in Athens all the time, though there isn't any truth involved at all, one way or the other, because truth is a relation between an assertion and what it points out.
And there's nobody around making any assertions about gravity that point anything out.
So though everything is obeying the laws of gravity, there isn't any assertions being made that are true about it.
You standing here can say now that Newton's done his job, but it was true all along.
And that's right, that only after Newton has done his job, and now you can point out gravity and you see that there's always been gravity.
It's slightly weird, and you're putting your finger on what's weird, and I'm trying to get used to what's weird.
So if you're all colorblind and I say the blackboard is green, am I colorblind in your example too, or everybody else is, but I'm not?
I think it's two different interesting issues.
Let's first, I see it's colorblind, and I see it's green, and I point it out it's green, and none of you see it's green, then certainly my assertion is still true, isn't it?
It points out the blackboard as it is in itself, namely green.
Now we say, but now if we're all colorblind and I say the blackboard is green, I think it's still true, because it still points out the blackboard as it is in itself.
It doesn't, I mean, to be true, it doesn't have to correspond to your experience.
That sounds too inner.
It has to correspond to the object.
And you can make true, I mean, if maybe I would understand that everybody was colorblind, and I'd say that anyway, and it would be true anyway, because I had done some other test on it, or because somebody else who wasn't colorblind said so.
Go ahead, if you can make it more problematic.
Yeah.
Why are you thinking people because it's true anyway?
Everybody lives in different ways.
Why do you have the previous position of saying color support?
That sounds like an ontic question.
Why do I have, so to speak, right to say that it's green?
I think that's a question about science has a view about that, what wavelength is coming off it, but that isn't enough because you can create illusions in which you can have green with no green wavelength coming off it.
What you have to say is, whatever our procedures are for objectively determining and reaching agreement on the property of it, that's the property it's got.
It certainly isn't going to stop being green just because a bunch of people's brains don't make it see it as green, nor is it going to be green just because, say, my brain is so fixed up that it sees it as green.
There's got to be objectivity and agreement.
I don't see why Heidegger is going to deny that.
Now, Curtis, you've got a view about this.
I mean, walking through the room and not finding space, let's do the board of things.
You've got a situation where even the person, the observer is saying the board is green.
There's those three words might be not like what just is very peculiar, but special case, but the general case is that we have agreed ways of determining objectively what the situation is or what the object is and so forth.
And I don't we're agreeing, I think.
And Heidegger's at a level of abstraction where he isn't interested in that or caring about it.
What he cares about is that, however, things do have objective characteristics, and assertions are true when they point the things out as they are, namely as having those characteristics.
That's at that level of abstraction.
Yeah.
Second line?
Oh, he does, he does, but we haven't got there yet.
Okay, yeah.
Oh, there's a that's the most that's the more exciting part.
This is really rather boring, but still has to go, we have to go through it.
But his view about primordial truth is really exciting and weird and plausible and new stuff.
But anyway, so everybody's happy now?
Tyler, is your hand up or you're scratching your forehead?
Well, but you're getting to the background.
I mean, that all he's saying so far is in a kind of decontextualized way, my assertion can correspond to the object.
But, and both of you are sort of pushing him toward the primordial truth, that it's not, you can make easily think of cases in which the background skill or background interest determines what the properties are.
And that's being ignored right now.
And he's going to say later, you really, it's always in terms of our skills, in terms of the context, and in terms of the purposes that you can make these true assertions.
And that's really what's being left out in the correspondence theory.
He's telling you sort of the simple phenomena of the correspondence theory.
He's not going to go back on it.
It's true.
The assertion is about whatever it's about, and it's true if what it's about is in itself that way.
But generally, things sort of aren't in themselves anyway in such a simple way.
I mean, he's got an easy case with the blackboard and screen.
I'll give you a case in a second in which you can see how much he has to leave out to get this simple case and how misleading it is to think that this could be an adequate account of true assertions.
There's a whole he's interested in this simply because really, I don't know how I put it, he thinks that this story about correspondence he's telling you is the truth about the phenomenon.
But he also thinks that it leaves out a much more important aspect of this whole truth-telling situation than we've even touched on yet.
And that's what you're asking about, and he's asking about.
Now you're going to do it too.
The black green things to be sunserving.
Again, we've got, but that's what I, I mean, that's what seems ontic.
We've got practices for finding out whether the black counts as green.
We could bring a color chip from a paint store and hold it up, and we could say, well, look, the blackboard is green 13.
And we'd all, and why would we all agree?
Because we've got practices like that, for agreeing if we have to on what color something is.
That's terribly ontic.
I mean, surely, that's what I said.
We've all got practices for sort of settling the question of the facts.
And but there is a very peculiar thing going on.
I don't think maybe you're pointing to it.
I can't tell.
But I'm going to take it that you're pointing to it.
And I'm going to say there is a sense in which the blackboard is green is a too simple example.
I'll give you one that sounds just as simple, and I make it very complicated in a minute.
But I saw one other hand, yeah.
And a couple of sections here about character length.
It sounds like that's one of the things we don't want to put in because of scientific exploitation.
But I'm curious as to where in this thing does our when you made mistakes, it immediately occurred to me as not very because of what they're talking about.
It's not true that the blackboard is green?
That's very peculiar.
Well, because of these issues, maybe that therefore finds for the people doing now interesting is gravity.
Well, wait, look, okay, put, I understand, put gravity aside.
That's the interesting Newton thing gets raises this whole thing to a different level of theory and science.
And I don't want to do that yet.
The greenness I'm talking about, as I said, isn't a certain wavelength coming out of there.
That's why I said it's a color patch thing, which you can do without any commitment to any theory of color and the physics of color and of the brain.
But let me give you an example, one of mine, and then I'll show you that Heidegger's really got the same example in view.
But this one, I had this fuss with Charles Taylor at one point, in which he said, Well, it's a simple fact that there are 13 chairs in the room.
And I began to think about that, and it didn't seem simple at all anymore.
And that's just probably a Wittgensteinian point, but I'm not sure.
But because you can say, Well, what about suppose these chairs are in boxes, but suppose you're just about to give a lecture in there?
Then, if you ask, Are there 13 chairs in the room, and somebody says yes, and when they go in there, there's no place to sit?
That seems like they've misled you.
Or if there are 13 chairs, six of which are broken, then if your purpose again is to seek the class, then it isn't a helpful, even though it's sort of true that there are 13 chairs in the room.
You mean 13 chairs that work.
Or you can make more examples too.
But anyway, the idea is that the context determines even something as seemingly settled as how many chairs there are in the room.
There could also be chairs in the room that were museum-like chairs that nobody was allowed to sit on.
I mean, will they count as chairs in the room?
Well, they will, for some purposes, and in some contexts, and not others.
But so that begins to show, it seems to me, that the purposes might determine what counts as how many chairs there are in the room.
And it looks like I am not very good at imagining things.
You could go on and on imagining ways in which there are and are not 13 chairs in the room, and so forth.
But let's skip, you recognize this as Heidegger's got his own example.
Ah, Stephen, yeah?
One question.
In what way is this a corresponding theory of the green state?
If assertions don't have representational content, what is corresponding to the object?
What's corresponding to the object is the assertion.
And it's corresponding to the object.
If I assert that the blackboard is green, what corresponds to the assertion is that the blackboard is green.
You don't need any representation.
But it's always a good thing to try.
I mean, try to, it's hard to get out of a Cartesian way of thinking.
But there's no reason to bring mental representations into this story at all.
The assertion is doing fine to just point out the blackboard, which is also doing fine, without any representations of either one.
Their blackboard isn't a representation, it's a blackboard.
And the assertion is a sort of representation.
It's a linguistic something or other.
But it doesn't need any mental representation.
And it's not a bunch of phonetic noises on which we have to build some kind of representation.
Heidegger would, of course, say that's just bad cognitivism.
The assertion just is something we all understand and make.
But I want to go for a different direction now.
Namely, do you recognize Heidegger's example in it here?
In his classroom, he's got his blackboard.
But let me read what he says right after the blackboard.
He makes a general claim.
And then I'm going to switch to his book example.
The meaning of an assertion, I'm reading now, right after the blackboard.
The meaning of an assertion then is to be cashed out in terms of that towards which the speaker and hearer of the assertion are directed through the assertion.
The relation between an assertion and the world is thus not a relation of representation, according to Heidegger.
No, I stuck at it.
It's not a representation, but a relation of indication.
I mean, as if she was talking to Stephen there.
But now, remember, his example is that you have your back toward the wall, and you make the assertion that the picture on the wall is crooked.
I just, I have this idea, I'm sort of spelling out this more than Heidegger does.
I think that there are three sort of background qualifications that you have to have to be able to sort of fix what you're talking about and how the assertion works.
And we've seen one with the chairs, sort of what you're trying to do with whatever you're talking about might turn out to determine how many of whatever's there are.
But now, what's going on with the picture behind you?
It's crooked.
Well, I think two more qualifications are in there.
One is that you've got to have what Charles Taylor calls an epistemological skill.
He writes about this picture example.
And he has his example of Johnny, and you send Johnny into the room and you ask him, is the picture crooked?
And Johnny has an epistemological skill, namely, and this is more Merleau-Ponty than Heidegger, though Heidegger wouldn't disagree, namely, he knows how to get the light right and to get the distance to the picture right and to stand on his feet and not lie down and look at it and so forth.
So he knows how to tell whether a picture is crooked.
That's a skill.
And when he, with his skill, says it's askew, then he gets it right.
And that's bringing, we are always bringing in that kind of skill whenever we're, I mean, it's much hidden in the back, in the blackboard one, but it's there too.
I'm sure we could figure it out.
But I want to think of something.
I was about to say something just a second.
Oh, yeah.
Just the other half of Taylor is to say, and Johnny doesn't have the skill.
If you'll say, go in and tell me whether the picture on the wall in the other room is a Matisse picture, then Johnny lacks that skill.
So you can see that it's a skill to be able to tell if the blackboard is crooked.
He has that one.
Well, my favorite one is that there's also a kind of not an epistemological skill, but a specific skill that's required.
And Heidegger doesn't seem to see this at all or doesn't care.
But if you ask somebody, is the picture on the wall crooked, then if they've got the skill, say, of an architect in postmodern houses, they may tell you it's perfectly straight.
Whereas if they're some earthquake insurance company coming to tell you whether the earthquake has damaged your wall, they have a different view about whether it's crooked.
And if it's a stella, a painter that some of you probably know, or I don't even know what you call a painter anymore, but making sort of things which come outside the frame in all directions, so you can't tell whether they're right side up or upside down, let alone whether they're crooked, then you'd have to have that kind of skill to be able to answer this question.
And if you're an architect, you know, you would then know how all the walls are supposed to work together.
You can get these situations where the picture looks crooked and it isn't really, or whether it really is crooked and doesn't look crooked.
There are all kinds of possibilities.
And that means that you need to be a kind of coping expert and have familiarity with pictures and walls and rooms before you can just march in and answer the question: is the picture behind me crooked?
Now, I'm sure Heidegger doesn't object to that.
He just isn't talking about that at this point.
He's making it like the blackboard.
But when I did the blackboard, you all had this sort of intuition of various sorts that that wasn't the whole story.
And if you change it to the picture example, you can see that it isn't the whole story.
It's not easy just to say that my assertion, the picture on the wall is crooked, corresponds to the state of affairs just as it is, whether the picture is crooked or not.
The state of affairs of whether the picture is crooked or not, in the case I just invented, isn't some objective fact that you can, without any skill and any familiarity, just discover.
There is no simple right answer to whether the story, whether the picture on the wall, the stellar on the wall in this postmodern house is crooked.
But that's all right.
I mean, in fact, that's what Heidegger wants.
He wants to go on from the example, the classroom example, or his picture example, to bring in what I've been sort of smuggling in, which is a whole lot of background, including, I just smuggled in, familiarity with rooms, which have to be already there in place before you can just make a true assertion that the picture on the wall is crooked.
Let me catch up where I am now.
So on 260.
That's the picture.
Just so I mean, you know where it's over at the bottom of 260, I read it.
What one has in mind is the real picture and nothing else, any interpretation and so forth and so forth.
That he doesn't go on and tell you a whole story about crooked, but he will in a minute.
So something like that.
So I'm just going to sum up.
I mean, I'm going to go on to the primordial issue in a second, but let's just sum this up.
So Heidegger isn't against the correspondence theory of truth.
You who are reading the secondary sources, if any of you are, I haven't really asked myself this.
Do they all think that he's trying to get rid of the Heidegger's rejecting the correspondence theories?
Lots of people do.
Any of you read anything that I have assigned that disagrees with me on this?
Good.
How many are reading this?
I mean, you shouldn't be.
I mean, you'd be much better off reading just the Heidegger over and over, day and night.
But how many are reading the background books?
Very few.
One.
Which one?
Blattner, I suppose.
It's worth reading the Blattner book.
And Blattner's not going to make this mistake, I'm sure.
Well, I'm pretty confident.
Okay.
But I want to now, so Heidegger sums it up.
Let me see now where we are.
261.
Well, now that I reread this sentence, after all that interesting discussion, I think you can see that people were on the track of thinking that was a little too simple to say, as he does eight lines down, and he knows it's simple.
The entity itself, which one has in mind, shows itself just as it is in itself.
That is to say, it shows that it is, that it in itself sameness is just as it gets pointed out in the assertion as being, just as it gets uncovered as being.
Well, that's going to turn out to be too simple.
But that's a kind of first-level ontic story about truth.
And it tells you generally what happens when an assertion captures the way things are.
That is, when an assertion or a belief is true.
And it tells you, and I'm just going to summing up what this simple example tells you before we go on to the fun one.
It tells you also that assertions are equipment for pointing out things.
So on 267, and we've been assuming it's equipment for pointing out things.
But it's something you have ready to hand, like equipment, to point out things like green blackboards or crooked pictures.
About eight lines down on 267.
The assertion expressed is something ready to hand, and in such a way that as something by which uncoveredness is preserved, it has in itself a relation to the entities uncovered.
So now it turns out assertions are, skipping a little, the assertion is something ready to hand.
The entities to which it is related as something that uncovers are either ready to hand or present at hand within the world, and so forth.
But mainly, assertions are then equipment for indicating.
And that's fine.
And then 267, again, no more mental or ideal entities.
I think maybe we've read this already, or if we haven't, it isn't something we need to read right now.
I shouldn't be reading that right now.
It's my mistake.
I mean, because there is a story on 267, which we're going to have to come back to today or probably, maybe next time, where he's going to derive the kind of correspondence theory of truth that traditional philosophers have believed in, which is just not to be mysterious, that present-at-hand assertions have a present-at-hand relation, namely correspondence, to present-at-hand states of affairs.
He's going to say that's not wrong, that we can get there step by step from the ready-to-hand to the unready-to-hand to the present-at-hand with assertions, just like you can with baseballs or what is his when we do it with hammers.
But I want to save that.
That doesn't really belong in my current discussion.
All we need finally is that pointing about things as they are as a kind of relation of uncovering, and that's what we've been talking about.
So back to 261, and that basic quote which I've read already, the uncovering the entity as it is in itself, is as far as we've gotten.
So now, having had, but now we're ready to go on to something which he calls primordial true.
That's already a kind of very unfortunate, misleading way to call it.
I mean, I've been saying, look, the background plays a role in what statements are true about the picture on the wall or the chairs in the room.
And it turns out to be epistemological skill and purposes and familiarity with that kind of object in that kind of situation.
All of that adds up to a lot of background that has to be in place before you can make these kind of assertions.
It's just that if everybody shares the background, like the students and the blackboard, you don't notice it.
But if it turns out to be a funny kind of thing, like pictures in postmodern houses, where most people don't share the background, then you notice that there is a lot of background involved.
And so far, so good.
And then Heidegger makes this alarming and crazy move, which it took him about 50 years to admit that he had made a big mistake.
He's a terminological mistake.
He calls this background primordial truth.
And that's because, I've said this before, when we did talk, when we did discourse, that primordial discourse was something like the, never mind, let's not fall into any further problems about discourse.
The primordial always for Heidegger means the condition, primordial X is always the condition of the possibility of X.
Or, it's more, I'm putting it oddly, Heidegger reserves the right to name primordial X, whatever he discovers, is the condition of the possibility of X.
That is, now, if it turns out that the background familiarity is the condition of the possibility of using assertions to point things out as they are, then that background familiarity is going to be called primordial truth.
And why does Heidegger regret it?
Because everybody gets confused and was confused for years.
It was only in the last thing, I think, that he published that he said he regretted his tendency, his methodological principle that you should always name the condition of the possibility of X primordial X because it had misled people about truth.
And what people thought was, well, truth is really background stuff, and it isn't really correspondence, because it looks like, I mean, there are books about Heidegger's two notions of truth, and which one is the one he really believes, and which one does he think, you know, truth is, and people get all worried and upset about that.
But there's only one notion of truth, really, correspondence, as correctly explained by, which we've said over and over.
And then there is a big story about the conditions of the possibility of truth.
And if he hadn't called it truth, everything would have been all right.
And so you have to just keep in mind that there are always these two kinds of meanings of truth.
You could make one small and one capital or something that suggests they're two different words.
And there aren't two different words.
They're just one word, Barheid.
And he just uses it in two different ways.
Okay, so we're making the transition to an ontological level in which there is the condition of the possibility of making true assertion.
And whatever goes on on that level, Heidegger's going to call primordial truth.
And the better thing would have been to call it other names he gives it.
Disclosing is going on there, or unconcealment is going on.
That's what the background gives you.
There's a distinction just to get you to notice it.
It took me years to notice it.
Discovering is the ontic story.
So you can discover that the blackboard is green or the picture is crooked.
Disclosing is his name for the ontological background conditions, roughly familiarity, which makes discovering possible.
So if you don't know anything about architecture and modern pictures, then you haven't got the disclosing practices that enable you to make, to discover whether the picture is crooked or not.
Once you get used to it, it's simple, but you've got to keep your eye on the way he's using these weird terms.
So at the bottom of 261, just this paragraph I've been reading over and over follows the following paragraph, which is now what I've been saying over and over.
Being true as to be uncovering.
And that's uncovering is the, I never even put that down.
So there's two things: there's discovering and uncovering.
They mean the same thing, dis and un.
And sometimes we get one and sometimes we get the other.
But now we're going to, we're moving from discovering and uncovering, which is blackboards and pictures, to disclosing and unconcealing.
And so those are two words for the same thing.
So being true as to be uncovering is in turn ontologically possible only on the basis of being in the world.
Now we're at this background level.
This later phenomenon, which we have known as the basic state of Dasein, is the foundation for the primordial phenomenon of truth.
You should just cross out primordial, I mean, if you want to keep your wits.
But you've got to say something like foundational or basic, which would be a better thing to say.
And on the next page, he gets to the primordial phenomenon of truth, and then he's going to show you the way that traditional understanding of truth presupposes and depends on this primordial one.
That's what you, again, were all forcing me to try to think about.
I mean, even with the chairs in the room, the discovery and uncovering of how many chairs in the room turns out to be a lot of familiarity with chairs and rooms and lecturing and so forth.
And that's what he's now going to tell you.
And so in 263, he's telling it all over the place.
And I'm going to read a lot.
Because that's his real contribution.
As I kept saying, it's sort of nice to sort of take on correspondence and sort of assert the phenomena in a kind of direct, simple, un-Cartesian way.
But it's important for Heidegger to say that there couldn't be correspondence if there weren't for this more primordial background coping, which is being in the world.
And now he's going to say it over and over on 263.
And I'm starting with the first, second full paragraph.
Being true as being uncovering is a way of being for Dasein.
What makes this very uncovering possible must necessarily be called true in a still more primordial sense.
That's this funny move with the word true.
The most primordial phenomenon of truth is first shown by the existential ontological foundations of uncovering.
Now we're going to find out more about what they are, skipping a little to the skip a paragraph.
Now, really important stuff happens.
Our earlier analysis of the worldhood of the world and of entities within the world has shown, however, that the uncoveredness of entities within the world is grounded in the world's disclosedness.
You're getting all these terms there now.
But disclosedness is that basic character of Dasein according to which it is its there.
That is, remember, that is being in the world from some point of view.
Disclosedness is constituted by, and here comes one of those three things that you keep your eye open for.
It's already got this one on my chart.
Disclosedness is constituted by disposedness, understanding, and discourse.
Discourse, there, you know, sometimes discourse is the third one, and sometimes falling is the third one, and Heidegger's pretty confused about that.
This one has got to, and pertains primordially to the world, to being in, and to the self.
Of course, they all have that structure.
And now get the care structure thrown in there too.
This is a big summary, this paragraph.
In its very structure, care is ahead of itself.
That's the understanding part.
Being already in a world, that should be the falling part, but here it's the discourse part.
As being, no, being already, no, you have to read more, sorry.
Being ahead of itself as, now, being already in the world as being along, amidst entities within the world.
That's the falling part.
And it shouldn't be the discourse.
And this structure, and in this structure, the disclosedness of Dasein lies hidden.
Wait a minute, what am I doing here?
It's ahead of itself is understanding.
Already in is.
Ah, no, I misread it.
Cancel what I just said.
Erase it.
This is what happens in the podcast.
Now, eternally, everybody's going to be confused about this.
And all over the world.
And other galaxies, even.
But let's get it straight.
I'll try it again.
In its very structure, care is ahead of itself, that's understanding, pressing into possibilities.
Being already in the world, that's throwingness.
That's the whatever disposedness and all that you have.
As being alongside entities within the world, that's coping.
Being amidst entities within the world.
And again, I keep wanting to say that should be called falling by his definitions.
And he does in Division II, but here he got disclosedness mixed in there.
I'm sorry, got what am I trying to say, discourse mixed in there.
But what you really want is understanding into the future, throwingness from the past, and coping in the present.
If you keep in mind all the time that these three these threefolds aren't just any old threefold, there are the threefold structure of temporality that he's got up his sleeve, which I'm giving you a secret heads up on, then that threefold structure, you can always map it.
Okay, now let's see where I'm supposed to be.
Then go on.
Oh, I want to go a little further.
In its very structure, care is, no, I read that.
Okay.
Disclosedness, okay.
Hence, only with Dasein's disclosedness is the most primordial phenomenon of truth attained.
And you have to translate that, is the most primordial phenomenon that makes truth, of which there is only one kind, namely correspondence, attained.
It just only confuses things.
But there is, I mean, don't let me talk you out of the phenomenon.
There is the important phenomenon that if it isn't for the background skill of Dasein being in a world and throwing into it and dealing with things right now in the pursuit of its ultimate for the sake of which, all the stuff he said earlier, if it weren't for all that stuff, you couldn't have the kind of set of distinguishing of a particular state of affairs, like the blackboard being green, and a particular assertion, like saying the blackboard is green.
That presupposes all of the rest of this stuff.
And that's his important point.
That's his criticism.
That's his real criticism of the correspondence theory, is that it thinks that all it's got to do is tell you about correspondence.
And in fact, the correspondence theory is wrong because the real story about truth must still already bring in and understand that there is this background condition necessary for being able to make any true assertions.
Now, so ontological truth, ontological, primordial, I'm squeamish about it, but I'll have to talk Heidegger jargon from now on.
So I will just say something like this: quotes truth.
Ontological, primordial, that kind of thing called truth, makes ontic truth, real truth, possible.
Propositional truth, that's the real ordinary kind, depends on a prior disclosure of the entities in the world.
That's right, which Heidegger calls primordial truth, unfortunately.
So, or in simple Heidegger, sorry, in simple Dreyfus talk, ontic truth requires the background.
And that's what I've been talking about.
And then, so what I just wrote it again: what counts as a skew for the picture depends on whether you're cleaning house, whether there's been an earthquake, whether you're hanging the picture, whether it's a stella, whether you're an architect, and so forth.
And that's all familiarity and context.
And now comes the strange example from science.
I really like it because I think it reveals some deep understanding of science and how it works, and I think it casts light in a funny way on the fact that you're going to have to make the claim, it's going to follow from this, that you make a true statement in science, like Newton saying something about things fall because of gravity, you're going to have to do that on some kind of background.
And what he really has in mind there is, well, let me retell you the true phenomenon before you read the weird words, because this throws everybody off, including me, when I read it.
But I know what the phenomenon is, and you've got to hold on to that.
Remember, I say that a dozen times a day, and Heidegger says it at least once a chapter.
So take the take, how many know Kuhn's structure of scientific evolutions?
Good.
More would be even better.
Everybody should read it.
It's the Heideggerian book on what science is and how it works, although Kuhn never read Heidegger as far as I know.
Every once in a while I would run across him in some meeting and say, read Heidegger, and he would say, Yes, yes.
But that didn't seem to, there's never been a reference to Heidegger in any Kuhn thing that I've ever read.
But Kuhn has this idea that scientists can only get their, do their work and make their assertions, their theories, by relating to what he calls a paradigm.
And a paradigm, it used to seem to be an example.
And so he said Newton's Principia is a paradigm for Newtonian scientists.
That is, what they do, they understand as okay if it's similar to the paradigm.
Where similar doesn't mean it has a certain bunch of features in common, he very rightly says.
But similar is is rock bottom.
You just have to have a sense of whether it's similar or not to the paradigm.
And that isn't quite Heideggerian yet, although Heidegger's later going to come around to paradigms.
In later Heidegger, they're called works of art and sometimes gods.
But and he has different interests in what.
But both Kuhn and Heidegger think that there has to be some special thing which isn't just an ordinary thing in the world, but is this an example of how things uh what really counts as something uh I don't know, valuable or positive or something like that.
You maybe you could say, no, you can't say truth, that was only confusion.
Some counts as the right way of doing things or something in the world.
So the scientists, never mind the the works of art and so forth, the scientists know that they're doing good science if what they're doing corresponds to the paradigm.
And now, but then Kuhn comes around and changes it, right?
More into Heidegger.
When he decides, well, there's more to the paradigm than just the Principia book.
There is what he calls the disciplinary matrix.
That's the crucial thing.
The disciplinary matrix is the skills of the scientists, what problems they sets they had to solve when they were students, how they see the world so that the world looks totally different to a scientist.
I'll say, oh, he says, to take an example, uh uh a stone on a string that's swinging back and forth looks like to a n Newtonian scientist like a pendulum, but it looks to an Aristotelian like an object trying to get to its natural place, namely straight down, and having trouble for some reason or other that the Aristotles can't explain getting there.
Now, what's the story?
Why is all that important?
Because that says that Newton, unless you are inside the Newtonian paradigm, and even more generally, the Newtonian disciplinary matrix, which determines sort of how you see things, you can't make true Newtonian statements.
An Aristotelian can't understand anything about a pendulum.
And a Newtonian certainly doesn't know how to use this phrase seeking its natural place.
That just seems like craziness and weird words.
Particularly when for Aristotle, some things' natural place was up, like hot air balloons, and some things in the natural place were down.
It didn't even tell you, it didn't even map on gravity.
So, okay, what's the moral?
Then, the moral is you can't make Newtonian true statements until the Newtonian disciplinary matrix is in place.
And that's what Heidegger's trying to say, I think, in these weird claims at the bottom of 269, which I said I would get to.
He says, bottom paragraph: to say that before Newton his laws were neither true nor false cannot signify that before him there were no such entities as has been uncovered and pointed out by those laws.
Through Newton, the laws became true.
And with them, now, that's the funny kind of truth, I take it.
And this is what's so tricky.
Through Newton, though, well, no, wait, that's, no, that corresponds to reality.
That's the correspondence kind.
Through Newton, the laws became true.
And with them, entities became accessible in themselves.
That is, he could point out something as having a certain mass.
Once entities have been uncovered, they show themselves precisely as entities which beforehand they already were.
That's all the ontic story.
And what's the primordial truth story, the background story?
Well, that until Newton was around and Newton science was established and there was a disciplinary matrix so that people had Newtonian skills, they couldn't point out these entities or not point out these entities.
There was no access to these entities.
They couldn't be discovered or uncovered or gotten right or gotten wrong.
You could get the mass wrong or right.
You can't get the mass wrong or right.
You don't even know what mass is.
I mean, it's not just not knowing.
There's no way to know because nobody could tell you because there was no set of background practices in place relative to which something can be pointed out as having mass.
But it doesn't mean anything weird.
It doesn't mean that if gravity is true and Newton is true, it wasn't true at the time of Aristotle.
It was.
Let me read the first paragraph now and see if it fits in with this.
Dasein, the first meaning, the middle paragraph on 269, after the kind of being which truth possesses.
Dasein, as constituted by disclosedness, is essentially, you know, disclosiveness is the ontological one now.
Right?
I hope.
Always worried about getting discovery.
Yes.
Discovery and uncovering is the ontic one.
We're now in the disclosing and unconceiving.
Okay.
Dasein as constituted by disclosiveness is essentially in the truth.
Well, it's in the familiarity.
I mean, I don't know what to tell you.
I think it would help to cross out truth and put something like background or familiarity all the time.
It's in the background.
Disclosiveness is a kind of being which is essential to Dasein.
There is truth only insofar as Dasein is and as long as Dasein is.
Notice how that puts the blackboard as green and in a much more relativized place than it sounded like at the beginning of the lecture, that you can't even make that true assertion.
I mean, it wouldn't, as long as there was no Dasein around, that assertion would be neither true nor false, according to the way Heidegger's talking about it.
There is truth only insofar as Dasein is, and so long as Dasein is, that means so long as, I'm saying now, that means so long as there's being in the world, that means so long as there's a background of skills.
Entities are uncovered.
Now that's, remember, that means discovered.
This is now ontic talk.
Entities are uncovered only when Dasein is, and only as long as Dasein is, are they disclosed.
So you're not, so entities with mass are going to be discovered only insofar as Newtonians are, and so forth.
So Newton's laws, the principle of contradiction, any truth whatever, these are true only as long as Dasein is.
Now that makes people, it is so weird that I still have trouble getting my head around.
If truth means pointed out as they are in themselves, which is what it means, then if there isn't any Dasein and there isn't any understanding of whatever it is, say mass, then there can't be anything, any mass being pointed out as it is in itself, so there can't be any truth.
That's what he's claiming.
There are all kinds of statements are true only as long as Daseine is.
Before there was any Daseine, there was no truth.
That is, nothing was pointed out as it was, obviously.
Nor will there be any after Dasein is no more.
For in such a case, truth as disclosedness, uncoveredness, uncovering and uncoveredness cannot be.
Before Newton's laws were discovered, they were not true.
This is this hard thing to take.
But if you understand the way he's defining it, you can see that that's right.
It does not follow that they were false or even that they would become false if ontically no discoveredness were any longer possible.
I don't know what the next sentence.
I wasn't going to read, but let's see what happens if I read it.
Just as little does the restriction imply that the being true of truths has in any way been diminished.
Does this restriction?
Yeah, well, hang on.
He wants to say nothing he said sort of makes something which we thought was true count no longer as uh how does he put it?
The being true of truths.
He's not, well, I guess when he says he's not restricting the being true of truths, having just said if there was no Dasein, there wouldn't be any being true of truths.
He wants to say that we're here, and since Dasein is, then we can talk about gravity at the time of Aristotle and so forth.
And we, I mean, I haven't got the text here to back me up, but I'm sure he's saying that we are, and once we are, then, and we have, insofar as we have the relevant practices, we are able to make truth claims about everything that we would ever want to make truth claims about.
We, Newtonians, can make truth claims about the mass of objects in Athens and so forth.
But what he is restricting is some kind of some notion that assertions exist or propositions in some kind of eternal way, and states of affairs exist in some kind of internal way, and have some kind of correspondence to each other, whether Dasein exists or not.
That's all representational talk, and he's rejecting it.
Okay, I got as far as I thought I was going to get.
But I want to raise at least the next move, which is because we have five more minutes.
But first, more important than me is you all.
Have you followed that move from ontic to ontological quotes, truth?
And everybody with it.
Yeah, Curtis.
Well, there's certain gapsions.
The thing, as it's not clear.
If the room is all the color lines evolved to be heard of color lines.
And the onlybody else who hasn't seen the black dwarf and they've never learned about anybody who was green, it's probably not true.
So somebody who's not color lines was the blackboard and discovered the black hole is green in the first place.
Well, if I followed you, I think what happens is, and that's why it's so hard to think about it, you are thinking about it from the point of view, you know, as a Dasein who's already understood what it is for the blackboard to be green, and either what you're saying is true or false, you can't get yourself into the position in which you can't understand what it is to point out the blackboard is green, where you'd have to where you'd have to be to make, to see this weird Heidegger thing, that there wouldn't be any truth to the statement because there'd be nobody to make it, or better, no disciplinary matrix, no practices in which it made sense.
Well, maybe he did talk about he actually has to even blackboard, and that case is true.
With no background practices, then that's right.
It would be like somebody saying that things, that gravity is the in Athens before Newton.
That's right.
It would just be a meaningless bunch of noises, I think, for Heidegger Heidegger would say.
Not making the truth because lyrics outstream and just blacklisted screens, you know.
Okay, if everybody, I see, in a culture in which everybody's colorblind and so forth, because you have to get rid of the fact that if he's just in a culture in which that proposition would make sense to other people, but just not to them.
Not even false, right?
I mean, yeah, he, there would be no truth or falsehood in his assertion.
They would just be meaningless noises.
I guess that follows.
Okay, let me, I have three more minutes.
I just want to prepare you and make sure that when you're reading this, you know what to look for.
There's one interesting sort of issue that we haven't talked about, and that is the fact that there is the truth, and this used to worry me a lot.
It still worries me a lot, but it's an interesting thing to worry about.
If truth is disclosing, or even better, unconcealing, that is primordial truth, that is the background.
Never mind.
I mean, if there is such a thing, it has to be such a something as unconcealment and disclosing going on in the background familiarity and practices for there to be ontic truth.
Why do we call it unconcealment?
What's the concealing?
Why is it disclosing?
What's closed up?
Heidegger needs this whole story about untruth and the essential structure of untruth to explain why he would want to describe the practices that make true assertions possible as having to unconceal things.
I'm never sure quite what's going on there, but I think we have to talk about it.
So, what I'm going to talk about next time is, and it's in this same chapter, is Heidegger's view about untruth and the essential concealing function involved in the background practices that make true assertions possible.
The essential concealing function and the essential unconcealing function, which you could only have if there was already concealing going on.
Well, I don't expect you to understand that, and I'm hoping to understand it by Thursday, and you too.
Okay.