So the problem remains that I'm going to go on to spatiality now.
So we're going to talk about Heidegger's attempt to give an account of our experience of space and our way of being in space and found that, that is, show how that is intelligible on the basis of Dasein's basic existential structure.
And then at the end, show how you can, by leaving out more and more of the richness and intelligibility of existential space, you can get to Cartesian or more general, physical space.
Now, that's what he wants to do today.
So I will start by reading on 134.
I'm going to read a lot because I figure you couldn't really understand this stuff if I didn't read it sentence by sentence and explain it.
And I'm not always sure that I've got it right when I do explain it.
But sometimes things are simple.
Here on 134, he says what he's going to do.
Where?
Maybe it's not so simple.
Where is my.
Well, he's talking about Dasein isn't inside the world in the sense of included, the way chalk is included in a box.
I didn't talk about it, but in my commentary, I went on for several pages about the difference between two kinds of in, which you can say in English better than you can say in German.
And Heidegger would have been jealous.
We can talk about inclusion and involvement.
And inclusion is the way physical things are inside other physical things, and chairs are inside rooms and so forth.
And involvement in the world and with equipment and with other people is the kind of in that Dasein has.
And Heidegger is saying here at the bottom of 134 that he wants to say Dasein doesn't have the kind of in that objects have, substances, or the present at hand, to talk Heidegger, has.
And he did about ten lines down in section C there, which is what we're going to talk about, that's where it begins.
The aroundness of the environment and Dasein spatiality, he says, what it's on the left.
Yet, even if we deny that Dasein has any such insideness in a spatial receptacle, this does not in principle exclude it from having any spatiality at all.
It merely keeps open the way for seeing the kind of spatiality which is constituted for Dasein, then that's what he's going to set forth.
So if we're not in some sort of receptacle like called space, in which we are some place in it, then how are we spatial?
And now I want to lay out something, because it's sort of one of the few things that's clear and illuminating, I think, is to contrast Cartesian space and existential space.
Maybe this has never occurred to you.
It certainly hadn't occurred to me before I read Heidegger, that there are two extremely different notions of space.
Well, yeah, even experiences of space, because you can get an experience of Cartesian space.
He'll try to show you how to do that at the end.
So let's start with existential space or lived space, the space we actually move around in and cope in.
It's got a center, that is, there's a here where I am.
And I'm going to keep going back and forth between this and present-at-hand Cartesian space, because that, of course, has no center, no here.
If you just think of the space in the universe, there's no here in the space in the universe.
There's only a here where a Daseine is.
And then when there's a here, then things can be near and far from me.
That is, there can be closeness.
And that he's talking about on 135, where he says the middle of the bottom paragraph.
Well, no, let's start a little four lines down in roughly in the second paragraph of section 22 on page 135, 102 in the German, all that.
So it says, we have been talking about what is approximately ready to hand.
This means not only those entities which we encountered first before any others, but also those which are close by.
Now he's doing this closeness story.
What is ready to hand in our everyday dealings has the character of closeness.
And that's what I mean when I say you can be near and far from it, and you can be close to it.
I mean, I think you want to, we need, in English, we've got a distinction, but it sort of gets covered up.
It's not adhered to.
But I think there is the difference between closeness and which goes with nearness and nearness, farness, closeness.
Those are all existential ways that we are related to each other and to stuff in space.
But and what about galaxies?
Well, they are a certain distance from each other.
And so are, so is the lectern a certain distance from the chair.
But we, and maybe you might want to say it's close to the table or near to the table, but I think it would be better not to, to try to purify.
I think English has gotten sort of unclear about it, but I want to say, no, no, the lectern can't be close to the table, but it can be very small distance from the table or right on it.
But I think being near and far and close are something that we, only we have in relation to other stuff.
So, and so then, and in our space has in it, now the next point, directions like up and down, right and left.
That's not out there in the space in the universe.
In the universe, space is homogeneous.
Cartesian space has all points are equal.
There's no center, there's no here, and there are no places.
And Heidegger talks about that on 145, the second full paragraph, a little above the 111 in the margin.
The space which is thus disclosed, and that's the space of our copy space, our dealing space, the space which is thus disclosed with the worldhood of the world lacks the pure multiplicity of the three dimensions.
It doesn't lack them in a funny way.
It has something better, maybe, but it doesn't have the three dimensions.
In this disclosedness, which is closest to us, space is the pure wherein, in which positions are ordered by measurement, and situations of things are determined, and the situations of things are determined.
I don't know what that means.
What is ordered by measurement in the situations of things?
I wonder what that is in German.
That doesn't make any sense, but it doesn't matter.
It's not important.
What's important is the end of that sentence still remains hidden.
I say, I want to stress that because every once in a while it glimmers through that Heidegger thinks that the Cartesian space is real and it's there all along and in some ways underlies this existential space, the one with centers and ups and downs and rights and lefts and so forth, just the way the present-at-hand hammer underlies the ready-to-hand hammer.
And I just say this over and over because people who read Heidegger come to the conclusion that somehow he doesn't believe that the physical space is real.
But he does.
He just thinks that it's not what we normally experience or deal with.
It's hidden.
And I'll get back to that.
But you may think I'm sort of obsessing about it, but you'll see if you read secondary sources how they can't believe that Heidegger thinks that though Descartes got it wrong about the thinking thing, there are no self-contained subjects.
There are no minds that would keep their content even if there was no world.
Descartes has just got it wrong, and Heidegger's got plenty of arguments about it, which we'll come back to next time.
But I think Heidegger thinks that Descartes got it right about race extensor.
There is this physical, homogeneous space underlying, what is the word, hidden, in our everyday coping, and we can reveal it just the way we can get to the shank and blob that is that underlies the hammer.
And remember that I keep going to repeat this, it's so important.
That doesn't mean that the stuff is more basic.
It isn't as if Cartesian space is more basic than lived space.
In fact, just the contrary.
Lived space is much more rich and much more intelligible than Cartesian space.
But nonetheless, if there weren't Cartesian space, which had its distances, there couldn't be here and far and near and all that.
Yeah.
No, of course not.
Good point, good point.
In fact, that's right.
It crossed my mind to say that.
Then I was trying to say too many things at once, so I didn't.
But it's important.
When Heidegger says that Descartes is right about the race extensa, he certainly doesn't mean that Descartes, who was doing pretty well given that all he had to go on so far was Galileo, he didn't even have Newton yet.
He thought there were chunks of extended bits and that they were organized in vortices which were objects.
Now we would say there are clouds of electrons or maybe we've gotten beyond clouds of electrons and something fields of quarks or who knows strings or whatever.
The point isn't that Descartes got it right about what the ultimate spatialness of the the universe was, but that he saw that there was a kind of spatialness of the universe that made no reference at all to us and had in it and that it had no human meaning.
And that's what I think Heidegger thinks Descartes got right.
And that's our modern physics still has always will have some version of that right now, and maybe it's Einsteinian space-time, but something or other that's there that has a kind of measurements in it and those and are and is totally independent of us and is somehow the causal basis of this lived space.
I don't think anybody in their right mind would want to deny it.
And I think Heidegger is certainly a very sensible guy and doesn't want to deny it.
Now, yeah, Curtis.
Ah.
Well, okay.
Well, I've got.
Yes, I mean that if it weren't for its structure and its causal properties, there wouldn't be any existential space with us in it.
And he's got words like it's hidden, it's veiled, which is the same sort of thing.
I wonder if he's got an underlies.
I have another quote here, but I don't think underlies may unfortunately be my term, and you're sort of calling me on it.
But something, we have to have some term like that.
Let's see.
Here's another one on 134, I believe.
As long as I've got us into this, yes.
Let's try 134.
But yeah, this is probably the clearest statement of what I've been saying.
At the very end of section B, that is above section C, that is about five lines above section C, there is some phenomenal justification for regarding the extensio as a basic characteristic of the world, in quotes, that's the universe, even if by recourse to this, neither the spatiality of the world, that's this world with us involved in it, nor that of entities we encounter, that is, their being near and far, even if all that, a spatiality that we proximately discover, that is where we most immediately are, even if all that, and even if Dasein itself, now I've lost myself in the sentence, so I'm going to read it again.
There's some phenomenal justification for regarding the extensio as a basic characteristic of the world, in quotes, even if by recourse to this, neither the spatiality of the world, without quotes, nor that of the entities we encounter in our environment, the spatiality which is proximately discovered, nor even that of Dasein itself can be conceived ontologically.
I can't make much sense.
Enough, I can't parse that sentence right now, but I know what it means.
It means that you can't have an understanding of the being of Dasein and the being of our world on the basis of this Cartesian space.
You can't have an understanding of it.
It won't be intelligible to you.
But it doesn't say, it doesn't deny what I was looking for.
But I think, but I'm getting it out of phenomenal justification.
He wants to regard the existential existential as a basic characteristic of the universe.
And what else could it be doing?
This is my point, as a basic characteristic of the universe except having a kind of structure that underlies and makes possible our experience of existential space.
Yeah.
Yes.
No, I know it doesn't.
I'm disappointed about that.
But I mean, but it seems to me, well, let's keep our eyes open.
I'm going to get back to this at the end.
I jumped ahead.
I mean, I assert, and I'm ready to be shown that I'm wrong, that Heidegger thinks that it's that there is a kind of physical space and that Descartes is right.
That physical space makes possible causally, structurally, our everyday space.
I'll try once more.
I'm really funny giving this lecture from the end back, but I can't resist now that I've got us into this.
Well, he talks at Topa 147 about the discovery of pure space, which is at the end of the top paragraph.
But he still hasn't said what Curtis challenges me to say, that in some sense it underlies and makes possible our kind of space.
Well, again, he says he wants to establish the phenomenal basis that is our experience upon which one can take the discovery of pure space as a theme.
Well, I'll try again, but it never says what I want it to say, but it never denies it.
And I think it just, I think Heidegger just thinks it's obvious.
But anyway, the end of the first full paragraph on 147, the homogeneous space of nature, that's the universe again, shows itself only when the entities we encounter are discovered in such a way that the worldly character of the ready-to-hand gets specifically deprived of its worldhood.
So there is a homogeneous space of nature anyway, and it does show itself to pure discovery.
And then you ask yourself, well, how does that relate to the space that we normally live in?
And I can't think of any other possible candidate for except that.
For instance, if it takes a long time to get from here to there because here is far from there, it's got something to do with the way the universe is, though not simply, I mean, because Heidegger talks about how sometimes it's harder than others to bike there or walk there.
Lots of our capacities are in there, but also something is in there that just makes it hard to get from here to there or takes a certain amount of time to get from here to there.
And that's nature, I bet.
But I'm going back to where I belong here.
So where were we?
There are places.
I was just got to places on 136.
And I think I read something already about that.
No, I didn't.
So let's read about places.
There are places in this existential space, and there are no places in Cartesian space.
So here's places.
It says equipment has its place, or else it lies around.
I take that to be in the workshop.
There's a place for the saw and a place for the hammer and all that.
And if you're really sloppy, your tools can just be lying around.
But there are places in the shared world.
The ceiling is a place for the lights, and the floor is a place for the chairs.
In our ordinary world, in a spaceship, things will have to get their places in some different way, either derivative from us, or they'll have to work it out when there isn't any ceiling and there isn't any floor.
But in our world of our practices and our workshops, the equipment has its place.
I'm going on.
When equipment for something or other has a place, this place defines itself as the place of this equipment.
That's the hammer holder.
As one place out of a whole totality of places directionally lined up with each other and belonging to the context of equipment that is environmentally ready to hand.
Lined up with each other means that some things are nearer than others.
So the hammer's place is nearer than the jigsaw's place, which is nearer than the generator's place and so forth.
And Heidegger's just telling you that.
And he says more about it at the very bottom, similar to what I just said.
The above is what is on the ceiling, the below is what is on the floor, the behind is what is at the door.
All wares are discovered and circumspectively interpreted as we go our way in everyday dealings.
Good.
Already, there's a problem lurking there, which I just is part of what's going to mess up everything.
I mean the question is partly what role public space has, uh vis-à-vis the space of particular Daseins.
In some ways, space depends on where I am, me, somebody specific here, so that things can be near and far from where I am.
But the kind of spaces that's got to do with the ceiling and the floor seems to be a kind of public space, which is there is sort of not it depends on Dasein, but it doesn't depend at all on any particular Dasein.
So there seems to be two senses of space which Heidegger hasn't distinguished very well and which are very importantly different.
Look, I'll come back to that.
But right now, that's enough to say.
But I want to stress again, there are these public regions.
And he talks about that on 36, 136 again.
And so I'll look at that again.
I mean, where he defines regions.
Regions are very weird and hard to define.
But Heidegger's phenomenology is so fascinating.
He finds phenomena so obviously right and so peculiarly familiar and transparent that nobody's got a normal language for talking about them.
Here I'll so let's talk about regions, the middle 136.
This wither, which makes it possible for equipment to belong somewhere, and which we circumspectively keep in view ahead of us in our concern for dealings, we call the region.
What's a region?
Well, I used to think the region was the workshop, but I d I don't that's not right anymore.
And that's I just decided this morning.
I don't know what his name for the workshop is, but regions are much more s peculiar.
The middle of 137, right at 104, for the Germans, the middle of it, the house has its sunny side and its shady side.
The way it's divided up into rooms is oriented towards these, and so is the arrangement within them according to their character's equipment.
Churches and graves are laid out in certain ways.
The regions of life and death, which are determinative for Dasein itself, show up in the way the graveyard is laid out, for instance.
So regions is a very peculiar thing.
It's sort of the, I'm just groping, the meaningful dimensions of spatial experience that have to do not with Dasein's location, but something like what concerns Dasein.
So what concerns Dasein is keeping the house warm or cool and being able to build your house.
So if you build it around here, you want to build it so that it faces the sun at the my house, which I didn't build, is brilliant.
It faces the sun at the time in the middle of December when the sun is furthest over that way.
And then when the sun goes way over that way, the house is so that the sun hardly shines in at all in the summer.
You can build a now I take it that's got to do with my concern with regions of light and warmth and so forth.
And it's, I don't know, we don't, I mean, just nobody has a word for it, so we might as well call them regions.
Anyway, that's something that public space has that physical space doesn't have.
And let's see now, I'm still looking at these things I wanted to talk about.
Wait, just a second.
Okay, now I was just looking at one.
I've already said equipment belongs somewhere.
So I went back to that.
Yeah, Dave.
I want to ask you the issue we were presenting earlier about weather line things.
Well, that might be right.
He certainly.
Well, I think that's nice.
I mean, I hope it's true, because in the back of my mind, and you could do it too, I sort of map this on temporality, which, of course, you can see that there is no now in the universe, which is a trickier thing and makes you dizzy when you think about it.
But in Division II, which we're not going to get to, Heidegger's got lots to say about the fact that there's no now in physical time.
And maybe then there's nothing sort of like what we normally call time in physics.
But let's not go into that.
But I do know, why am I saying this?
Just a second.
Oh, yeah.
But there is something like world time in the time part, which has to do with clocks.
And clocks, the sun is a is like a clock, he says.
The clocks are just fancier versions of the sun.
They're tracking something physical, but they're tracking something physical in a way that's relating it to our projects and so forth.
It looks like here, the houses and the graveyards are tracking something physical and relating it to our projects.
So even though Heidegger never uses the term, I think he could and should talk about world space.
I've been saying public space, but if there's something like world time that takes account of the clocks in nature in the sun, then there's going to be world space and regions are the name for it.
That's what you're thinking.
I'll go along with that.
We made progress.
Okay, back to these juxtapositions.
So public spaces, I think I've said all I need to say about that, but I want to make sure.
So 137.
I just read that.
And yeah.
Okay, and then, nicely, the familiarity comes in again.
Familiarity, you know, is what I keep saying, is a very important character in all this.
Absolutely crucial, as I said last time, to get around all kinds of problems that cognitivism and AI get into about how we find our way around in the world and know at every moment what's relevant and how when something changes we know what changes and doesn't.
All that is this kind of familiarity.
And of course, this whole story about space has its own kind of familiarity, and he mentions it just in passing.
And he mentions it in a way which is, of course, important to me and should be to you.
That familiarity is always invisible.
It withdraws and so forth.
You don't have to be noticing, least of all, thinking about how familiar it is that people face each other when they talk to each other, or that they move forward more easily than backward, or that the whole room here is designed to take account of the fact that I can stand up here and face you and so forth.
That's just totally, in his language, inconspicuous.
It would only become conspicuous if it was a room in which you could move the chairs around and see people had moved them all so that they pointed in the wrong direction.
You must have all gone to classrooms like that.
Then you have to move them back, and it becomes conspicuous that the teacher is supposed to be facing the students who are supposed to be facing the teacher.
And that whole thing is built in.
So he's talking at the bottom of 137: the readiness to hand which belongs to any such region.
And now we've got this business about houses and so forth.
Let's say anything in world space, we're going to say now.
The readiness to hand that belongs to anything in world space has the character of inconspicuous familiarity in italics.
I mean, though he never makes a fuss about it, he always, when he brings it in, he knows it's important.
And it has in it an even more primordial sense than does the being of the ready-to-hand.
That's a one-sentence condensation of the claim that even the ready-to-hand wouldn't make sense to us and be available to us if it wasn't already on a background of familiarity, of generally organizing stuff and coping with it.
So that he gets this punchline, I've already read two or lectures or three.
Our understanding of being finally goes back to familiarity.
And that's even more basic than the primordial intentionality of the ready-to-hand.
Familiarity is the condition that makes possible primordial intentionality.
It's not itself intentionality.
It's a background of something, a background of really know-how for coping with everything.
So, I mean, I just review that every once in a while because that's one of the clearest and importantest things.
So, now we've got the familiarity.
And what have we got?
We've already said the contrast then is present at hand, Cartesian space, which is the Cartesian extensio.
There is the three-dimensional multiplicity of positions, and they are at the bottom of 136.
I read this already.
They're never proximally given, where that means that's not what we come across normally and first, and it's when you're just going around in the world.
So the space has no center, it has no here, that is universe physics space.
It's homogeneous, all the points are equal, there are no places in it, it has no up and down, and no right and left, and it has distances, greater and lesser distances.
The galaxies are a lot further away from me than the Campanille, but it has no center, so it has no near and far, the way I'm using them.
Only where, like, I can only talk about things that are near and far from me.
Now, you know, I'm forcing English because you might say, well, the galaxies are pretty far from each other.
But I want to say, shouldn't say that.
That's really mixing levels.
We should say the galaxies are great distances from each other.
Whereas, and you shouldn't say somehow that the lectern is uh a very short distance from the table.
That's weird.
It's just very close and near to the table.
Okay, so let's see now.
One I just see another interesting reference.
What have I got in mind here?
Let's see.
No, that's fine.
Now that we've described the spatiality of the everyday, ready-to-hand dealing Daseine, I get alliteration anyway.
And so now we're going to go to the ontological condition of the possibility of that.
And that's going to be something about the way Dasein is always in the world.
So coping with things in order to, just to keep reviewing, satisfy the two for the sake of which is coping with things because it's hungry and because it needs shelter and so forth.
That's part of our coping in the world, and coping with things because you need to do things in order to be to be something.
So that's the way your identity requires coping.
And all that, this background coping, oh, I'm doing it again, aren't I?
The background dealing, you need an account of how it makes possible our experience of the near and the far and of regions and of places, all the things we've just been talking about.
And and that's going to be the ontological story about how how we ontologically open up a space.
And now comes the most complicated and confusing term that it's time for me to explain.
And that's this desevering.
De severing is Heidegger's name for this abstract, or no, it's not abstract, this very familiar, concrete capability we have of coming across things as near and or and or far.
Now I have to say a lot about that.
I mean, it's ent thernung in German.
Entfernung, the normal word in German, means distance.
There's a footnote, so I don't know so I don't have to write this on the board.
They explain it all.
Heidegger writes it with a hyphen, ent thernung, where int means taking something away.
So it's the right way to translate ent fernung, it's not very pretty, is de-distancing.
D-E hyphen distance.
Joan Stanbaugh gets it right, which is nice for a change.
And that she's the only one who's got de-distancing.
These guys have got the worst translation as usual.
That there's no way to make any sense of this notion of what is it?
I can't even remember their word.
What?
Deseverance.
That's just crazy.
And I tried distance because I tried to take the word distance apart the way he takes the word enthernung, which is distance apart, and get this sense of some kind of stance in there, but I don't think dys hyphen stance means anything either.
So, whenever you see de severing, you've got to think de-distancing.
But now, what is de-distancing?
Well, you might think it's the basic capacity that Dasein has to get nearer things, that they are at a distance and we have a tendency to bring them close.
I think Heidegger does think that.
I think it's a sort of a Merlot-Ponty idea that we want to get an optimal grip on things, and getting an optimal grip on things means getting them sort of in front of us, arm's length from us.
But that's not what de-distancing means.
It's an ontological notion.
That would be too existential.
That would be sort of psychological, that we do have a tendency to want to bring things close.
What de-distancing is, we are the kind of being who are in the near and far business.
That is, we open up the space in which things can be near and far.
And that's what de-distancing is.
It's very confusing and misleading.
It sounds like you're removing distance, but it isn't that at all.
Dedistancing is opening up the possibility of things being distant or being near, either one.
Now, I owe you some quotes to try to show you that he actually is trying to say that.
Let's try 139.
Okay, yes, yes.
I'm going to read it with de-severing.
And no, I'm not.
I can't do it.
I'm going to read it with the right thing in it.
Okay, about 10 lines down on 139.
It's in the German middle of 105.
He defines it, or roughly, we use the expression de-distance in a signification which is both active and transitive.
I'm not sure what that means, but I think maybe the active is this ontological one, that it's getting into the distance business, and transitive maybe is what you get out of it.
Then, when you're near this and far from that, that's already sort of inside the distance-playing game.
It stands for a constitutive state of Dasein's being, a state with regard to which removing something in the sense of putting it away is only a determinate factical mode.
That is, removing, meaning taking to a distance.
He says, whatever de-distancing means, it doesn't mean taking things further away.
It doesn't mean bringing them near either.
It's something more basic.
Here's this, and this is all so dense, and who knows whether I'm getting it right, but he says, de-distancing, next sentence, amounts to making the farness vanish.
That is making the remoteness of something disappear.
That means bringing it close.
Now, that's, I think, sorry, I misled you.
I mean, that's what I think is misleading.
I mean, he misleads us.
After all my trouble to tell you that de-distancing means a capacity of Dasein to open up an existential space in which things can be near and far and in which we can get nearer and further from them, he then messes up.
So that sentence seems to be to mess up.
It says, the distancing amounts to making the farness vanish.
No, no, it doesn't make the farness vanish.
It makes farness show up as a possibility.
That is, it makes remoteness of something disappear, bringing it close.
Dasein is, now that's when he's, according to me, I'm not sure I can, I got it right, he's falling into a talk in which it's too psychological, it's too existential.
It's as if he wants to explain back to this Mirabel-Ponty thing, that we have a tendency to get close to things.
We would really like to get a good look at everything and get as clear a grasp on everything as we can, Mirabelau-Ponty says.
And you can think of it sort of evolutionarily if you want to.
You feel much safer and secure the clearer you got.
If you're going around in a fog and with your glasses off, in my case, it's very dangerous.
But that's not what he's talking about.
So all I can say is when you read this, you just have to.
Yeah, I was going to say, and it gets straightened out again, doesn't it?
Yes.
After saying that, wait a second.
Just when it looks hopeless, he straightens it out again.
So he says, Dasein is essentially disseverant.
It lets any entity be encountered close by, and that's not what we want.
De severance discovers remoteness, and remoteness, like distance, is a determinate categorial characteristic of entities whose nature is not that of Dasein.
Now, there he's getting it.
And now he tries to really nail it.
Desseverance, however, is an existentiale.
You see, it's been sounding sort of just like a kind of existenciale, a fact about how individual people deal with individual things.
No, it's supposed to be an existenciale.
That means a basic structure of Dasein's being.
This must be kept in mind.
Only, now I don't know what's going to come out of the next sentence.
Only to the extent that entities are revealed for Dasein in their de-distancedness do remoteness and remoteness and distances with regard to other things become accessible in the entities within the world.
I rest my case on that one.
I mean, that's the right thing to say.
That says if you ontologically, it's an existential structure of Dasein, that it's in the near-far business.
Now, hand up.
Yeah.
Aha, interesting.
The funny thing is, he does say that exactly.
He uses the word released.
And he says, thanks to us, the space is released.
I wish I could just go to it because I'm not sure that it's how it works there.
I remember saying, gee, this is like freeing the chalk, and yet it's not like freeing the chalk either, because it's hard.
With the chalk, you can at least understand that in my language, you let the chalk do its thing when you free it.
But here, it's, I don't know what you're releasing when you do it.
I wish I could just open to release.
If anybody's got that kind of mind or immediately checking computer, tell me where it is.
But if not, I'll just take a quick look.
If not, we'll just have to wait till we get there.
But that's a very sensible question.
I'm afraid we have to wait.
If anybody, yeah, yeah.
Okay, well, let's not say freeing because I mean, maybe it's important that he says releasing it, though I don't think it's different.
So when we release spatiality or space, when we resist this kind of openness in which when we release the kind of openness in which things can be near and far, I find it very hard to understand sort of where they were before we released them.
And in fact, I just remember, this is fun, Heidegger has lots of marginal notes in here, which I haven't been talking about much.
But I did put Joan Stanbaugh on reserve in the philosophy library because she translates the marginal notes.
They're not in here.
And they're not in the normal German edition, except the collected works.
Anyway, and there are funny things.
And this one, there's a marginal comment very interestingly related to what we're talking about.
So I'm going to find it.
Ah, okay, here we are.
Heidegger's noticing that something's mixed up here at the top of 140 because he's talking about bringing close.
And when he talks about, he says, well, there are all kinds of ways to bring things close, which is true.
You can grab them or you can think about them and so forth.
And he's getting off in the wrong direction, notice, in italics.
In Dasein, there lies an essential tendency toward closeness.
Every time he says that, I get upset because we want not an essential tendency toward closeness, but a tendency to open up the world in which there.
You could have both.
Maybe we should just have both.
But then let's keep the ontic and the ontological.
Here's my proposal.
Ontologically, we have or sort of are this tendency to open up a space in which things can be near and far.
In fact, ontically, we tend to prefer that we get close to things than that they get far away.
So we can have it both ways as long as we keep the ontological one not being closeness.
Yeah.
You found the release passage?
Great.
Oh, is there a freed passage too?
Whoa, what are we doing back there?
Okay, tell me about it.
Yeah, well, this is just our analysis.
There's shown that what we have found within the world.
Where are you on 114?
So, section 18 about.
Okay.
I see something about freed there, yeah.
Yeah.
World has very freed, of course, the circle freedom.
So what do you get out of that?
World without it, of course.
And then freed in the sense that you can come close to us in a certain effect with concern.
Okay.
Well, the question is sort of, what was it freed from?
And from not being close to us.
Okay, well, a lot of people want to help me out.
Go ahead, Tyler, and then each of you.
Go ahead.
Freed from being homogeneous.
Okay.
Don't you find that sort of so unintuitive?
I mean, why you would think that it was a sort of captive of homogeneousness, and when it gets all this distancing in it near and far, it's now released from its captivity.
Then I can only say to myself, aha, it's doing its near and far thing, but I find that very weird.
Okay, wait, let me, yeah.
No, sir, there were two other hands, weren't there?
I mean, I just want to.
Oh, well, go ahead.
One hand disappeared.
From being disclosed or by disclosing.
Yeah, we free things by disclosing them, that's sure.
Or better, or discovering them, depending on whether we're on an ontological level where we're disclosing stuff.
Discovering is freeing, according to Heidegger.
My problem is, and you can use words any way you please, I just find that so unintuitive.
But you know, if it makes you happy, anybody, then it's all yours, yes.
Bringing it into relevancy to your own design.
That's good.
That's the truth.
Now, why you would call freeing it, since it's as if it's been imprisoned, but now you rescued it so you can be relevant, you know, get related to it, that's what seems to me so peculiar.
He's certainly talking about bringing it into your familiar world where you can deal with it.
And he calls it freeing.
And when he deals with space, he's the one who started all this.
He calls it when you release it.
That is, when you do your de-distancing thing and open up a space in which things can be near and far.
You've released existential space.
Okay, if that makes anybody happy, then let them be happy.
Last comment, yeah.
What?
It's nowhere.
Right.
I'm happy to say it's nowhere, but it sounds like it's imprisoned nowhere and you've rescued it.
I mean, released and freed in their normal meaning means that something's got to be unfree and you free it.
And I just don't get it.
Okay, your last comment.
Yeah.
How this is what?
For our circumstances, well, I don't know.
He does say that the existential space is released in the de-distancing.
That's what he started.
I don't want to spend more time on it.
If other people have, ah, you're the last one, I keep saying.
Okay.
They've been freed.
Only, only, only, I think you could find that helpful.
I mean, whether they were, whether they've been freed or whether they're being freed or whether they're about to be freed, I swear it's the same problem.
Okay, now wait a minute.
I want to go back to this.
Yes.
One possibility of a gripretation, maybe, is that it's freedom that doesn's brought for life somehow.
That before, without us, space is stagnant.
I mean, it changes physically speaking, but there's no involvement.
And only once the involvement begins, it becomes free.
Well, that's how I capture it.
It gets to do its thing.
I mean, it was just doing nothing, and now it's doing something.
That's the only way I can talk about it.
It's free to do whatever it can do.
And before that, it was just lying there.
Okay, I don't, now, certainly there's no reason to talk more about this.
It can't be that important, I swear.
And I don't even know if the marginal note is important anymore, but it's fun to see that he's getting confused about closeness.
Because remember now, closeness is a very tricky term at the top of 140.
Closeness can be this ontic business of getting nearer and further, and we can throw in if we want, having a tendency to get nearer, or it can be opening up the whole near-far dimension.
And he says in Dasein there lies an essential tendency toward closeness.
And that sounds, I want to say, too ontic, too existential.
It sounds like, because I say Marilla-Ponte.
And he sees that.
He writes in the margin a funny thing.
How much closeness?
And why?
Being as constant presence has priority making present.
There are two things going on there.
One, he's saying that talking about closeness as really reducing the apartness can't be the ontological one because there's no amount of closeness of this ontological tendency.
That's because it's opening up the dimension of closeness.
And he sees that there's a problem.
But then he adds a new problem.
And being as constant presence has priority.
That means that he's trying to swear.
This is the marginal note written much later.
Later, he thinks that there's just being present at all in the space in which it can be near and far or far is the most basic thing.
And you shouldn't think of, you shouldn't talk about de-distancing or closeness or anything.
You should talk about presencing.
And Dasein has the capacity in interaction with whatever there is that there be presencing.
While I'm at it, there's another place where it's fun where he says no on 138.
It's not very often that Heidegger says no.
Oh, by the way, I'll read you two more, and then I've got to stop by.
Stop that.
But it's, okay, on 138, about six or seven lines down, he says, the bare space is still bailed over.
And then he says, but space has been split up into places.
And then he writes in the margin, no.
I think what that means is that however bare space is covered up, it isn't as if it's the bare space that we operate on when we make things show up and not show up as near and far.
I mean, you can't, and that's the way the underlies is so peculiar.
I mean, in general, that there's physical space somehow underlies our capacity to experience things near or far.
But we don't give nearness or farness properties to bits of race extensia.
You see what that would be like, saying we give function properties to the present at hand.
So he writes in the margin, no exclamation marks.
He sees he blew it on that one.
And now for the presence issue, I'll give you one more funny thing about close.
He's getting all upset about close in the margins.
So back to where we were, where that sentence that I sort of threw up my hands in horror on 139, about 10 lines on, decevering amounts to making the farness vanish, that is, making the remoteness of something disappear, bringing it close.
And he writes in the margin, making it present doesn't mean near.
The distance of separation is irrelevant.
So you see what he's doing?
That's the right thing to say.
He's saying this dimension of what I'm calling the near-far business can't be getting something nearer or farther.
That's what takes place inside that dimension.
So it isn't a question of getting it closer.
It's a question of opening a space in which you can get further if you want, or closer if you want, or whatever.
He sees the problem right at the point where we saw it and fell into it.
And he tries and he gets out of it again in the text when he says, let's look, remember it's an existential.
Okay, I spent much more time on this than I meant to, that I hope I had.
And I don't want you to all worry about trying to understand this.
I said I would just fall into a lot of holes to show you where they were, and I'm demonstrating that.
Let's see now, where we are.
Close, oh dear.
Kind of close.
139.
We did that, thank goodness.
And he admits he mixes up the ontological existential dimension with an onticoexistential one, I claim.
And he tries to straighten it out.
And that this is tied up with the sense in which existential space is centered in me and isn't centered in me.
I mean, there's in the sort of ontic space is centered in me.
I'm always in it here, and things are near and far from me here.
They're not just near and far in general.
That's right.
On the other hand, at this ontological level, where Dasein, by its shared familiar activity, is opening up a space in which things can be near and far.
That's not going to be existencial.
That space centered in me, seems to me, has to be ontic existential.
And at least that's how I want to read it.
I'm looking at 140.
Let's see what I've got here.
Well, I just read that closeness thing, which I'm disagreeing with.
And now, okay, I'm not going to say more about that.
And I say, when Heidegger starts admitting he's confused, what do you do?
Well, you try to keep your eye on the phenomena, if you care, and describe what it is that's going on, what farness is, what nearness is, how they're related to my being here, how they all presuppose some basic ontological capacity of Dasein.
That's what we should look at.
And I summed it up.
There is an ontological existencial condition, which is the condition for the possibility.
Dasein is that.
And it's the condition for there being the kinds of near and far that there are, whether they're public or regional or personal.
That's all got to be ontic.
And that's what I've been trying to say.
And that is basically, when it's ontic, is about the nearness and farness of things from me here.
Now, let's see.
Okay, next.
So, but then things get worse, or I don't think they could get worse, but a new problem arises.
You want to be able to explain nearness and farness somehow in terms of the coping capacity of Dasein.
That's what I keep saying, right?
That we somehow, because we have this shared familiar coping, can, let's say, release things or free them as far and near.
But it should be, I think, the shared practices.
Familiarity isn't something that you've got or I've got.
It goes with the whole way of finding your way around in the world, which we share with other people whose world we share.
Familiarity in the room doesn't have to be near or far, and it doesn't have a here and so forth.
So he should, I think, try to get nearness and farness to be like the level of familiarity.
But he doesn't.
He relates nearness and farness to the coping or dealing activity of individual Daseins.
That keeps happening.
He keeps falling back into the closeness thing, into the ontic thing.
Now, let me tell you what his problem is, and then how he tries to deal with it.
That's the next thing.
So let's get back to it.
This is going to be simpler from now on, thank goodness.
We don't have to worry about all that for a minute.
Let's just try to see what he's trying.
Another way to look at what he's trying to do.
What is the problem?
One way to think about the problem of nearness and farness that gets it wrong from the ground up, which Heidegger is never going to make this mistake, is to think that we are in what my old teacher, when I first did philosophy, I had a famous philosopher, C.I.
Lewis, as my teacher.
Anyone ever come across C.I.
Lewis anymore?
I think he's, unfortunately, justifiably forgotten.
He believed the Cartesian story.
He was the last of the kind of Kantians.
And he said that the first thing you have to realize is that we're in a here-now predicament, each of us.
All we can ever really experience is what's happening here and now in our stream of consciousness.
So the question is: how, given that we're this inner stream of nearness and now-ness, how do we ever get out into the world?
It's that old external world story.
And Heidegger's trying to say that there isn't any here-now predicament.
That when you're Dasein coping in the world, remember that every here is all tied up with a yonder.
That's what I'm leading up to.
That's his next claim.
Not only is the world all laid out in terms of near and far, thanks to us, but there is always a here and a yonder thanks to us.
And that begins to get him both in the right direction and the wrong direction.
He gets him in the right direction in that he's not thinking that we're just in a here-now predicament, that there's already a yonder and a future and a past in our experience.
But it gets him into the trying to ask how we as individuals contribute the yonder as well as the here.
And that's what he's going to go on about now.
So we're going to, not only do we open a spatio-temporal shared world of equipment, which is what he should be talking about, but each of us opens, and this is we're not wrong, there's another phenomenon which he's more on to, which each of us opens his or her own spatial perspective.
What he's really discovering is this complicated problem that we are in the world.
We are being in the world.
It's not that you're in your world and I'm in my world.
That's the I.
Lewis problem and Day Park's problem and the problem of the external world and the problem of other minds.
No, Heidegger knows that we're in the world, but we're always in the world from sort of a point of view, a perspective.
Because Heidegger says Dasein is its world existingly.
I wanted to make that a paper topic.
CSI's beaten me up because they said it would be too hard, but it's something to worry about.
I mean, he says Dasein is being in the world, Heidegger, and he says, I've got a line I quote from way back on 414, whatever it is, Dasein is its world existingly.
And what he's got is now he's got that problem.
He's trying to talk about how we are open heads turned toward the world, but from a particular point of view.
And you mustn't hear the point of view as particular like in the Renaissance when they were trying to exactly figure out where the perspective on the world is.
That's getting you too much into subjects.
Think of medieval painting.
Think of Giotto, who painted things as big or little, depending on how meaningful they were.
There was still a point of view.
He could see that the donkey was nearer than Jesus in this procession or something, but there's a big Jesus and nearer a little donkey.
And that's because he wasn't trying to paint geometrical perspective.
Heidegger knows that we don't have a geometrical point of view on the world.
That Descartes worked like that, Renaissance way of thinking about it, grew out of it.
But we do somehow see the world.
I see you from here and you see me from there.
That's the sense in which we have, each of us have our openness on the world.
And that's what he wants to try to get a grip on.
It's so hard that he doesn't get much of a grip on it.
But he wants to talk about the sense in which de-distancing is something that he not he wants to stay away.
I mean, this is what he's getting at right now.
He doesn't want to talk about de-distancing as bringing things close to me.
That's the wrong thing.
That makes it look like my world is prior to the world.
What he wants to do is distinguish how we, each of us, experience nearness and farness from us.
And that's all right.
Remember, I want to say that's ontic compared to the big question about how we ever open up a world at all.
But now there's a new question.
I hope I haven't lost you.
That it's true that this is nearer me than you guys are, than my car is, and that's nearer to me than my house is.
How are we going to talk about that?
And it's all right now.
I'm changing the, we're in the new section.
I mean, now he can ask that.
He can say that once we've opened up the world into the near, far business, and granted, even that we have a tendency to get nearer to things, what does nearer mean?
What is it to be nearer to something?
Is it being a certain number of feet from something?
And if I'm 10 feet from it, I'm nearer to it than if I'm 50 feet from it?
No.
That would be a Cartesian way of thinking.
Well, what is existential nearness?
That's his new question.
What is it to be near or far?
It's a great question.
It's a good question.
It's phenomenologically important.
But I think he sort of opens it up and he sort of blows it at the same time.
And what I'm going to try to say in the next five minutes is that he's got something like five different stories about what existential nearness is.
And I'll begin next time by telling you the pages, but it'll help you when you read it.
There is accessibility nearness, in which case something that is locked in a box in front of me that I don't have the key is further from me from, say, the microphone drawer over there where I do have the key.
So there's accessibility nearness.
You can find that on 135, but I'll read the passages later.
There's the mattering nearness, where my son in LA is nearer to me than lots of people that I barely know.
And the more, that's, that is, they really matter to me.
And so there's that kind of nearness.
Then there's attention nearness, where Heidegger talks about how my glasses are, when they're on my nose and I'm not noticing them, are further from me than whatever it is, the picture I'm looking at in the museum, which is several feet away.
So what he's trying to tell you is that existential distance is, or distance is the wrong word, nearness and farness is not measurable in terms of Cartesian distance.
Because the same thing is going to be near and far depending on whether you're looking at it as available, accessible, mattering, attention.
And then there's something else, the Merleau-Ponty issue about maximum grip, which he also sees, that when I've got a maximal hold on it for manipulation, that's when it's nearest.
If it's right up against me and I can't get a grip on it because it's, I don't know, here, that doesn't have, that's not near.
What's near is just when I can face it and hold on to it.
That's another possibility.
Well, oh, look, I've got seven minutes.
I'm going to give you the page numbers, and we will have done this.
So, okay, here goes available near on 135.
Don't lose track of the question.
I mean, what does nearness mean if it doesn't mean spatial distance, measurable spatial distance?
And that's what he's trying to tell you now.
And it's clear that he's got some interesting phenomenological point because all these different existential nearnesses that he plays with, they're all different physical distances.
So it can't be that nearness for Dasein means physical distance when it's engaged in its everyday dealing.
So, okay, accessibility is on 135, where he's talking about the middle of that big bottom paragraph.
To be exact, closeness of equipment has already been intimated in readiness to hand.
Every entity that is to hand has a different closeness, which is not ascertainable by measuring distances.
This closeness, oh, we're going to find maybe, anyway, never mind.
This closeness regulates in itself, regulates itself in terms of circumspectively quotes calculative, manipulating, and using.
I mean, it isn't really any calculating.
It's just getting a figure, just automatically, practically, getting the best grip.
At the same time, what is close in this way gets established by the circumspection of concern with regard to the direction in which the equipment is accessible at the time.
So I'm calling that availability or accessibility nearness.
Then there's mattering nearness, on 141, your near and dear people.
At the top, German 106.
The objective distances of things present at hand do not coincide with the remoteness and closeness of what is ready to hand within the world.
Though we may know these distances exactly, this knowledge still remains blind.
It does not have the function of discovering and so forth.
This knowledge is used only in and for a concernful being which does not measure stretches, being towards the world that matters to one.
That's what I'm calling what's near to you is what you care about, or what you're concerned with.
He goes over it again on the top of 142.
Circumspective concern, five lines down, decides as to the closeness and farness of what is proximately ready to hand environmentally.
So now he's decided that it's concern, how much it matters to you.
Whatever this concern dwells alongside beforehand is what is closest.
So now if I'm concerned about my son in LA, my son turns out to be closest.
So that's another.
I mean, what's a trouble is that these are all contradicting each other.
And Heidegger has no way of sorting it out.
I don't know if there is any way of sorting it out.
There are a lot of different existential nearnesses and farness.
None of them have anything to do with Cartesian feet and miles, but they're all totally different from each other.
One that has a closeness will have a farness in another.
So this is a funny one, where my glasses turn out to be far away on 141, about 15 lines from the bottom.
When, for instance, a man wears a pair of spectacles, which are so close to him distantially, I think that means in real physical space, that they are sitting on his nose, they are environmentally, which is existentially, more remote from him than the picture on the opposite wall.
So that means the more you've got, whatever you're paying attention to is what you're nearest to, that one claims.
Now I've got a maximum grip one.
Let's see where that is on 141.
Second paragraph.
I'll start at the beginning.
When one is primarily and even exclusively oriented toward remoteness as measured distances, the primordial spatiality of being one is concealed.
We're used to that.
That which is presumably closest is by no means that which is at the smallest distance from us.
That's important.
It lies in that which is de-distanced to an average extent when we reach for it, grasp it, or look at it.
So that's what I call the maximum grip kind.
The nearest thing is what we are able to reach for and cope with.
Never mind the de-severed or de-distanced in there, because that's the confusing word.
Here it's being what I call ontical.
It's not the big ontological dimension of opening up.
Now, let's see where I am.
I'm happy to think that I'm just about where I want to be.
I think he's got all kinds of problems.
I'll just say this last.
He's got problems with left and right.
He's got problems with up and down.
He's got problems with anything that involves my body.
Left and right has to be with a body that has the two sides.
If I were a completely spherical being, there wouldn't be any left and my head wasn't pointed in one direction, but I don't know, with a big eye straight up or something.
There wouldn't be any distances.
It's of right and there wouldn't be any right and left.
And he doesn't have a way to deal with it.
If it wasn't that I was the kind of being that stood upright and so forth, up and down might not make any sense.
You might want to think down is the direction things fall.
But he's got all these problems because, and this is the last thing I'm going to read, because he thinks he can get along without bringing in the body, which I think he can't.
So there's one sentence, I just want to call your attention to it, in which he mentions the body, he then drops it.
This is right at the bottom of 108 in the German on 143, just below the middle.
So he says, out of directionality arise the fixed directions of right and left.
Dasein constantly takes these directions along with it.
That is true.
Whatever right and left is, I take it with me.
Just as it does its distance, distancing.
That's confusing, never mind that.
Dasein spatializes in its bodily spatialization in its bodily nature is likewise marked out in accordance with these directions.
This bodily nature hides a whole problematic of its own, though we shall not deal with it here.
That's the body in being in time.
That's the big weakness in being in time, that he hasn't got it.
But I'm not complaining.
I mean, he's got so many phenomena already on his plate, so to speak, and he's doing such an amazing, original job of dealing with them.
But he makes space for Merleau-Ponty.
That's what Merillau-Ponyonty's whole book, The Phenomenology of Perception, is Heidegger with the body in it.
So, well, here's what we are.
I just threw that in.
Then now, all we have to do is cover existential space and how it gets turned into physical space.
And I can do that in 15 minutes.
So, start reading the Anyone chapter for next time.