So I want to go back a little because I said something which it took me a long time to figure out and somebody encouraged me to repeat it by saying after class that it was interesting.
And I think it is interesting to ask yourself why Yvonne, remember, Yvonne has picked up the peasant.
He's decided that he's going to go confess right away.
He's feeling joy for the first time I think you ever hear that Yvonne's feeling joy.
And he's also sort of embracing another human being.
I think it's the first time, I said it was the first time he ever touched another human being.
That's not quite right.
Somebody pointed out to me, Alyasha kissed him at the end of the Grand Inquisitor story, but that's different.
He was touched by another human being.
That he should actually, so to speak, be carrying this peasant in his arms.
That's new for Ivan.
And it would be wonderful if he's now able to become, to accept his involvement in the world and accept the fact that he's got a concern for other people.
And he thinks he's going to do that.
And he thinks that he's going to go right away to the police and confess because that's...
Uh-oh.
This is not going to get any better.
Where does the noise come from?
I don't know.
Okay, so now he says that the middle, this is where we were, on 598.
He's made his resolution to turn himself in because he now thinks that he's responsible for the murder of Ol Karamatsov.
And then he doesn't do it at the bottom of 598.
Just as he reached his own house, he stopped, asking him suddenly whether he'd better go or not tell, whether he should go right away.
And he says, everything together tomorrow, he whispered to himself at the top of 599.
And strange to say, almost all his gladness and self-satisfaction passed in an instant.
Now that's pretty mysterious when as soon as he goes into his room, he's going to see the devil.
But before we can get to that, which is where we were just about last time, what why was it that when he saw said everything together tomorrow, he lost his joy and, well, period.
Well, the first thing to say is what he obviously lost was his conviction to go do it, because he didn't do it tomorrow.
And why did he have to lose it?
Well, that's the part that's interesting.
Dostoevsky thinks that, given that people are selfish and trying to protect themselves from pain and suffering and so forth, nobody is going to just rationally turn themselves in for a murder, say, that nobody knows they committed, or do any of the other sort of things that you do when you're in this other world, so to speak, the other world where you feel your connectedness to other people and where you understand that if you do anything wrong, you have to confess it to the people you've done it to so you could be back in some intimate relation with them.
You only have that understanding when you are acting impulsively.
Because as soon as you act philosophically, that is, stop and reflect, then this selfish or self-protecting side wins out in the argument.
Don't do it.
Nobody knows and it's not going to hurt you.
I mean, it's not going to hurt not to tell them, and it's going to hurt you to tell them.
So, as soon as he decides not to confess impulsively, which he had decided all of a sudden on the previous page, he's lost it.
He's never going to confess at all from Dostoevsky's point of view.
So, I wrote here: to accept this kind of responsibility that you have to accept, because that's how the world is really put together, everybody responsible for everybody, you have to do it spontaneously.
As soon as you reflect, your selfish nature takes over.
And remember that the mysterious visitor confesses because he sees Zostima impulsively throw away his gun at the duel.
And then the mysterious visitor impulsively runs in and confesses to Zosima.
That you can only, and the final one, which ties up with where we were last time, is Dimitri's big experience that he has to go and suffer in some way to show everybody the right way to suffer.
That's also done impulsively.
And in fact, there is something, the very nature of the paramatsovs, one of their sort of redeeming features is that they're impulsive.
And since they're impulsive, every once in a while they do something really good.
So at the bottom of 484, this is about Dimitri, but it's, you'll see, it generalizes the story about how, if you're impulsive, you do sometimes good things, which if you're reflective and detached and rational and philosophical, you wouldn't do.
This is about a fourth of the way from the bottom of 484.
It's about Dimitri now.
And he felt that a passion of pity, such as he had never known before, was rising in his heart.
That he wanted to cry, that he wanted to do something for them all, so that the babe should cry no more, so that the dark-faced, dried-up mother should not weep, that no one should shed tears again.
From that moment, he wanted to do all this at once, at once, reckless of obstacles, with the recklessness of the Karamatsov.
So that's the, the Karamatsovs have the impulsiveness that drives them sometimes to do really good things.
Of course, if you're an angel like Alyasha, you're always spontaneously doing good things, but that's because he's already been touched by Zosima, who's been touched by Markle, and he's already had his religious experience in the middle of the book in which he's in touch with the love that streams around from all, in all connectedness.
And so Alyasha doesn't ever reflect.
He doesn't ever have to reflect.
And he never doubts his spontaneous responses.
Okay, now comes this funny and interesting part where, as soon as Yvonne decides that he's not going to confess, or that he's going to confess the next day, which we know now that I've explained it, I hope, that he means he's not going to confess, because once he thinks it over, he's not going to do it.
Then he comes into the house, his house, and feels this cold.
Now we're going to look carefully for a while from 6:12 on, where Yvonne confronts the devil.
And this is not, I think I should say this now, I have to say it sometime.
Look at that, I didn't get the lights on back then.
But anybody who wants to, let's have some lights.
Not much.
Anyway, so he confronts the devil, which is not a demythologized, that is an existentialized devil.
That's Rakitin.
I mean, Rakitin is an example in real human terms of the kind of vanity and the desire to see the fall of the people who are better than you are that is devilish.
This is a different thing.
This is a psychological story in which the devil plays a certain role in Yvonne's psychic constitution, which tells you something about what it is to be Yvonne and something about what it is to be a human self.
So now we're going to find out on 6:12, starting.
Where?
Why?
Ah, it's more about the impulsiveness.
I forgot this passage.
Yvonne's devil, of course, and we'll hear more about it, but you know already, is really Yvonne talking to himself.
It's a hallucination.
He even knows it's a hallucination.
It's his dark side externalized and talking to him.
And so the devil tells him the same thing about impulsiveness that I've been telling you about 12 lines down on 6:12.
The devil says, and I swear to you by all the sacred, I long to join the choir and shout Hosanna with them all.
The word had almost escaped me, had almost broken from my lips.
You know how susceptible and impressionable I am, but common sense, that's like this rational reflection, but common sense, oh, a most unhappy trait in my character kept me in bounds, and I let the moment pass.
See, that's exactly the same, that's just the transition to getting the devil.
Yvonne let the moment pass, the moment in which he was not being sensible, but being emotional and impulsive.
And when he does that, he comes back to his room, and there's something cold waiting for him in his room.
Why 599?
Oh, that's where it starts.
599 starts the devil story.
And at the end of the top paragraph, he knew that he was not well, but he loathed the thought of being ill at that critical time and so forth.
Never mind, I don't know why.
I don't need that right now.
What I want to talk about right now is why it's cold.
I must have thought you're the wrong quote.
Yeah, I mean to read the top.
As he entered his room, he felt something like a touch of ice on his heart, like a recollection, or more exactly, a reminder of something agonizing and revolting that was in that room now at that moment and had been there before.
Well, there is something agonizing and revolting in the room right now.
It's Yvonne, of course, who's being arrogant and detached and selfish and self-protective and so forth, as usual.
But this time it's Yvonne sort of confronting himself in the form of the devil.
And it's interesting that there's a touch of ice on his heart.
I think I may have mentioned this before, but it won't hurt to repeat it.
That hell is coldness in Dante, not jumping around in fires.
Jumping around in fires is a Protestant kind of hell, and I don't really know why it's that way.
It's somehow an active conception of evil.
But Dante and Dostoevsky share a Catholic conception of evil as being more and more cold and detached, so that in the Divine Comedy, Dante has the worst souls.
I said this when we talked about the third man, I remember now.
The worst souls who betray the people they love and who love them are frozen in ice at the bottom of hell.
And the more you get unable to love and unable to be impulsive, the more you get unable to move.
So that instead of jumping all around like Satan does in Milton's Paradise Lost, which is sort of the ultimate Protestant picture of hell, Satan is frozen in ice at the bottom of hell and Dante and barely can move.
He just can clap his wings and he acts like a big refrigerator, flapping his wings, chilling all the people in hell.
So they're all cold.
There was a cartoon in the New Yorker, I think, about a week ago, I just remember of these older people, you know, are always cold and so forth.
And these older people in hell are complaining that it's too hot.
And saying, why don't they raise the temperature?
You call this hot and so forth.
And if they're really being Dante-like, they're probably bad old people.
They're icy.
So now let's see where we are.
So the devil, and the devil turns out to be the side of Yvonne, which is rational and European.
He speaks French every once in a while.
At one point, he talks about how, like Yvonne, he can't stand ugliness.
Where is that?
The top of 6-12.
He says, I am perhaps the one man in all creation who loves the truth and really desires good.
That's Yvonne's view of himself.
That's why he says he's going to kill himself at 30, because the world isn't good enough for him.
He won't make any moral compromises.
And living in the world is a compromise.
So you get all these views that Yvonne has, but they're sort of extreme and parodied by the earthy, that is, latty from Yvonne's point of view, side of himself, which is what the devil expresses.
And that, what's what Yvonne can't stand in himself on 637?
637.
No, I'm getting it wrong.
Christ 6:12.
Yes, at the bottom.
Yvonne, he says, all my stupid ideas, outgrown, thrashed out long ago, and flung aside like dead carcasses, you present to me now as something new.
So he knows that these are his own stupid, old ideas, and he knows that that's the lackey, flunky side of him, he says at the top of 6.13.
But he's also denying it.
This gets complicated in a second.
He says, no, I was never such a flunky.
How then can my soul beget a flunky like you?
Well, that's what he's trying to figure out.
How he can be related to this unpleasant, stupid, sort of generally obnoxious devil.
And he knows that the devil is a hallucination, but he has a very peculiar relation to the hallucination, which I'll tell you first.
But first, but first you have to see that he knows it on 202 in the middle.
He says, Never for one minute have I taken you for reality, Yvonne cried with a sort of fury.
You're a lie.
You're my illness.
You're a phantom.
And skipping a little, you are the incarnation of myself, but only one side of me, of my thoughts and feelings, not only, but only the worst, most stupid.
Keep in mind the self.
Keep in mind that for Yvonne there is the lofty side and the lacy side, and the lackey side is the sensual, selfish, dark side.
And Yvonne wants to deny that he's ever like that.
He always thinks he's the lofty person.
So now, there you see him resisting taking the devil to be real.
What's much more interesting is that he wants the devil to be real.
On page 609, this is really the crunch of Dostoevsky's analysis of what happens if you get the wrong relation of the self to the self.
About ten lines from the bottom, he says to the devil, but I would like to believe in you, he added strangely.
Now, this is a question for somebody here.
Why does Yvonne want to believe the devil is real?
I mean, it's easy enough to see why he's resisting believing the devil is real.
He doesn't want to go crazy.
But why would he wish that the devil were real?
Yeah.
He doesn't want to believe it's him.
Explain that.
That's good.
Well, he won't say he's having the levels.
Well, I'm not sure I understand you.
Are you saying that he wants to reject the part of himself which he finds lacking-like?
Right.
And what?
Well, no, no, I think that's not it.
He sees it in the devil, all right, his lackey side.
But if there is a devil that has his lackey impulses, why would I even like that?
Yeah.
It's terrific.
Perfectly put.
Instead of objectified, though a little better would be externalized, but that's what you're saying.
He's externalizing, putting outside of himself that lacky side of himself.
He's always been denying it.
He's a negative R2 person, remember.
That is, he relates himself to himself by denying the dark side of himself.
Well, now he's got a new way of denying it.
Deny it by saying, well, the devil comes around and makes me do these slacky things, but that's because it's not me.
That's some other force that's causing me to do these lacky things.
That's what he wants to say.
So he wouldn't be responsible.
He doesn't have to take responsibility for his lacking side.
But, of course, there's a downside to that, obviously.
He he can only get that by going crazy.
And he knows that.
And this trade-off is what's worrying him.
You just have this funny thing at the top of 605 where this is happening.
They're talking about whether there's an axe in hell and whether people could the more sadism, by the way.
If anybody's left doubting that Yvonne is sadistic, he's worrying about the idea that maybe it's so cold in hell that people who put their tongue on an axe will have their skin on their, will freeze their tongue immediately to the axe, and their skin will, the other tongue will come off.
That's what he's now interested in.
A pretty weird thing to be discussing for him.
And then he says, and can there be an axe there?
Yvonne interrupted carelessly.
He was exerting himself to the utmost not to believe in the delusion and not to sink into complete insanity.
So there's the two directions.
I mean, he wants the devil to be real.
He knows that if he takes the devil to be real, he will be, so to speak, exonerated for all the bad things in him, but he'll be crazy.
And he doesn't want to be crazy.
So, and the devil is sort of playing on that.
Now, where am I?
So, the devil, then, I'm trying to say, is not an existentialized version of some Christian sacrament or symbol.
The devil is a real psychological manifestation of what happens if you push the sort of R sub, the R2, negative R2, relation of repudiating half yourself to the limit.
So that would lead to madness.
And what's saving him from madness?
Well, as usual, when there's a devil around, who comes rushing in?
The angel.
Alyasha arrives at that point, just when he's beginning to go completely crazy.
And it saves him.
Oh, boy.
I don't understand.
What do I do?
Anybody have to do my dude?
Do I touch this?
I don't think so.
Very strange.
Well, if anybody discovers what I do to make all that noise, please tell me.
I'll try to stop.
Okay, so there isn't any Satan, but it's giving Yvonne a new insight into himself by putting him in this position of having to repudiate himself and so forth.
So on page 617, he explains it to Alyasha, the ta.
You would have driven him away.
You did drive him away.
Of course, angels drive devils away.
He disappeared when you arrived.
I love your face, Alyasha.
Did you know I loved your face?
And he is myself, Alyasha.
All that's base in me, all that's mean and contemptible.
See the dark side in him.
He kept haunting me with believing in him.
I skipped a little.
And that was how he made me listen to him.
He followed me like a boy.
Followed me?
I think it's fooled me in another translation.
I don't see what followed means.
I think it's take a chance.
It's fooled me like a boy.
He told me a great deal that was true about myself, though.
I would never have admitted it to myself.
Do you know, Alyasha?
Yvonne added in intense, earnest, and confidential tone.
I would be awfully glad to think it was he and not me.
And there's his point in so many words.
And that's the whole story going on there.
Now, the little standing back, it's just as it's interesting, and I tried to do it the last time, think about what prayer means in the various stages of Christianity, from Markle to Zosama to Alyasha.
So you could ask yourself, well, what do the devils mean in various stages?
Well, the worst, the craziest view of the devil, I'm not sure these are stages.
Maybe we should take that.
No, never mind stages.
But there are three different views of the devil and more and more sophisticated views of the devil.
There's Father Farrapont's view of the devil, that there are these ugly creatures with big tails and he goes around slamming the doors on their tails and letting them rot.
That is, and there's a whole bunch of them.
And there's Zostama's view of people who see devils.
I couldn't find the quote, but I think somewhere it says that Zosima gives people medicine.
They blame him for that.
That he thinks that there are certain kinds of hallucinations, and I think the devil is one of them, that Zosima thinks you should give people medicine for.
And I guess the most sophisticated view would be Dostoevsky's own view that you existentialize the devil as Rakhitan.
And you say the devil is are, devils are people who bring out the worst in other people and delight in their despair.
And they're not real.
I mean, they are real.
They're not hallucinations.
So that that's really the I mean that's well, that that's various views.
I don't, I mean, now that I say all that, I don't think that's all that interesting because it doesn't map onto the three stages.
They're just, so you could forget that what I just said if you want.
I don't think it's wrong.
Don't think it's deep.
So let's go to something deeper.
We're going to go now to where we were heading last time.
It would have been nicer as far as the whole symmetry of lectures go to have had this last time, but time ran out.
There's one sort of one shoe hasn't dropped, and that means that there's something important going on here that we haven't talked about, namely how Yvonne is the wrong kind of crucifixion.
There is, we've seen that Dimitri is existentialized, crucifixion, suffering on the cross, all of his way of talking, which leads him to be reborn, a new man, in joy, to arise, to have arisen.
That's resurrection talk.
But what about Yvonne?
Remember, I said at the very beginning last time, there are two parts of Christianity, a kind of masochistic part that wallows in suffering, of which I think the movie, what's his name, the movie, the Passion?
Mel Gibson, the Mel Gibson movie, he is certainly in that tradition.
And then there's the, and that kind of crucifixion, Dostoevsky thing, that sort of wallows in the suffering and paints pictures of the suffering, makes movies about the suffering, that doesn't lead to resurrection.
That's a form of laceration, and that's going to lead, at the extreme, to death.
But it's going to be told as sort of the negative version, the wrong way of understanding crucifixion.
And there are people in the book who have that.
And the question, and Yvonne is the person who has it perfectly.
He is the, so to speak, incarnation of the wrong kind of crucifixion.
Don't say it that way.
That's confusing.
Okay.
Here's what happens.
Now, remember, Dimitri gets happier and happier and talking about singing a hymn and being reborn.
Here's how Yvonne ends up crucified and suffering.
On 646, the second paragraph, Yvonne is now at the trial, in the middle of the second paragraph.
Yvonne walked up very slowly, looking at no one, with his head bowed as though plunged in gloomy thought.
He was irreproachably dressed.
He's always impeccable.
But his face made a painful impression on me at least.
Notice in the trial and so forth, the omniscient, but not very smart, narrator comes back every once in a while, who's the person in the town.
That's the me.
On me at least, there was an earthy look to it.
It looked like a dying man.
That's the crucial thing.
You'll see more.
If you're crucified the wrong way, instead of being reborn to a new and better life, you're just dead.
And Dostoevsky, of course, isn't going to let you miss that.
First, Yvonne gets a chance to do what he said, what the devil told him he wanted to do, and what he said he wanted to do, was to, so to sort of speak, spit on the faces of all the people who are at the trial, who feel that they're good and that he's bad.
He wants to show that he's the good one and they're the bad ones and he says at the bottom of 647 they all desire the death of their fathers this made a big impression on Freud there and wrote an article about it but there was no reason why Dostoevsky has to say that but that's just because he has this some of these amazing intuitions one reptile devours another if there hadn't been a murder they'd have been angry and gone home disappointed it's a spectacle they want bread and circuses though I am not one to talk now he's realizing that he's also implicated that's what he realized with the devil that's why he was going crazy that he's equally sadistic equally wanting to kill his father equally a murderer or more than anybody else that here's and will Dostoevsky hit your head hit you over the head with the fact that this is a kind of negative version of the crucifixion the wrong way to suffer the amazing thing is he does it at the top of 648 he always does it and the last thing he says is have you any water give me a drink for Christ's sake he suddenly clutched his head so there you go those who know the Bible that's in one gospel if anybody here know which one it where Jesus says he's thirsty I think it must be John so in the Gospel of John let's say Jesus says something and they say what he they they translate it as he's saying give me a drink so what do we that's just to tell you yeah Ivonne is crucified, all right and and carrying a cross, all right.
Remember, we talked about how the first bullish he was bent over with his left shoulder lower than his right, like, I guess, like that, and staggered as he walked because he was carrying this heavy cross.
From the beginning of the book, he's been the person suffering the wrong way, and now he's just told that, and instead of being resurrected, he's going to die, it looks like.
He had the look of a dying man.
If you suffer the wrong way, you get crucified, all right, but you don't get resurrected.
And suffering the wrong way is suffering with pride, suffering to somehow prove something, suffering to show you're better than other people, and so forth.
So that's the end of Yvonne, it looks like.
In fact, it's not really the end of Yvonne, because we know from one sentence, which I'll come across in a minute and tell you, that he didn't die, that he came very close to dying, and we don't know why he didn't die in this book, but something saved him.
I suppose it was probably Alyasha.
We just don't know.
But at this moment, it looks like he's definitely losing his wits and his life.
So Yvonne sums up what's going on with Ivan in his prayer on 745.
It's interesting that Dostoevsky is very clever there.
No, not 745, 619.
He wants to sort of give the final view on Yvonne, right where I should be giving it now.
But he can't just sort of interrupt and say it.
He can't have the rather stupid narrator say it.
So it finally, and the only person who has a right to say it and who understands enough to explain it is Alyasha.
So he's going to explain what is happening with Yvonne.
I mean, I've sort of explained it my way, but I think it's important to see how Alyasha says it.
The middle of 619.
And this is, it may be an explanation, and that's certainly what Dostoevsky wants us to understand.
But boy, is it hard and obscure.
I don't think I fully understand it even now after years of help and trying.
So if anybody understands it better, get ready to help.
We're in the middle of 619.
This is his prayer.
Or this is what Alyasha thinks.
Alyasha took a pillow and lay down on the sofa without undressing.
As he fell asleep, he prayed for Dimitri and Yvonne, and he began to understand Yvonne's illness.
Now we're going to understand Yvonne's illness.
The agony of proud determination, conscience.
Now, that's his illness.
That is, that's what I've been calling, and Dostoevsky is calling pride.
Now, God, in whom Yvonne disbelieved and his truth were gaining mastery over his heart, which still refused to submit.
Well, let's start with that.
What does that mean?
That is tough.
Anybody know?
Well, let's start.
What is God?
God, remember in Dostoevsky, don't have your stock responses to God being the supreme being.
God is the connectedness of everything that Alyasha experiences.
And God is winning out with Yvonne.
How is God winning out with Yvonne?
Has Yvonne understood the connectedness of things?
Yes, in a way.
That's what's getting at him.
He discovers that he's implicated in the murder.
Just how he's implicated in the murder, we haven't got to yet, but I'm afraid I'll get to today.
How many know how Yvonne is implicated in the murder?
Oh, good.
More, I hope.
Well, anyway, okay, but I have to tell you, Yvonne is very implicated in the murder, and that means that he's implicated in a way, which is very interesting.
It's his disconnectedness and detachment which has implicated him and attached him to the murder.
It's such a brilliant plot.
But in any case, so in that way, sort of connectedness is winning out over him.
Yes, the thought floated through Alyasha's mind.
Yes, if Snerzhikov is dead, no one will believe Yvonne's evidence.
I wonder if I should read this later.
I think I have to.
We have to wait till Snerzhikov is dead.
And what's well, I can tell you a bit.
Can I tell you anything?
Not really.
Okay, I think that's a mistake for me to try to put that there.
I'm going to take it out of the lecture right now because I'll talk about it, but later.
So there's a prayer.
I have written more here.
A way of meditating on Yvonne's condition with compassion so that he can understand it clearly.
And help the connectedness get to Yvonne.
So what would it mean that Yvonne is, that God is gaining control?
Well, it would mean that Yvonne is in the world and he's responsible for the evil in the world, whether he likes it or not.
And that responsibility is getting through to him by way of his implication in his father's murder.
And so, but Yvonne is still resisting this kind of interdependence.
And never mind about Smezhikov confessing, I can read the rest of it anyway.
He thinks, Alyasha thinks God will conquer, he thought.
This is the hardest part.
Yvonne will either rise up in the light of truth, that would mean that he would recognize the connectedness and be reborn, arisen, like Dmitry, or he'll perish in hate, revenging on himself and on everyone his having served a cause he does not believe in.
That means he never accepts the relatedness, but he pretends to accept the relatedness in order to look good because he knows that, and now we're going to have to find out more about the plot, knows things about what really happened in the murder.
And so something like this.
Yvonne either has to accept the fundamental truth that all creatures are interrelated, that's God, and admit his involvement.
Now comes the very obscure part, or else he'll destroy everything in himself and everyone else who questions his self-sufficiency, his purity, and his perfection, and which reminds him in any way of his complicity in the suffering of the world.
So he is involved.
He knows he's an accomplice, but he's got this struggle that he might, and that's what the devil, he might go mad and die as the one way not to accept God, not to accept his relatedness.
And it just left open here.
So Alyasha is praying for Yvonne.
That is, he's praying to understand Yvonne so that he can help Yvonne and keep him from perishing in hate.
And somehow he does understand him and help him, but there's nothing in this book that tells us he's done.
After the confession, I don't think he, after the trial, he don't ever hear anything more about it.
I don't remember that we do.
He's just, he's as good as dead.
Yeah.
Having told Yvonne this confession.
He wants to point out the connectedness.
That he was, yeah, tightly interconnected, even though he doesn't believe in interconnection.
Yeah, that's the plot is so well worked out to show this peculiar thing that Yvonne is connected by way of being disconnected.
And that's what we have to see now.
Now we're going to go to Yvonne's.
Well, that was a good stopping point for a minute.
So, anybody want to say anything about any of this?
It's sort of hard, but it's not impossible.
Yeah.
That's why he's all messed up, right?
Because he wants to deny the connectedness.
He wants to be autonomous and self-sufficient.
And in showing that he's autonomous and self-sufficient, it turns out that's just exactly how he got involved.
And so he's in trouble.
I mean, we have to say now, it's not a secret.
We're going to get there probably before the end.
But so far, we know what his, what this mysterious thing we're all talking about.
Well, how did his detachment turn out to be part of the problem?
Well, he made a deal with Smershikov to leave town so that Smershikov could sham a fit so that Dmitry could run in and kill Terematsov.
So at least, this is the first thing we know, at least he is...
Saying, I don't care.
I'm not my brother's keeper.
And I'm certainly not going to save my father's life.
I'm going to go.
And if Smershikov wants to kill him, then that's okay.
And Dmitry's really the one who's going to kill him because Dmitry's been threatening to do that all along.
So that's it.
It's the leaving town.
It's the verse that's sung by that peasant.
Vanka's gone to Petersburg, and I won't wait till his return.
So, in fact, Dmitry, sorry, Ivan has gone to Moscow, and somebody didn't wait till his return, but killed old Terematsov.
And Ivan knows that if he hadn't gone to Moscow, the old guy wouldn't have been murdered.
And he also knows that if he does go to Moscow, the old guy will be murdered.
And that's what he knows when he stands on the stairs that he always looking back felt was the most awful thing he did in his life, listening to old Terematsov.
He was listening to what he thought was the last night that old Terematsov would be walking around in his room and so forth.
So he knows that he's responsible, sort of, for the murder.
And that's driving him crazy, because that means that his very attempt to say, I'm not responsible, I'm leaving, is the main thing that made the murder possible.
Good.
That's clear?
Okay.
Anything else?
If it's not clear, you should ask.
Or if it's clearer than I've made it, you should tell me.
Well, it's got to be murky at first, because the whole point is that Yvonne doesn't understand his role in the murder.
Even what I just said is not his role in the murder.
What I just said is how he understands his role.
At this point in the book, now he's going to have three interviews with Smershikov that are going to change his understanding and make everything much worse.
And the prayer that I read sort of prematurely is really after he fully understands.
And that's what almost kills him.
That's when he's dying on the cross.
So let's go into it now.
For the rest of the time, we have three interviews with Smershikov, which are going to finally clear up this very, very purposefully murky plot that Jostovsky has put in here.
So let's look at that now.
Starting with something that's not yet the plot, but we've never discussed enough Ivan's relation to Smershikov.
And it's another case of his making a kind of parody of his own ideas, showing that they can be wrong versions of them.
Remember, that's what we just said: is that where was my last one?
Something where he shows you the wrong version of it.
Could be suffering.
Yeah, the masochistic version.
Here he's going to show you the wrong version of a defining commitment.
We know that Alyasha has a defining commitment to Zosima.
It turns out that there is also a sick defining commitment.
If you say to Dostoevsky or to Kierkegaard, yeah, but if you get your whole being of your life out of devotion to somebody else, that's sick.
You have to have a sense of your own independent value.
And Kierkegaard says, yes, you do.
You've got to have a sense of your own value.
You can't just be, and you have to be able, in principle, you know that you could always break out of the defining relation and you'd still have something.
But there's a defining commitment which is so much of a dependency that there's nothing left of the person who has it.
They're just defined as the lover of such and such.
Yeah.
I don't know if you like the way that I actually believe you definitely.
Boy, you're really following this very well.
I'm impressed.
I sort of fudged that, you know, and I thought I don't want to go into detail, but now let me think about it.
Yes, you lose your identity and you lose your world.
But there's something else, which is something like your eternal validity, which is what you have when you make the movements of resignation.
And he says you discover your eternal validity.
I think that means something like that, though you've lost your identity and your world, there's still something about you that enables you either to go into resignation or to go into faith.
And that's some freedom you've got to do something even when you've lost yourself in your world.
I mean, this I am certainly not very helpful.
That's right.
No, I meant that you could choose at this point.
Remember, there's this funny point where you make the movements of resignation and, oh, well, we're all back in Kierkegaard.
You can make the movements of resignation without becoming a knight of resignation.
The movement of resignation is to discover your eternal validity, which means some ultimate thing about you, which is the part of you that can freely choose.
And then you can either make the movement of resignation, having, oh, sorry, then you make the movement of resignation, that you realize the part of you that can freely choose.
Then you can either become a knight of resignation, and then that's when you're stuck.
That's what you're talking about.
Or you can become a knight of faith.
Or you can go back to lower immediacy and become like a butterfly caterpillar.
So you have this minimal kind of not your identity, not your world, but your ability to choose which kind of life you're going to lead in Kierkegaard.
And that's compatible with your whole world going crash, because there's still you there experiencing grief when your whole world and identity crashes.
That's the you that has this eternal validity.
Does that help any?
Okay, good.
You don't seem too convinced, but I don't blame you.
It's not too.
But there's a right question.
Okay, I left myself open for that one.
But now we're back in Dostoevsky.
And in Dostoevsky, we're going to see a character who has no eternal validity to talk Irkevard jargon, no self, and gets all of the meaning of his life by his total sort of parasitical dependence and devotion on somebody else.
And you know who that is, I presume.
Who's that?
Hmm?
Somebody said it.
Smerzhikov, I think somebody said that.
Did somebody say that, or did I just hallucinate you?
You said it.
Okay.
Anyway, it's Smerzhikov who is plugged into Yvonne and gets everything from Yvonne.
His motivations, his philosophy, his understanding of what people can and should do, everything.
But we have to work that out in detail.
It's brilliant in Dostoevsky.
It's very, very important that Dostoevsky wants somehow to.
I don't know if I'm ready to say this yet.
No, never mind.
Let's go back.
So here we're going to go to Smershikov, whose relation to Yvonne is a kind of parody, a sick version, would be the best way to put it, of the relation of Zosima and Alyasha.
Alyasha gets the whole meaning of his life from Zosima, but not the way, not the kind of total parasitical way that Smerzhikov gets the whole meaning of his life from Ivonne.
So let's start in 573.
All these interviews are so interesting, and you've got to go through them slow because everything in here is important.
On 573, he says about two-thirds down, why should I play with you?
Smershikov says to Yvonne, when I put my whole trust in you as in God Almighty, which is to say, you are my totally defining person.
And he says it again.
He says it again later, but I don't know where, so we'll wait.
I'll get there.
So everything about him he gets from Yvonne.
Dimitri talks of him as if he had no sort of self and no life of his own.
Remember, he has no self of his own.
That is, ever since Gregory said that he has no self, he's not a person, he grew from the mildew in the bathhouse.
We discover that he has no side.
Remember, he has no dark side and no bright side.
He has no divided self at all.
He's the last moment he had any divided self was when he was hanging the cats.
I noticed something new, by the way.
It doesn't mean anything, but he's the one who told Ilusha to put a pin in the meat and throw it for the dog.
He seems to be like a lot of, he seems to be sad.
Yvonne is sadistic at a high level.
He's sadistic about people, and himself, masochistic, but more sadistic when he goes to Lisa and says it was good that she slammed the door on her thumb and was bleeding and so and and so forth.
But it's it's as if, I've never said this before, but it seems to me it's like Smershikov is a kind of parody.
He's a kind of animal saddest.
He seems to be very mean to cats and dogs.
And that's with people, he doesn't have any view, any impulses of his own.
That's all he's got for impulses that he didn't get from Yvonne is how to be mean to cats and dogs.
Yeah.
He doesn't have a self-right.
He feels closer.
He likes animals better.
Is that what you said?
Well, he likes to torture them.
It's a hard, funny kind of liking.
But anyway, I never thought of it before.
But it does, yes, he's got this interesting problem of inventing the something-like human being, which isn't quite really a human being because he hasn't got the basic defining thing about a human being, namely that he's got these two factors, that he's got to take a stand on these two factors.
He doesn't have any factors, and he doesn't have to take a stand on any of these factors.
And then you ask, well, how can he be anything like a human being?
And the answer is only by living through Yvonne and taking over, in a way, Yvonne's way of his way of life.
Yeah.
His what?
When framing Dimitri with the murder.
Yeah, I suppose.
I don't call that sadistic.
He's clever.
I mean, he's that's another feature he's got.
Without he gets, I mean, he didn't get clever from Yvonne, though he uses his cleverness to imitate Yvonne.
He just, that's just cleverness, I think, that he's protecting himself.
He's what he really wants to do is commit a murder and then go and go to France and live off the money, or go, remember, that was his plan.
That's all just cleverness.
Yeah.
Well, not really.
I don't think she's ever described that way.
She's a holy fool.
I think, I mean, you don't get much of it in the book, but apparently people took these people who were insane and couldn't take care of themselves and weren't selfish and weren't possessive and were sort of street person, really, and took them and took care of them and thought of them as sort of saintly.
So I don't think she's like an animal.
That's just a direction that doesn't work, I think.
Did I see another hand?
Yeah.
With how Collins found that a lot of murders animals children?
Who I thought, you know what I thought that personal said?
No, I don't know.
But it's funny, I mean, not funny, but interesting that Dostoevsky has thought of this idea that this murderer does abuse animals, but he hasn't even, I want to make clear, I mean, we just don't put too much interpretation into the psychology of him, because he only is a murderer because he thinks Yvonne wants him to be a murderer.
We have to find that out.
He hasn't got any motivations of his own, except the only two motivations of his own we know is that he puts a pin in the meat for the dog and he kills and does ceremonies over cats.
Everything else he does is a kind of parody of Yvonne.
And we're supposed to understand that he's sort of Yvonne's double.
Dostoevsky hints at that because they're the same age.
And that's sort of, you're supposed to see that there's some deep something going on between them.
And I've only been talking about it in the direction of how Smershakov sort of is plugged into getting all of his motivations from Yvonne.
But Yvonne, I'll say it now, but we have to see it in more detail, is plugged into Smershakov as the way to enact his darkest desires without being responsible for them.
Because he wants to get Smerzhikov to help him get Dmitry to kill old Karamatsov.
And Yvonne really wants to kill old Karamatsov, it turns out, but he's not going to do it.
He wants, and Smershikov enables him to sort of take all of his evil impulses and act on them without, seemingly without being responsible for them.
Of course, it turns out that he is responsible for them.
But that we have, they've got to.
We're all still in the complications of the plot.
Let's go on.
And where are we?
Smerzhikov needs, is he?
Okay, total dependence.
Yeah.
He needs something from Yvonne.
And we have to see what he needs and why he gets it from Yvonne.
And you see something of that when you get Dmitry's characterization of Smerzhikov at the trial, which I think is on 454.
Here we are.
This is the sort of sense in which he's got no self, no motives, and so forth.
Dimitri sees that.
The big middle paragraph skipping in to the end of the first line.
Smerzhikov is a man of the lowest character and a coward.
He's not a coward.
He's the epitome of cowards in the world, walking on two legs.
He has the heart of a chicken.
And then skipping away down.
He doesn't care for money.
He wouldn't take my presence.
Besides, what motive had he for murdering the old man?
That's enough.
I mean, the idea is that he doesn't have any motives at all.
So Dmitry thinks there's no, it couldn't have been Smerzhikov that killed old Karamatsov.
So it's looking more and more unclear who could have done it.
And the way Gusti sets it up, it's true that on his own, he couldn't have killed old Karamatsov.
That's very important.
And why does he attach himself to Yvonne and imitate him rather than say Dmitri or Alyasha?
Well, that's because Yvonne, like Yvonne, Smerzhikov has no sense of involvement, no sense of guilt.
All he's got, and that's partly what I said to him, is that he's clever and he has contempt for everybody, and he's detached and ironic and conceited.
I mean, I don't know how much of that he gets from Yvonne and how much of that is what makes him attach himself to Yvonne.
We don't know that.
But he begins to imitate Yvonne.
He imitates his fastidiousness.
Remember, he's always impeccably dressed.
He imitates his being anti-Russian, his being anti-Christian, his being pro-French, all of those things.
On 129, you hear about that.
I think I read this once way back, but I read it again.
The end of that big paragraph on 129.
He came to us from Moscow after he went off to cooking class, well dressed in a clean coat and clean linen.
He brushed his clothes most scrupulously twice a day and was very fond of cleaning his smart calf boots with a special English polish so that they shone like mirrors.
And right after that, it says, which I did read, he's got contempt for the female sex as for men and so forth.
So that he has no sensuous side whatsoever.
Those are the things that would make him a self.
And he's imitating Yvonne in the way he's polishing his boots.
On 696, there's more about that.
Sort of a little below the middle.
But this is his view of Russia.
Of course, people who don't like Russia are really bad guys for Dostoevsky.
And he, like Yvonne, doesn't like Russia.
This one is about Smershikov.
He cursed and jeered at Russia.
He dreamed of going to France and becoming a Frenchman.
He often said that he hadn't the money to do so, I believe, but he loved no one but himself and had a strangely, oh, sorry, money to do so, period.
I believe he loved no one but himself and had a strangely high opinion of himself.
His conception of culture was limited to good clothes, clean shirts, and polished boots.
That's all correct, except the prosecutor who's talking doesn't realize that Smershikov did love Yvonne.
He says he calls it love at one point.
We'll see.
I mean, that means he just is totally attached to him, gets all the meaning of his life from him.
But he has no motive of his own for killing old Karamatso.
Let me see where I am.
454.
Did I just read that?
I think I did.
Did I?
Yeah, I did.
Okay, I see where I am.
So all of his motives and his philosophy he gets from Yvonne.
Well, I did read all that.
And I just read, okay, and he's against Russia, Christians, and so forth.
That's all 696, which I just read.
And that's all a parody of Yvonne being refined and impeccable and European.
Yvonne says in one point that he wants to go off to Europe and fall on the graves of the great Enlightenment thinkers and weep.
It's a kind of interesting, crazy parody of falling on the ground and weeping of the Zosima sort.
He's sort of weeping for the Enlightenment, but I didn't read it because it's not central enough here.
But he's definitely anti-Russia, definitely pro-Europe.
And 696, I think, I don't know if I've read that either yet, so let's see.
Yeah, that's what now I know where I am.
That's where I just read it.
That's the prosecutors talking.
So, and being a lackey or a valet is the worst thing Ivan can imagine.
That's what he keeps calling the worst side of himself.
So, he really can't stand Smerzhikov.
That makes it all the more strange that he gets so involved with him.
But you can see on 258 that he represents just the side of him that he can't stand.
Three-quarters of the way down on 258, on the bench in the gateway, Smerzhikov was sitting enjoying the coolness of the evening.
And at first glance at him, Yvonne knew that it was Smerzhikov who was on his mind and that it was this man that he loathed.
Well, that's just to say, of course, that Smerzakov is the lackey side of Yvonne.
He doesn't have a lackey side because he doesn't have sides in himself, but he is like the side of Yvonne that Ivan doesn't want to be.
And so he hates him.
And yet, and this is where Dostoevsky starts doing weird things.
He senses that there's some kind of connection between them, which there is.
Smerzhakov is a kind of parody of him and devoted to him.
But also, Smerzhikov is trying to involve him in something.
So at the middle of that paragraph on 259, 259 now.
But what irritated Ivan most and confirmed his dislike for Smerzhikov was the familiarity which Smerzhikov began to assume.
Excuse me a little.
He had obviously begun to consider, goodness knows why, that there was some sort of understanding between them.
He always spoke in a tone that suggested that they had some kind of compact, some secret between them.
So there's some secret deal that very complicated psychologically, that Ivan senses that Smerzhikov thinks that Ivan has made with Smershikov.
And there is.
But Yvonne has got sort of this ability to screen out of his consciousness sort of the dark impulses and the dark things that he's doing so that he doesn't consciously admit to himself that he's made any kind of deal with Smershikov.
But Smerzhikov thinks he has, and indeed he has.
And it's interesting that when he knows this kind of deal, he calls him on Smerzhikov on 265.
You seem to be.
What is he saying to him?
Oh, he's advising him to leave town.
This is this sort of murky moment where Ivan makes a deal with Smershikov without admitting to himself that he's made a deal.
Smerzhikov is advising him to go away because Dmitry knows where the money is and all that.
And a sort of shudder on the top of 265 passed over Ivan's face.
He flushed.
Then why on earth, he suddenly interrupted, you advise me to go to, I wouldn't try to pronounce that, wherever place.
Why did you mean, what did you mean by that?
If I go away, you see what will happen here?
Yvonne drew his breath with difficulty.
Precisely so, said Smerzhikov, softly and reasonably watching Yvonne intensively.
What do you mean by precisely so?
Yvonne questioned, restraining himself with difficulty.
I spoke because I felt sorry for you.
If I were in your place, I would simply give it all up, answered Smerzhikov with a candid air.
And then Yvonne unconsciously understands what he's proposing.
And he says, you seem to be a perfect idiot and what's more, an awful scoundrel.
Ivan got up suddenly from the bench and he was about to leave, but then just as he, and he looked like he was going to hit Smerzhikov, he has this complicated relation to him.
And then he says, I'm going to Moscow tomorrow, if you care to know, early tomorrow morning.
That's all, he suddenly said aloud.
And he wondered afterward what need there had been to say this to Smershikov.
Okay, so there's the compact, the secret deal that they made, which is, remember, Ivan deciding to wash his hands of it all, to let Dmitry kill Termatsov.
And what's neat, and it's typical Dostoevsky, when he calls Smerzhikov a scoundrel in 265, remember what he says when he's on the train leaving, going to Moscow, having listened to old Terematsov on the steps in the meantime, he's now on the train, and he says to himself in the middle of 271, the train flew on, and only at daybreak, when he was approaching Moscow, did he suddenly rouse himself from his meditation.
I am base.
The other translation, surely right.
You can cross out base.
It says, I am a scoundrel.
I mean, I'm sure it's the same Russian word that he accuses Smerzyakov of, that he understands he's implicated in it.
He does realize that, sort of, some of the time.
Now, let's see.
And why is he a scoundrel?
Because he's washed his hands of what's going to happen.
So now we get the first interview.
I think we won't get to the second or third, which is fine.
In the first interview, Smerzhikov is extremely weak.
And now you're supposed to be able to figure out after what I've said why.
Because Dostoevsky never tells you why he's weak.
But you're supposed to know why.
So let's just ask you as soon as I read the part.
At the bottom of 572, from the first glance, Ivan had no doubt that Smerzhikov was very ill.
He was weak.
He spoke slowly, moving his tongue with difficulty.
He was much thinner and more sallow.
Now, what happened to Smerzykov?
Why is he sick?
Why is he weak?
How many have read the three interviews already?
Okay.
You notice in the first interview, Smerziakov is very weak.
In the second interview, he's full of pep.
In the third interview, he's even weaker.
What's going on?
You're supposed to see it because Dostoevsky never tells you.
Well, what's going on is nobody's going to tell me.
Yeah.
So, let's not really going to bright side.
No, no, I don't think so.
But I see you're trying.
I think you have to understand, and it's sort of subtle and hard to see.
You've got a hand up?
Yeah.
No, well, no, not really.
I have to tell you.
I mean, you just have to sort of make it up.
What's happened is Smerzhikov has done something.
Old Karamatsov is dead.
Ivan ought to be there congratulating him on his part in it, whatever it was.
And Yvonne has been avoiding Smerzhikov.
So he's, so to speak, unplugged.
And that expresses itself, as it often does in Dostoevsky, by him being weak and thin and as if ill.
He's just lost.
He's lost his motivations because Yvonne hasn't been around.
Yeah.
Yes.
Exactly.
And he's been unplugged from the host, and he's a dying parasite.
But luckily for him, he's about to get plugged in again.
And that's why in the second interview, I'm jumping ahead, but in the second interview, he'll be full of Pep again.
But right now he's almost on 570.
He's almost dying at the 570, the bottom.
Smerzhikov, who was ill, almost dying, had been with him ever since Fedor Karamazov's murder.
With them, namely with Mario, the neighbor who's taking care of him.
But he's so unplugged, he's a parasite without a host, that he's just about gone.
But he's saved, so to speak, by Yvonne going to talk to him finally.
And by the way, his loving somebody, some sort of loving, is what he says to Yvonne in the middle of 576.
It was through my complicity.
I never have shammed a fit in my life, but I only said so then to boast to you.
It was just foolishness.
I loved you so much then.
Loved is what the other translation says.
Liked must be too weak.
I loved you so much then and was open-hearted with you.
So we're getting him telling Yvonne that he could sham a fit and was ready to do it and did it in order for Dimitri to come in and commit the murder.
And what Yvonne says as he leaves, at the bottom of 576, is goodbye.
I won't say anything of your being able to sham a fit, and I don't advise you to either.
Something made Yvonne say suddenly.
He's always saying these things impulsively that he shouldn't say, like, I'm going to leave for Moscow, he says, and he doesn't know why he said it.
That's because he's this weird split character who's got this dark side that he doesn't recognize, and this dark side sort of does things that he doesn't recognize or control.
It's like, and it occurs to me, Dr.
Strangelove, when he's having this business of saluting and saying Heil Hitler, when he's supposed to be on the other side, and he's just split like that.
He's got this double commitment.
So now it turns out, and Yvonne says to him, in effect, I know what you're up to, and I, in effect, affirm it.
We're in this together.
And I'm not going to tell anybody, and you better not tell anybody, that you could sham a fit.
Okay, now what do you expect?
I gave it away already.
Having said that at the end of the first interview, how do you expect him to be, how do you expect Smerzhikov to be well or sick in the second interview?
Well, right.
He's now reconnected with Yvonne.
They've admitted, Yvonne has admitted they have this secret deal, admitted it without noticing or sort of impulsively and sort of unconsciously admitted it.
So when he gets back, second interview on 579, he notices immediately that Smerzhikov is now in good shape at this third paragraph of that section 7.
Ivan saw at once that Smerzhikov was completely recovered from his illness.
His face was fresher, fuller.
His hair stood up jauntily in front and was plastered down at the side.
And he was sitting in a wadded dressing gown, rather dirty and frayed.
Now comes this typical neat little move for Dostoevsky.
He was wearing glasses, which Yvonne had never seen him wearing before.
This trifling thing suddenly redoubled Yvonne's anger.
A creature like that wearing glasses.
What is all that about?
Well, that's a way that he's copying Yvonne and being an intellectual and sort of upper class.
And it's driving Yvonne crazy that this guy is kind of a parody of him wearing glasses just like he does, although he is not an intellectual like he is.
So, and now Smerzhikov thinks that he has an understanding with Ivan, and he's full of energy because of that.
So, you see that on 579 at the bottom, all this struck Ivan instantly.
He took it all in and noted it at once.
Most of all, the look in Smerzhikov's eyes, positively malicious, surly, and haughty.
Why do you want to intrude?
It seemed to say.
We've already settled everything.
Why have you come again?
Ivan could scarcely control himself because Ivan can't stand it when Smerzykov accuses Yvonne of having made this deal with him where he's going to scam a fit so that Dmitry can commit the murder.
I'm trying to keep to what everybody knows at the point because different things are coming out little by little.
So he's got back his will to live.
And let's see, we're now on 580.
He says to Smerzhikov in the middle of the page, were you threatening me?
Am I in some sort of conspiracy with you?
That's this secret compact.
And he knows he is, but he doesn't want to admit it.
And he doesn't want Smerzhikov to push him to admit it.
And Smerzhikov keeps telling him the truth on 581.
As for the murder, you couldn't have done that and didn't want to.
But as for wanting somebody else to do it, that is just what you did want.
That's crucial.
He knows, Smerzhikov knows, Ivan knows, but doesn't want to admit that he wanted old Taramatsov killed, but he didn't want to do it.
It's like, how responsible are you?
We should stop with this.
Think as you read this or reread it of the levels of possible guilt, because it's a kind of amazing story in which all sorts of people are guilty for the death of Karamatsov in all sorts of ways.
Let me read you at least four or five kinds of responsibility.
You can just desire that he be dead.
That's like Dmitry, that he keeps saying how much he loathes him and how much he wishes he was dead and how much he might well do it.
And then there would be getting out of the way and letting it happen.
That's what Ivan did: let Dmitri do it, leave for Moscow.
That's called letting die.
If somebody is very sick, you can't kill them, but you can turn off the life support system.
That doesn't count as killing them exactly.
It's not a murder, not murder, then, not full-degree, first-degree murder.
That's letting die.
So Yvonne is at least responsible for letting die.
And then you could go further.
You could set things up so that the murder would happen.
And that's beginning, and Yvonne seems to be guilty of that too, by making his deal with Smerzhikov.
Then you could put somebody up to it, like hiring a killer.
That would really be first-degree murder.
You go to the mafia and you hire somebody to kill old Karamatsov or whoever.
And then there's actually doing the killing.
Somebody has to do that.
And at this point, Yvonne feels guilty, but only for the letting it happen kind of guilt.
557.
He's upset enough about that.
But that's all he's upset about at this point.
Where, where, where?
579.
Hmm, that's not where I want to be.
557.
Okay, here we are.
It isn't around 557.
Okay, I got problems.
557.
Why isn't it there?
I don't know.
But he does feel guilty for letting it happen.
Anyway, it's time to stop, luckily, because I'll start there with the right quote.
And now we're ready for the second interview, which we're going to go on and do, and the third interview next time.
And try to finish.
I really haven't quite given it away yet.
So try to finish before I have to give you the whole complicated, true story.