So we were looking last time in the Twilight of the Idols.
I'm just reviewing this just because for me, there was a piece missing which I now can just put in, and because it is one of the two places where it looks like Nietzsche and Dostoevsky are so similar.
So we were reading all this last time from Twilight about how you can't judge the value of life, that that makes no sense, that you're always in it, that you can't stand back as if you weren't in it and judge it.
And if you do, this was on 55, remember, to do that is what Nietzsche calls rebellion on 55, section 5.
If one has grasped the blasphemous of such a rebellion against life as has in Christian morality become virtually sacrosanct, one is fortunately therewith grasped something else as well, the uselessness, illusoriness, absurdity, falsity of such a rebellion.
Well, of course, Yvonne isn't making the rebellion from the point of view of Christianity, but from a point of view of his own rational demands for justice in the face of the injustices of the world.
But rejecting life as if you had that option is, and as if that was a good thing to do if you did have that option, is what Nietzsche is calling rebellion.
Well, Dostoevsky has a similar notion.
Ivan wants to step out of life.
Remember, I told you to bring your Dostoevsky, to bring Brothers Karamatsa today, so I hope some of you have it.
On 238, I told you there was a chapter called Rebellion.
But when I tried to find where in the chapter he actually talks about rebellion, I couldn't find it.
And it does go by very fast, although the whole chapter is called Rebellion.
It's at the bottom of 238, where after Yvonne has said all this big talk about, in effect, for the love of humanity, he doesn't accept the world, and he's giving back the ticket.
That's rebellion, murmured Alyasha, looking down.
Rebellion, I'm sorry to hear that.
I'm sorry you call it that, said Yvonne earnestly.
One can hardly live in rebellion, and I want to live.
Then he switches to another subject.
So there's, I mean, that they should call it rebellion, which isn't an obvious thing to call it, is interesting.
That they have the same view is more interesting, that you can't stand outside of life and judge it because you are totally immersed in it.
You wouldn't be able to ever see the world from any place but involved in the world.
Now we're switching.
That was just a review of, or a bit of the end last time.
We're switching totally to the gay science and to the most important passage I presume everybody would agree in the gay science.
At least I can't imagine any candidate that comes close for having said so much in so little open space, having had so many people commenting on it.
That's on page 181.
Is there anybody who has a different edition so that I should say the numbers of these aphorisms?
Okay, that's number 125 on 181.
And for a while, I'm just going to read this, but every sentence is interesting and important.
So, the madman.
Have you not heard of that madman?
Uh-oh, I've got to turn this one out.
Have you not heard of that madman who lit a lantern in the bright morning hours, ran to the marketplace, and cried incessantly, I seek God, I seek God.
As many of those who do not believe in God were standing around then, he provoked much laughter.
Has he got lost, asked one.
Does he lose his way like a child?
asked another.
Is he hiding?
Is he afraid of us?
Is he going on a voyage?
Thus they yelled and laughed.
The madman jumped into their midst and pierced them with his eyes.
Whither is God, he cried.
I'll tell you, we've killed him.
You and I, all of us are the murderers.
How did we do this?
How did we drink up the sea and wipe away the horizon?
That's enough for a while.
So what does it mean to say that God is dead and that we have killed him?
Well, to say God is dead means that God doesn't have the importance and place in the culture that God had up to Nietzsche.
That is, the idea that if you believed in God as the creator of the world and the source of all meaning and all intelligibility and all morality, you had sort of the common sense of the culture on your side.
But at some point, it switches over, and more and more that you have, it's the secular people who don't have to explain what they believe.
Those who still believe in God have to explain it and justify it more and more.
And the people who don't have to explain it and justify it less and less.
It just seems obvious to them that given science, given evolution, given all the things of the Big Bang and all that, it doesn't seem a plausible hypothesis anymore that there is this one supreme being that creates and explains everything.
So he's, so in Nietzsche talk, God is dead.
And that means you would think that the people don't believe in God because it says that those who did not believe in God were standing around and they said all these things.
But if you skip now a bit of all the list of all the bad things that are happening, I'll just, you know, we've unchanged the earth from the sun and it's plunging around and there's no longer any up and down and so forth and so forth.
And then at the end of that paragraph, do we hear nothing as yet of the noise of the gravedickers who are burying God?
Do we smell nothing yet of the divine decomposition?
God's too decompose.
God is dead, remains dead, and we've killed him.
And so far that's the same as I've been saying.
But now the next strange thing is the bottom.
Is not the greatness of this deed too great for us?
Must we, so no, I don't want to read that yet.
What am I looking for?
I don't see what I want yet.
Just a second.
Oh, yeah, it's the top of 182.
Here the madman fell silent and looked at his listeners and so forth.
Then he says, I've come too early, he said then.
My time is not yet.
This tremendous event is still on its way, still wandering.
It has not yet reached the ears of men.
Do you hear any contradiction in what I've just been reading you?
No, no, something more simple and sort of so obvious that you don't see it because it's right in front of you.
Yeah.
That's right.
One, that's the second thing you're saying.
The first thing is just the strange contradiction that there are always people standing around who don't believe in God.
Then it turns out that they haven't heard about what happened yet.
This event is too tremendous.
It hasn't reached the ears of men.
But it's the men in the marketplace who think that there's no God.
And in a certain way, they all seem to think that God is dead.
And what you said is the second point.
Say it again.
Yeah, good.
Right.
And the second point is: if they've done it, how come they don't know they did it?
And this is all very murky, but it's clear if you understand what's going on in Nietzsche's way of thinking about this.
So the interesting thing is that the unbelievers who think they don't believe in God, one, are still believers in God and have already killed God.
How could this be?
Well, I think there are two components to what it is.
One is that the people in the marketplace are, I think, scientists and people who believe in science.
But like I said, that in our secular culture, it looks like science is explaining things and that science knows the truth, the objective truth about how the universe is.
And the people who know that are unbelievers, one might think.
But if you understand what Nietzsche means by God, it turns out that these scientists and metaphysicians who think they don't believe in God really do.
Because God, in the idea of God, is the idea that there is one objective, right story about the universe.
That is, they believe in objective truth in science and in metaphysics.
And whenever you believe in objective truth, you believe that there's some God's eye point of view which sees the world, the universe, as it really is.
And of course, we can try to approximate this.
People like Einstein thought that we, the scientists like him, had the job of trying to see the universe from God's point of view, see the whole thing.
And Einstein understood that he was a believer, that he believed in God.
And he was doing science to find out the structure of the universe.
And he thought God had created the universe in a way and then created the minds of human beings so that they could understand it.
So he was sure that someday he'd get it all figured, he could contribute at least to getting it figured out.
And even more recent than Einstein is Hawking, who wrote the brief history of Time.
Any of you remember that?
It sort of stands on a lot of people's coffee tables about, what, six years ago or ten years ago?
I don't know.
And not that anybody ever read it, got very far in it as far as I know.
So anyway, about the end of the book, if you get there, not that I read all the pages in between, but if you get there, he says that the job of science is to know the mind of God.
That is, if you knew all the laws of the universe and why the physical constants were the constants that they were, you'd understand sort of the ultimate, I don't know if he wants to say meaning of things, structure of things or something like that.
So people like Einstein and Penrose are still believing in God.
And even scientists who say that they're secular, don't believe in God, still believe in objective truth.
And that's enough from Nietzsche's point of view to show they haven't really stopped believing that there is some point of view from which you could get the truth about things.
This is on 283.
And he says, but you will have gathered what I'm driving at.
This is aphorism 344.
That is, that it is still a metaphysical faith upon which our faith in science rests.
That even we seekers after knowledge today, we godless anti-metaphysicians, see, that is, we think we're godless.
That is, that we are saying we don't believe in God anymore.
We don't believe in metaphysics anymore.
We're just solid secular believers in science.
We godless anti-metaphysicians still take our fire from the flame lit by a faith that is thousands of years old.
That Christian faith, which was also the faith of Plato, that God is truth, that truth is divine.
Then skipping a little.
But what if God Himself proved to be our most enduring lie?
That is, there is no objective truth.
What would He be if there was none?
Well, I'm going to talk more about that later, but just so you won't find it totally mysterious, all there are are interpretations, according to Nietzsche.
You've got your interpretation, I've got mine.
Our culture has its interpretation, Buddhist culture has its interpretation.
There's no right answer to which of those interpretations is the right one.
There's just a whole lot of perspectives.
Sometimes Nietzsche's view is called perspectivism, namely, all you've got is descriptions of yourself, your situation, the universe, the world, and those descriptions are all interpretations.
And it isn't as if there's a right answer, but you just don't know it, or that there's a better interpretation, and they get better and better until they get it right.
No, it's just interpretations.
That's all there is.
That's what he's saying.
And that's what it would be to really realize God.
And that's what, now you see, the people in the marketplace who think that God don't believe in God, and they haven't heard the news that God is dead.
That's the puzzle.
Well, they think they don't believe in God, but they haven't heard the news that there's no objective point of view, no truth, that it's not enough to be anti-metaphysical and anti-theological as long as you believe that there is something with the faith of Plato, that God is true, truth, that there is truth, you're still a believer.
You're a believer who hasn't heard the news.
So now back to 181.
That answers your.
No, it doesn't mean it doesn't have.
No, it only half doesn't answer yours.
That's enough point one.
Point two is: yeah, but what does it mean to say we've killed him?
And how could we, whoever we are, we'll find out, have killed him without knowing that he's dead?
Well, that is even harder, because the one I just did was easy.
He just renamed God, and then he discovers, says that though people think they don't believe in him, they still believe in this objective truth.
But now it's, what's going to happen next?
Well, we're now back on 181.
We're in italics, Nietzsche's screaming at you, we have killed him.
And now, how can that be?
Well, I think for Nietzsche, science kills God, and more interestingly, Christianity kills God.
I'm not going to say much about sciences, because I think that's a whole big thing Nietzsche's view on science, which we don't need to understand breathless, and we don't really need to understand what's important to us about Nietzsche.
So I'll just say, sort of dogmatically: since Nietzsche thinks that there isn't any truth, and everything is interpretation, he thinks, and he thinks, that science is admirable because it's very clear-headed and sober, and has to have agreement and has to follow methods and has to get repeatable answers and so forth.
Science is trying to find out the truth about the universe.
And Nietzsche admires that.
He admires it especially because he thinks that when science finally gets really good at finding out the truth about the universe, he's going to find out that it's all interpretation, that it's chaos of people, that there's no structure except what we read in.
So that science will undermine its, it won't undermine itself as science, because it can still make very important predictions and find causal laws and do nanotechnology and DNA work.
That's fine.
It's just that science can't claim, once it sees what the universe is really like, that there's any one right answer.
There's always whatever science discovered is relative to our interests, our capacities to perceive, and our kind of mind.
And there's no reason to think that God has made the universe to conform to our way of thinking.
And so we're just putting our way of thinking as a kind of projection on it.
And that's fine.
And what interests me is, I would have thought that scientists, at least, wouldn't like this view that science is a social construction, which is very popular in English departments, conflict departments, and rhetoric departments.
Philosophy departments are more resistant to it, I think.
But there are plenty of smart philosophers who think it too, that there isn't any right answer in science.
It's a kind of power game and a respect worth something or other.
Well, I would have thought, and certain philosophers have said, scientists have to believe at least that they're getting the real truth about the world.
Otherwise, why would they work and sacrifice their leisure and struggle on?
Why would there be Nobel Prizes if the Nobel Prize was just a prize for somebody's interpretation, triumphing over somebody else's interpretation?
Well, when I talk to younger scientists, my daughter among them, Humans, but also, I mean, people who are not influenced.
I'm still the old school.
I really like to believe that science is going to be getting it righter and writer about the universe.
But I do see that Nietzsche's winning out.
That he would be pleased to say, he did say that people wouldn't really accept his views and understand him for 300 years.
Turns out it's happening a lot faster than he realized.
The people I talk to in physics and so forth don't anymore claim that there is some one right answer of the structure of the universe that they're getting.
They're making some interesting construction that they will try to convince everybody of, which will correspond to some observation, so forth.
Now, that I said isn't very interesting to what we're talking about.
What we're talking about, because this course is all tied in with the Judeo-Christian tradition, not with the fate of theory, is whether the Christians themselves kill God.
Nietzsche thinks that.
And that's a lot more interesting and ingenious.
How could it be that Christianity, in Nietzsche language, overcame itself?
What would it be for Christianity to overcome itself?
Well, it's a funny variation on what I just said, because what I just said was: science is dedicated to truth.
The truth about the universe is that there isn't any truth about the universe.
It's all just chaos.
So science, in its serious devotion to the truth, will come to the conclusion that there isn't any truth of the sort that, say, Einstein and Newton believed in.
Well, Christianity is also devoted to the truth, a different truth.
Getting people to be honest about their desires.
Remember from the very Sermon on the Mount on, Christianity takes people's desires very seriously.
And you are what you desire.
You better purify your desires and face your evil desires and so forth.
So Christianity develops a whole technology for analyzing people's desires in confession, helping them realize that a lot of what they think they desire is really they're fooling themselves.
They're covering up their dark desires.
And like Yvonne is, I mean, he desires to torture people.
It's nice that Elisa slammed the door on her finger, thumb, or whatever, and while sitting there bleeding and so forth.
But Yvonne would be the last to admit it.
So people have a lot of dark desires that they don't admit.
But Christianity, trying to get the truth about them and get them to confess and get them to face their dark desires in order to finally get them purified and so forth, has become very good at finding out whether people are fooling themselves about their desires or not.
And now the picture Nietzsche has is, well, and we'll hear more about this in a minute, they, well, I think we should better hear it now.
But Christian, well, I'll read this first and then I'll tell you more.
I mean, what people desire, I'll just say it, is that the universe has meaning and a place in it, and that morality makes sense, and that God isn't dead, so all things aren't lawful.
That's what they would like.
But is that a cover-up of what is really the case?
They've got to not fool themselves by thinking that just because they would like it, that's the way it is.
So now comes Christianity around to analyze people's desires and beliefs and see whether they really are justified.
And in this, and so here you hear them on the middle of 307, you're going to hear how Christianity did in Christianity.
It's 357, aphorism 357, page 307.
You see what really triumphed over the Christian God?
Christian morality itself.
The concept of truthfulness that was understood ever more rigorously.
That's how it worked in science too.
If you're dedicated to the truth and there isn't any truth, then someday you're going to undermine yourself.
The Father Confessor's refinement of the Christian conscience translated and sublimated into a scientific conscience, into intellectual cleanliness at any price.
Interpreting, I'm going to skip a bit, interpreting one's experiences as pious people have long enough interpreted theirs as if everything were providential, a hint designed and ordained for the sake of the salvation of the soul.
It is all over now.
Nietzsche's always sort of screaming about this.
That has man's conscience against it, and then, skipping down a bit, in this severity, if anywhere, we're good Europeans and heirs to Europe's longest, most courageous self-overcoming.
So, science self-overcomes by discovering that all you've got is interpretations, instructions.
And Christianity overcomes by discovering that, and now we've got to go into more detail, that something that people always wanted, but which isn't there, is something that they've been fooling themselves into believing is there.
And of course, that's God.
But now let's look at it more carefully.
Nietzsche has this idea that what human beings want more than anything else is meaning in their lives.
And we are, in our culture, especially good at convincing ourselves that it all makes sense and that there's some reason why the world is the way it is and we're in it.
So, this is on 75.
It's aphorism one of book one, page seventy-five.
And what happens is people get more and more interested in finding meaning in the world and fool themselves more and more in thinking that there is some kind of meaning in the world.
So, in the middle of the paragraph below the middle of the page, he says: human nature has been changed by the ever-new appearance of teachers of the purpose of existence.
It now has one additional need, that is, between the kind of need that animals have, that normal people have.
It has one additional need, the need for the ever-new appearance of such teachers and teachings of a purpose.
Well, that's only part of the story.
The story is, we'll read more.
Gradually, man has become a fantastic animal that has to fulfill one more condition of existence than any other animal.
Man has to believe, to know from time to time, why he exists.
His race cannot flourish without a periodical trust in life, without a faith and reason in life.
And again and again, the human race will decree from time to time there is something at which it is absolutely forbidden henceforth to laugh.
Well, lots of things are happening there.
But basically, the idea is, I think, it's sort of in two parts, I think.
I don't know how much Nietzsche has worked this out.
Not any place I've seen it, but it seems like it's something he needs to believe.
When he says, sort of, all human beings and all animals know why they exist, I think he means that's true, the Native Americans and the Bali people and the Japanese.
Every culture has some myths and some ritual that tell it sort of what's going on in the universe and its place in it.
But Nietzsche also thinks that no culture has ever gotten so addicted to so much meaning as this culture.
Because when you think of it, it's pretty amazing.
We're the only culture that has the kind of monotheism, which has this notion that there is one creator, God, who is the source of everything.
Remember, all meaning, all intelligibility, all moral laws, and actually created the universe itself.
I don't think there's any other religion that the Judeo-Christian, and I suppose the Muslims too, which is part of that same Western kind of religion, this particular Western culture, with its particular God, has pushed this meaning of why we exist to the absolute limit, and we become completely meaning addicts.
That is, we have a super monotheistic understanding, partly because of the way these two cultures came together.
On the Hebrew side, there was this creator God, who seemed to be the source of everything.
And then on the Greek side, there was the Plato good, the good, which was some sort of super being that was the source of morality and intelligibility of everything.
And then they got put together.
That's the story I told you in the first lecture by Augustine and the church fathers and then St.
Thomas.
They kept trying, because they looked so similar, because they were these two very, very meaning-oriented, supreme being-oriented cultures, they just merged to a super or supreme being-oriented culture.
What Nietzsche calls monotonotheism, because he doesn't like it.
And he wants to say, everything gets explained finally in terms of this Supreme Being.
For Nietzsche, that's monotonous theism.
Now, I wrote here, but I don't remember why.
You should look at 725 in the Brothers Karamatsu.
It seems strange to me.
I'll go there and I'll tell you what happened.
725.
Here it is, my boy.
What is that?
Suppose we look at 725 in here, but I don't know what happened.
Something in the computer is crazy.
I don't know.
So I'll have to come back and tell you if there is any interesting point behind that.
Let me just mark it.
I can't think of anything about why the Brothers K would be relevant.
Okay, so the important thing is Nietzsche's views.
And now let's go to 343.
It's only when you sort of build up what God means, not only that it's the truth of science, but that all meaning comes from God, that you see how what a terrible thing it would be if we, how much we need God, how much we're ready to fool ourselves into thinking that there's a God, and so forth.
This is on number, this is number 343, page 279.
I'm going to start reading about 10 lines down.
This follows on the death of God story.
The event itself, that's the death of God, itself is far too great, too distant, too remote from the multitude's capacity for comprehension, even for the tidings of it to be thought of as having arrived yet.
Much less may one suppose that many people know as yet what this event really means.
Now, now remember, that's the people in the marketplace.
So they don't really understand that science has undermined belief in God as the truth, and that Christianity has undermined our desire to believe that there's some cause, there's some meaning in existence, because they, I didn't know if I made it clear enough, they're very good at seeing the way people fool themselves into believing what is not, because they want to believe it, what isn't so.
And what they fool themselves into believing is that there's this unified meaning behind existence.
And the techniques of determining how people fool themselves undermine that belief.
I'm just going back over that.
But now, what does it mean?
The death of God.
They don't know what it means.
But now, how much must collapse now that this faith has been undermined?
Because it was built upon this faith, propped up by it, grown into it.
For example, the whole of our European morality, this long plentitude and sequence of breakdown, destruction, ruin, and cataclysm that is now impending, who could guess today, enough of it today, to be compelled to play the teacher and advanced proclaimer of this monstrous logic of terror, the prospect of a gloom and an eclipse of the sun whose light has never yet occurred on earth.
That's it.
You see why he can be confident that nothing like this has ever occurred on earth before, or in the galaxy for that matter, or in the universe for that matter, as far as he can tell.
Why is this so special, this breakdown?
Well, it's just the other side of what's special about the monotheistic Western super monotheism.
I mean, it's only a culture who thinks that there is one God that explains everything that will have this total collapse of its morality and its intelligibility if that God becomes unbelievable.
If you're a polytheist, you've got thousands of gods like in Japan, one more or less doesn't make much difference.
But if you say everything is coming from this one, and then the collapse of that is absolutely unique.
But and yet, these people haven't admitted it yet.
That's because they have become so addicted to meaning and this God that gives the universe meaning that they don't want to acknowledge that there never was anything.
There never was anything.
God is dead, of course, doesn't mean there was once a God that was alive.
There was a God once that was important in the Middle Ages and so forth.
But now, in retrospect, it turns out it was all a self-deception.
That's what Nietzsche thinks.
So, and that people will do anything to believe in that kind of God.
So, in 33, for instance, he's got just one interesting sentence in the maxims of Twilight of the Idols, page 33.
If we possess our why of life, we can put up with almost any how.
Now, that means to say, if we can get this explanation of why we're here and what we're supposed to do, we'll suffer, we'll be willing to suffer, we'll be willing to fight religious wars, we'll be willing to do all sorts of things.
If only we can believe that there's an answer to why we're here and what we're supposed to do.
But when religion gets good at finding out the truth, then it finds out that this craving for meaning and order has been souped up to this kind of addiction to meaning and order.
I mean, every, remember, I think all animals, all human animals, have a craving for meaning and order.
But none of them got into such a delusion of having totally satisfied it as we did.
And then when the craving for meaning and order doesn't have any evidence to support it, then Christianity undermines itself.
That's the sense in which God is dead.
We've killed him.
Christianity undermines any reason for believing in God by examining the motives for believing in God and finding out that those motives are all what people would like, but they aren't based on anything that people can, that you can believe or trust.
I'm looking for something to see if I've already said certain things.
But let's go look.
Have I already talked about page 307?
It seems to me I have.
It's right to see it again.
But yeah, that's the, I was just coming back.
That's just to say we've gone through the longest and most total collapse that any culture could go through.
Anyone want to say anything about any of this so far?
Yeah, go ahead.
Nietzsche would like that.
Now, where's Fuhrerbach?
He's after Nietzsche, presumably.
I'm not chronology isn't any good.
Anyone know?
When is Fuhrerbach?
You brought him up.
I think he's before Nietzsche.
Okay, well, Nietzsche would like that if he knew Feuerbach.
Yeah.
Ah, that's a terrific question.
We have to put that off.
Let me think when we're going to get to it.
I think not next time even, because it doesn't matter for breathless.
But in the end, that's the confrontation find between Kierkegaard and Nietzsche.
I mean, because Kierkegaard says that Christianity has no objective validity.
He says it.
I mean, because it gets all of its validity from the commitments of the people in it.
But if you are committed to it, then you get eternity and time and all that, even though it hasn't got the kind of meaning grounded in a supreme being that Christianity thought it had.
Instead of thinking, well, that must be the end and the disaster, Kierkegaard says, no, that just shows what a strenuous and interesting and exciting thing it is to be a Christian.
Yeah, that's exactly the right question, but I'm not going to talk about it yet.
Anybody else?
Okay, then let's go back to this again.
So now comes the fun part that when Nietzsche gets into describing the disaster that's going to follow, we read some of that already, but that's only part of it.
Let's see now.
So it's going to be a kind of reign of terror.
We just read that on 343.
I want to come back to it now because this is the result when finally science and Christianity both become suspicious of this belief in God as founded only in this strong desire to have meaning without any evidence for it, then everything falls apart.
And Nietzsche calls this collapse a cataclysm, which is a nice thing to call it because what is a cataclysm?
I gather that a cataclysm is a kind of breakdown of the foundation.
It's a kind of huge earthquake in which everything collapses.
And it's a neat name for this because God has been the foundation, the ground, the support of everything.
And when God gets undermined, even though the people who do the undermining don't realize they've done it, as they begin to realize they've done it, then it begins to be a complete breakdown of everything.
And when they finally realize it, it will be the total breakdown of everything.
And that's the cataclysm he's talking about: this long plenitude and sequence of breakdown, destruction, ruin, and cataclysm that's now impending.
Who could guess?
Stop with that.
Now, this is interesting in itself, but it's particularly interesting if you're asking yourself, could Nietzsche, does it look like Nietzsche read The Brothers?
Do you recognize that?
Probably not.
But does that strike you as familiar, this talk about the cataclysm?
Yeah.
That's right.
It's one of Yvonne's papers or whatever they were.
And who tells him about it?
The devil.
The devil comes and talks to Yvonne when the devil is there talking to Yvonne.
Yvonne is hallucinating the devil.
And you have to read this to see.
Now, I haven't told you the whole Nietzsche story yet, but just enough to get to the word cataclysm.
So now we're going to see the Dostoevsky story.
And then we'll go back and see how much Nietzsche could have gotten from this Dostoevsky story.
It's really absolutely wonderful and amazing.
And so we start on 6:13 of the brothers.
This is called, this paper, The Geological Cataclysm.
See that about 12 lines down?
The devil says, and the geological cataclysm.
Do you remember?
That was a poem.
And Yvonne says, keep quiet or I'll kill you.
And then they go around saying funny things to each other for a while until about the very middle of the page.
I'm going to read the whole thing because it's just so similar.
As soon as men have all denied God, and I believe that now the devil is quoting Yvonne, and I believe that period corresponding with geological periods will come to pass.
The old conception of the universe will fall of itself without cannibalism, and once more the old morality and everything will begin anew.
Men will unite to take from life all that it can give, but only for joy and happiness in the present world.
Man will be lifted up with a spirit of divine titanic pride, and the man God will appear.
Extending his conquest of nature by his will and his science, man will feel such lofty joy from hour to hour that it will make up for all his old dreams and the joys of heaven.
Everyone will know that he is mortal.
Everyone will know that he is mortal and will accept death proudly and serenely like a God.
His pride will teach him that it's useless for him to grieve at life's being a moment, and he will love his brother without need of reward and love the fact that life is a moment.
You will see more about that later.
Love will be sufficiently only for a moment of life, that this very consciousness will intensify its fire, which now is dissipated in dreams of eternal love beyond the grave, and so on and so on, in the same style.
Charming.
And I better read you a little more at the bottom of the page, because it's all so relevant.
Four lines from the bottom.
That since owing to man's stupidity, this cannot come about for at least a thousand years.
Everyone who recognizes the truth now may legitimately order his life as he pleases on the new principle.
In that sense, all things are lawful for him.
What's more, even if this period never comes, since there is anyway no God and no immortality, the new man may well become the man-God, even if he is the only one in the whole world promoted to this new position.
He may lightheartedly overstep all the barriers of the old morality, the old slave man, if necessary.
There's no law or God where God stands, and so forth.
Okay, now that's Dostoevsky.
Now look at Nietzsche.
We'll see what he thinks.
This is, remember, this is Yvonne's version of what will happen when there is this cataclysm and God is dead, and everybody recognizes that God is dead, and the whole world collapses into this terribly dark situation.
I just want to read more in 181 of the darkness before I get to the, on 180, on 125, page 181.
Remember?
No, I think that's enough.
I'm going to go on with Nietzsche's response.
So notice now, yeah, I think I should just go directly to page stand 279 where we were.
So we've just read about the sequence of breakdown, destruction, cataclysm, and so forth.
Who could guess enough to be compelled to play the teacher and the France proclaimer of this monstrous logic of terror, the prophet of a gloom and an eclipse of the sun whose light has probably never yet occurred on earth?
Why?
We thought, because it's everything at last.
Now, what's peculiar about that particular aphorism on page 270?
I just read you about the most dark and gloomy and horrible prediction you could imagine.
Everything just goes completely to hell, and there's nothing left but darkness and disaster.
Well, that's called the meaning of our cheerfulness, if you look back up at the top.
Now, that needs some explaining.
Somebody thinks it's funny.
I think it's funny.
And so, why is it the meaning of our cheerfulness?
Well, it isn't as if we're going to get the meaning back.
That would be the first thing.
Maybe there'll become a new God, maybe a better God, something, we'll all believe in something else that's meaningful.
Now, that's not how it's going to be.
Look at 124, right, before the madman, back on page 180.
We have left the land and have embarked.
We burned our bridges behind us.
Indeed, we've gone further and destroyed the land behind us.
Now, little ship, look out.
Beside you is the ocean, and so forth and so forth.
Hours will come and you realize that it's infinite and nothing more awesome than infinity.
And then what will skip, woe when you feel homesick for the land as if it offered you more freedom and there's no longer any land.
Well, that's pretty metaphorical.
But that says something like: you can't go back to the solid foundation on the earth, on the ground, on the basis of which you can make sense of things.
It's gone.
And you burned the bridges behind you.
You've destroyed the land behind.
Now, it's interesting to try to figure out why it's destroyed and why there is no more land once this all collapses.
Well, the answer is, of course, that it's because everything has been built into it.
That's back on page wherever.
Let's see now.
Yeah, on the middle of 279.
Much less may one suppose that many people know as yet what this event really means, how much must collapse now that the faith has been undermined, because it was built upon this faith, propped up by it, grown into it, the whole of European morality, for example.
Okay, so if everything we understand in our morality, in our understanding of the universe, in how we make sense of things, if it's all built into this supreme being, this monotheistic account, and we stop believing in the supreme being by undermining it through our suspicious kind of belief about our own, getting the truth about our own desires, and our finding out about the universe is just chaos.
If we undermine this, then we undermine everything, because it's all built into this.
And if we undermine everything, then you can't go back.
You burned your bridges behind you.
There's no land behind you.
We've destroyed the land behind us.
Because once, I mean, you don't, the cultures, my Bali or Japanese are my favorite examples and so forth, cultures who never had one God, don't have this problem.
Their values aren't all built on some one thing, so that if that collapsed, everything would collapse.
They still got the ground.
They've got their local traditional ritual mythical ground to stand on.
But if you, if this is the penalty, so to speak, Nietzsche would say, for having built this beautiful edifice of meaning in order to satisfy more and more our desire for meaning and produce the most meaningful culture ever, the cost of it is it's a lie.
And when the lie comes out, the more you build it all into this, the more it all collapses.
You can't get it back.
There's no way to get the people.
So now, and what is Nietzsche's response to that?
Well, that's, it would begin to sound familiar.
So let's start the bottom paragraph on 181.
How shall we comfort ourselves, the murderers of all murderers?
What was holiest and mightiest of all, that the world has yet known as bled to death under our knives?
Who will wipe the blood from us, and so forth and so forth?
Is not the greatness of this deed too great for us?
Must we not ourselves become gods simply to be worthy of it?
Sound familiar?
Like what he might have been reading?
I mean, Dostoevsky says we should become gods ourselves.
And then Yvonne's got this whole picture.
Let's go back to 739.
It's spread around in Dostoevsky, I think.
I mean, I haven't ever looked it all up, but oh, what's happening here?
Seven.
I'm wrong about seven thirteen.
Six thirteen in Dostoevsky and the brothers.
More of Yvonne.
Okay, the God-man will appear.
Well, I read that already.
Okay, let's see if that's what we want.
Yeah, the God-man will appear.
And now there and how will people feel about this?
Well, they'll be very happy.
They'll be joyful, Yvonne says.
And everyone will know that they're God and be proud and serene and loving and so forth.
And they will order their lives on this new principle.
They'll be as happy as if they were in heaven, he says.
And the new man becomes the man-god and so forth.
Well, Nietzsche has the same view.
It's going to be terrific.
That's why he's cheerful.
Once you get over this cataclysm, you will wake up as if from a long sickness, and you will be all the healthier and happier for having overcome the sickness.
That is, you will have what Nietzsche would call the greatest overcoming that any culture ever had.
I mean, that's the other side of the greatest collapse.
No other culture had the opportunity to have, so to speak, the open sea before us and be able to start from scratch to build our own world as this culture does.
Because it's not bound by tradition and ritual and myths.
They're all gone.
They all got swallowed up by Christianity and then they collapsed.
And now you have this wonderful feeling of having sort of waked up from a bad dream and full of health and vigor.
And that's sort of behind the gay science.
He's built it into the gay science from the very start.
The gay science is about recovering from a sickness and what a positive thing that is and how new and joyful you feel.
That's the gay science.
It's sometimes translated the joyful wisdom.
It could be either way in German.
But he starts right out in the preface to the second edition on page 32 to do this, to say that this book is about an experience.
And it's about an experience of, at the end of the first paragraph, the proximity of winter and the triumph over winter.
Or to put in the middle of the next of that page, it's about the hope of health and the intoxication of convalescence.
That's the state the culture is in.
Once there, I mean, he thinks probably it's not there yet, except for him.
And he remembers it might take, sometimes he says 300 years, sometimes he says 1,000 before people will be able to recognize that there isn't any God and accept it.
And they have to go through all this disaster of everybody killing everybody and this clear failure of all morality.
And so everybody's thinking that God is dead, all things are possible.
But when they finally get over all that, then they are in good shape.
And he talks about that in about 15 lines from the bottom of 32.
He talks about the rejoicing of strength, that is, the returning of a reawakened faith in a mot tomorrow and a day after tomorrow, a sense of anticipation, impending adventures of seas that are open again, we recognize the infinite open sea because they got rid of the land, of goals that are permitted again.
Or at the bottom of 33, in some it is their deprivations that philosophize.
That's what's wrong with philosophers like Yvonne.
In others, that there are others who can philosophize out of richness and strength.
That's Nietzsche.
The former need their philosophy, whether it be as a proper sedative, a medicine, redemption, elevation, or self-alienation.
But the latter, it's a beautiful luxury.
So that's not so important as the claim that all of this is going to be like recovering from a sickness.
And that means that it's the most, it's a very healthy thing.
In fact, it's the healthiest thing you can do is to constantly outgrow and overcome whatever it is that's holding you back, drawing you down, like a sickness.
So we have to read more about that, what he calls the great health, which is 382 in aphorisms, 346 in our pages.
So now he's talking about, and let's give them a name.
He's talking about what he calls the free spirits.
Those are the people who are happy and cheerful and feel grateful about this collapse.
They even feel grateful that there was this thickness so that it could collapse, because it made them stronger to have gone through it and then recovered from it.
So here he's talking about this great health at the bottom of 346 in the last paragraph, page 346.
And now, after we've long been on our way in this manner, we aggregate, argonauts of the ideal, with more daring perhaps than is prudent, and have suffered shipwreck and damage often enough.
We are to repeat, healthier than ones likes to permit us, dangerously healthy, ever again healthy.
It will seem to us as if, as a reward, we now confronted an as yet undiscovered country.
Now, last time it was the open sea, whose boundaries nobody has surveyed yet, something beyond all the lands and nooks of the ideal so far.
A world so overrich in what is beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible, and divine that our curiosity as well as our craving to possess it got beside itself.
Alas, now nothing will say to us anymore.
Well, that's nice and interesting, and that's the part of this experience of the great health.
But what's interesting on that list, and I'll come back and talk to more about this after.
Well, to mention it now, it's got to have some relevance.
That do you notice what is not on that list?
It's very hard to notice what's not there.
That there's something, he says how beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible, divine the world will look to these new healthy people who survived the collapse.
Well, it won't look meaningful.
That's what's not on the list.
How intelligible, how understandable, how, what was the phrase on 33 that in the maxims that people had to have or die, that's not on the list.
The why of life.
Well, yeah, it's not going to give you a meaning.
It's not going to give you a why.
It's going to give you a whole lot of other things.
Beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible.
And he's going to redefine the divine.
The divine in this sickness that the culture went through for 2,000 years was the why, was the meaning.
Now the divine is all this other stuff.
If you need one word for it, I think Nietzsche's got the notion that instead of the world of meaning, it's a kind of wonder world.
Everything is wonderful and strange and surprising and all these things, beautiful, questionable, terrible.
That's all wonder talk, as opposed to meaning talk.
He's inventing this whole thing, he needs to.
If he's going to tell us what it's going to be like for these happy people after the world has collapsed and there's no meaning left, he's not going to be telling you, or it'd be very boring.
There would be a new meaning now.
Science will tell us, psychoanalysis will tell us, whatever, DNA will tell us.
I mean, he's not going to find some new answer to why.
He's going to say, well, it's just wonderful to be on this open sea with no boundaries, no landmarks, no rules, inventing, constantly reinventing ourselves, reinventing the world.
And you'll see when you're reading, having new suns, for instance, we've let the old sun go.
He said it's disconnected because it was part of the divine picture.
But we'll invent new sons.
And that's the idea.
And it goes on on 347.
So let's read more of it.
First, I want to see where I am.
Yeah, let's read it.
Another, a second paragraph.
I'm going to read all of that too.
Another ideal, because this is related to the movie.
Another ideal runs ahead of us, a strange, tempting, dangerous ideal that which we should not wish to persuade anybody because we do not readily concede the right to it to anybody.
An ideal of a spirit who plays naively, that is, not deliberately, but from overflowing power and abundance, with all that was hitherto called holy, good, untouchable, divine.
For whom?
For whom, where were we?
I've lost it.
Oh, yeah, for whom those supreme things that the people naturally accept as their value standards signify danger, decay, debasement, or at least recreation, blindness, and temporary self-oblivion.
Now, this is the good thing: the ideal of a human, superhuman well-being and benevolence that will often appear inhuman, for example, when it confronts all earthly seriousness, so far all solemnity in gesture, word, tone, eye, morality, and tasks and tasks, all these, so far as if it were their most incarnate and involuntary parody.
In spite of all this, or perhaps with it, let's stop with that.
So that's, again, one way to put this, remember, is that the old sacred was something at which you couldn't laugh.
And remember, he said that, I read that earlier today.
And remember in the brothers, Alyasha tells the boys that there's something at which they cannot laugh.
That's what now, even everything, even the sacred, is up to make jokes about.
There's nothing at which one cannot laugh.
That's what Nietzsche wants to say.
It was kind of a cowardice to take something and say that you can't.
In the brothers, it's a little below the middle of 728.
Together at this stone, the cruelest and most mocking of us, if we do become so, will not dare to laugh inwardly at having been good and kind at this moment, and so forth.
I mean, because that's a sacred moment.
The sacred moment, remember, keeps its meaning no matter how much other things come in and try to change it.
And Nietzsche doesn't believe in any sacred moment.
We'll come back to that again later.
We don't need to talk about it in more detail right yet.
Anybody want to say anything about this?
This is the next sort of big chunk of what we should be talking about.
So there's the great health, and we've just been reading about the great health.
And now they have to relate that to something else.
Why is it sort of, why is this, what is this sort of the basis of this health?
Why is it important and good, it's sort of the good in Nietzsche, to be constantly outgrowing and convalescing from and taking, leaving behind everything that you were and cared about before.
What's so good about that?
Well, we haven't really got that yet, but we will right now.
So the bottom line in Nietzsche is that life, life is constant overcoming.
Just being alive on 291, 349 aphorism.
Yeah, I would love to have you ask your question.
Yeah.
No, I didn't, did I?
I wondered if anybody would notice.
Good for you.
I find that very hard.
Do you know what to say?
The tragedy begins.
Okay, I'll tell you what I think, but I'm not sure.
Tragedy doesn't have to mean, you know, bad stuff.
I'm sure this is right.
I mean, people think now that tragedy is about suffering and not just any old unhappiness, but some kind of necessary suffering.
That's what happens to Oedipus.
That's what happens in every tragedy in Hamlet.
There's lots of suffering.
People learn from their suffering.
But it's not so upbeat.
I mean, but it's already implicit.
But in the first tragedy, I'm thinking, let's go back to Aeschylus.
I remember Nietzsche knows all of this.
The tragedy of the Oristeia, which my teacher in philosophy fixed, is that through going through a lot of suffering, something utterly new and better comes out of it.
You know the Oristea.
Suffer, the chorus keeps saying, suffer, suffer, but good comes out in the end.
That's a refrain in the Oristeia chorus.
Well, if that's, that would fit this.
Suffer from the total collapse of everything.
But good will come out in the end.
It is, yes, we'll have a new health, we'll be better off.
What do you think?
Does that make sense?
If not, I don't know what to say.
Hmm.
Then I don't know what to say.
You guys go back to that page.
I really don't know what to say.
That was the best I ever came up with right now.
But let's try.
What page are you on?
347.
Now, somebody should figure this out, but it must be very hard.
Our visitor here from another university who teaches Nietzsche doesn't know, and I don't know, but let's read it.
I purposely didn't.
But on the middle of 347, in spite of all this, it is perhaps only with him, that's the free spirit, that great seriousness really begins, that the real question mark is posed for the first time.
The destiny of the soul changes.
The hand moves forward.
Tragedy begins.
It says the reference doesn't have the.
I was going to say that it must have to do with Zarathustra, but what it has to do with that.
That's another book written by Nietzsche.
So, what does it mean?
The destiny?
Does it have to do with the eternal return, or what would it have to do?
Okay.
He also all suffering.
Even the most free spirit has to go through all kinds of tragic stuff, which is going to end up, presumably, with the triumph of outgrowing in health, I guess.
Anyway, so okay, if you are helpful, what can you do with it?
That's the birth of tragedy.
He left that a long time ago, but that, I mean, this is, you know, that was the first thing he wrote, and this is one of the last.
But that doesn't mean that he isn't.
What would he be doing if he were talking about it?
Oh, now we're back in it when we can really experience tragedy in a good sense.
Maybe.
I mean, I don't know.
You're going to say something good, Chrissy.
That's good.
Yeah.
Maybe.
One thing, each of these things suffering is important and a good thing, but you end up with something better.
And that's something like that has happened.
The tragedy isn't a bad kind of suffering.
It's a good kind of suffering.
And the other kind of suffering that they've been doing for all this time, this self-deceptive happiness and cheerfulness, the divine comedy, that's really sad.
What's not sad is facing the suffering somehow and growing because of it.
That's the best I can do, too.
And this, you're telling this particular story of how particularly tragedy works to sort of through this merging of the two and to produce something better.
Yeah, yeah?
Okay.
Um you look you're on his side.
Good.
I'm on his side too, if we can understand it.
370, where?
Okay, okay, let's look at that.
That sounds right, that it's tragedy is some kind of good thing.
I'm looking down even further, the desire for destruction, change, and becoming can be an expression of overflowing energy that is pregnant with future.
My term for this is Dionysia.
So you're on the right track.
The Dionysian tragedy is a kind of tragedy which fits with the kind of energy that's constantly destroying what's behind and moving on.
I think that's it's got something to do with that.
Let me write that down.
I'm glad glad you questioned it.
So now we want to when he says the tragedy begins, where is that?
347.
Okay, we want to refer ourselves back to 329.
Sounds good.
Here we'll refer to 347.
Okay, now I want to just go a little further, because they're kind of loose end unless we go a little further.
And that is, what is life?
Well, we were on 291.
Or really, 280, yes, 291, a very important line.
It's not a big deal in this book, but it's a big deal in Nietzsche's mind.
So at the bottom.
And it's tied up with tragedy in a way.
Because it's going to say sort of destruction and rebirth is what's important.
The wish to preserve oneself is a symptom of a condition of distress, of a limitation, of the really fundamental instinct of life, which aims at the expansion of power.
And wishing for that frequently risks and even sacrifices self-preservation.
And so forth.
And then skipping to the bottom of that aphorism.
The great and small struggle always resolves around superiority, around growth and expansion, around power in accordance with the will to power, which is the will of life.
So the great health is the happiness that comes from outgrowing what you are and going on to something further, constant or overcoming.
And the collapse of the whole Christian, Judeo-Christian Greek thing that the culture has been in for 2,000 years until Nietzsche thinks he should helped collapse it.
Of course, he didn't make it collapse.
He just saw the collapse and sort of pushed it.
But in any case, the collapse of that culture is the greatest overcoming, the most alive, the most terrific thing that could have happened.
That's the point of the cheerfulness.
And that's what the free spirits understand.
The free spirits are enjoying the suffering and the collapse.
Or more, no, that's not the right word.
They're enjoying what comes after it.
They're enjoying the open sea of being able to do something new, something wonderful, not something meaningful, and open up new worlds, as he says.
I'll go back to that next time.
I want to stop now.
Just reminding you that next time now is Monday from 5:30 to 7 in Mulford 159.
What I'm going to talk about a lot more is what it is like to be a free spirit.