So, the first thing I wanted to do was to go back for a minute to brief habits because we had a discussion.
I had it with someone over there, I believe, about what Nietzsche thought was the worst thing, where there was a kind of brief habit that he couldn't stand.
And I forget what whoever it was said.
If you remember who you are, you can say it again.
But I said I thought that was wrong, and I think I found a passage to show it.
But what did you say again?
Why is having no habits at all bad?
Ah, that's not it.
Interestingly enough, I found a passage.
I said I thought that he thought that I didn't say it clearly enough.
Oddly enough, Nietzsche, who's telling you that he's a kind of, sort of free spirit, is plugging brief habits, which already are out of the meaning business, out of the eternity business, into the wonder business.
But he's not the freest spirit.
There is a kind of free spirit, sort of really postmodern, which he's imagining, which he couldn't, he says is just too much for him.
He couldn't stand it.
But you need two passages put together to see this.
At the bottom of 237, that is, in 295, which is the brief habits piece, he says, most intolerable, to be sure, and the terrible par excellence would be for me, that is Nietzsche, a life entirely devoid of habits, a life that would demand perpetual improvisation.
That would be my exile in my Siberia.
Now, maybe that, you might think, would be a kind of nihilism, but it isn't.
He says on 290 that that would be the most extreme and I guess good kind of brief habit, though it's hard to picture what it would even be.
If you look on 289 at the bottom, that's 347, but way into it.
Just at the very end of aphorism 347, that's page 289.
He says, one can conceive such a pleasure and power of self-determination, such a freedom of the will, that the spirit would take leave of all faith and every wish for certainty, being practiced in maintaining himself on insubstantial ropes and possibilities and dancing even near abysses.
Such a spirit would be the very spirit par excellence.
Now, I don't know for sure, but it looks like he's saying that's even freer than he can be with his feeling that he should sort of sink into each brief habit and hold on to it as long as it lasts.
I guess I can't even picture what this free spirit would be because he wouldn't even hardly be outgrowing anything because he wouldn't be in anything in order to outgrow it.
But I just read you what's there.
You might come in and tell me some way to read this.
You have a view about that?
And even dancing around abysses, that doesn't seem like, I mean, maybe, but what would be then this most, well, never mind.
Let's talk about it more.
I don't know what it is.
I just wanted to tell you, because last time I said, I thought there was something about dancing somewhere in here, and I finally found it.
So now, end of that.
That's just a leftover little piece from last time.
The main subject for this time is the almost free spirits, and they include, and this is what's interesting, Jesus, and they would include Markle.
And that begins to bring me to the similarities between Nietzsche and Dostoevsky on the one hand.
And then the second half of the lecture, we'll get to the big differences between Nietzsche and Dostoevsky.
And that's where I want to sort of compare the various views of life that are being proposed by Kierkegaard, Nietzsche, and Dostoevsky.
And finally, after that, if there's time today, and if not, that's fine.
On Tuesday, I want to hear your views about, or take a vote at least, about which way of life is the one that you find convincing, if any.
But it takes a while, so let's go.
So we've got Nietzsche's Jesus.
I told you to bring the Antichrist and the Twilights of the Idols.
So we're on 152.
And that is, he says, in aphorism 29, what I am concerned with is the psychological type of the Redeemer.
And we don't know yet what that means.
And it starts out looking rather bad for the Redeemer from Kierkegaard's, from Nietzsche's point of view.
That is, he says, where he doesn't say it.
Or 155.
He says it in about five lines down.
One has to regret that no Dostoevsky lived in the neighborhood of this most interesting decadent.
That's Jesus.
I mean someone who could feel the thrilling fascination of such a combination of the sublime, the sick, the childish.
That should remove you who read The Idiot, and I remember there were very few, that sounds like a very quick summary of the view of Jesus as the idiot in The Idiot.
And that suggests that maybe Dostoevsky read it.
Nietzsche read it.
People think that if Nietzsche has read any of the Dostoevsky novels, that would be the one he's read.
And it also could remind you of Markle, who is sublime and sick and childish, but is saying these wonderful revealing of God and connectedness and love pronouncements.
But he is a decadent.
So we have to understand what's that.
He's not like a Socrates decadent.
That's the next thing to say.
I mean, Socrates was really decadent.
I mean, his instincts were all in total chaos, and he wanted to die, and he was against the body and against life and so forth.
That's the picture that comes down of Socrates through Plato.
That's not at all like Jesus.
And now comes one of the most surprising lines in the book about on 156.
After all the ranting against Christianity, about 15 lines from the bottom, one could, with some freedom of expression, call Jesus a free spirit.
And now, why would he do that?
Well, he has certain things in common with Nietzsche as free spirit.
He cares nothing for what is fixed.
That's good.
He's not, according to Dostoevsky, in the eternity business.
He's in the constant overcoming.
The word killeth, everything fixed killeth.
He's putting his version or his spin on it.
The concept, the experience of life, in the only form he knows it, is opposed to any kind of word, formula, law, faith, dogma.
Remember, Jesus says he comes to fulfill the law.
He doesn't have to obey the law anymore.
He goes on the Sabbath and cures people.
You're not supposed to do that.
And Nietzsche's got something right there.
Remember, way back I said that's where your feeling, your desire, your joy or non-joy is the test of whether you're a good person or not, not whether you obey the law or not.
And that makes Jesus, if you cut it up that way, sound like Nietzsche.
And he wants to, but if you're going to say that, then you've got to distinguish Nietzsche from the Christians, what they made of Nietzsche.
And that's on 154.
No, it isn't.
That's still.
Why am I saying that?
Just a second.
Ah, oh, I'm saying, get ready for the fact that we're gonna, he's going to be telling you about Jesus for a minute, but then he's going to tell you, of course, the Christians immediately lost it.
But this is still what makes Jesus look like a free spirit on 154.
He says that the aphorism 31, I have anticipated my answer to the problem.
That is the problem of Jesus.
Its presupposition is that the type of the Redeemer has been preserved to us only in a very distorted form.
So he's picturing his own view of what Jesus was doing and saying.
And then he's telling you, it's, boy, is that not what Paul, particularly Paul, turned it into.
But let's go on with what he thinks it is.
He again goes back to Dostoevsky at the bottom of 154.
That strange and sick world to which the Gospels introduces us, a world like that of the Russian novel, in which the ref in which refuse of society, neurosis, and childlike idiocy seem to have a rendezvous, must in any case have coarsened the type.
The first disciples in particular had to translate a being immensely immersed entirely in symbols and incomprehensibility.
That's complicated.
That says that Jesus was talking in parables.
Jesus was bringing in such a new world, being a a super free spirit, he's opening up a whole new world.
I mean, there was the ancient world, there was the Hebrew world, pretty soon there's going to be the Christian world, but the Christian world isn't here yet, so at that point.
So Jesus has to talk in parables and symbols, and these are incomprehensible, naturally, to the disciples who are still have the only only the old vocabulary, and only the Hebrew world can make sense of this, which can't make sense of this.
So obviously they're going to get it wrong.
So Nietzsche's got an argument, which is an interesting argument, that it must be distorted, which we're going to read in Paul and in the Gospels.
They couldn't understand it.
And every once in a while you see in the Gospels Jesus says things and the disciples say things, and you can see Jesus is exasperated because the disciples haven't understood anything.
And that's because, I mean, Jesus sounds to them crazy, just as Markle sounds to everybody crazy.
Remember, Markle is the Jesus figure in the book, childlike, sick with tuberculosis, brain fever, and saying utterly incomprehensible things, or pretty incomprehensible, not really because 2,000 years of Christianity have made them comprehensible, but saying the servants should wash the feet of their masters and saying we should love everything and everybody, even the birds.
I don't think even Jesus said we should love the birds.
St.
Francis said it, and Markle says it.
So let me go a little further, the bottom of 154.
So they translate these incomprehensibilities into their own crudity in order to understand anything at all.
For them, such a type could not exist until it had been reduced to more familiar terms.
That's all exactly what I'm saying.
And Nietzsche is absolutely right.
That's bound to be a problem.
But Jesus, you can glimmer through their incomprehension that Jesus is, as I said, against fixed moral laws.
That was the bottom of 156.
And a belief in, and then now look at the middle of 157.
He thinks that the Christians soon thought Jesus was talking about denial, about denying your sensuous side, your body, your impulses, the sins in your members, as Paul would put it, and so forth.
But he wasn't, according to Nietzsche.
He says denial is precisely what is totally impossible for him.
Dialectics are likewise lacking, so he's not going around making arguments like Socrates.
The idea is lacking that a faith, a truth, could be proved by reasons.
That's what Socrates thinks.
That's what, according to my son, Buddhist, thinks.
Buddhists, at least his kind of Tibetan Buddhists, I get constantly bombarded with arguments that are supposed to convince me that the Buddhist way of looking at things is true.
That's not Jesus.
His proofs are inner lights, inner feelings of pleasure, self-affirmations, nothing but proofs by potency.
That is very Nietzschean.
I mean, he thinks that Jesus thinks sort of power and joy is evidence that he's on the right track.
In effect, he's saying what Markle says, when Markle says that we're in paradise here and now if we would only see it.
That is exactly what Nietzsche is attributing to Jesus.
If you look on 158 now, at the end of number 33, the profound instinct of how one would have to live in order to feel oneself in heaven, to feel oneself eternal, while in another condition, one by no means feels oneself in heaven.
This alone is the psychological reality of redemption, a new way of living, not a new belief.
Well, that's complicated, but what that says is, like Markle, if you feel that you're in heaven here and now, that is, as Markle puts it, if you're in paradise here and now, if you'd only see it, then you are in paradise.
And that's what Jesus was defending, not some other world, but a way of living in this world that turns it into paradise in heaven here and now.
In other words, it's all gotten existentialized by Nietzsche.
So one more on 159.
So he's going to talk about the notion of the Father and the Son.
So he says, I grant, about five lines down, in the word Son is expressed the entry into the collective feeling of the transfiguration of all things.
In that sense, Markle is like Jesus, who is the Son, not S-O-N, but S-U-N.
But remember, the idea is that Markle and Jesus manifest this new way of life, this loving way of life, and it enters the world that way.
The connectedness enters the world.
So in the word Father, this feeling itself, the feeling of perfection and eternity, I'm ashamed to recall what the church has made of this symbolism.
So he's happy, Nietzsche, with some feeling of, if not an ocean of love quite, but some feeling of happiness here and now, power outside of the law, and so forth.
And suffering doesn't play any role in his reconstruction of all this.
So yet, okay, so far so good.
Anybody want to protest?
I mean, you can protest that, boy, is this far from the Bible, but if I'd let you protest that, I should have.
Then I would give you Nietzsche's story I just did, but you can't expect the Bible to get it right.
It's too much a new world, a new sun, a new perspective, a new interpretation, a new everything for them to get it right.
So we have to get it right.
Nietzsche is going to fix it by existentializing it.
But here's the next question.
But why is then he called a decadent?
So far, it looks like everything about him is the whole right.
Well, gee, I didn't read the crucial sentence.
How peculiar.
What happened here?
I mean, before we answer that, where is the, I'll find it in a minute.
Here we are.
The top of 163.
Oh, I was going to get there, but I'd rather read it right now.
The middle of.
Yeah, the top of 163.
I resume.
I shall now relate the real history of Christianity.
The word Christianity is already a misunderstanding.
In reality, there has been only one Christian, and he died on the cross.
So we're talking about the one Christian who was a free spirit, but it all got changed.
But back to, so what about what happened there?
That his dying on the cross was already a sign that, well, no, I better say something else.
That Nietzsche doesn't tell you right off.
You have to figure it out.
I want to know whether anybody can figure it out.
Given all that description of Jesus, what did he do wrong?
And it has to do with dying.
Anybody know?
Well, I think it's that he was meek.
I mean, he should have fought back.
He should have led a rebellion of freedom fighters.
Maybe he was trying to lead a rebellion of freedom fighters, I think.
But in any case, he didn't.
He was meek.
That was part of the problem.
And he was compassionate.
Now comes the real standoff between Nietzsche and all of the Christian view, even the very, very nearly right you that Jesus had.
And the big issue is: what do you do with the people who are weak and don't have the power to have brief habits, to constantly overcome, to turn against the ethics, to open new worlds?
What do you do with them?
Well, it clearly, in Dostoevsky, somebody like Alyasha helps them, tries to prop them up and get them as near to being, and get them in touch with the love, and never mind that they're in touch with the love, they don't need any more strength than that.
That'll do it.
But Nietzsche, and now we have to look at 159, where you get a hint of this thing I'm telling you.
I didn't make it up completely.
And now we're at 35.
This bringer of glad tidings, that's the Bible.
I mean, Nietzsche thinks that the glad tidings that Jesus had got turned into bad tidings by the followers.
But the bringer of glad tidings died as he lived.
Died as he lived, as he taught, not to redeem mankind, but to demonstrate how one ought to live.
What he bequeathed to mankind in his practice, his bearing before the judges, before the guards, before the accusers, in every kind of calamity and mockery, his bearing on the cross.
Now comes the trouble.
Sorry.
He does not resist.
He does not defend his rights.
He takes no steps to avert the worst that can happen to him.
Now, that kind of nonviolence, that kind of pacifism, boy, is that not a Nietzschean virtue.
I mean, that's not life.
That's not overcoming.
The best place to see more of that is in what he says.
I thought I had it here, but I'm now wondering where.
We'll find out.
So.
Funny.
It's a very important quote where I guess we'll have to wait till we get to what I'm in my.
I would have put it here.
Just a second.
It's about life.
Here they are.
Let's look at 27 and 28 of Twilight.
Well, no, 127.
Try that.
You have to see how un Christian this is.
Ah, yeah, this is what I was looking for.
Starting at the bottom of 127.
Try this on, try this on.
Jesus.
What is good?
All that heightens the feeling of power, the will to power, power itself in man.
What is bad?
All that proceeds from weakness.
What is happiness?
The feeling that power increases, that a resistance is overcome.
Now, then, not contentment, but more power.
Not peace at all, but war.
Not virtue, but proficiency.
Virtue in the Renaissance style.
The weak and ill-constituted.
Now, I mean, that's already sort of un Jesus un-Christian, but it gets extremer.
The weak and ill-constructed shall perish, first principle of our philosophy.
And one shall help them do so.
I mean, that's getting really the opposite.
I mean, so if you find weak people, the best thing you could do is sort of put them out of their misery.
What is more harmful than vice?
Active sympathy for the ill-constituted and weak.
Christianity.
Well, that little bit of Christianity is enough, I take it, to disqualify Jesus as a free spirit.
Although he, except for that, he comes close.
There, he slips over into Dostoevsky-like compassion and connectedness, and Nietzsche doesn't believe in that.
Any questions about that?
Yeah.
Wait, we can somebody close the doors?
I don't know about you guys, but I have trouble hearing because of the background noise.
Go ahead.
Well, probably, but you'll have to say it again because I couldn't hear it because of the background noise.
Try again.
Yeah, it is.
No, what gives you power is healthy because it's life.
Life is constantly getting more powerful, overcoming what you were.
He keeps talking like outgrowing, getting stronger.
And that's all life.
And Socrates' interest in truth doesn't give him power because it leaves him with this other world of truth that does in this world that he doesn't really wish he wasn't in this world, struggling, overcoming, and so forth.
Have I understood you?
Oh, okay.
So, anything else?
Nobody?
Oh, there's plenty of other issues, but if there is on this issue, I'm not going to.
This is all I have to say about this, but this is all he says about it.
Yeah.
Yes, I'm glad you asked.
I'm glad you asked.
Yes, but in a funny way, that you, I was discussing that with the TAs this morning.
It's true that up to the last minute of the movie, you can't tell whether he's got power and control of his life.
He seems sort of to be, but he's sort of just, he's not getting anywhere, and he's running from the police and so forth.
But what is there about the last what?
Well, it's about his death.
He shows that he's not just a sort of anybody bounced around by forces that he doesn't control, and that his life is just out of control.
He takes control of his life completely in his death.
He, you know, I've said he runs to the crosswalk, he falls down, he takes his last puff, he throws away the cigarette, he gives her the three grimaces to show that this is terrific and he's doing it just right, and he dies, he closes his own eyes.
I mean, that might be the last one.
I didn't mention that.
He closes his own eyes and he dies.
We couldn't have a more sort of joyous, positive, powerful, self-contained view of dying.
And then you could look back and say, if you're reading the film, I'm going to read it.
So, aha, he was really a free spirit all along.
We couldn't tell for sure.
But yet now we know.
That's at least that's one way to read it.
Anything else?
Yeah.
Aha.
Well, that's interesting.
I think you may have something there.
He does say he's tired of running from the police.
And he's very unhappy that she's not going to share his life his run to Italy.
It it looks like, I don't know where this is going to lead, it looks like he wouldn't have given up if she had said, I'll go to Italy with you.
He would have kept the car and done a great chase all over Paris and left all the police cars in the ditches and went off to Italy.
So it's partly he's ready to live dangerously up to the point of death.
But it does look like this phrase when he says he's tired, that does show that he's not absolutely invincible power man.
But I think we're supposed to think that that sort of with all those odds against him, the the police already are now his own girlfriend.
He's he was too much for him.
So he's certainly not the ultimate.
He's a you remember he's a kind of pop punk, a punk free spirit.
Anything else?
Yeah.
That's good.
That's what you were saying, I bet.
I felt I didn't understand you, and I was surprised you agreed so easily.
You wanted to answer, Ian?
Go ahead, you try.
Yes, that's right.
That's the I give a cockta Escalapius is what he says, which means pay off the doctor for curing me.
Right, which means dying.
So in his case, okay, but I don't think you sort of described the problem, not the answer.
What's wrong with the way Socrates relates to truth, in that it gives him a certain makes him, for instance, happy to make, and it makes him able to get everybody, get these his disciples to follow him.
And after all, Plato's the, if anybody wants a powerful follower, certainly Plato's terrific.
You want to get back into this discussion.
You started it.
Go ahead.
Let me try.
I think Nietzsche would say that it's the will to truth is fine as a means but not as an end.
And like convictions, you can use them.
Well, certainly criticism and mediation and truth are powerful things and you can use them.
But if you make, I think the story is supposed to go, but if you make truth the end and not the means, you don't have any outgrowing to do.
It's a static thing.
You achieve the truth.
It's the eternal truth.
It's the objective truth.
It's sort of independent of you.
You don't have to, you know, two things.
You don't have to put in any particular work to make it true.
So it's not like Kierkegaard's subjective truth, that the princess is adorable.
The princess is adorable only if you adore her.
There's a kind of truth that depends on your energy.
But Socrates' kind of objective truth is truth whether anybody knows it or not, like 2 plus 2 equals 4, or what justice is, or what courage is.
Since you haven't read much, Plato, Socrates, I don't want to go too much into examples.
But whatever it is, Socrates wants to find a truth that is fable and that doesn't require, doesn't depend in any way on him to preserve it.
And therefore, it isn't the kind of outgrowing, power, always inventing new world story that he wants.
But I think what you're adding, and I think it's important, and I wasn't stressing it enough, both of you are onto it, mediation is okay as a means.
It's a necessary means.
I mean, if you didn't go through criticism so that you got rid of all your all the untruths and lies, that is, and distortions and superstitions that you have, you wouldn't be able to go on and be free spirit.
So Socrates shouldn't have been given such a bad deal.
That's what's strange about it.
I mean, there should have been more about the positive side of Socrates.
Not my fault.
I don't think I missed it.
But he is, he just doesn't, in this, at that moment, want to give Socrates any credit at all.
And because he's so against the two things, that he doesn't have any heroic, noble instincts, and that he'd rather be dead than alive.
But there is, now I'll see if I can jump to it, place for criticism and mediation.
I think we'll have to wait till I get there.
It's someplace in the lecture, but if I go looking for it, I will just mess up things.
Okay.
Then we'll go on.
So now we're ready for a whole more, yeah.
Domino.
Yeah?
I don't think it's like a big answer.
He's not trying to advertise slave morality, but he's showing, but he certainly thinks that it doesn't matter whether you're a slave or not, every human being has innate ideas which are a vision of the truth that they had when their soul wasn't in their bodies, and the truth is there, eternal, independent of them, and anybody can be led to remember it.
And he's showing how the slave boy remembers it.
And it makes another reason, a point like I'm making.
No passion is needed on his part or the slave boy part to make the Pythagorean theorem true, which is what they're discussing.
Yeah, yeah, it's way back to the first lecture.
It's objective truth that doesn't depend on us, and the more disinterested we are, the more we are able to discover it.
Whereas Nietzsche has his own verse.
Kierkegaard thinks the more passionate you are, the more you discover the important kind of truth, namely the princess is adorable or the black people must be given justice.
And Nietzsche thinks that what?
Well, that you should be doing anything you can to be self-critical and discover the truth, but you should go, but you should use it as a means.
It's not a goal of the way of life going around objective, discovering objective truth.
Being a theoretical person is, for Nietzsche, not a living, outgrowing, powerful way to be.
So Nietzsche, even more than Kierkegaard, is against objective truth, I think, because Kierkegaard's against it only because he thinks there's a higher truth, namely subjective truth.
Nietzsche thinks that, well, they both have in common.
It's okay, it's a good thing, as long as you don't make an end of it.
It's a useful, power, even powerful means.
I think they both think that.
I don't think Dostoevsky thinks it.
He doesn't have much of a view of it.
But if he had a view of it, it would be Yvonne, remember, who's the scientist and the philosopher, who does natural philosophy, which is something between science and philosophy when he's in the university.
And that doesn't seem to do Yvonne any good at all.
Philosophy is a kind of too detached.
I mean, theory is too detached.
Nothing is worse than being detached.
It's a kind of curiosity, I think, of Dostoevsky.
He doesn't see the power of theory, as far as I can see, at all.
Okay, back to where I was.
We're in the ballpark of where I was, but there's an interesting abstract story going on between Nietzsche and Dostoevsky about something they have in common.
And you'll see, but they diverge before the end of my explaining what they have in common.
But they start out with what Nietzsche would call a critique of metaphysical explanations.
That is, they've got a wrong view about causality.
That means they think that there are these special powerful entities like the Supreme Being and eternity and the network of connectedness, which are real.
They're metaphysical.
They're ultimate reality.
They're the way the universe is.
And they think that on the basis of that, you can explain why people should love each other, get childhood memories, and so forth.
And according to Nietzsche and Dostoevsky, they really got things the wrong way.
That is, you don't explain the right way of the best way of living by bringing in metaphysical theological beings.
Rather, you explain the best way of living is self-evident.
And if anything is evidence of these other metaphysical things, it would be.
But really, you don't need them.
But this, I've jumped ahead.
I always shouldn't do that.
It's not clear what I just said.
I'll try to make it clear.
One way to see what's going on is that for Nietzsche and for Dostoevsky, religion really hasn't got to do with beliefs.
That is, it hasn't got to do with beliefs about these metaphysical entities that in some way or another seem to justify religion.
This is all on page 163.
Lots of important things are going on.
So let's look at it.
Starting about 15 lines down.
Genuine primitive Christianity will be possible at all times.
That's a nice line, because Dostoevsky thinks he's got genuine primitive Christianity.
And I think probably Nietzsche agrees with him.
And Markle and Alyasha show that genuine primitive Christianity is possible at all times.
And that it's a pretty good thing.
It has a lot of elements of free-spiritedness in it.
Although, finally, it's not.
But what they agree on now is that it's not a belief, but of doing.
See where I'm reading.
Above all, it's, well, that's fine.
Let's see what I want to say more about that.
Let me just go on reading.
States of consciousness, beliefs of any kind, holding something to be true, for example, every psychologist knows this, are a matter of complete indifference, of the fifth rank compared to the value of the instincts.
To speak more strictly, the whole concept of spiritual causality is false.
That's what I was trying to say.
When you bring in a supreme being, and that causes you to have belief in God, that's got it upside down.
Now, I haven't proved that yet.
So if you think that because you believe, and oh, now comes another truth, that if you think that your beliefs are caused by the Supreme Being and all that, that's wrong.
But if you also think that your beliefs are what save you, that's wrong.
That nothing, anything that you, your beliefs don't do any good at all, and they don't cause anything.
Let me read what I wrote.
If you think because you believe some truth about some ultimate reality, such as the Creator God, or that Christ died for our sins, or that God loves us, and therefore you'll be reborn, and so forth, you're mistaken.
Not that that's false, but that reverses the causality.
Whether that's true or false isn't the question.
The question isn't about what you believe.
And now you should see the existentialist refrain coming.
It's what kind of life you live and whether it works.
That's the final test.
And that's not about whether any particular entities exist, although maybe you can figure that out from whether your life works.
But it isn't your beliefs that make you do what you do, and it isn't your beliefs that make your life work or don't work.
It's how you act.
So now we have to look at that more.
So we should look at page 64 of something.
I wonder which.
There's too many things around here.
Yeah, the top of 64 in Twilight.
Morality and religion fall entirely under the psychology of error.
In every case, cause is mistaken for effect.
Or the effect of what is believed true is mistaken for the truth.
Or a state of consciousness is mistaken for the causation of the state.
That's all very obscure, I should think, to you yet, but he will explain it.
So, for instance, it turns out that it's the experience that matters.
It doesn't matter that there has to be any cause behind it.
Take baptism.
It isn't that baptism is sort of magical and works because there's some kind of causality that when you get prayed over the right way or water put on you the right way, it will do something about your spiritual state.
If baptism is true, it's because the experience you have, like Alyasha, of being held up to the icon, has an effect on how you act later in life.
That's the basic thing.
And then you can say if you want, baptism is powerful, baptism is true, and so forth.
But that's not the point.
The point is there are certain ways of acting that give you positive experiences.
You don't need to ask what causes them.
Beliefs don't explain a way of life, I agree with you.
Let's look on 157.
This is sort of hard, but if you go through it, you discover interesting similarities and differences.
I don't see anything.
No, 157.
What's on the bottom?
Oh, wait, which way?
Are you in gay science or?
Well, no, I'm looking there too.
I don't see it in the Antichrist.
The bottom of 157?
Ah, yeah.
Yes, that's right.
That's it.
That's what I was looking for.
That it's not a belief which distinguishes the Christian.
The Christian acts.
He is distinguished by a different mode of acting.
Neither by words nor heart.
Does he resist so forth?
That's it.
Then he doesn't resist the man who does him evil.
That's not the important thing.
We're doing the general thesis now.
Beliefs don't cause or explain any way of life.
I want to look just to see by coincidence if there's something about it here also.
That would be peculiar.
No, you're on the right track.
So I noticed when I was thinking about this today that I don't think Alyosha has any beliefs about anything.
He's the test case.
He doesn't believe that there is a supreme being.
He doesn't believe that baptism is necessary.
He doesn't even believe in prayer, though he prays sometimes.
It's a funny kind of prayer, you remember.
He does it at night, and he sort of helps him collect his wits, and it helps him understand what's happening.
But he doesn't pray to God, the Supreme Being, because there isn't any in Brothers Karamatsa, there's the connectedness, and we can't pray to the connectedness.
So whenever he does all sorts of things, but they don't follow from his belief about anything.
And you keep your eyes open if you're looking at it again.
And if anybody finds any evidence that Alyasha believes anything about religion and how to act in Christianity and sin and redemption and incarnation and resurrection, confession, and all the things that Dostoevsky writes about, if you think Alyasha has any beliefs about any of them, let me know.
I hope he doesn't.
I think he doesn't.
For Dostoevsky, it's not a belief in connectedness that produces the experience of connectedness, just the reverse.
When we experience ourselves as part of the whole of connectedness and see we're accountable for everything, then we do believe it, but that's not important.
It changes our way of acting.
Act like Alyasha or Zosima.
It's the experience that causes us to act that way.
And now comes the really interesting, complicated one.
If you experience eternity in time, then what about that?
Have you shown just by virtue of having the experience that there is eternity in time as possible?
What do you think?
I think it's kind of tricky what I think you have to think.
I don't think Dostoevsky actually says it.
Well, so dust is, so here's what's going to happen in this argument now for a minute.
So Nietzsche says, I don't care whether you believe in eternity in time or not.
It's an experience, if there is one.
And then Dostoevsky says, okay, good, I'll take that because I win.
I've described experiences in which there is eternity in time.
We get it when Alyasha gives the boys the childhood memories at the end of the book, which are going to keep them from becoming cynical and so forth later.
Well, what I think Nietzsche has to say first, anyway, is: well, we don't know yet.
We won't know until they die whether those memories have lasted forever.
Maybe there isn't any.
Maybe he hasn't given them any memories.
And maybe you never can.
You outgrow them.
Or the other thing Nietzsche will say is, okay, so he gives you, you get these memories, and you hold on to them for the rest of your life.
Does that show that there's eternity in time?
No, that just shows you're sick and weak.
If you were strong enough, you wouldn't need to keep those memories.
And they might not be the thing that makes you powerful.
Maybe the boys at some point in life will come, some boy will come into a situation in which being cynical and laughing at the authorities, or laughing at the authorities, or whatever, is the right thing to do.
And maybe it will contradict what looks like the right way to live at the moment around the tombstone, around the church, the rock of Alicia.
And the highest thing is to be adaptable, Nietzsche will say, not to have these experiences, even if you had an experience that lasted all your life.
It would, at most, it would show there is something like forever and eternity in time, but it wouldn't show that forever and eternity in time is a good thing.
Nietzsche's never going to admit that.
But they agree at least that if there is eternity in time, if there is a forever, it depends.
The only evidence could be that there are people whose lives get that, whether through romantic love or any kind of unconditional commitment or a moment in which they're all together like the boys and having a special kind of revelation that you can have and it could control your life for the rest of your life.
And but so you don't know who wins.
I mean all I can say is they agree that it's not a question of causality.
It's not a question of objective belief.
Is there eternity?
Can anything be forever?
That's a question of how people act.
Then there's a further question of the sort of value of having in your life something.
That's a different view, again, about how people act, how people should act.
But I'm not ready for that yet.
I really got ahead of the story.
Let's look at this.
I'll give you another illustration.
What about if God is dead, all things are possible?
Is that a causal claim?
Well, sort of.
That is, but it should be based on experience.
All this is sort of weird and tricky.
And if you don't understand it, it's partly my fault, I suppose, but try.
So it looks like you ought to ask yourself the question: well, is the statement, if God is dead, all things are possible, true or not?
And the answer ought to be, it's not a question of objective fact, it's a question of how particular people are.
And does anybody anywhere in Dostoevsky ever act as if all things are possible?
We've gone through this.
And the answer is no.
In Crime and Punishment, in the Brothers Karamatsov, in all of Dostoevsky, it looks like the experience is that if you do something immoral, you will feel guilt.
You won't get away with it, and that's the important.
It sort of follows from that, that God isn't dead, but that's not the importance.
You've got to reverse the causality.
The question, the causal question to ask is: can you get away with murder, in effect?
And the answer is going to be found out by what people could do, get away with.
Okay, in the meantime, I have to put in a parenthesis here.
I've had time to see Match Point because you all told me to see Match Point.
He says, How many of you have seen Match Point?
Almost everybody.
Okay, well, there's a sentence in it that you're going to help me remember who said it.
But obviously, Match Point is on the side of Nietzsche against Dostoevsky, it taking back the claim that you can't just go around murdering people for your own convenience and feel okay about it and get away with it.
Now, let's go through it because it's not as conclusive as Crimes and Misdemeanors, which you haven't seen, which it's a rerun.
In Crimes and Misdemeanors, it's clear, one, that the guy who murders his mistress, but she's getting in the way, is first overcome by guilt, and then finally and tortured by the idea that he should go and confess, like in Crime and Punishment.
But he doesn't go and confess.
Finally, he feels better.
And we know that later in his life we see him back being a pillar of the community, respected by everybody, giving charities to everything.
And he doesn't seem to be tortured like the mysterious visitor.
He seems to just be okay.
Well, it's a rerun of that, except that we don't see what happens to, what's his name, Chris, what's the guy's name?
Wil Chris Wilson?
Wilton.
I mean, we don't see what happened to Chris Wilton much later, but we do see him reading Crime and Punishment, and he does kill his girlfriend and an old lady, just like Risvelnikov kills the porn broker and an old lady.
And it looks like, and now you have to help me, he feels terrible about it at first.
Don't we see him looking really sort of sickened by what he's done, or am I imagining?
After shooting the lady.
Ah, okay.
So he feels guilty, but he did it.
And now when does he say?
My wife says he doesn't say it, but I swear he says, if I'm not caught and imprisoned, it shows that there's no meaning in the universe.
Did I make that up?
Did I hallucinate that?
Oh, that's when he says it.
I mean, the challenge was, but who would he say it to?
You can't say it to anybody, because they turn to you, and that's right, the ghosts come.
And he says to the ghosts that if I get caught, then you'll turn out to be right.
But if I don't get caught, it shows there's no meaning in the universe.
And that's the crucial line.
You're all supposed to know that.
And that's because, and that's why we're showing him reading crime and punishment, because that's the line that takes back crime and punishment.
Because it looks like, in this case, he's not going to confess, and he's not going to get, well, and we've discovered that he doesn't get caught.
And that means that the universe is not a moral order, and psychology, too, is not such that you can, and human psychology is not such that you can't just murder people and get away with it and feel okay about it.
He already feels okay about it, as far as I can tell, by the end of the movie.
Now, it's inconclusive, but it's not meant to be.
I mean, it could, like the case of Dan White, remember I said who killed Merrill Moscone, it took him two years before he killed himself.
But we don't get the impression at all, as far as I can see, that Chris Wilson is going to have a relapse and kill himself later once he's happily settled in his new family with his kids and his job and all of that.
He's just going to forget Nora, is that her name?
Noah.
Something like that.
Anyway, does anybody want to say any more about it?
Because you sort of put a new movie in the course, which is nice.
And Woody Allen is certainly out to get Dostoevsky.
I mean, it's funny to do it twice.
He really cares a lot about this, that people can forget awful crimes and just feel okay about it.
He's thinking of himself.
But in any case, anything?
Okay, well, I'm going back to this then.
So where are we?
So it seems, just to sum up, that it was random chance.
It was sheer luck.
That's how it's set up.
Just as Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky feared, Kierkegaard says: if the world is just a kind of chaos, in which, remember, people don't get, those who work don't get the bread, and it turns out just random, who that would be terrible.
But luckily in the world of the spirit, it's okay.
And Dostoevsky, through Yvonne, considers the possibility that it's just random chaos.
And he has his own arguments, that you can't get away with it.
Yvonne is his argument.
It's not okay to just decide to kill your father.
But it looks like for Woody Allen, Nietzsche's right.
The world is just chaos.
It's sheer random whether you get away with murder or not, or and whether you feel bad about it or not.
And that's got to do with this causality issue.
So now the question is: the question whether God is dead is not a metaphysical question about some entity and whether that entity is still around or not, this supreme being.
It turns into an existentialized question: can you live as if there were no God and all things were possible?
Or can't you?
And Dusty S says you can't.
And Nietzsche says, yes, you can.
Woody Allen agrees with Nietzsche.
But the causality is reversed.
Once you say that you discover you can't live without feeling guilt, finally sort of falling apart after you killed your girlfriend, then you can use that as an argument for the existence of God.
But that's the other way around.
See, you don't feel bad because you believe in the existence of God, and therefore you feel guilty.
If you feel guilty for these people who have reversed the causality, that will be an argument for the existence of God.
But that's not important, the argument for the existence of God, whether you believe in God.
The question is whether you feel guilty or not.
You understand?
You're looking all baffled.
Okay, I'm going to go on.
Maybe it'll unbaffle you.
Unless somebody wants to ask a question, explain to me why you're all looking so bad.
Yeah.
Wow, that's great.
Wouldn't that be a neat exam call?
We don't have that kind of exam question, unfortunately.
But maybe we will someday have to think about that.
I mean, let's just spell out what they mean.
Remember, for Kierkegaard, God is that all things are possible means that, not that you can just do any old thing in ethics, because he believes that ethics is based in, well, he has two views about ethics.
Either it's based in what counts as good in the community and is intelligible to the people in the community, that would be Hegel's view, or that there is, it looks like sometimes, an absolute ethics, there is a right and wrong, which would be Kant's view.
So, and yet he believes that, as you say, and I keep saying, God is that all things are possible.
Well, he doesn't mean all actions.
There are just some moral actions that you can do and you should do and other moral actions you shouldn't do.
So, what does he mean, all things are possible?
Well, he means, remember, that Abraham could somehow kill Isaac and still have Isaac.
Or that you can teleologically suspend the ethical and yet you can be doing your ethical duty, even though you can't explain to yourself or anybody else how you could be doing your ethical duty by doing this awful thing.
So, it's specific impossibilities that if you're a moral person and a sensible person, certain things will be impossible for you.
Like, let's take the two extreme cases, like living, like getting more and more involved with somebody or some cause and taking this incredible risk that it can throw you into grief.
It looks impossible to see the sword hanging over the head of the beloved and live as if it's the surest thing of all.
That's the sense that if you believe, but if you believe that God, for God, all things are possible, you can get more and more involved with the beloved, see the sword hanging over the head, and go on getting involved.
That's what, because for God, that crazy way of acting is okay.
And of course, it turns out to be okay because in grief you can interiorize and so forth, but that's not important.
You can't say that to yourself.
You can't say, oh, I'll get more and more involved with Mary after all.
If she dies and I go through grief, I'll marry somebody else.
It doesn't look that way.
From inside, it looks very risky and terribly threatening.
And yet, now we're back, because God is all things are possible, a knight of faith can do it.
And the endesteriological suspension example to keep in mind, remember, is if you're a homosexual in 1850 Copenhagen and it looks like anything you have a lover of the same sex, and this is absolutely disgusting and awful and depraved and sick and all that, it still can look to you as if it's the best thing you ever did.
But that makes no sense.
That's absurd.
That's paradoxical.
But you can do it because for God, all things are possible.
Maybe the crucial, I'm trying to figure out how to sum this up.
For God, even the impossible is possible.
That's the way to put it.
That's the paradoxical occurrence.
It isn't that all actions are equally okay.
That gets us to Dostoevsky and Yvonne and so forth.
If God is dead, all things are possible means that if there's no basis for the moral order in the universe, all actions are equally okay.
Those are just two completely different stories.
Have I finally nailed it down?
I think so.
So in one case, the impossible is the unthinkable, in the sense of paradoxical, incomprehensible.
I'm going to kill my son, and yet he's not going to be dead.
And that's Kierkegaard.
On the other hand, if God is dead, all things are possible.
That means if God is dead, you can do all anything you please.
You just know there's no punishment.
There's no moral law.
There's no moral order.
That's just a totally different story.
And all you can say is they sound the same, but if you put them in the context they are saying, they're not even saying opposed things.
They're just saying totally different things.
I hope that helped.
I don't know.
Did it help?
Thinkable.
Yeah, Osaba, ethical permissibility versus thinkability, that is conceivability.
Yeah, when Kierkegaard says all things are possible, he means even the inconceivable can happen.
That's the absurd.
When Nietzsche and Dostoevsky argue about whether when God is dead, all things are possible, they are talking about whether all actions are morally permissible.
And that's just another issue.
Okay, I saw another hand.
Didn't know.
Yes.
Ah, interesting.
Uh-huh.
It is in a way.
Yeah?
These are good questions.
Dostoevsky would have liked a lot of things about careful government.
Remember, subjective truth, he would have liked, that is, that something is true for you insofar as you're absolutely committed to it, and as long as you're committed to it, he just would have said it was, you shouldn't get stuck in it.
We'll get to that.
But let's stick to what you said.
So, live dangerous.
You want to say something about that?
Good.
No, I mean, not the way.
Although, if you hear it a certain way, because Nietzsche says you should use commitments, but you shouldn't get stuck in them.
Well, okay, but that's a different issue.
But I put nothing wrong with what you said, but it isn't going to help him, me answer him.
There are two different ways of living dangerously.
That's the issue.
Just as there were two different meanings of all things that are possible.
Now, when you live dangerously in Kierkegaard, you certainly do see the sword hanging over the head of the beloved.
But if you're a knight of faith, you find you do it as if it's the surest thing of all.
So it's a funny kind of dangerous.
It does have a certain kind of dangerous.
He says it's like swimming over 50,000 fathoms.
I mean, there's nothing to support it, and it could fall, you know, it's vulnerable, this relationship or whatever.
It could disappear at any minute.
But if you're a knight of faith, you know that to talk now like Dostoevsky talking about Alyasha, you act as if in everything you do that nothing could hurt you.
Because Aliyasha has that kind of faith, and so does the Knight of Faith have that kind of faith.
Yeah, well, no, no, I think it really is risky and dangerous, even to you, that you will lose this loved person.
But you have this paradoxical, remember, not rational belief, and it doesn't matter whether it's a belief, because you can't really believe a paradox.
You have this completely absurd, unthinkable way of acting in which you are both taking this complete risk and living dangerously, and living as if it's the surest thing of all, not dangerously.
The free spirit isn't, I mean, the light of faith is not really risking anything.
But the knight of faith can only do that because they live in this field of faith that all things are possible.
Otherwise, it would be dangerous.
And then you get the knight of resignation, who doesn't want to live dangerously.
Trying to put into an eternal, secure relationship to an idea that you can't die or go away.
The knight of resignation doesn't live dangerously at all.
They want to be peaceful and secure.
The knight of faith isn't peaceful and secure.
They have to constantly live in an absurdity they can't understand.
But it's not the same kind of living dangerously as building your house on the slopes of Vesuvius, where you know that you are living in Berkeley, where you know that an earthquake of nine is supposed to happen somewhere in the next 30 years.
I mean, that's a different way of living dangerously.
That's something bad that can actually happen to you and be devastating.
And you've got no backup that you, that, that no matter what happens, it'll be okay.
Nietzsche thinks you have to really take the risk, but there are bad things that can happen to you and it won't be okay.
Your loved one won't be returned to you even though they died or you failed them.
And if you Vesuvius erupt, you had it.
So I think that's the point.
I mean, there's a kind of peculiar, absurd protection in Kierkegaard's Christianity.
But he's as close as you can get, because he, let's faith something like live strenuously.
They both have.
That is, that's this swimming over 40,000 fathoms.
And that goes back to Pascal, who thinks that you have to live constantly anxiously to get Christian.
Remember, anxiety is the ultimate test of whether you're not.
But anxiety isn't the same courage to go on doing all kinds of dangerous things, knowing full well that something very bad might happen, period.
Okay, that's the best I can do with that.
They're good questions.
I think the questions are better than the answers.
I have a feeling there ought to be a decayer thing to take.
But they don't confront each other, these funny questions.
They come at each other from different angles so that they don't really meet head on.
Each in a context has its own sense.
Okay, let me see where we are so I can find out where we should stop.
I'm going to just summarize maybe.
Dostoevsky and Nietzsche agree that religion is not a matter of belief and not based on belief in metaphysical and theological realities.
That gets the causality reversed.
What matters is religious experience.
But now comes the big thing we've been saying, but let's just sum it up.
But they have a totally different view of the religious experience that is the crucial question.
Nietzsche's against all versions of the Christian religious, except Jesus, which is only lasts until he's taken down from the cross.
So Nietzsche's against all versions of Christian experience, even if it's based on revelations, as it is in Dostoevsky, like Alyasha's experience of the connectedness of everything.
And how does he criticize Dostoevsky?
I'll just stop with that.
There's this funny critique, again, as if maybe he's been reading the brothers.
Dostoevsky says, look, there's a connectedness of everything.
How do we know?
Well, Alyasha has an experience of it when he goes and throws himself on the ground and feels connected to all the worlds.
And Nietzsche answers at the top of 178.
Christianity has made a great contribution and taught moral skepticism trenchantly and effectively.
Now, the skepticism issue is what I want to talk about.
On page 185 now of Twilight, he seems to be, I think, let's hope that that's it.
No, not what I want.
Let's see if I can find it.
Ah, 253 of the gay science.
That's it.
He says, you can have what look like religious experiences, but they really grow out of your needs.
You fool yourself.
And that Christianity has taught us not to fool.
At first, it taught people how to fool themselves.
That's sort of what the Grand Inquisitor did.
But then Christianity, being so critical and skeptical, taught people out of it.
So I'm just going to read this, stop by reading on 253, number 319.
One sort of honesty has been alien to all founders of religion and their kind.
Christianity finally gets it, but not the founders.
They have never made their experience a matter of conscience for knowledge.
What did I experience?
What happened in me and around me at the time?
Was my reason brightened up?
Was my will opposed to all deceptions of the senses and bold in resisting the fantastic?
None of them have asked such questions.
Now look at this.
On the contrary, they thirst after things that go against reason.
They don't want to be too hard on themselves.
So they experience miracles, rebirths, and hear the voices of the little angels.
Well, I mean, probably he hasn't read Alyasha's experience, but what he would say is: well, Alyasha was frantic to have a miracle.
He was just, he hadn't eaten and he hadn't slept for days.
He's sort of just wishing with all his might that there would be some sign that there would be a miracle.
And then he goes to Zosima, sorry, to Gushenka, and he experiences this miracle, and he views it as a miracle and as a rebirth.
And then he falls on the ground and he has this experience of everything being connected to everything.
But he doesn't ask himself, gee, isn't it funny that it happened after two nights, let's say, of no sleep, and that I was very hungry and that I was absolutely desperate to get in touch with some religious something or other.
He's just happy to have it.
Well, Dostoevsky would say, well, I told you sort of all there is to tell about it.
He really had it, and it really gave him a connection to this ultimate order.
But Nietzsche would just say, well, you certainly didn't tell us how that he had it when a lucid day after a good night's sleep at noon in broad daylight, after several cups of coffee, he felt connected to everything.
I mean, that would really convince Nietzsche.
But not falling on, not on a warm autumn night when he was desperate.
Okay, so let me see now.
So, finally, then, on, I'm just going to, this just finishes it.
So, a weak person can't be honest, he says on 185.
I'll stop with that.
About 15 lines down.
Not to see many things, not to be impartial in things, to be party through and through, to view all values from a necessary perspective.
This alone is the condition under which such a man exists.
That is, a weak person.
That he is thereby the antithesis, the antagonist of the truthful man, of truth.
The believer is not free to have a conscience at all over the question of true and false.
To be honest on this point could mean his immediate destruction.
The pathological conditionality of his perspective makes the convinced man a fanatic.
Okay, so he's going to say that the trouble is that people get the, it's out of their needs that they get their experiences, therefore I don't believe them.
One last comment.
What page was I just reading?
I was reading 185 of the Antichrist.
And I'll start with that issue again next time.
Bring the Antichrist as well as the gay science.
Sure.
Next time.
Okay.