So we've talked about the fact that what Kierkegaard is interested in is something very special in our Western culture: unconditional commitment to something finite which gives you your identity, which gives you a world in which what's important and not important is sorted out, and which is irreversible and vulnerable.
And that's very strange.
That raises the question: why should you ever get into such a kind of relation if its ending is going to destroy you and your world, and it's very likely to end sooner or later, but maybe sooner than you end, and then you'll be in trouble.
In that sense, this kind of relation is always impossible.
It's not just like the prince, the lab can't marry the princess because they're of a different class.
It's impossible in some, it's the wrong kind of relation for anybody to think makes sense to do.
And in that sense, it's impossible.
It can't do the job that it ought to do, namely, be a solid foundation for your identity and your world.
It should be somehow guaranteed, and it's not.
But Kierkegaard thinks that only through this kind of defining commitment to something finite and vulnerable, and a kind of eternal commitment to something temporal, can you have a meaningful life?
So, and moreover, this can't be a commitment to some kind of idea, some future utopia, because that's not finite and temporal enough.
It has to be something that tells you from moment to moment what you have to do next and what you can ignore as irrelevant.
And if it's going to be a fully meaningful life, if it's going to be the most meaningful life you could possibly get, it's going to have to be something that you'd be willing to die for.
It's not enough that you have a job that will tell you from day to day.
This came out in office hours yesterday.
Always learn new things.
A student came in with a good counterexample to why do you need to have an unconditional commitment just to know from day to day what's important to do and what's not.
If you have a job and like it, you'll know that.
Or if you're devoted, as this person said, to some kind of science, which most a lot of people in the university are, doesn't that tell you what's important and not important?
And I was puzzled by that, but I think the answer is yes, it does, in a mild way, tell you that.
Just like playing having a role of husband and wife tell you what your jobs are, so to speak.
And Kierkegaard talks about marriage and how it's a good thing, but there's a kind of marriage which is just, which is not the highest kind of commitment.
Not that this highest kind of commitment couldn't show up in marriage, in the picture of romantic love.
It's supposed to go together, love and marriage.
But it's there, and then there would be, there could be, both in your job and in your marriage, an unconditional commitment.
I mean, it's not excluded that you're unconditionally committed to doing science in such a way that it tells you what to do day by day.
And if it turns out your whole life you've been working on a hypothesis which finally turns out to be wrong, you'd be in the kind of lostness and grief from that.
But it requires that you are devoted to something finite and temporal so totally that if it failed, you'd be lost.
And that means you can't just be devoted to your job as a job or to your wife or husband as a role that you socially play.
It's got to be something you're willing to die for, to be a martyr for.
That is, if it's going to have the kind of super meaningfulness that it's got to have, if you're going to have a life that's as joyful and blissful and meaningful as a human life can be, then it has to be a commitment to something finite and temporal, and in a way that you're willing to make sacrifices for it, and finally ultimate sacrifices.
A French writer named Malreaux said that nothing is worth living for that isn't worth dying for.
It's that kind of experience or feeling or understanding that Kierkegaard has in mind.
So it has to be, your unconditional commitment has to be to something finite, temporal.
Those go together always.
That just means another person right here now.
And to something which is crucially important to you.
And you can see it has to be if it's defined you.
Because if it's defined you, then you can't just stand back and say, well, I'm not going to sacrifice for it.
That's too much.
I mean, you have to sacrifice for it because you wouldn't be you and you wouldn't have the world you have if it wasn't there.
And you have to, so that you can't just wash your hands of it.
We'll come back to that in a minute.
I didn't say that very clearly yet.
And the question is: is there any way to keep this meaning and commitment in your life and avoid the vulnerability?
That looks like what you'd want to do.
And all the story about resignation is about that.
The Knight of Resignation is able to perform an amazing sort of movement that any person who has the strength of will to do it can do it, which preserves the unconditional commitment and its meaning.
and your identity and does it in a way that's not vulnerable.
How that happens is going to become something much later.
We have to go through all the wrong ways first, the wrong ways of trying to make your commitment safe.
And so the first one is a little before your reading, but it's so important and has a kind of moral I want to give you.
I want to go back and read it.
And that's, no, it's, why do I say it's before?
No, it's not.
It's on the first page, on page 57.
And 57 doesn't have a number on it, but he comes between 56 and 58, as you will rightly guess.
So here we are.
So I'm going to read a chunk of it because it's going to be both a statement.
I'll tell you first what I think it's why I'm reading a lot of it.
One, it's a clear statement of you can't have the bliss without the vulnerability, which is what the Knight of Resignation is trying to do.
And we're going to see that all versions of Knights of Resignation fail to do it.
And it's going to tell you that it's going to show you that Kierkegaard's kind of Christianity doesn't give the usual meanings to the terms.
I wanted at some point to warn you against what, when I was an undergraduate anyway, people were warning us about stock responses.
I don't know if that slogan is around.
That means don't, when you hear something about the afterlife or about faith or about God in this book and in Dostoevsky and in Nicholas, particularly in this book, don't just think that you know what that means because you've heard what you what you heard from whatever in Sunday school or in reading or something.
You'll see what he does with the afterlife here.
Okay, so here we go.
An old proverb I'm getting right at the beginning, pertaining to the outward and visible world says, only one who works gets bread.
Oddly enough, the saying doesn't apply.
By the way, every once in a while, what I'm reading is going to differ by a word or so from what you've got.
Sometimes that's me being dyslexic, but I think I am usually I can read, sort of.
But the trouble is that this translation that I'm reading from is just an earlier printing of the one you've got.
But every once in a while I notice that something's happened, like the word rest in another quote has turned to repose.
So if I'm reading along and it doesn't say what I read, somebody yell and stop me.
And one, I may be just not seeing what's on the page, or else I should correct this version.
So does it say that?
Only one who works gets bread?
Or is that what it says?
Okay, I'm going on.
Oddly enough, the saying doesn't apply in the world to which it most properly belongs.
For the outward world is subject to the law of imperfection.
There it happens time and again the one who gets bread is the one who does not, who gets bread is the one who does not work.
The one who sleeps gets it in greater abundance than the one who labors.
That's just a fancy way of saying that, as you all know, it isn't the way, it doesn't work out that you get what you deserve.
The one who works very, very hard finally and puts a lot of money in Enron's stock ends up broke.
And the people who are running Enron and taking it easy and sleeping late make millions of dollars.
In this case, maybe they're going to be punished, but you can't count on it in the everyday world.
But now, later, he says, skipping down to the middle of the page, it's otherwise in the world of the spirit.
Here there prevails an eternal divine order.
Here it does not rain on the just and unjust alike.
Here the sun does not shine on both good and evil, on both good and evil.
Here only one who works gets bread, and only one who knows anguish finds rest.
Only one who descends to the underworld saves the loved one.
Only one who draws the knife gets Isaac.
Okay, well that's to say that in the world of the spirit, whatever that is, and I'm going to talk about that in a minute, the people who take the risk get the rewards.
And always, and if you want to be safe, you can't get the bread.
And if you're willing to take the risk of the defining commitment, you will.
Now, how that's going to happen, we don't know yet.
But in the world of the spirit, I want to talk about.
That you might think that means in the afterlife.
That even if something bad happens here, this is the way sort of orthodox Christians and Orthodox Buddhists too think about it.
I mean, what happens here gets compensated for by whether you go to heaven or hell in the afterlife.
And you'd think Hierkegaard's a Christian, but he he must be saying something like that.
Don't worry, in this life if bad things can happen to good people and good things happen to bad people, but in the world of the spirit, in the afterlife, everything gets fixed.
Well, that's not what he means.
He says, let me just go on now to, where is it?
Well, I better stick to my notes, then we'll find it.
Oh, that's what's earlier there.
I knew.
Something's earlier.
Okay, he says right off that if you believe that it'll be settled in a future life, then you haven't understood what he's talking about.
When he says that only ones who live in risk will get bliss and eternal life, he means right here and now.
And he talks about that on page 53.
That's for this little important bit that's before your reading.
The bottom of the page.
But Abraham had faith and faith for this life.
He's going to give you a weird definition of faith, which I won't even be able to finish till time after next, because next time it's the movie and the time after we're going to talk about Hiroshima.
But so what he means by faith is very complicated.
But whatever it is, it's faith for this life, not in the afterlife.
And then how he explains that.
Yes, had his faith only been for a future life, it would have been easier to cast everything aside in order to hasten out of this world in which he did not belong.
But Abraham's faith was not of that kind, if there is such.
He doubts whether that even counts as faith to believe in the future other world.
For a faith like that is not really faith, but only its remotest possibility.
This faith that has some inkling of its object at the very edge of the field of vision, but remains separated from it by a yawning abyss in which despair plays its pranks.
Now, Kierkegaard's hard reading.
It's hard to know.
I know what that means, but I could see the first number ten times.
I read it, I didn't.
What he's saying is: faith in the future world where everything comes out all right is, on the one hand, a kind of glimmer that if you've got faith, everything is going to turn out all right.
That the amount of risk you take and the amount of bliss you've got and the amount of meaning you've got are all going to equal out.
But if you think that that's going to happen in some other world, then you're in a kind of despair because that's this yawning abyss in which despair plays its pranks.
The abyss is, sort of, what's going to happen to you between now and when you die?
Well, you're sort of in despair for that part because it looks like that's up for grabs.
And the point is, somehow this rule that the more risk, the more bliss ought to apply right now, not only after you die.
And that's, and he says that, going on.
But it was for this life that Abraham believed.
He believed he would become old in his land, honored among his people, blessed in his kin, eternally remembered in Isaac, the dearest of his life.
That is, he somehow believed, and this is the puzzling thing that we're not going to get to yet, that even though he was going to do God's will and kill Isaac, he was going to keep his identity as the father of the faith, and somehow that required Isaac.
But don't worry about that instance of it.
Just realize that Kierkegaard thinks that faith of the sort he's talking about, which is very strange and hard and paradoxical, promises you in this life all that you could ever have.
And whether there's another life afterward or not, he says in other places he's neutral about that.
He doesn't know.
Nobody knows what happens after you die.
But it doesn't, but it's not important for this because it better work out right.
You better have the right attitude.
And somehow in the world, in this very world, if you've got the right kind of faith and the right kind of attitude, it's got to work out in the right kind of way.
Or you should be in this faith.
That's the first thing to get out of the way.
So now back to Kierkegaard's view that there's a necessary connection between the way an unconditional commitment gives you an identity and meaning and its being risky and making you vulnerable to grief, total breakdown.
And that's because if it's concrete enough to give you day-by-day meaning, it's concrete enough to be lost.
The slogan is, no risk, no bliss.
And all religions, I said at the end last time, try to get around this painful situation.
And now we're going to start a sort of survey of the way people have tried to get around it and make it safe in this world, but make it safe in this world in a way that, in the end, doesn't work because they make it safe in this world by somehow giving up the finite and the temporal to make it safe.
Because we have to look at how that happens.
So, first you get nights that you get people who aren't really knights.
That is, ways of not being a knight, of avoiding, of having defenses against unconditional commitment.
And that's something I want to cross out.
I just read something in my notes that I don't believe anymore.
I believed it this afternoon while I was writing this, but I now think that's not right.
Okay.
So, so the but I do stick to this.
We're going to talk about first ways of avoiding the risk, modes of defending yourself, having defenses.
And the first one is that he talks about.
I sort of gather them from all over the preliminary, the preamble from the heart.
The first way of not being a knight is simply just not to let yourself get committed.
By getting, by the, not letting anything be the whole content of your life.
That is, have lots of affairs.
There's a movie that's, you won't remember, it's a little too before your time, Shampoo.
Has anybody seen shampoo?
What's interesting about shampoo is everybody has other possible girlfriends, boyfriends, jobs always sort of on the horizon just in case something goes wrong with this one.
Right?
And that's the first way of avoiding the risk.
On 72, Kierkegaard's talking about that.
So the knight would have, this is how he differs from this person who's not doing it right, will then, in the first place, the very top of 72, will then, in the first place, have the strength to concentrate the whole of his life's content and the meaning of reality into a single wish.
That is, you don't spread it around.
If a person lacks this concentration, his soul is concentration, this focus, his soul is disintegrated, and so forth and so forth.
And he's like a capitalist.
This is the shampoo part.
He will act prudently in life like those capitalists who invest their capital in every kind of security.
So they gain on the one where they lose on the other.
In short, he's not a knight.
Okay?
But I want to fix the translation here.
You've got to have enough.
I'll remind you where we are.
I know it's sort of confusing, but it's bad to say concentrates the whole meaning of his life into a single wish.
Wish is the wrong word.
Do you get the feel for that?
Did Martin Luther King sit around wishing that things would go well for the black people?
If somebody's committed to somebody, do they wish that the other person doesn't leave them?
And no, that's wrong.
It's too wishy-washy, if you would.
It means they concentrate the whole of their life and meaning of reality into a single commitment.
That's what we've been calling it.
But that's not, of course, that's me.
But what does the Norwegian say?
Well, another translation, Danish say, another translation says, heart's desire.
Now that's fine.
That's a kind of romantic way of talking about this unconditional commitment that fits in with the kind of vocabulary he's using.
It doesn't sound like just sitting around doing nothing.
Martin Luther King had it certainly his heart's desire that there would be equality for the black.
So that's a lot stronger, I hear it, than a witch.
Okay, having fixed that, let's go on.
So if they lack this, then they are just dispersed, and that's and they are a lower nature.
Let's just put that in, because lower nature is the same as lower immediacy.
He uses them interchangeably.
Where is it?
Ah, here we are.
About in the next, in the first full paragraph, that is way below the middle, about six lines in that paragraph.
Only lower natures forget themselves and become something new.
Thus, the butterfly has altogether forgotten it was a caterpillar.
Perhaps it can so completely forget and turn that it was a butterfly that it becomes a fish.
Deeper natures never forget themselves and become something else, of course, because they get an identity.
But these people will be like lower organisms as far as the way they live their lives, from going from this job to that, and this person to that, and so forth.
And they aren't knights at all.
Knights, all the kinds of knights that we're going to talk about, have to have an unconditional commitment, and they're different kinds of knights because they deal with their unconditional commitment in different ways.
So, but even if you're not a lower nature, you can deal with your unconditional commitment now, it turns out, in ways that make it safe, but undermine its finite temporal meaning.
Those are interesting ways.
These are defenses, but not just your defense or mine, but the whole history of the West not only invented unconditional commitment, but it invented interesting ways of life to avoid the consequences of unconditional commitment.
And the first kind I want to talk about is the Greek philosopher.
The Greek, I think, he doesn't say much about that.
He doesn't care much about that.
But I think the philosopher has, I'm going to read this, and so it's about a knight, but it's about a knight that doesn't stay a night, I think, because now let's read it.
So the knight makes the movement, but what movement?
Does he want to forget the whole thing?
Because in that, too, there's a kind of concentration.
No, the knight does not contradict himself.
Oh, I misspoke.
Kierkegaard's right.
I was just innovating an explanation.
The point is, this paragraph is not about the knight.
The knight really does do the right thing, but it's a second sentence now.
This is what philosophers do: they forget the whole thing.
And what it means to forget the whole thing, I want to tell you now.
I doubt very many of you read Plato's Symposium.
Oh, more than I realized.
Okay, Plato wrote a dialogue called the Symposium.
Try to write that.
And in the Symposium, he talks about, I've mentioned it before, I realize now, but I never wrote it on the board, I don't think, did I?
Thanks.
It's a dialogue about love.
And it's a dialogue that, I did mention it in connection with the joke in it from Aristophanes: that people were around once, and they're now chopped in two, and the two halves are going around looking for each other, and they've only got one other half.
When they find it, they hold on to each other and feel happiest they could ever feel.
And when they haven't found it, they're feeling very unhappy and lonely.
And Aristophanes thinks that's a joke.
But that's just a description of romantic love.
That just shows the big difference between the world of Plato and Aristophanes and Kierkegaard.
But what happens instead of the joke when Socrates tells Plato's, or Plato through Socrates, tells his story.
It's the story I mentioned that you love one beautiful body, then you go on and love many, and then you love one beautiful soul, and then you love many, and then you love the beautiful.
What I want to say about it this time is slightly different than what I said last time, though, not contradicting it.
What's interesting is, how do you feel about the one beautiful body and the one beautiful soul you love once?
And so let's go just for fun put them together in this nice super person who's got a beautiful body and a beautiful soul.
Well, you forget them.
They are petty things.
What the translation I was reading says.
Or I forget, there's another translation I wrote down here.
What did I say?
Of no account.
There's another translation.
That is, it turns out that there was never anything significant about their relationship to the beautiful, whatever.
You just realize that the beautiful, whatever, was not what you really were looking for.
You were looking for the beautiful.
And so you forget the whole thing.
And but what's interesting is it requires a kind of concentration.
I mean, he thinks that that's a kind of mediation, and mediation is already a kind of achievement over just lower immediacy where you go after some particular body or soul and just get fixated on it and stop there.
But the achievement, the concentration, consists in, so to speak, dumping the individual altogether.
Okay, that's the first one.
We don't want to spend much time on it because it's not the one that he's interested in.
There's another one next because he says there are three.
And another one we're not going to talk about right now, which is the tragic hero.
We'll get to the tragic hero three lines, three down.
I just, it's too complicated, and we don't need it.
The next one is what interests me a lot, Christian philosophy.
Because in a way, that's a contradiction in terms, the way I've said it up.
Christian philosophy, they're supposed to not go together.
And of course, they don't go together well.
And my example already, you've heard me talk about St.
Augustine.
St.
Augustine takes the Judeo-Christian world and maps it onto Plato.
And it doesn't work very well, I said, but I said it about the creation and about how he couldn't explain why the world was good and he couldn't explain God-man.
But now I'm going to tell it how he views love.
He's very interesting on love.
And it's a perfect let what happens.
It's a beautiful example of what happens if you try to graph together Plato and Christianity.
So I'm going to read you just a few things from Augustine's Confessions.
So what happens is, I don't tell you what pages, but you're not going to be reading this translation, probably.
Okay, it's by somebody whose name you can't forget, a guy named Pine Coffin, who was, and so now I'm going to read from this Pine Coffin translation just what Augustine says about what was clearly what would look like an unconditional commitment to a friend who he's talking about the love of the friend and the friend dies.
So we'll find out what happens there.
So he talks about ours was not a friendship between friends and so forth.
There was a sweetness in our friendship mellowed by the interests we shared.
I'm not reading what I want to read.
Yet in a moment before we had reached the end of the first year of friendship that was sweeter to me than all the joys of life as I lived them, that sort of world-class commitment, you took him from this world.
The friend died.
And he describes how they never left each other's sides.
They were so deeply involved with each other.
And when the friend died, because they were so deeply involved with each other, he says, My heart grew somber with grief, and wherever I looked, I saw only death.
So he's got a really good description of commitment, and there's more about it, but I don't want to read it all.
Really nice things he says about how close they were to each other.
Well, he wondered, I wondered that other men should live when he was dead, for I had loved him as though he would never die.
I wondered that he should die, and I remain alive, for I was his second self, and so forth.
I felt that our two souls had been as one, living in two bodies.
So it's really, Augustine is a Christian, and he's got these Christian feelings that no Greek could have.
I mean, look how different that is than you just forget the beautiful soul and the beautiful body that you've been attached to, and just because they're really not important.
The friend was terribly important, and he describes beautifully how important.
But then, what happens with Augustine?
Well, what conclusion does he draw from the fact that this friend has been taken away?
He says, the well-loved man who just a second.
We're talking about somebody else here, but it doesn't matter.
The part I want to read is, tears alone were sweet to me, for in my heart's desire they had taken the place of my friend.
That's all just, but now I'm ready for the conclusion that he wants to draw about it.
And he concludes from it that, boy, do I have trouble finding?
I can't believe my own page numbers.
There we go.
He concludes, what madness to love a man is something more than human?
What folly to grumble the lot of man has to bear?
Well, you see what's beginning to happen?
He's beginning to say, there must have been something wrong that I put all my love into that relationship with somebody who was vulnerable.
That's crazy, he says.
So, what's the moral of all that?
Well, the moral of it is that he shouldn't have.
You should never build your life so that you go into total grief, get so close to somebody that they seem to be the other half of you, and so forth.
He says, For the grief I felt for the loss of my friend had struck so easily into my inmost heart simply because I had poured out my soul upon him like water upon sand, loving a man who was mortal as though he would never die.
That's the problem, all right.
And what's the solution?
Well, he says, Blessed are those who love you, O God, and love their friends in you for your sake.
They alone will never lose those who are dear to them, for they love them in one who has never lost God.
Now, he never explains what it is to love your friend in God.
But the liking thing about the confessions, now we see him switching over to sort of Plato.
You give up the vulnerable love for the love of God, who is secure and presumably eternal, and so forth.
The question is: do you remember the friend?
Well, in Plato, it's clear you don't remember the beautiful body and the beautiful soul.
They don't even have names.
Well, this friend doesn't have a name either for that.
So forget that.
But anyway, the friend, you, Augustine says you love him forever in God.
You just don't love him in a temporal, finite way.
And he never mentions him again in the whole book.
So it really turns out that when you love him in God, he gets sort of subsumed into the beautiful and the good and the eternal and doesn't, and his individuality just gets wiped out.
And the significance of that relation gets wiped out.
And that's what I was saying.
That's what happens when you try to put Plato together with Christianity.
I mean, he comes as, Augustine comes as close as he can.
He has the whole unconditional commitment experience.
And then he puts it in what look like Christian terms, something about God and love.
But it turns out really in Plato terms because what happens to the friend is he's just gone.
So what else could you have?
Well, we can finally get to real nights of resignation.
Augustine, I don't think, counts as a night of resignation because he isn't holding on to that.
Well, I don't know, he's a marginal case.
He's holding on to the memory enough to write about it for five pages, but he's not holding on to it in the sense that it makes any difference for the rest of his life.
So I don't know, call him a night of resignation, call him an honorite night of resignation.
I think he's not a night of resignation because he never thinks, I, well, you really don't know what to think because he never says, well, I'd be, who I am is the lover of this friend.
But he does say, you know, we were so close to each other that we couldn't be separated, and we can't imagine what we would be apart.
And he does go into grief, weird grief, when the friend dies.
So I guess he had an unconditional commitment and then betrayed it, from a Kierkegaard point of view.
That is, he used the concentration he had in a philosophical way, namely the concentration to finally annihilate it, give it up.
The difference is clearer if you just skip from the set to the second kind of Christian philosophy, which instead of trying to get Plato together with this Christian, Judeo-Christian commitment experience, you end up trying to get Aristotle together.
Then you get Dante.
When St.
Thomas in 1300, roughly, puts Christianity into Aristotelian terms, Dante comes along and writes about Beatrice.
And he never forgets Beatrice.
The whole meaning of his life is to be the lover of Beatrice.
That's his lady.
That's who he is.
And he says he's going to write a poem about her like nobody ever wrote before.
And I forget, did I tell you already?
I get so confused because I tell different people different things in office hours about what he does with Beatrice?
I don't think so.
I'll try to tell you fast.
In the divine comedy, they get up to the, I didn't tell you this, they get up to the top of purgatory, and the procession of the books of the Bible go by.
Didn't say that.
Okay, and the whole Old Testament goes by, and then it comes to a stop, and it's pulling a chariot, and in the chariot, there's some figure covered up, and the angels fly over the chariot and say, Blessed is he who comes.
And what can be there?
What would be the thing that followed the Old Testament if it had angels and so forth?
It should be Jesus.
I mean, that's what you're getting is the history of the church.
And guess who's in the chariot?
Beatrice.
Beatrice is his Savior and therefore his God person.
And he's never going to forget her.
He's writing this whole poem about her.
Well, then, why isn't he doing it right?
Well, the reason he's not doing it right is he's still got this Greek element.
At the end of the whole book, having re-seen Beatrice and having looked at Beatrice's legs and felt the same old hot flames, which is really interesting.
I mean, the body is important to Aristotle in a way to Dante that Augustine was trying to deny.
But she finally says, you couldn't have cared about my body when I died.
You should only have cared about my beautiful soul, and you can see what's happening.
And when they finally get to the end of the poem, she goes back to looking at God, and he goes to looking at God, and they stop looking at each other.
Oh, he's going from legs to smile to eyes, and he's looking into her eyes, and he sees Jesus reflected in her eyes because she really is Jesus for him.
And then at the last lines of the poem are, and my love became one with the will that moved the sun and the other stars.
That's universal.
That's Aristotle's prime mover.
The love as unconditional commitment is just gone.
And so that didn't work either.
That's the best you can do trying to combine Christianity and philosophy and make any sense out of this experience.
So what do you do?
Well, you've got to go into another move, with the move against the important move to us, but I think it's good to have a running start.
Is there any way then to make a defining commitment to an individual safe from the vulnerability and risk?
We just seen you could protect yourself against getting it.
You could seem to have it and then deny it.
Or what?
Well, that's the interesting one.
The knight of resignation has a way of staying in the defining relation.
Never deny the crucial importance of the other person.
Let's do it in terms of romantic love.
And yet convert it into something safe.
How could you do this?
Well, what would it be like?
Remember, now we're talking about the deeper natures.
They never forget themselves.
I wear a page with 72.
So here's...
Whoop.
I just did something.
We have to step out.
Now what am I going to do?
Well, don't lose your wits.
I got one more thing to read about Dante before I get to Beatrice, before I get to our way of doing it, because there's the perfect description of this Dante thing that I want you to realize I didn't make it up.
The bottom of 72.
Deeper natures never forget themselves and never become something other than they were.
So the knight will remember everything.
This is Dante.
But the memory is precisely the pain, and yet in his infinite resignation, he's reconciled with existence.
Now comes the Dante move.
His love for the princess would take on for him the expression of an eternal love, would acquire a religious character, be transfigured into a love for the eternal being, which, although it denied fulfillment, still reconciled him once more in the eternal consciousness of his love's validity in an eternal form that no reality could take from it.
See, that's just a complex, condensed description of what Dante did with Beatrice.
He saved the part of the relation to Beatrice, which was the.
What was the real significance of it?
Well, the real significance of it was that she was the way that led him to this experience of God.
And that made her so important that she's his Savior and so forth.
He did that.
Now, could there be, and we showed, not only did we do it, but you see, if he turns it into an eternal love transfigured so that it's, let me read a little further.
It turns into love of the eternal being, that God, although it denied fulfillment, in the bottom of 72, still reconciled him once more in the eternal consciousness of his love's validity in an eternal form that no reality could take from him.
He remembered the love of Beatrice and wrote about it for the rest of his life.
What could be even better?
Well, it's what you could do or I could do, or we'll see people doing it, but I don't want to tell you who for reasons that should be obvious.
But anyway, it's what it's what it's don't transfigure it into an eternal universal love of God.
Just stick to the relationship and discover that what's important about the relationship isn't the physical, finite, temporal part of it.
It's the significance of the relationship.
So and the significance of the relationship, that's the modern thing.
You idealize the relationship and you say what was important about it was that I could know that person and they could know me and we could have this relationship that is so full of meaning that whether they're there or not doesn't matter.
The meaning is preserved.
That should sound familiar.
There are several movies like that.
But unfortunately, my TA said I should give you a list of movies that you could see, like a recommended reading.
And you can take them out of Next List or whatever.
The movie that shows this very well is a movie called A Man and a Woman.
Anybody ever seen that?
A few people.
It's a good movie.
And it's a story about a woman who was in love with a stunt man, a movie stunt man, who got killed, I forget how, in some kind of accident of the set, I suppose.
And we, but her experience with him was so vivid and important that she just continually keeps it fresh in her mind and remembers it over and over.
And there's this very important scene, I think, in there for what's really going on in the movie is she's finally got interested in another man a little bit, and he's interested in her.
And they're together in a hotel room in bed, I think.
I don't remember clearly, but I think so.
Anyway, and it's dimly lit in the room.
And what's happening is she's trying to relate to him, but what she keeps getting on the screen are these bright flashes of making love in a sleeping bag in the snow with her stuntman, first lover, which are so vivid and so important that they keep her from paying any attention to the man she's with.
And that's exactly what the night of resignation does.
The night of resignation can manage to make their one first crucial love so vivid and so important that they don't need to keep the other person around.
They don't even want to keep the other person around, because that would make them vulnerable.
But all of the significance they can keep, because that's solid.
So let me tell you, let's read Kierkegaard on it now.
I call this the movement of resignation to idealize this love, the love affair that you have, and to internalize it.
That is, take it into yourself as a memory.
Kierkegaard talks about it on 74, on the first full paragraph.
In infinite resignation, there is peace and repose.
Anyone who wants it, who has not debased himself, and so forth, can discipline himself to make this movement, which in its pain reconciles one with existence.
And that's now what we want to hear more about.
And it's pain.
Why is it pain?
Well, because you lack the presence of the other person.
And that's you feel you feel lonely, and you feel you're really missing something.
However, it's joyful too, because the significance is preserved and it's safe.
This he says on 78, the end of the middle paragraph.
But by my own strength, let's see, I'm continually using my energy to renounce everything.
By my own strength, I can give up the princess, and I'll be no sulker, but find joy and peace and repose in my pain.
But with my own strength, I can't get her back.
For all that strength is precisely what I use to renounce my claim on her.
All that is to say, you're sad because you've missed the person, but you're joyful because you did have this relationship and it's still vivid, but you can't have it be safe and get her back.
So you settle for the fact that you have repose, meaning, and a certain minimal kind of joy, but it's not altogether joy.
You find joy in the pain of resignation, as he puts it on 79.
Every moment to see the sword hanging over the loved one's head, and yet find not repose in the pain of resignation, but, and down we go to the night of faith, which we're not ready to go to.
So I won't read the rest of this paragraph yet.
And he says now, and it turns out to be important, I guess.
I don't know why, because the examples are usually what people do after they lose their loved one.
But, well, maybe Kierkegaard's saying this is, no, I don't.
Is this related to Regina?
Let me go.
No.
No, he says that if you've got enough imagination, you can see that the relation is, the ship is vulnerable, and you should immediately make this movement of resignation and only relate to the significance of the other person right away, and so you won't be hurt.
Because if you don't do that, then when they die, you'll be very much sort of plunged into grief and confusion and so forth, and you may not be able to make the movement right.
And in fact, I think that's what happened to Kierkegaard when he broke his Regina.
He just never got it together to figure out whether he was a knight of resignation or nothing or nothing at all.
But so, anyway, so he says that you should make the movement before it's too late.
Where's the way that's that?
Yeah, the bottom of 74.
It talks about it's precisely spirit that is needed, that is real strength of emotion, that is needed to make this movement.
What matters is it's not being one-sided results of dire necessity.
The more it is that, the more doubtful it is that it's a proper movement.
That is, if you're reconciling yourself to the loss of the other person once they're lost, it's not nearly as sure that you're doing the right thing, namely the right thing meaning perhaps a resignation person.
But you're not being a good knight of resignation if you wait until you have to do it.
You ought to see, if you're a knight of resignation, that the significance is all that matters, and just do it right away.
So, the good side, now I'm going to do the good side and the downside.
The good side, I'm going to let you all talk.
I've got feelings.
Anybody want to say anything?
I've been talking to you.
Anybody?
Yeah.
It looks like not.
Well, yes, give it, yeah, take it, because I can hear you, but they remember the podcast all over the world.
Okay.
So, meanwhile, then damn it, so the Knight of Resignation, meanwhile, is still absolutely committed to the significance of this memory of his.
Is that so?
Okay, and this is a little bit of an aside, but could you clarify exactly what was so Aristotelian about what Dante had to say?
Okay, not much, because it's so much inside of Aristotle.
But for Aristotle, I did mention what God is called the unmoved mover.
And God is this sort of force outside the universe that everything is tending toward.
And that's what Dante is talking about when he says, My will became one with the will that moved the sun and the other stars.
He pictured this sort of the whole world as a kind of wheel and turning, and God is turning it, and Dante gets turning too.
It's all so metaphorical because no one knows what it means that you have this mystical experience that Dante had.
Okay, anything else?
Yeah.
Yeah, what happens if you're not going to mean what happens if you want to understand what you have to die?
Oh, no, that's a very, very basic question.
She's asking what happens to your unconditional commitment or to your identity when the other person dies.
The answer is: if you're a knight of resignation, nothing.
You keep your identity just as you had it.
So Dante stays the lover of Beatrice, and Beatrice dies.
She dies young.
Anyway, and Dante marries somebody else and has kids, but that doesn't matter.
He always understands himself as the lover of his lady Beatrice.
So that's the trick in them that the resignation people pull off.
They manage to have an identity, and it stays, and it stays eternal.
That is, you remember the forever.
It's forever what's important in their life from the beginning where it's absent to the end, where it guides everything they do.
They've got all that.
What they haven't got is it's it.
I said something wrong.
It doesn't guide everything they do.
Take that back.
It's there.
It's important to them.
It's their identity.
Wow.
But it guides everything Dante does.
Let me think about it.
He doesn't have Beatrice anymore.
That should be something he worries about.
Beatrice says he shouldn't have worried about it when she died.
He should have thought just that was fine.
And it's fine in the sense that he keeps his identity.
What's bothering me is: does he know day by day, finitely and temporal, what's to do?
Yeah, right about Beatrice.
But what doesn't he know?
He doesn't know that there's anything worth sacrificing for.
He's logging because Beatrice is dead, and it's all secure, that his identity is preserved.
And the high-powered kind of meaning that you get if you have to day by day support the cause.
I think that's it.
Martin Luther King can't sit back and say, well, I know what I'm supposed to do today, and he does it.
But it isn't as if if he failed to do it, the whole thing would crash and the meaning would go out of his life.
It doesn't have that kind of vulnerability and that kind of grip.
And I think that's the point.
So you have to picture Dante writing about Beatrice, caring about Beatrice, understanding himself in terms of Beatrice, but it isn't as if he thinks that his relation to Beatrice could call on him to make some kind of sacrifice.
It's not that immediate.
It's not that intense because if the relationship is secure, there's no, what would you do to sacrifice for it?
I mean, he's got it.
She's in heaven.
He's attached to her and knows that she is.
So I think I just have to say something like that.
Remember way back at the beginning, must seem years ago of this lecture, I said that we're talking about what gives you the highest kind of meaning that a human being can have.
And part of that is that what you are committed to is dependent on your commitment, such that you have to be ready to sacrifice yourself for it.
And that's what he hasn't got.
But what he has got is an identity.
He keeps his identity.
But what you've got to keep this as subtle.
He keeps his identity, but the finite and temporal world does not have the highest meaning for him that it could have if she were there.
And her being there was tied up with him having to constantly sort of affirm in his actions toward her that she was his savior.
Oh, and being ready to die if need be.
Yeah.
Ah, that's a very good question.
How is the knight of resignation not an obsessive fanatic?
Look at your chart.
I'd forgotten all about the trouble of getting out this chart.
Where are we?
Okay.
You're at a part of the chart which is at the bottom and doesn't isn't, but we need to go through it.
It's that the lower natures, looking at the top chart, that's the only one we're going to talk about today, have to go through the ethical, universal, that is, mediation.
Remember, the lower natures are the lower immediacy.
They are the ones who are fanatical, fanciful, driven, and everything like that.
My favorite example, it's always in movies.
How many have seen this wonderful movie, M with Peter Laurie?
Anybody ever seen that?
Peter Laurie is in lower immediacy, all right, when he kills young girls, the guy he plays, and he is driven to do it.
And he can't resist, and he tries when he sees some attractive little girl.
He goes to a cafe, he drinks cognac, he tries to read something or think about something else that he eventually kills her.
And he in the in the movie, he's explaining how terrible it is to be driven like that.
And now the idea is anybody has the strength, according to Kierkegaard, I think.
I don't know what Kierkegaard would think about.
This parachute.
But I mean, supposedly, if you have enough critical ability, you can therapize yourself out of it.
Or if you can't, you can go to a therapist who can help, you know, mediate you out of it.
So it's only after you've been mediated out of all your obsessions and any ways that you're driven that you can make an unconditional commitment.
Otherwise, you're absolutely right.
It would just be fanatical.
Now, there's another movie.
I'm going to give you a list of the nights.
If anybody can help me remember, when you write down all the movies I'm talking about, we talked to T.A.'s and I about the movie Adele H, which is a beautiful example of life, even better than M, really, because it's a case of romantic love gone wacky.
She is overly obsessed with some one particular man who's in the army.
And the whole movie is about what this obsession does to him and to her.
And it's crazy.
I mean, she has no critical sense that he doesn't care at all about her and she's just in his way and so forth.
She has the illusions that they're going to get married and so forth.
Anyway, that won't work.
So Kierkegaard just has one general way to deal with your problem.
You can't have an unconditional commitment and distinguish it from some fanatical craziness unless you've gone through mediation and rationally criticized all of your immediate impulses.
Okay, that's it was very important.
Anybody else?
Yeah.
I say Dante is a night of resignation.
I know that you saw me getting all upset and confused about this.
It's where the Aristotle and the Christianity come close together.
In the sense that he transformed his love into this universal love, I think he's not.
Well, what's he say about it here?
Is he a knight or isn't he?
Let's read the passage that describes Dante.
He transforms.
Okay, we're on page 72.
Before I make a big speech, I want to know which side I should be on.
So the knight makes the movements, but what movements?
Yes, he's a knight.
Well, no, no, no, no.
It's a contradiction if you get the whole thing.
Only the lower natures, deeper natures never forget.
The knight will remember everything.
Okay, he is a knight of resignation because even though he stops looking at Beatrice, even though he becomes one with the will that moves the sun and the other stars, he always takes this relationship as the most important thing in his life.
It's tricky.
I would put it in the jargon of the Gospel of John that some of you will know, where the Gospel of John says that Jesus is the truth and the way.
And I read that to be that Jesus is both the Savior and calls you to be, have an unconditional commitment to him, according to the Gospel of John.
But it looks like what happens is that they two come across.
Beatrice is the way, that is, she leads him to God.
That God is the truth, the reality.
But because she leads him to God, she has this unconditional importance in his life.
Even though when he gets to God, God is so important that he doesn't have to pay any attention to Beatrice anymore.
It's such a, you're not looking happy.
I wish I could be clearer.
I think what this shows is that Aristotelianized Christianity gets as close to the getting it right as you can get, but doesn't because, now I'm back to struggling, because Dante has taken the vulnerability out of the situation.
Beatrice says, you shouldn't have been upset when I died, because it was the meaning of our relationship.
But, and that's the night of resignation part.
But then, because it all has been stuffed into Aristotelian categories, he messes it up at the end.
And instead of saying, and he remains true to Beatrice all his life, he lets the higher supreme being sort of come in and wipe out Beatrice.
I guess I should say, no wonder we're all confused and I'm confused.
That's what happens when you put Aristotle together with the Gospel of John.
You're bound to get hosh, the sort of medieval stew that lasted for a thousand years.
So, why should I be out of it when I'm trying to explain it?
Anyway, let's.
So, he is the limiting sort of knight of resignation.
But the true knight of resignation, who does it right and successfully, is the one we're talking about.
And now, what the night of resignation does is two things, and we've got to make sure we get to them.
Well, first, I'm going to just say, like we said, the good side of it is that it reconciles you with existence and gives you pain and joy, but takes away risk.
And now I want to say, but the downside of it is that you're never fully joyful.
You never can experience bliss because you never get this liver-dies, super strong relation to something finite, and that's the most fulfilling thing you can get.
And you always, therefore, feel that you're missing something, I take it.
Where is this now?
63 at the bottom.
I am happy.
This I, you know, who is the I that's saying I am happy?
Let's make sure everybody's with us.
The night of faith.
Which page?
Oh, sorry, which page?
63, bottom.
So I am happy and satisfied.
Who's happy and satisfied?
You better know this, or I will be very unhappy.
Who's writing this book?
Johannes de Salentio is writing this book, so that's odd.
And what is Johannes de Salentio in this story we're telling?
Is he a knight of faith, a knight of resignation, one of these lower natures?
Well, that's not obvious, so I won't be upset that you don't know.
But it's certainly time I told you.
Johannes de Salentio is the perfect knight of resignation.
He can do it, he keeps saying.
I can be a resignation, I can suffer this kind of resignation and feel the bliss of it, not the bliss, sorry, the joy of it, and feel the pain of it.
But I can't understand the night of faith, he keeps saying.
But I can go as far as the night of resignation can go.
Let's read it.
I'm happy and satisfied.
If my happiness is not that of faith, and compared with that, it is indeed unhappy.
That's the night of resignation speaking.
So, what's the main thing wrong with the night?
Now we have to talk about that.
The night of resignation is certainly missing the further joy of having the other person there day to day, bodily present, or the cause there day to day, demanding them and all of their energy to keep it going and to get them out.
And they're getting out of it meaning all the time.
And what's wrong?
Well, once you've committed the movement of resignation, this is this very interesting move that Thierry Garden owns and could worry about this.
He worries about what would happen if you got the loved one back.
What would be your situation then?
Why is there a problem about getting the loved one back?
Why wouldn't that just be a bonus?
You've done it, you've made it safe, and then you get the loved one back.
Good for you.
That's not how it looks.
Yeah.
I could be right.
I'd probably be right about a man and a woman.
The stuntman is such a sappy ideal in the movies, but that she's so impressed by him.
But no, that needn't happen.
Let's say you have a very realistic ideal.
It was a terrific relationship.
You know that it was.
Yeah.
Ah, you got it.
You either.
It's really an either in it.
Does anybody have another?
There are two possible things.
It's sort of like a ping-pong ball.
You get lost because what?
Why?
You're on the right track.
Let me put words in your mouth.
Okay, you wouldn't know what to do with them as you want to say something about it?
What?
Say it louder.
No, I'm not sure.
You have to tell me later.
But let me put words in both your mouths.
That is, the other one possibility is what he said, that you can't help but get involved and vulnerable again if they're there and they're as attractive as ever, or else you really have succeeded in preparing for their death and making only the significance of the relationship important.
And then you've got this klutzy person around who does all the things that people do get in your way and make a mess and have other plans than you have and so forth.
And everything they do is just a bother because it only gets in the way of the significance of the relation, which is all that matters.
So either you make the significance wholly so that you become utterly self-sufficient.
Don't need the other person at all, in which case, what are they doing in your apartment causing all this trouble?
Or they are there, and moreover, they're so attractive, you start falling back into involvement with them, and you're all lost again.
Yeah.
The wall in Sartre, where he thinks he can die and he lies himself to you, and he doesn't think he's like that.
Ah, yes, sort of.
Is it like the wall in Sartre, where the guy thinks he's going to die the next morning and manages to go through a kind of resignation in which he doesn't care about the cause he's been fighting for?
Not quite.
No, it's too sark.
He sort of sees the insignificance of what he was doing before.
That's different.
It isn't as if he sees that all that matters.
No, just the opposite.
Sartre is typical.
I mean, what he sees is, when he sees he's going to die, he thinks, why was I ever concerned about that woman?
Why was I ever ready to give my life for that cause?
And then they pardon him the next morning, but he just falls down laughing because he's seen that there's absolutely no reason why he should care and do anything.
Whereas that's not them saying the same, because what's happening in Kierkegaard is that you have seen the completely important significance of the relation, and you've seen that you don't need, and now I'm adding, don't want the other person around, and now you get them back, what are you going to do about it?
Yeah.
Yes.
And that's why having the actual person around is either going to be a bother or it's going to get you committed to them instead of the memory.
And what's beautiful about it, Kierkegaard thinks, is if you can, just commit yourself to constantly remembering it and dwelling how great it was.
And then the other person is a bother.
So let me go back to this.
So his resignation has made the temporal finite presence of the other person at least irrelevant, at most a kind of bother.
Her presence or his presence of the loved one is not essential.
It's going to become awkward to have them around and so forth.
Now let me see where I then go from here.
So he would be at a loss to get him back.
This is how Abraham differs, but we're not going to get to Abraham.
But on 65, about eight lines down, my behavior would vitiate the whole story, for I would have been at loss had I got Isaac back again.
Isaac is the loved one, the significant one.
What Abraham found easiest to do, to find joy again in Isaac, for he was with all infinity on his own accord, his own responsibility, for he who, with all his so-and-so and so-and-so, has made the infinite movement and can do no more.
That person keeps Isaac with pain.
Now let's look at the chart.
We just have time.
What is it now?
It's very tricky.
And it took me years to sort it out, and I think I've got it.
After you make the unconditional commitment, everybody has to make the movement of resignation.
That is, they have to discover that they could be sufficient unto themselves, that they could get along with just the memory.
I don't know if I can just flip to it, but I was going to.
Yes, on page 73, I'm going to start a little about 50 lines down.
This is the night of resignation.
He keeps his love young and it grows with him in years and beauty.
On the other hand, he needs no finite occasion for its growth.
From the moment he made the movement, the princess is lost.
He needs none of this erotic titillation of the nerves at the sight of the beloved one, nor does he need in the finite sense to be continually making his farewell, for his memory of her is the eternal one.
That's a good summary of what we've been saying.
And now, a little further down, he has grasped the deep secret that even in loving another, one should be sufficient unto oneself.
Now, that's really important.
That's related to his move.
I mean, that is, he's made an even more extreme kind of mediation.
He's seen that you could get along just on the memory of the significance of this, and that saves him from a certain kind of fanaticism.
I mean, when Lear goes crazy because Cordelia is dead, it's because he can't live without her.
And Romeo and Juliet each kills themselves because they can't live without each other.
That's not what should be happening.
I mean, that everybody should be able, and this gets rid of total dependence.
I mean, like the story about women who love too much and so forth.
You're not supposed to be in a frame of mind where you think that there's no substance in you, no meaning in you, that you don't get from the other person, because then you can be completely dependent on the other person, like at LH, too.
So first you have to see that you are a real person, and you could get along without this other person.
You wouldn't be in despair.
You wouldn't have the blissful life that human beings could have.
But you don't have to go into grief either.
You see them.
You could live without them.
But, of course, when you see that, Now you have a choice.
That's the movement of resignation up on the chart.
You become self-sufficient rather than dependent.
But then you can become a knight of resignation, a full-fledged card-carrying knight of resignation.
The one who really does it exactly right is someone who now lives their life in terms of the movement of resignation.
That is, they constantly live by the fact that they're self-sufficient, that they've got the memory in them, that there's nothing that they need outside of them.
And what happens with the knight of faith?
Well, the knight of faith does something higher.
The knight of faith manages, and this is the puzzling thing, to become, to see the sword.
I wish I could open to that one, but I probably can't.
To see the sword hanging over the head of the beloved.
Now I read the first half of it and live as if it's the surest thing of all.
Yeah, 79.
Every moment to see the sword hanging over the head of the beloved's head and yet find not repose in the pain of resignation.
See, the sword is the vulnerability, of course.
But joy on the strength of the absurd, that's wonderful and so forth.
Now, what does that mean?
That means that by some kind of faith which we haven't defined yet, and it certainly isn't faith that you're going to get it settled in the afterlife or that God's going to intervene and make everything all right.
But something called faith, the knight of faith, is able to, and this is the tricky part, see the vulnerability and go on getting more and more deeply involved completely defenselessly.
And that's just paradoxical because you can't make any rational sense out of it.
Why would anybody who sees the vulnerability just go on and on getting more deeply involved?
Well, and the answer is: there's no way to make sense of why anybody should do it.
And of course, they could always take the chicken exit and just become a knight of resignation.
But the question is, why would, but then they wouldn't be getting more and more involved.
There's this peculiar state of mind, and it's not a state of mind exactly, that the knight of faith sees that it's completely irrational to get involved with another person without any defenses of the sort that the knight of resignation, and then gets more and more defenselessly involved anyway.
So, what their reason does and what their emotions do are in conflict, and they are able to live in that conflict.
And by that, they get the bliss because they get everything.
They get the other person.
Now, there's lots of puzzles there.
Have they made the other person immortal some way so they can't die?
No, they see that the other person can die.
And yet they get more and more involved.
How can that be?
Well, that's the subject for the next lecture when we get to the night of resignation.
Now we'll have to stop.
I'm going to I'll talk to you.
Come on up.