The mysterious visitor has gotten away with murder, become completely isolated, can't be intimate with anybody.
That's the existentialized version of being in hell.
And after 14, or I think it is, years of it, he feels he has to confess.
That's the existentialized version of confession.
Turn it up.
Well, it's I tried, but I'm getting this kind of feedback.
Let me see if I can do something with it.
I think I can solve this by getting it up closer to my mouth.
How's that?
Better for this, too, I think.
Okay, so now, and then somebody asked me the very good question based on the fact that he makes a public declaration to all his colleagues and his family, and that's supposed to put him in the relation to them that they really know who he is, so that he can at least relate to them honestly, which means as a murderer, it's not a very good relationship, but at least he relates to them, and they aren't relating to some imagined nice guy.
But he's become such a nice guy over the years, suffering for what he did and regretting it, that nobody believes him.
And they think he's a good man and a loving father, not a murderer.
And so what's going to happen then?
Well, I think his confession is nonetheless valid existentially because he has honestly told them who he was, and they have, so to speak, reacted by telling him that he's not that person anymore.
It's exactly like the death row issues.
When somebody's been on death row for 20 years, I don't remember the name of that person about four months ago, was it now or something, who's become a Christian, who does good deeds, who terribly regrets whatever it was they did.
And do you kill that person now for what they did 20 years ago?
Or do you not because of what they've become?
It's a big dilemma.
And Dostoevsky's taking a side on this dilemma, which is, I guess, the Christian side, namely, you can be reborn, and this guy is reborn.
He's now a loving person who wants to be in touch with everybody, not an isolated criminal.
So the fact that they don't believe him doesn't really matter.
The current Michael is not the man who murdered the mistress.
He wouldn't harm anyone now.
And so, therefore, having made the confession, yeah, go ahead.
He also had to use like seconds away from killing.
That's right.
And that's interesting.
But he didn't.
And he was tempted.
It's so painful to have to confess to your family and your colleagues that you're a murderer that he almost murdered Zosima rather than confess it.
That would have been certainly to throw him back into hell and to confirm existentially that he was still a bad person.
But he didn't do it.
And I think that's supposed to show that in the end he wouldn't hurt anybody anymore.
You don't look convinced.
That's all right?
Okay.
Yeah.
He was wanting to murder.
He had the desire.
Well, it's interesting.
I think while he was having the real desire to kill him, his heart was dark and he was still a criminal.
But now what's in his heart is he's glad he didn't.
And so the man now, standing before everybody and confessing, is getting what he deserves, so to speak, back in touch with everybody.
And in effect, existentially, this is Dostoevsky's story.
You don't have to buy it, but what the book wants you to believe is that he is in heaven.
That is, at this, having done this, he goes, he gets into, why is this not what I expected?
Hmm.
No, that's because I'm looking at the wrong quote.
Okay, on 301.
He always puts it in traditional Christian terms.
This is a kind of trick of Dostoevsky because he wants you to both see what he's existentialized.
He wants you to see the existentialized experience, but he wants you to see what he's existentialized.
So somebody always describes it in the pre-existentialized language.
And so here, Michael at the bottom of 301, just as he described hell in the pre- and falling into the hands of a living God, both of which Dostoevsky thinks really happened to people, but they don't happen to people in some supernatural way, but in some what he calls psychological, and I'm calling existential way.
So he's in heaven at the bottom of 301.
He says, God has pity on me and is calling me to him.
I know I'm dying, but I feel joy and peace for the first time after so many years.
There's been heaven in my heart from the moment I did what I had to do.
Now I dare to love my children and to kiss them.
So he's now dying, a happy, fulfilled, blissful person.
But there's, and that's fine.
And it's interesting that the mysterious visitor has a reciprocal effect on Sosthamus.
Just as Zosima, by throwing away his gun at the duel, inspired the mysterious visitor to confess.
The confession of the mysterious visitor had an effect on Zosima.
This is on 349.
Looking at where I think it is.
Oh, again, I'm getting confused.
It's on 302.
I'll learn to read before the end of the lecture, I promise.
Here we are: 302 at the bottom.
Zosima ends this by saying, But I held my tongue, and very shortly, that is the telling that he really was a murderer, since it doesn't matter anymore.
I held my tongue, and very shortly after, I left the town.
And five months later, by God's grace, I entered upon the safe and blessed path, following the unseen finger that had guided me so clearly to it.
But I remember in my prayer to this day the servant of God, Michael, who suffered so greatly.
Now, for years, that passage puzzled me.
It ought to puzzle you, too.
I mean, I thought the unseen finger was a sort of metaphorical way of referring to the fact that the mysterious visitor sort of pointed him his way to the monastery.
That's not right, because the translation says, and they all do, so I'm sure that it's the right thing to say, that he went into the monastery, guided by the unseen finger.
But I remember in my prayer to this day, not and, I mean, there are two things going on.
He goes to the monastery, already guided by the unseen finger, and Michael, in effect, confirms him in it, just the way he confirms Michael, and who had already decided he ought to confess into confessing, I take it.
But that leaves the puzzle, doesn't it?
What about this unseen finger?
There's a movie where there's this person always in the background watching out over the other guys.
A sequel to The Sundance Kid, I think.
You know what I mean?
That finally it turns out to be this woman who's protecting him all the time.
What movie is that?
What?
The Sting, exactly.
It's like the Sting.
There's somebody in the background.
You'll hear about them again a little while in this lecture who is guiding people around and literally guiding them around and pointing directions and influencing their life.
And you haven't seen them yet and you don't know who they are.
And this is the first hint of this.
And you won't know for a while who they are.
But I want to say one more thing, and then that's the end of what was supposed to be the lecture last time.
And we go on to a new issue.
But there's one more thing.
It's interesting that once he goes into the monastery and takes what he calls the safe path, there's an implication already that there's something wrong with him, that he feels responsible for everybody, but he doesn't do anything.
And he doesn't do anything.
He doesn't perform, Zosima, that is, any more miracles in the course of the book.
I mean, he saves the mysterious visitor.
I mean, let's not call it a miracle, but he doesn't perform any existential good deeds, so to speak, from then on.
He still is a great elder, and he has confessions, and he tries to, and he bows down to Dimitri.
He still knows that he understands love like a science, but he doesn't do, he doesn't make any difference in the world.
And on the other hand, Alyosha never does any good deeds until he leaves the monastery.
As somebody pointed out to me, but I just realized now I didn't have time to look it up.
Alyasha's attempted good deed, when he tries to give money to this guy, I forget who, just leads to the guy having a sort of fit and throwing down the money and trampling on it.
I didn't go back and look it up, but it was a very unsuccessful good deed.
Were you the one who told me about it?
What page?
206, 207.
Just, I mean, I think it's no coincidence.
Dostoevsky knows perfectly what he's doing.
And now wear on 206.
Okay.
Okay, why look, squealed the captain suddenly, and showing him the two notes which he'd been holding in one corner between his fingers and so forth.
He crumpled them, seized them tight.
Do you see he shrieked pale and infuriated and fling up his hand?
He threw the crumpled notes on the sand.
You see he shrieked again?
Look there.
And that's Alyasha's only attempted helping somebody before he leaves the monastery.
We'll see that he performs all sorts of interesting things once he does.
In fact, that's the subject for today's lecture.
So from now on, we're looking for the next existentialized something or other, sacrament, I've been calling him big deal Christian symbols.
And the most interesting, the most important, because Dostoevsky manages to make every possible relevant move at once and brings it off, I think, brilliantly.
And thus, what is the existentialized miracle?
Remember, that's the toughest hurdle for Dostoevsky, because a miracle, in principle, ought to just be against the laws of physics and chemistry.
I mean, I suppose you've heard things like this.
Every once in a while, people try to explain away a miracle by the laws of physics and chemistry.
I once heard, I don't know if this is still a popular view, that the Red Sea has a sandbar in it, and when the wind blows a certain way, you can walk across the sea, and that's what Moses and the Jews did.
But then the wind changed, and that sunk all the Pharaoh and his people.
It was just a kind of meteorological fluke.
Well, that's not a miracle, that's what a miracle looks like.
It's got to be, I mean, that's not what a miracle looks like.
I mean, it's got to be some intervention from outside the natural order to be a miracle, one would think.
And Dostoevsky is in a tough mind here if he wants to existentialize miracles and make sure that they don't go against the laws of physics and chemistry.
Because one of the points of the book, I mean, I've never said this, it's so obvious to me.
Have I said it already?
That he's, I think I must have.
He's trying to save Christianity by not letting it run head up against science because he knows that we're becoming a secular culture, and if you try to do that, science is going to win.
So his whole project when he existentializes the Christian symbols is to not run up against the laws of physics and chemistry.
After all, confession turned out to be a kind of religious spiritual event, but it didn't go against the laws of physics and chemistry.
But now, how's he going to do it with the miracle?
That's the interesting thing.
Well, the first question, we have to do it step by step.
All of this is going to go back to the Grand Inquisitor story, don't forget.
The issue in the Grand Inquisitor story we're now asking ourselves is: one, do people need miracles?
Remember, Jesus figure says no, they don't need miracles.
That coerces them to believe, but they really ought to believe freely.
And then if they get miracles as a kind of bonus, that's all right.
But you don't need miracles to believe.
In fact, if you have miracles and believe because of them, that's the wrong kind of belief.
But the Grand Inquisitor says, but people do need miracles.
And so the church, that the Grand Inquisitor represents, makes up miracles in order to keep people believing.
So the issue is: do people need miracles in order to keep their faith?
And the Grand Inquisitor says yes, and we'll make them.
And the Jesus figure says no, and I won't do it.
I won't jump off the temple and get held up by angels, because that's not the way to get people.
That's not what I want people.
That's not how I want people to believe in me.
So the issue then becomes: can people live without miracles?
I see something here.
I want to fix something.
I think on 248.3.
248, I mean, 248, but I'm not sure because I can't read what he's written.
So let's hope.
Oh, yeah, that's a very important quote.
So 248, about two-thirds of the way down, or three-quarters of the way down, the Grand Inquisitor says, is the nature of men such that they can reject miracles?
And at the great moments of their life, the moments of their deepest and most agonizing spiritual difficulties, cling only to the free verdict of the heart.
Now, you've done the reading for this, those who have.
Can they?
Do you remember what's happening?
I just want to see how many.
Dostoevsky is so oblite.
He's so, he never lets you know what's happening so head-on, and yet he's also so anxious to make sure you get it.
Do people need miracles in order to keep their faith?
Anybody know?
Does Alyasha need a miracle in order to keep his faith?
Nobody has an opinion?
This is scary.
I can hear you.
You don't think so?
Okay.
Well, let's look and see.
So we're going to look at this now and find out whether Alyasha needs a miracle to keep the faith.
But it turns on the death and decomposition of Zosima.
And so now we have to look at that.
There's so many issues now.
If I lose you, raise your hands and scream.
I'll try to be clear and slow.
But Dostoevsky does about, I don't know, 10 things at once at this point.
And it's very hard to keep them all going at once.
But they're all very clear.
And at the bottom of 325, we will see, in the middle of that bottom paragraph, Alyasha thought of that sorrowful day as one of the most bitter and fatal days of his life.
This is, Father Zosima is now stinking, as Rakitan says.
If the question is asked, could all his grief and disturbance have been due to the fact that his elder's body had shown signs of premature decomposition instead of performing miracles, I must answer, yes, it certainly was.
Well, now I ask you again: does Alyacha need a miracle to keep his faith?
Yes, he needs a miracle to keep his faith.
It gets clearer as we go on.
But before we go on, we better get, I have to say something about the bad odor of Zosima.
There is three possibilities that Dostoevsky sort of toys with.
There's the, you could have a natural explanation of the smell.
It could be a positive miracle showing that somehow, I don't have it to be a positive.
I guess they wanted a positive miracle.
They wanted him not to decompose.
Or this could be a negative miracle.
He's decomposing faster than he should.
And it shows that his bad moves, like eating pineapple compote and having group therapy sessions, is being condemned by God.
All these issues are in the air.
So I want to just make clear, partly because the interpreters I've read get this all wrong.
Later in the book, there's another corpse that is smelling totally sweet, even though it was past time for it to start smelling decomposing.
And now, and the contrast, people think, must be that Dostoevsky wants us to see that there's something wrong with Zosima and something right about this way at the end of the book, dead boy.
But I think that's clearly wrong.
And sooner or later, I have to talk about it, so I'm going to talk about it now.
In the middle of 318, he's talking about it.
This is, or afterwards, even many years afterwards, some sensible monks were amazed and horrified, as they recall that day.
They skipping a little God-fearing men and so forth.
Yet from their humble coffins, too, other people who died, other elders, the breath of corruption had come, naturally, as from all dead bodies.
That it caused not the slightest excitement and so forth.
In other words, you could have taken this naturally, but okay, let's stop with that.
And then on 318, looking, well, then there have been positive miracles.
Then he goes on, right where I'm reading.
Of course, there had been in former times saints in the monastery whose memory was carefully preserved and whose relics, according to tradition, showed no signs of corruption.
This fact was regarded by the monks as mysterious, and the tradition of it was cherished as something blessed and miraculous, as a promise by God's grace.
That's the kind of against physics and chemistry miracle.
Dostoevsky's not going to tell you the story of how some normal dead body was left undecomposing.
And then there are the ones who think that the smell showed that there was some intervention of God against Osama at the middle of 319.
That, I believe, was the reason why many people were pleased at the smell of decomposition, which came so quickly, or not a day had passed since his death.
They were pleased because it showed that he decomposed too fast.
On 327.
Really?
Oh, yeah, oh, I see.
Yeah, okay.
About 15 lines down.
Even had there been no miracles, had there been nothing miraculous to justify his hopes, this is Alyasha thinking.
Why this indignity?
Why this humiliation?
Why this premature decay in excess of nature, as the spiteful monks said?
That would be a negative miracle.
So the question is then next: did the smell go against physics and chemistry as a kind of negative miracle?
Well, you've got to know, and you've got to ask yourself way later in the book what else happened, what happened with the other corpse.
In this case, Dostoevsky sets it up to make sure that you know, if you're paying attention, that this was all perfectly natural and within the laws of physics and chemistry.
The windows were closed.
I'm just going to give you a list of that together show, of course, the corpse should smell.
The windows were closed at the bottom of 317.
The question of opening the windows was raised among those who were around the coffin, but this suggestion was unanswered and went almost unnoticed.
Okay, that's the first thing.
Now, the reason it was suggested that they might open the windows but didn't is because it was a warm autumn night.
We're told that every once in a while, but for us, let's just look at this time.
I really take my word for it, it's a warm autumn night.
More important, and take my word for it too, since you won't be getting a notice of it, there were no flowers.
See, I'm setting it up, this is no big secret, that at the next dead body, the windows are open, it's the middle of winter, there are lots of flowers, and finally, that body, the one you're going to get to later, was washed.
Whereas we go out of the way on 3:15 to learn that the bodies of dead monks and hermits are not washed.
Third line of the chapter.
So, naturally, it smells bad in the room.
Windows closed, no flowers, hot autumn night, and unwashed corpse, and it's just straight fine with the laws of physics and chemistry.
So, what did Alyasha want?
Well, he wanted some kind of supernatural miracle that made Dazasima's body not decompose.
And that's what he's not getting.
And when he's not getting it, he's falling into, he's losing his faith.
This is on 317, about in that big paragraph about halfway down.
The narrator appears.
You know, I say this narrator comes and goes.
This narrator says, I personally feel it almost repulsive to recall that event which caused such excitement and was such a stumbling block to so many, though in reality it was the most natural thing.
I've said that this narrator is not very smart, so I can't take much pride in the fact that Olmos Casey's on my side.
I would, of course, have admitted all mention of it in my story if it had not exerted a very strong influence on the heart and soul of the chief, though future hero of my story, Alyasha.
It brought a crisis and turning point to his spiritual development, giving a shock to his intellect, which finally strengthened it for the rest of his life and gave it a definite aim.
Okay, so there we go.
It turns out to be a very important experience for Alyasha because it's an experience where he almost loses his faith, but doesn't for reasons that are very interesting and complicated.
Now, the next thing is to understand why Alyasha is going into such a fit about this situation.
Well, that should be obvious to all of you already, but I think I have to just put it into got all the points.
I mean, he's got all his love wrapped up in Zosima.
He's suffering, not all, he's suffering from not, he's suffering from losing the person you love, and then all this humiliation on top of it.
So he has every reason to be very upset.
So look on 326, just a little below the middle.
The fact is that all the love that lay concealed in his pure young heart for everyone and everything had for the past year been concentrated, and perhaps wrongly so, on one being, his beloved elder.
You might notice a little interesting thing there if you're paying attention.
He's not a Kierkegaardian, Dostoevsky.
He is not happy that this was an unconditional, total commitment in which everything that Alyasha cared about was tied up in Zosima.
How that could be wrong, and yet Dostoevsky be a Christian, is not yet clear.
Dostoevsky would, you can begin to see that Dostoevsky, because Kierkegaard is this Lutheran Protestant, is not going to like anything in Kierkegaard, including unconditional commitments.
So tied up in his beloved elder, it's true that his elder had for so long been accepted by him as an ideal that all his young strength and energy could not but turn toward an ideal, even to the forgetting at the moment of everyone and everything.
Now, here, if you're reading carefully, is a hint of what's wrong with unconditional commitments.
They're too exclusive.
If you really get all wrapped up in one person, you forget to love and help a lot of other people.
And that's just what happened to Alyasha going on.
He remembered afterwards how on that terrible day he had entirely forgotten his brother Dmitri.
See, who forgets and remembers his brother is very biblical and it's very important.
Ivan says at one point he doesn't have, he's not responsible for his brother Dmitri.
Smerzhikov says at one point he's not responsible for Dmitry.
Alyasha thinks he is responsible for Dmitry, but he forgets it when he's so upset when Zasima dies.
He forgets it, and we see that here, but we see it also on 257.
It's a big deal that he forgets it.
The 257 is what he's thinking back to from the passage I read at the end of that section.
Several times afterward, Ivonne wondered how he could, on leaving Yvonne.
Oh, no, he forgets, yes, so completely forget his brother Dimitri.
He had that morning only a few hours before so firmly resolved to find him and not to give up doing so, even should he be unable to return to the monastery that night.
He resolved to find him and do that, but he didn't do that.
So that's part of the problem.
So with the death of Zosima, he's lost the object of his defining commitment.
That was just an aside, a defining commitment, which, well, maybe wasn't a good thing to have anyway.
But it was too.
You'll see.
Dostievsky's got subtle views.
I mean, he isn't saying, he isn't saying he shouldn't have loved Zosima with all his might.
He's saying something much more complicated and interesting, which we'll get to.
So Alyasha, so now let's see.
So the loved person has died on 215.
I don't know why I say that, but let's look.
Again, how it looks to Alyasha on the middle of 215.
And now, on top of it all, my best friend, he's talking to Lisa, the best man in the world, is going, is leaving the earth.
If you knew, Lisa, how bound up in my soul I am with him.
That's this sort of thing.
He's got this temporary unconditional commitment.
And then I shall be left alone.
I shall come to see you, Lisa.
For the future we will be together.
That's the hint, by the way, that they're existential doubles, and that he's going to marry Lisa someday.
But not in this book, but in the other book that never got written.
Okay, now, where are we?
And Aliasha says that what he wants is justice, even when he's all upset about it.
So on 340, he thinks that Zosima should be appreciated.
Where we are, 340.
Hmm.
That's not it at all.
Okay, I have to fix this.
Then try looking at 3.
Well, that's funny.
330.
Oh, I'm again.
I was.
Boy, am I being weird today?
It is on 340.
I don't know why.
I was just looking at 341.
Not really.
It's worse than I thought.
Okay, let's look at try again.
I don't understand yet what I'm doing, but in a minute I will.
Okay.
You collect your wits while I collect my wits.
Let's see.
Well, what I say is when I've got to find the place where Alyasha says what he wants is justice.
327.
Why am I?
Where do you see that?
Oh, yeah, good.
You're absolutely right.
327 at the top of the page.
Why haven't I got that?
I don't know.
Nothing to do with what I got.
Okay.
So he wants justice.
And it's part of the influence of Yvonne that he sees what's happening with Zosima as some reason to reject the world, you'll see in a minute.
But he thinks somehow that the world isn't properly set up if Zosima dies.
But let's just go head on into what's important: the way Alyasha is losing his faith over it.
Starting at the bottom of 327.
Or really, starting, let's start with 328.
No, let's start at the bottom of 327.
It was dusk.
Well, let's see.
The faith of his soul had been shaken.
You see about eight lines from the bottom of 327.
I mean, remember, now, he didn't get a miracle.
And moreover, he got what might even be a negative miracle.
And he's losing his faith.
And when he's losing his faith, who should appear but the existentialized devil?
You're getting used to that by now, if you're reading carefully.
Who's the existentialized devil?
Rakitin, right, who always says the devil only knows when he talks.
It was dusk at the bottom of 327 when Rakitin, crossing the pine grove from the hermitage to the monastery, suddenly noticed Alyasha lying face downward on the ground under a tree.
He went up and called him.
You hear Alyasha?
And then skipping to the middle of the page, can you really be so upset simply because your old man has begun to stink?
You don't mean to say you seriously believed he was going to work miracles.
And Alyasha says, I believe, I want to believe, I will believe.
What more do you want?
And Rakitin says, starting one sentence, and damn it all, why no schoolboy of 13 believes that now.
But there.
So now you're angry with your God.
You're rebelling against him.
And this is the Yvonne rebellion.
Everybody influences everybody in the book.
That's one of the themes I keep telling you.
It has more effect on others than they realize, good and bad.
And one of the ways this shows up is a kind of plagiarism in which people get sort of taken over by other people's ideas.
Right now, Alyasha is getting taken over by Yvonne.
So he says, I'm not rebelling against my God.
I simply don't accept his world.
Alyasha suddenly smiled a forced smile.
Well, that's certainly plagiarism from Yvonne, but it's what Alyasha is beginning to believe.
So now we need to see where we are.
Let me see.
Okay.
Now, so when Rakitin sees that Alyasha is losing his faith and rebelling, what does he do?
Well, the job of the devil is to help people, help in the sense, to help them despair.
That is, the job of the devil is when people are losing their faith to do everything he can to get them to lose their faith, to make them more miserable and more despairing, and finally to get them to just do something that is unpardonably against their faith.
So it gets to be kind of fun.
Rakitin sees this and immediately thinks that he can now sort of seduce Alyasha to do things that he would never have done before.
He sees that he's rebelling, as he says on 328, which we read.
He's a regular rebellion.
And so he tempts him with sausage, vodka, and Grushenka in that order.
On 329.1, he says, I got some sausage, the top, I brought it from the town in case of need.
Only you won't eat sausage.
It must be Lent or something.
What happens in August that they wouldn't eat sausage?
Does anybody know?
When is Lent?
Not in August.
But it isn't August, autumn.
I don't know.
Anybody know why he's not eating sausage?
I don't either.
But anyway, he's not supposed to, and he says, okay.
And he says, give me some.
And then he says, but vodka's going too far for you.
No, give me some vodka.
That's easy.
Then comes the exciting part.
He says, let's go to Grushenka.
Will you come?
asked Rakitin at last.
Let's go to Grushenka, Alyasha answered calmly.
And then we are told a little further down the very devilish thing about Rakitin.
Why was he doing this?
Well, in that bigger paragraph, his object in this case was twofold, of a revengeful desire to see the downfall of the righteous and Alyasha's fall from saint to sinner.
That's the typical job of devils.
And in the second case, a material gain for himself.
It turns out Grushenka has offered him money if he'll bring Alyasha.
But that's important to us as the devilish motivation.
By the way, I've been talking a long time.
Is everybody okay with so far and thinks that I'm not doing anything wrong?
This is all setting up some big deal thing, which we will, so I'm perfectly happy to keep setting it up.
So Rikitin is just demonic, devilish.
He's doing this gratuitous, evil thing.
And now we switch to Grushenka.
Okay, Grushenka is now 22 years old, and we need to know about her past.
She was seduced and betrayed by a Polish soldier when she was 17.
And then he left, married somebody else, and she became a prostitute, a sort of high-class prostitute, relatively speaking, kept by a rich merchant.
And she and everybody in the town consider her a fallen woman.
Then the the Pole's wife dies and he sends a message to Grushenka that now he wants to marry her.
And this is obviously not, well, it it's confusing to Grushenka to say the least.
On the one hand, she's sort of be saved from being kept woman, and she gets the Polish lover.
On the other hand, it's pretty insulting that he has married somebody else, and then when that person dies, he just calls in Grushenka as a sort of second the second backup person.
And so her alternatives are to go back to him, as she puts it, like a dog, meaning grateful that he's finally got chosen her and saved her from the merchant, or with a knife, revenging herself on him for all that he's done to humiliate and insult and hurt her.
So she's in a frenzy over these two possibilities of 341.
The middle, a little below the middle.
If he comes and whistles for me, I'll creep back to him like a beaten dog.
And then at the bottom of that long paragraph, perhaps I'll take a knife with me today.
I can't make up my mind.
So she's got two destructive alternatives.
If she does either one of these things, sort of it's the end for her.
She ends up totally humiliated and a sort of slave married to him, or she ends up murdering him.
So, and she has to do something because he's called her, and she wants to go and take advantage of that, but she doesn't know what she wants to do.
So she says, about 15 lines from the bottom of 341: Where am I?
Before you came in, I was lying here waiting, brooding, deciding my whole future life, and you never know what was in my heart.
Well, we know what was in my heart because we just read it.
Which way to go back to the old lover, to humiliated like a dog or revengeful with her knife.
And then, at that moment, in comes Alyasha and Retitin.
And it's important to know that Alyasha is totally lusts for Grushenka, just like Dmitry and just like the old Taramatsov.
The only person who isn't totally bowled over by Grushenka is Ivan, who seems to be completely immune to such kinds of sensuality.
But you're supposed to think, I told somebody after class last time when I think of it, there was going to be a movie of the brothers, and Marilyn Monroe was going to play Grushenka.
That would have been right if she had a black wig.
I can't think of a blonde Grushenka.
But anyway, somebody as sexy and as attractive as a human being at the same time.
And that's supposed to be, it would have been perfect.
And so here we are.
He is now right next to this woman whom he finds just absolutely, overwhelmingly, physically attractive.
And then what happens?
Well, she jumps on his lap.
That's what happens.
But we have to go back now to see where that is.
Is that 335?
Yeah, on the bottom of 335.
Rakitin says, his elder stinks.
And she says, what?
You are talking nonsense.
You want to say something nasty.
Be quiet.
You're stupid.
Let me sit on your knee, Alyasha, like this.
She suddenly got up and laughed, nestling like a kitten on his knee with her right arm around his neck.
I'll cheer you up, my pious boy.
Well, now things are getting really scary for Alyasha because he's getting the rebellion he sort of wants.
But it doesn't happen at all the way Rakitin thought it would happen, or Alyasha, too.
We have to read: Alyasha at the bottom of 335 didn't speak.
He sat afraid to move.
He heard her words.
If you tell me, I'll get off, but he didn't answer.
But there was nothing in his heart, such as Rakitin, for instance, watching him might have expected or thought.
The grief in his heart swallowed up every sensation that might have been aroused.
If only he could have thought clearly at that moment, he would have realized that he had now the strongest armor to protect him against every lust and temptation.
And what's happening there?
What's getting existentialized there?
Well, it's the fact that he's switched from eros to what Christian, agape.
Eros is the Greek word for desire.
And that's what he had for her.
We'll read more about that in a minute.
Agape is the Greek word that gets translated charity in Paul's faith, when Christians need faith, hope, and charity.
But charity has gotten so sort of, I don't know, made into just giving away money or something that now it gets translated love, usually.
But there are two kinds of love: there's desiring love, that's eros.
Plato says it comes from a lack, and you want something that you need, and you will pursue whatever it is that you're lusting after.
That's eros.
It can be from very low physical level to spiritual kind of desire.
But in this case, it's going to be physical desire.
And agape is Christian love, which is a kind of love that doesn't want anything that is already fulfilled and out to help other people who aren't fulfilled.
So, and it's a condition of some kind of total interestedness in the other person, but not to get anything from them.
And let's go on.
At the top of 336, he could not help wondering at a new and strange sensation in his heart.
That's agape.
This woman, this dreadful woman, had no terror for him now, none of the terror that stirred in him at any passing thought of women.
On the contrary, this woman, dreaded above all women, sitting now on his knee, holding him in her arms, aroused in him now a quite different, unexpected, peculiar feeling, a feeling of the intensest and purest interest without a trace of fear.
That's agape.
But the other translation, the one I used before this one, which made me want to go back to this one, the new one that was popular, says that he looks at her with the intensest and purest curiosity.
You see the difference.
I mean, curiosity is what Yvonne felt when he stood on the landing listening to old Karamatsov batting around and thinking about how he was acting, knowing that he was going to, with Yvonne knowing he was going to die, or somehow imagining that he was going to die.
Anyway, so it's curiosity is just the wrong thing.
It's Yvonne being the detached spectator, the one who does, I never can remember, what's it again?
The eyewitness.
Yeah, that's curiosity.
But this is something quite opposite of curiosity.
This is being totally involved with the other person.
That's why intensest interest is good.
And not wanting anything from them.
And so he's looking at her now for the first time, it turns out, looking at her with this kind of interest.
It's the first time he's looked at her at all, because he's afraid to look at her because she's so attractive.
So that now comes out and turns out to be very important.
So on the middle of 337, she says, It's true, Alyasha.
I had designs on you before because I was a horrid, violent preacher.
But at other times, I looked upon you, Alyasha, as my conscience.
I've kept thinking, anyhow, how anyone like that despises the natural, nasty thing like me.
I read that a little too soon, but it doesn't matter.
Why does she think that he despises her?
I said, because he's afraid to look at her.
And you get that on 340 about a few lines into that big bottom paragraph.
I wanted to ruin you, Alyasha.
That's the holy truth.
I quite meant to.
I wanted to so much that I bribed Rakitin to bring you.
That's now we know what the other motive was.
And why did I want to do such a thing?
You knew nothing about it, Alyasha.
You turned away from me.
If you passed me on the street, you dropped your eyes.
And I looked at you a hundred times before today.
I began asking everyone about you.
Your face haunted my heart.
He despises me, I thought.
Wait, you're losing me.
So now, now something very interesting is happening here.
We remember always that you affect other people for better and for worse in ways you don't know.
Alyasha had no idea he was driving Brushenka into a sense of total humiliation because she thought he was despising her when he was just busy trying not to look at her and lust after her.
But it turns out that this being despised by him when she was already humiliated by her position in the world was tremendously upsetting to her.
And that's what she's saying.
And now we put it all together.
She has no self-respect.
The one person whose opinion she would love to have admire her and respect her is Alyasha.
And he dislikes her so much she thinks that he can't even stand to look at her.
And then comes the big flip.
He's now sitting on her lap, and he's looking at her, protected by his sorrow, and full of active love.
And that changes everything.
He is, at this point, an angel, an existentialized angel.
Just as devils exploit situations to bring out the worst in people, angels in a situation bring out the best in people.
Now, the joke almost is that if I tell you Alyasha is an angel, you might say, well, sort of.
I mean, that's just a metaphor.
It's not.
He is an existentialized angel.
And Dostoevsky, in this funny way, never lets you forget what he's existentializing.
This one is at the bottom of 155.
Ivan is feeling very bad.
No, Dmitri is feeling very bad for himself and feeling despairing and in misery and so forth.
And let's go to the bottom of one.
Why go on blundering on earth, dishonoring it with my presence?
And then I heard you come in.
Heavens.
It was as though something flew down on me suddenly.
And here and so forth.
Well, that's a pretty weird way to describe the arrival of Alyasha's heavens, and something flew down on me.
And just that will connect with the fact that every time Alyasha does anything, from now on in the book, practically, people will say, you angel, to him.
And Grushenka's the first one to say that on 155.
No, not where am I?
That's where I was.
Let's go back to 344.
That's what I mean that so many things are happening.
Okay, here we are, a quarter of the way down on 344.
Why did you not come before, you angel?
She fell on her knees before Alyasha.
I've been waiting all my life for someone like you.
I knew that someone like you would come and forgive me.
I believe that nasty as I am, someone would really love me, not only with a lustful love.
That is not with Eros, but with Agape.
That's what she was waiting for.
That's what she got.
Now, it looks like, what has Alyasha done?
Well, if it's true that her only alternatives in going back to the pole were destructive ones, namely like a dog or with a knife, he's offered her, and that was because she was so humiliated and felt that she was so despicable, by giving her a sense of her own worth and value and looking at her with interest and treating her with respect and love, Alyasha's created a new possibility for her, which is not destructive.
He gives her a new, his love transforms her perception of her situation.
Nothing happens that's against the law of physics and chemistry, but nonetheless, he manages to change the world and save Grushenka.
Now, you might think, you might think, yeah, okay, that's right, that's what happened.
But that's not what Dostoevsky wants you to think.
Dostoevsky is about to hit you over the head with the question, suppose I had asked you at the beginning of the lecture, as I meant to do it for God, what's the miracle?
We've seen that you need miracles in order to have faith.
Alyasha demonstrates that.
Even somebody who's loving and having his faith as much as Alyasha and everything supporting him goes and almost loses his faith because there's no miracle.
That's the first thesis in the Grand Inquisitor.
Therefore, we have to have miracles.
But they better not be against the laws of physics and chemistry.
Well, what is a miracle then?
What's the miracle?
Well, the miracle, I don't really expect you to know, neither does Dostoevsky because he has to hit you over the head with it in a minute.
Well, the miracle is to create a new possibility and a new situation just out of love, which changes the world for somebody so that they can do something positive instead of something negative, that they can, and he just did this.
He just transformed Grushenka from humiliated and despised to having enough self-respect that it looks like she can, and it turns out she can go back to the pole and neither like a dog nor with a knife, but just to see whether she wants to ignore him, tell him how bad he treated her, marry him, who knows?
And why would one want to say that that's a miracle?
That seems a bit maybe much.
But here it goes on 345.
You could make your point best, remember, if you put your opinion in the mouth of your enemy, Dostoevsky thinks.
So who says, so Rakitin says, two-thirds of the way down.
Well, so you saved the sinner, he laughed spitefully.
Have you turned the Madeline into the true path?
Driven out the seven devils, eh?
So you see the miracles you were looking for just now have come to pass.
So there he is, saying it clearly that this is what Dostoevsky thinks an existentialized miracle is.
And it's great that he puts it in the mouth of the devil.
And then he says a little more, sort of funny at the bottom, damnation take you all, he cried suddenly, why the devil did I take you up to Grushenka?
I don't want to see you anymore, and so forth.
And he runs off.
Every once in a while, Alyasha drives off the devil, sometimes in more wonderful ways than this one.
Keep your eyes open.
And Rakitin is always being driven out.
The devil is being driven out by the angel here, existentially.
That happens every once in a while.
And now comes, but that's not enough.
I mean, maybe this is just an accident.
Maybe I'm making too much of a fuss about this being the miracle that the Grand Inquisitor, of the wrong, that the Grand Inquisitor has the wrong kind of miracle, that this is the right kind.
So Dostoevsky's going to hammer this one home.
So what happens next?
Well, the effect is reciprocal.
Not only does Alyasha transform Grushenka, but Grushenka restores Alyasha's faith, and he goes back to the monastery.
And something new and important happens.
Because we still have to ask the following important question.
Dostoevsky is so logical.
He never loses his trap.
We've only done half the job.
There's been a miracle.
But is it Zosima's miracle?
I mean, the question is, he needs a miracle to confirm his faith in Zosima.
He got a miracle with Grushenka.
But what's that got to do with Zosima?
Well, we'll find out.
Turns out that the miracle is traceable to Zosima.
And again, it's Rakitin who says it in a very funny way at the top of 342.
You are so primed up with your elders' teaching last night, and now that you've let it off on me, Alyasha, man of God, said Rakitin, smiling with hatred.
That is, he is loaded up with Zosima's love.
And now that Zosima is not the object of, that is, he's loaded up with the love that was generated by Zosima in him.
But now Zosima is gone.
And this love is free to go out to other people, as it starts out with Grushenka.
So he's loaded up on love by this unconditional commitment to Zosima.
That's the sense in which Dostoevsky agrees with Kierkegaard.
But once you've got this unconditional commitment, you've got to get beyond it to and not have all your love just going to one person.
You've got to take that love and make it available to and turn it on to the person, anybody in the vicinity who needs it.
That's how it happens.
So now it turns out that it was Zosima's love that created this miracle at second hand through Alyasha.
And again, of course, without any abrogation of the laws of nature.
So the saintliness of Zosima is now confirmed.
And so Alyasha can now love Zosima and love everybody else too.
But even then, Dostoevsky thinks you might miss it.
So we're going to get more.
I mean, he's going to rub it in that this is his version of miracles.
I think it's a nice thing he's doing it because it really is such a neat move.
On 347, he goes back to the monastery, and lo and behold, by an amazing coincidence, he walks in just as Father Pius is reading from the Bible about the first miracle at the bottom of 346.
And it turns out, and the third day there was a marriage in Canaan of Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there, and both Jesus was called and his disciples.
Marriage, what's that?
Floated through Alyasha's mind.
There is happiness for her too.
She's gone to the feast.
No, she's not taken the knife and so forth.
He's reviewing that Grushenka can now go back with self-respect.
And then he says a little about a third of the way down, I love that passage.
It's Canaan of Galilee, the first miracle.
Ah, that miracle, sweet miracle, and so forth.
And the miracle was that there was not enough, I believe, that wasn't that there was the time when there was not enough fish.
And Jesus, wine, not fish, only wine, no fish.
Okay, sorry about that.
Anyway, so he's making wine, and they made enough for everybody.
Are you sure there's no fish?
Because I read it The New Yorker, which is so accurate, had a funny story, which I thought was, I believed, and it's the story about, they had this story when the passion movie of what's the name of the guy who made it?
Mel Gibson was out.
And they had this diary of a girl who had a crush on Jesus at that time.
And it's a big old, crazy thing.
But in one place, she said, and he did the following marvelous miracle.
He was at the wedding and there wasn't enough fish, and he invented canopies.
You know what?
Those are little things with little bits of fish in them.
This wonderful, demagicalizing of the miracle in the craziest way.
So I believe there was fish.
And that'll teach me to believe what I read in the New Yorker.
Okay.
Anyway, so Father Pisces is reading about the miracle.
And it's traced back to Zosima.
And now he has a vision, which I can't fully explain why it's important.
Everything's happening at once.
In this vision, the elder took Alyasha by the hand, this is the middle of 348, and raised him from his knees.
And that's important, believe it or not.
It's important because he touched him.
I'm worried about this.
You'll see that there's going to be a demagicalized apostolic succession where bishops are created by the previous bishop laying his hand on that bishop.
It started with Jesus, I take it, laying his hand on Peter.
And I worried about this for reasons I can't fully explain.
Zosima had to lay his hands on Alyasha.
That's just something that has to happen.
It's like in Star Trek.
There's the time when Spock has to touch somebody to pass on his special spiritual thing to that person.
That kind of thing is happening in here.
But I can't tell you yet.
This is related to the unseen finger, believe it or not.
This is all kinds of weird stuff is happening in the background, which if you keep reading, you'll be able to figure out.
So he touches him, and then he says, Why do I need this?
448?
I know what's wrong there.
So look at 348 now, below the middle there, the end of the next paragraph.
And many of you have been given an onion.
Now, I can't explain to you about the onion yet, so just get to the last sentence.
Begin your work, dear one.
Begin it, gentlemen.
That is, begin your work of doing good things outside the monastery.
Do you see our son?
Do you see him?
Well, I've got to stop with that, because in a peculiar way, that's not a good idea for the Zosima to bring Jesus in, because Jesus has to be existentialized.
He's not just the sun with a capital S and a capital H.
We have to get a Jesus in the book.
We're going to get that next time.
But it's not sun in the Russian, interestingly enough.
And in another translation, it gets translated sun, S-U-N.
And would you believe, it seems incredible, that there could be a word in Russian that could either be translated sun and then mean Jesus, or S-U-N and then mean something like the Supreme Being.
And the answer is yes, there is.
It's a Russian word, I was told, that means something like the light of my life.
So Zosima is saying, do you see the light of my life?
And you can either hear that, as Zosima having a vision of Jesus, or you can hear it, I think, the way Dostoevsky wants to hear it, which is that there is something, which is a light in terms of which you see everything.
I have to try, this sounds very weird.
So think of it this way.
Just as in Kierkegaard, God was this field in which people lived, this atmosphere in which all things were possible if you were a Christian and believed that faith.
Dostoevsky believes there's a field of light in which everything lights up a certain way.
And that God is that field.
And you can say that when you see everything in God's light, you see it in a certain way.
And we're going to get there any minute.
We have time just to do it.
I can't say more about it.
Well, I will in an instant.
What would this look like, this story, that God is a field of something or other, which is what you can experience, and then you experience everything else in terms of that field?
Well, Dostoevsky's about to tell you.
Now he's going to existentialize God.
He's getting more and more out of control.
But this is the ultimate move.
And he's got his own story about God, and there's not going to be a supreme being in it, just as in Kierkegaard, there isn't a supreme being in it.
But it's so different from Kierkegaard.
So right in the middle of the book, Dostoevsky is going to do this.
He's going to show you, Alyasha is going to experience God, insofar as there is such something or other.
And so now let's sort of set the scene.
It's so moving, and I hope you all got here.
It is so beautiful.
So in the middle of the book, after he does the miracle, and after he sees that it was Osima's miracle, and after he sees that it's existentialized, Jesus' early first miracle, all of a sudden, he runs out of the monastery.
And so on 349, he runs out.
He didn't stop on the steps either, but went quickly down, his soul overflowing with rapture, yearning for freedom, space, and openness.
Now, by the way, if you think of this as a movie, it's a huge tour de force.
Everything has been, if you sort of think about it, up close, inside, sort of black and white, and everybody in everybody's face, always confessing and yelling and having outbursts of every sort and so forth.
All of a sudden, it's like it turns to cinema scope and color, and nature, which you never see in Dostoevsky, or hardly ever.
All of this.
I'm amazed that he can write this.
The vault of heaven, full of soft shining stars, stretched vast and fathomless above him.
The Milky Way ran in two pale streams from zenith to the horizon.
Let's skip a little, the white towers and golden domes, see color of the church gleamed out against the sapphire sky.
Autumn flowers in the garden were slumbering.
The silence of the earth, instead of everybody screaming at everybody, suddenly there's nothing on the soundtrack.
The silence of the earth seemed to melt into the silence of the heaven.
The mystery of the earth was one with the mystery of the stars.
Alyasha stood and gazed and suddenly threw himself on the earth.
He didn't know why he embraced it, but he could not have told why he longed irresistibly to kiss it and kiss it weeping and watering with his tears and vowed passionately to love it, to love it forever and ever.
That's something Zosima told him to do.
Now comes the field of love.
Why was he weeping?
Oh, in his rapture, he was weeping over those stars that were shining to him from the abyss of space, and he was not ashamed of that ecstasy.
Another quote from Zosima.
None more plagiarism.
There seemed to be threads from all those innumerable worlds of God linking his soul to them, and his soul was trembling all over in contact with other worlds.
And he longed to forgive everyone for everything and to beg forgiveness and so forth.
Now, that's the God is the field of connectedness.
That everything is, I'll quote you a quote in a minute from Zosima.
Everything is like an ocean, all interrelated, and everything touches everything.
So I have to find that.
So just let me review, no mention of God in that passage.
God is the experience that everything is linked to everything, the field in which all things are related.
Just as the sun is the field in which all things appear to one another.
Plato talks about the sun that way.
But the interesting thing is, Plato, when he talks about the sun as the field in which everything shows up and is intelligible, also talks about the sun as this supreme being-like something, which makes all of this field of light possible.
Dostoevsky's pulling an amazingly interesting move.
He's going to get rid of the sun and keep the light.
Because that's what he wants.
He wants this field.
He doesn't want this object.
In fact, if you start bringing in God as a supreme being, you get that you should be loving God instead of all these other creatures in the field.
In fact, that's what happens with Augustine.
Augustine takes over from Plato this totally fulfilling supreme being.
And then Augustine's love is all directed toward the supreme being, and he hasn't any love left over for particular people anymore, like he had for his friend early on that I mentioned.
And the same thing happens with Dante.
Dante loved Beatrice, but when he finally gets a vision of God, he just drops Beatrice, because after all, what could be more fulfilling than a direct vision of God?
That's a long way to go, Dostoevsky thinks.
I may have mentioned this.
I was delighted to learn from some student one day that Augustine is not considered a saint by the Orthodox fur.
I don't know any more about that, but I think that's brilliant on their part.
And I would like to hear, I'd like to hear more.
That's the beginning, Augustine, of Plato and philosophy sort of leaking into the early Christian church, and nothing to be proud of.
So Dostoevsky's got to keep the light and get rid of the sun.
That's his job.
And now we're going to find out about that.
First, it's about, let's first do it in terms of an ocean of love, and then I'll tell you about the light.
On 3:10, Zosimus is talking, and he says, in the first full paragraph, My brother asked the birds to forgive him.
That sounds senseless, but it was right.
For all is like an ocean.
All is flowing and blending.
See, all interconnected.
A touch in one place sets up a movement at the other end of the earth, like a butterfly and wherever it is sets up a storm in some place else in the latest chaotic attractor theory.
So he has this view, how everything is interconnected.
And it goes skipping a little.
It's like an ocean, I tell you.
And that's enough for the time being.
Never mind the birds.
We'll get to the birds next time.
So let's see now.
We got the threads to other worlds, which I'm sure we are.
Okay, now we get to the light.
Way back once upon a time, I told you that it was strange that when Alyasha was being existentially baptized by his mother holding up to the icon, him holding up to the icon, that it was strange that he remembered the slanting rays of the sun more than he remembered the icon.
That's because the slanting rays are the connectedness.
And he's getting a sense of the connectedness of everything.
That's what he's getting.
Now, if it only happened once with Alyasha, you wouldn't know what to think.
But look on 280.
This is how Zosima happened to go into the monastery, his first experience of the monastery, about in the last paragraph.
It was a fine day, this 280, and I remember today as though I saw it now, how the incense rose from the censer and floated upwards and overhead in the cupola, mingled in the rising waves with the sunlight that streamed in at the little window.
Well, you don't see the sun again.
You see the rays of the sun in the smoke of the incense.
But even that, I mean, that's too far-fetched.
I mean, if I had to base my case just on that, I wouldn't be happy.
But there's a further move.
So on the next page, he says about 15 lines down.
I bless the rising sun each day and as before, my heart seems to meet you.
But now I love even more its setting and the long slanting rays and the soft gentle memories that come with them and so forth.
So Alyasha, when he's baptized, experiences the slanting rays.
And again, it's the slanting rays that bring him to the monastery.
I read that earlier, that Zosima also was brought in by the slanting rays.
You don't have to make a big deal of it.
And I'm not even sure Dostoevsky knows that he's doing it, but he is doing what he should be doing.
He's sort of downgrading the dazzling experience of the sun and giving you the connection, giving you an experience of the field of threads connecting everything to everything.
And now I want to say something about these worlds.
Time is running out, but I think I can just finish.
What are all these worlds that are connected to each other that he experiences when he falls on the earth?
Well, I worried a long time about that.
I mean, it certainly isn't.
Who's the guy who believes that there are millions of other stars and life must be on some of them?
Can't think of his.
What?
No, not Drake.
No, this guy, he's died now.
He had a television program on it.
Huh?
Yes.
Who?
You said it, somebody.
Yes, Carl Sagan.
I mean, it's not Carl Sagan that there are millions of galaxies and millions of inhabited worlds.
What is it then?
Well, it's that whenever two people are gathered together, there is a world of living love.
I think those are all the worlds.
At the bottom of 311, if you, I've read it once, if two of you are gathered together, then there's a whole world, a world of living love, embrace each other, and so forth.
And all these worlds are interconnected.
And I think that's the world threads.
I don't think that's something important, but I just was curious to what it was.
Now let me skim and then because I'll sum up.
So the sun is too platonic.
It takes the love out of the world.
What you want is the love in the world and between the worlds.
And that's the vision that Alyasha has.
And that's the field of love.
That's the light in which you see everything.
Ah, yes, eternity.
Well, on 409, one, I told you so many things happen in this that you can hardly keep your width.
So now Dostoevsky is going to existentialize eternity.
And he's going to do it just the way Kierkegaard did it.
He's going to turn some kind of mathematical eternity that's outside of time into a forever kind of eternity.
That is something that's so meaningful in your life that you can never forget it.
And that, and it will sort of be something, wow.
Don't get it.
I'm doing it again.
I can't find it.
Show me back to the...
Ah, here we are.
At the bottom of 349.
I wrote 249.
At the bottom of 349, you get the forever experience.
Remember, it's very important to Kierkegaard, and you'll turn out to be very important to Dostoevsky.
Already you saw it with childhood memories, that there have to be experiences that you never forget and that give and whose meaning never changes, but on whose meaning you can interpret everything else.
And that's like this experience in the middle of the book.
So we're going to read this at the very bottom of 349.
And with every instant, he felt clearly, as it were, tangibly, that something firm and unshakable as that vault of heaven had entered into his soul.
It was as though some idea, I think that's a bad word there, but I think it is in the Russian.
Some, I don't know, some notion had seized the sovereignty of his mind.
And it was for all his life and forever and ever.
So, there, the forever and ever is he's had an eternity in time experience, and that's that's the forever.
And now, one last remark, and you will get everything that you can get.
And I think it's sort of mind-boggling that he's got all this in here, but this is almost like a joke at the top of 350.
Someone visited my soul in that hour, he used to say afterwards, with implicit faith.
Now, you just saw everything that happened.
Did anybody visit his soul?
Did we see Christ come and do something or fell up or God the Father or anything?
Whatever he's talking about, we don't know who visited his soul.
It's something that Dostoevsky now has to give you an existentialized account of.
But the someone who visited his soul, I'll just let you know, is, as you might guess, the same mysterious finger wielder that pointed Zosima into the monastery.
And that someone is, and that someone is what got passed on to him when Zosima put his hand on him.
There's somebody in the background that all this love comes from.
I wonder if anybody you know, I bet some of you know who it is.
It's going to be the demythologized Jesus in this book.
And you don't know who it is?
I'm not going to tell you.
You've got to figure it out.
We'll start with it next time.
Okay.