He, that is Merzhikov, met Yvonne with a slow, silent gaze and was apparently not at all surprised at his coming.
There was a great change in his face.
He was much thinner and more sallow.
His eyes were sunken.
There were blue marks on him.
He's back thick and wasting away again because he's feeling repudiated.
He's very ill, it turns out.
And what Martha says about him on 587 is he's not himself.
That's the middle of 587.
Merzhikov was very ill.
It's not that he's laid up, but he doesn't seem himself.
Well, that's sort of one of those Dostoevsky little tricks.
Remember, and it's important for you to remember, that he hasn't got a self.
That the self means the two factors, both a dark side and a light side, or an earthy side and a heavenly side.
He's got no self at all.
And that's what, remember Gregory says that to him.
That was his negative childhood memory.
You are not a human being.
You grew from the mold in the bathhouse.
That's all sort of, you're being reminded of that, that he doesn't seem himself.
But that's not important yet.
Let's just sort of put on hold.
He's lost his ability to live.
He's lost his ability to act.
Since he has no self, and he gets all of what motives he has from Ivan, and now he hates Yvonne, since Yvonne has not congratulated him, but repudiated him, his deed.
So that's the situation.
And Yvonne...
really doesn't know.
I think it's, again, again, so murky.
Yvonne suspects that Smershakov did it.
But he knows that Dmitry didn't do it.
But it's really not absolutely who did it until this minute.
And then finally, Smershakov just announces that he did it, and that settles then.
And he says he did it because Yvonne wanted him to.
And that's on page 589.
Finally, it all gets sorted out.
The middle of 589.
You are the murderer?
He says to, sorry, this is Smershikov talking to Yvonne.
You murdered him.
You are the murderer.
I was only your instrument, your faithful servant.
It was following your words that I did it.
That's the sort of, you hired me as a hitman line.
That's how Smershikov understands it.
Did it?
Did you murder him?
That's the first time Yvonne has fully realized it.
Up to now, he's just dimly thought about it.
He thought about it enough to want to kill Smerzhikov, but still.
Did you murder him?
Yvonne turned cold.
Something seemed to give way in his brain, and he shuddered all over.
Noticed, and another translation says with a cold shiver, all that is the coldness that you associated with the devil and with the people who betray and kill people close to them.
Smerzhikov looked at him wonderingly.
The genuineness of Ivan's horror struck him.
You don't mean to say you really didn't know, Smerzhikov faltered mistrustfully, looking with a forced smile into Ivan's eyes.
Ivan gazed at him, unable to speak.
And here's the evidence about why the peasant song upset him so much.
Ach Vanka's gone to Petersburg.
I won't wait till he comes back, suddenly echoed in his head.
Yes, that's right.
That line now means what it meant to Yvonne all along, that Vanka, that means Ivan, that's his nickname, has gone off to Moscow, Petersburg, it doesn't matter.
And Smershikov isn't going to wait till he comes back.
He's going to kill Fedor right away.
Because, this is the crucial thing, he thought Ivan wanted him to do it.
He has no motives of his own.
In the middle of 290.
Did you really not know till now, Smerzhikov asked once more?
No, I did not know.
I kept thinking of Dmitri, Dmitri.
He clutched his head in both hands.
Listen, did you kill him alone, with my brother's help or without?
It was only with you, your help, I killed him.
Dmitry is innocent.
All right, all right, talking about it later.
Why do I keep trembling?
You were bold enough, this is Smershikov, then you said, everything is lawful, and how frightened you are now, Smerzikov muttered in surprise.
And that's how Ivonne caused it.
In effect, he said to Smershikov, murder is okay.
Because this is Ivonne's view, God is dead, and all things are possible.
And since Smerzekhikov gets all his belief from Yvailable, he then just gets the belief that murder is okay.
So that's the sense in which he not only wanted him to do it, but gave him, so to speak, the license to do it.
And then, let me see, I just want to get to the crucial line.
So Ivan's the real murderer.
It's first degree murder.
And at least so it seems.
Again, he's repeating it, Smerchikov on 292, about two-thirds down.
No, he didn't kill him, that is Dmitry.
But I don't want to lie to you, because if you really haven't understood and are not pretending so as to throw your guilt on me, you are still responsible for it all.
Since you suspected murder and wanted me to do it and went away knowing all about it, so I want to prove to you that you were the real, the only real murderer.
I'm not the murderer, though I did kill him.
You were the real murderer.
So Yvonne is cracking up.
Why?
Why am I the murderer?
Oh, God, cried Yvonne, unable to restrain himself, and so forth and so forth.
Now, that does it.
I mean, Yvonne, we now understand.
He understands.
But there's now a new murky element that's fascinating.
In the middle of 593, and I, since you've been very good at getting the last one.
Let's see if you can help with this one.
The very middle.
Was I so eager then?
Was I, Yvonne cried.
To be sure you were.
This was the crucial part.
By your consent, you silently sanctioned my doing it.
Smershikov looked steadily at Yvonne.
He was very weak, you know, totally unplugged, and spoke slowly and warily, that some inner force urged him on.
He evidently had some design.
Ivan felt that.
Now, I don't know if any of you know yet.
You have to read it more than once, what design Smershikov had.
Do you know what Smerchikov is up to?
Why does he have any design?
He has lost all of his will to live and all of his motives by getting disconnected.
Well, that's very subtle.
So we won't, and I'm not ready quite to give us, to make the problem as clear as it has to be.
It takes a while.
So let's see where we are.
I just wrote again here, but it's worth reading again.
In a certain way, Yvonne did hire Smershikov to do it.
And in another sense, he didn't.
He would never commit a murder, horrified by it.
So Alyasha's right.
Ivan's not the kind of person who would kill old Karamatsov, and he hasn't killed old Karamatsov.
But Smershikov is right, too.
It's exactly the way Ivan behaved with Smershikov that is solely responsible in the finalist responsibility.
Everybody's got some responsibility, but the most responsibility is that Ivonne gave to Smershikov the permission to do it and made it clear that he wanted him to do it.
So the moral is that we're responsible not only for a lot more good than we normally realize, but we're responsible for causing a lot more evil than we normally realize.
That's the theme that comes up every once in a while and coming up again now.
And now comes the next strange event.
This is the one that you now need to explain.
So Smershikov gets weaker and weaker.
And he has some design.
He's lost his will to live, and he won't live for long.
And yet, and this is the peculiar part, he commits suicide.
That's the puzzle.
Why doesn't he just waste away?
Or that is, in the possessed, which probably none of you have read, the main character who is also very evil and has no real motivations of his own, dies of kind of lack of the energy to do anything, really sort of wastes away.
And if Smershikov would have just waited a little while, he surely would have died, unplugged from Yvonne.
But he doesn't wait a little while.
He goes in and commits what critics have thought is an act of guilt and repentance.
Now, surely that's wrong.
But Dostoevsky is playing this strange game with people.
It's as if he wants to mislead the stupid critics because he's got this book lying on the table at the bottom of 590 that he that Smershikov's been reading the sayings of the Holy Father Isaac the Syrian.
And the money is hidden under there.
But why is he reading it?
Well, I'm not sure I know, but if you go back and look at the writings of Ivan Theory, and which I did, is it Ivan?
Is that his name?
What's his first name?
Now I forgot.
Isaac, yeah, that didn't sound right.
Isaac the Syrian.
You discover that he's a father of Pharaoh.
He is very gloomy, and he thinks that the best thing people can do is live alone in the desert and eat roots and be silent and so forth.
So presumably, Smershikov is reading it because it's blooming, not because he's become suddenly converted to some dark form of Christianity.
But it just makes it harder for the critics who don't understand the suicide.
But then you can see why people would be tempted to say that Smershikov must feel guilty and see that he, in a sense, had misunderstood Ivan and was really he that was responsible.
This is the story the critics tell themselves, and therefore he's punishing himself and hung himself, and this is all nonsense.
But then you need a right answer.
Why did he hang himself?
And why did he leave this note, which is very interesting in what it doesn't say?
Where do we have to find the note?
619, maybe?
Well, 619 is important, but it's not what I want.
593.
We've got to find the suicide.
If anybody finds it, just yeah.
Where do we hear about it?
At the trial?
I'm completely puzzled.
Well, who knows?
Nobody's going to hear it.
I've got it written down.
Well, let's put it aside for a minute.
It'll probably show up.
Anyway, Smerzhikov does leave a suicide note saying nothing, saying in effect, I just killed myself and I'm not putting the blame on anyone.
And as one of the prosecutors says, if he was feeling guilty for the murder and wanted to assume responsibility for the murder, then he certainly would have said so.
He would have said, I did it, and I feel bad about it, and I'm killing myself.
And he didn't.
So we just have to keep open what's going on.
And I think you can see on 619, Alyasha understands what's going on.
Well, do you understand what's going on?
Well, why?
What's this strange design that Smerzhikov had that is carried out, presumably, by him killing himself?
And why is this?
Yeah.
Save him.
Einstein's service.
Einstein's top.
It's the time.
Ah, you got the right facts, but you got the wrong conclusion.
If Smerzhikov kills himself, no one will believe Yvonne's claim that he's guilty, that he put Smerzhikov up to it, that Smerzhikov really did it.
There'll be no evidence, right?
You're absolutely right.
And Yvonne can't be sent to Siberia, even if he confesses, right.
This is what Alyasha says, and you're on the right track, that you got it switched off at one point.
The middle of 619, Alyasha says in his prayer, yes, if Smerzhikov was dead, no one will believe Yvonne's evidence.
Now, assuming that Smerzhikov wants to hurt Yvonne, because he really hates Yvonne now, and we'll see that go back to the third interview.
Yvonne is now the god that fails, so to speak.
He's the center of Merzhikov's life, and he won't play that role.
So take my word for it.
If he hates Yvonne, why would it be a good thing to do just what you thought?
Make it impossible for Yvonne to confess and go to prison?
That's good.
That's half of it.
I think that's right.
And if you can spin it another way, too, which I'm not against that.
Yes, I think it's right that Yvonne wants to be approved of and to confess it and show that he's better than everybody, and that he admits he wants to kill his father, and he admits he did it, and now nobody was going to believe him.
And but the other half of the story is, think of how Yvonne will heal the rest of his life if Dimitri is in Siberia for having committed a crime that now Yvonne feels he's the one who did it.
And so Smershikov is putting him in this amazingly awful position by killing himself.
That seems to be the strange design.
Unless anybody's got a better idea, I go with that one.
Yeah.
The mysterious visitor, like he's connecting it, right.
That's right, it's like being in the hell of isolation.
Of course, the mysterious visitor, nobody believed him either.
It's rather complicated.
But he had really become a good man so that though they didn't believe that he'd committed the murder, because they thought he was such a good person all along, that at least he could now relate to them in a way that was honest from his side and not wrong from their side.
So bringing in the mysterious visitor probably doesn't help much, but go ahead.
Yeah.
That's good.
That that's very good.
That's right.
So yeah, there are two levels to what you said.
One level is, yeah, Dimitri is already, sorry, Yvonne is already an example of the bad kind of crucifixion, the laceration kind, the kind that sort of wallows in its own suffering out of pride.
But now, if Smerzhikov kills himself, then Yvonne is sort of stuck in that kind of suffering forever.
He can't confess and become like the mysterious, get people to forgive him and be willing to take on and so forth.
He's just, well, yeah, he's stuck in this wrong kind of confession, which can't, I'm just trying to say it as best I can, can't lead to expiation and thereby joy and reconciliation, because he could only expiate the crime if people believed he committed it and sent him to Siberia, which they don't, and won't, and didn't.
So Dmitri got, so Smerzhikov got what he wanted by committing suicide and leaving this note.
He could have also not committed suicide, it just occurs to me.
He could have just kept quiet and not said anything.
So it's a combination of committing suicide and as the most sort of efficient way of not being bothered and not saying anything, in any way, not having any reason to go on living, and at the same time putting Ivan into a sort of hell, a hell of isolation, in which he is guilty of a crime and can't relate to anybody because nobody believed him.
You want to say something about it.
Then you should want to say something.
Yeah.
Oh, the suicide note, thank you, is on 372.
Let me write that down.
So next time I do this, I won't be stuck there.
Right now, two what is it again?
672?
672.
Okay, it says, it says, yeah, there it is, this sort of minimal note here, 72, where he says, I destroy myself of my own will and inclination so as to throw no blame on anybody.
And then the prosecutor says what I think is important to say, what would it have cost him to add, I am the murderer, not Dmitri Karamatsov.
But that did not add.
And so the idea is nobody could believe that Smershikov was the killer.
Yeah.
Well, that's interesting.
Let's stop with what she's saying for a minute before we go to you, because she's raising, I mean, what in the world motivates Smershikov to do it since he has no motivations outside of Yvonne?
I had this, I don't think that, I don't know the answer to that really.
And maybe just a kind of glitch in the book.
But if there's any kind of answer, it's something like he's motivated simply by the negative kind of motivation that he's disconnected from Yvonne and he wants to revenge that.
That's not a new motivation, you know, not a positive motivation.
You all have things to say about that.
Okay, before the first hand I saw was over here somewhere.
Well, I guess you have next.
I could put you on hold.
Go ahead.
You're right.
There's this funny parallel.
You're not drawing any sort of existential conclusions.
No, neither am I.
Good.
It's just a kind of funny symmetry.
Got you.
Before you, somebody else had a hand up over here, which I have now lost.
Who who uh yeah, go ahead.
But now I'll explain to the problem.
That's right.
That's good.
Well, oh, well, I see, but I don't agree, I think, quite.
I mean, he does try to get Yvonne to kill him, and he doesn't, won't.
We'll read about that in a minute.
But it he doesn't have to kill himself.
He'll just go, he'll die anyway.
He's he's not himself, he's sick, he's weak and falling apart.
And the the idea that he does kill himself is some strange design, remember?
And so we're given that hint that he's got some, he's really upset with Yvonne, and he's so upset with Yvonne that he's got some weird plan.
I read you that sentence.
And that seems to be something more than just inevitable suicide.
Paul doesn't have a self.
How is it that you are?
Well, he doesn't have much emotions, does he?
I mean, he's he's except this emotion, I guess it's a funny emotion, of as she says, he's a parasite, he's been disconnected from the host.
He's got this kind of desperate attempt, first attempt to hold on to Yvonne and then desperate anger at Yvonne.
Why does he have that?
Well, when you say he doesn't have a self, it doesn't mean that he doesn't have consciousness and maybe even emotions of sorts.
He just doesn't have a dark side and a bright side, and that's sure.
I mean, the main emotions he has are nasty emotions like putting pins in the dogs and killing the cats and so forth.
But those are, whatever they are, they're not human emotions, I think the argument is supposed to be, yeah.
And I think, wait, I think I did this in the wrong order, and I don't mind, because but I think before we discuss it, we should look at a few passages in the third interview, which I jumped over because I got because I got off on that why does what is the strange design.
And so let's go back to 593.
Let me get just get back to where I want to be.
Not there.
593.
Okay, that's the strange design.
So now here we go.
All of this now has got to do for a little while with how does Smerzhikov relate to Yvonne after this has all become clear.
And that starts on 597.
And the first thing is this evidence that without Yvonne, Smerzhikov has no desires of importance.
Because Smerzhikov lifted the book off the notes, the bank notes, and laid them to the side.
Take that money with you, Smerzikov.
Of course I'll take it.
Why do you give it to me if you committed the murder for the sake of it?
Yvonne looked at him with great surprise.
I don't want it, Smerzhikov said in a shaking voice.
I did have an idea of beginning a new life with that money in Moscow, or better still abroad.
I did dream of it, chiefly because all things are lawful.
So now Smerzhikov has lost that motive because that was if the crime was not really a crime.
And so taking the money was something Yvonne approved of and wanted him to do and murder and so forth.
Then he had, again, a kind of parasitical desire, because Yvonne says way early on in the book, I want to go to Europe and so forth.
So he wants to go to Europe and live abroad.
And then now comes this funny conversation.
Let me read more.
That was right what you taught me, or you talked a lot to me about that.
Or if there's no everlasting God, there's no such thing as virtue and there's no need of it, you were right.
But that's how I looked at it.
Did you come to that conclusion by yourself?
asked Yvonne with a smile.
With your help.
And now I suppose you believe in God since you're giving back the money.
Listen, what these critics who care about that sayings of Isaac the Syrian should notice.
No, I don't believe in God, whispered Smerzhikov.
That's why I'm getting it back.
Now, why is that?
Well, because I think Yvonne is his God.
And now Yvonne has repudiated him.
He has no reason to go.
No, no, he can't go to Europe anymore.
He doesn't want anything anymore.
Yes.
No, I don't believe in God, whispers Smerzikov.
Then why are you giving it back?
And I think the answer would be because you were my God and you repudiated me.
But he just says, stop, that's enough.
Smershikov waved his hand.
You used to say that everything is lawful, and now you're so upset.
And okay, that's the beginning of why he's so upset at Yvonne.
He's carried out Yvonne's wishes as he understood them and rightly understood them.
And now he followed Yvonne's philosophy as he understood it and rightly understood it.
So he ought to be thanked and congratulated and take the money and go off to France.
But then, and it's that Smerzhikov has lost everything, lost his God, lost his motives.
So now he wants to die by 590.
There's nothing to live for anymore.
And he says at the top of 598, well, kill me, kill me now, Smerzhikov said all at once, looking strangely at Yvonne.
You won't even dare do that, he said with a bitter smile.
You won't dare do anything, you who used to be so bold.
Okay, so that's that's his final angry thing.
So since Yvonne won't kill him, he kills us himself, but he does it so that he can get revenge on Yvonne.
I mean, that must be the strange design.
At least that's how I'm reading it.
But I'm not sure.
Then comes the suicide, where he doesn't take the blame.
He doesn't do it out of jail.
And so the idea is, I gather, to get, he's so angry at Yvonne, if angry is the right thing, I guess you can have that emotion.
He's so angry at Yvonne for having repudiated him.
You see, for giving him the motive to do it, giving him the right to do it, making it look like he will, that Igoban, who is kind of his God, will be so pleased if he does it, and then recoil.
And then Yvonne recoils in horror, says he didn't want him to do it, seems to repudiate his philosophy that all things are lawful, and leaves Smershikov nowhere.
And so that's why I said, like a God that failed.
The God that asked him to do all these things turns out not to support him and not really to want him to do all these things.
Yeah.
Well, that is a problem.
How do you deal with it?
Yeah.
Yeah, let's see.
It's right here somewhere.
But anyway, that's right.
Oh, no, I did it for violence.
I've got nobody to blame but myself.
Yeah.
The only problem with that is that it doesn't explain the strange design that he seems to have.
And it doesn't fit with Alyasha's prayer that says now this Mezhikov has killed himself.
No one will believe Yvonne.
So I mean, I stick to my reading, though I'm open to things like what you just said.
Some ingenious better reading may still be lurking around the corner.
Yeah.
When you reach 30.
And he's, but I don't know if Mezhikov knows it.
And again, remember, you guys are coming up with ingenious things, but there is the phrase that he's got some strange design, and it isn't a design to imitate.
Well, it could be, imitate Yvonne, what Yvonne is going to do at 30, only do it early.
How old are they now?
About 24 or something, I think.
I'm not convinced.
Yeah.
It wasn't that I didn't understand you, I couldn't hear you.
Talk louder.
I don't know.
Did you all hear her?
Yes.
Tell me, well, either you talk louder or somebody will have to repeat it.
So say it again.
Louder.
But here and there, but I can't tell you which, so say it again.
Okay, now so Smerdyakov, I say this for the pod people anyway.
Okay, okay, the justice with, you think that it's justice with no mercy, Smershikov.
Okay.
Done.
Yvonne was his God and what?
His Christ figure.
Why, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
Why, why?
You know, I'm sure.
But why just go out and sell him?
Why am I going to tell him about him?
His Savior has rejected him.
Well, now that I've heard you, I still don't believe you.
Okay.
I mean, that's just, I mean, two.
I mean, when you start putting Smershikov in the place of Jesus as, I mean, Yvonne, in the place of Jesus, as somebody who should be saving Smershikov at his way, that is the thing Smershikov is thinking.
But Yvonne is similar, but I think, I just disagree.
I think nothing could possibly save Smershikov.
One, two things.
One, he doesn't even want to be saved in this, except he's given, maybe this is what you mean, he could save him by giving him motives and keeping him attached to things by imitating Yvonne.
That's what he did for him.
And that is the sense in which he saved him.
I'm sort of getting on into what you're saying.
And so at the gate, for instance, he's saying, in effect, I'm going to do whatever you want me to do.
I have no desires of my own, but as long as you're telling me what to do, I'm happy to do it.
That's, in a sense, the way Yvonne is his savior and is saving him.
And then Yvonne stops telling him what to do.
He says, I didn't want you to do that.
I'm horrified at what you've done.
I don't, and then his savior has abandoned him, and he's upset.
But more than upset, and we're just back to that again.
He's got this plan.
Now, how he can even be feeling a need for revenge, I don't know, except by saying it's not any positive motive that, like, anything that he wants to go after, like cooking or Paris or money, or not men or women, but it might have been.
I mean, no motives at all, just the motive to get to get revenge on Yvonne for not giving him any motives.
That's peculiar, and I don't know what to do about it.
Yeah.
I'm glad he didn't even want any thought and a bit of thought, defensive, and friendly.
And by the volume, I just called it very long, I heard something else responded.
But so far, I have been this area for exciting by finding something back.
But actually, he's a good size.
He gets their thoughts, they're always outside of the turnbuckle or whatever, but also in a way holding some part of that.
Holding him apart from this circle.
Yeah, well, okay, well, you added one important, interesting element, but I don't quite know what to do with it.
But I think you're right.
It's something to think about.
It's interesting you remember that.
Yes, Gregory read that book.
That's where Smershikov got it.
And it's this dark book that Gregory read when he was in a dark mood when their child died.
And Smershikov has been reading it.
And he put the money on it.
But I don't know how to make anything more of that.
And if you do, you come and talk to me.
That's because then it bought me a huge idea.
But maybe, maybe.
I don't know.
Well, last comment.
Smerykov doesn't have a spell.
I understand about how not being able to love the sound of other things inside the earth.
Ah, that's easy.
The first one I don't know about not being able to love.
But he asks, how does he see?
Because that's the mysterious visitor stuff applied to Yvonne, and that's getting too tenuous.
But he does understand.
He's smart, Smershikov.
He understands that Yvonne believes in justice.
I'm sure he's heard Yvonne talk about that.
Maybe the story about, you know, that he has to commit suicide because the world is a place where no just individual would want to live and so forth.
At least, he wouldn't understand it, you know, in the sense of directly understanding it, believing it, but he would accept it because it's Yvonne's view, and he knows, I suppose, that it's Yvonne's view.
Remember the phrase in that discussion, Yvonne says to Alyasha, I must have justice or I'll kill myself.
Now, Smershakov could hear that and understand that, though he couldn't understand it in the sense of understanding how anybody would want to do that or care about that, because he doesn't understand how anybody would want to do anything or care about anything.
But he could see that it would make Yvonne miserable to have Dmitry in prison and Yvonne running around in the world.
I don't think we should spend longer on it.
But if you have more to say about it, come and see me in office hours or write your paper.
But I told you there are the loose ends, and that's one of the strange ones.
I think you can understand more about why I'm making such a fuss about this if I go a little further.
Let me see now.
What I want to talk about is something, one more thing we have time for today, anyway.
The very basic Dostoevsky idea that nobody can commit a crime and just feel okay about it, get away with it.
And that's notice that Yvonne, in spite of his saying, for God, all things are possible, when it actually comes down to killing his father, even in the secondhand hiring somebody else to do his way, can't stand the idea that he did it.
And those of you who read Crime and Punishment, a lot of you know that Raskolnikov, who thinks he's above ethics because he's a superior person and kills the pawnbroker, can't get away with it.
He finally has to go to prison.
And Dostoevsky would have loved a case that happened in California, or maybe, I don't know if you remember it or not.
How old were you when the guy, I don't remember his name, killed Moscone?
Any of you that buy something his name, a former policeman, you don't remember the killers?
Went to City Hall and shot the mayor?
Yes, with the Twinkie Defense.
What's the guy's name?
I don't remember.
That was White.
What White?
Dan White.
Dan White just walked into City Hall and shot the mayor, Moscone.
That's why the Moscone Center is named after him.
And got away with it.
Got a very light sentence on this crazy defense that he had eaten too many Twinkies and he wasn't in his right mind.
That's why it's called the Twinkie Defense.
And everybody was outraged, but he got off.
And two years later, he committed suicide.
Very Dostoevsky sort of thing.
Obviously, he couldn't live with himself and his neighbors and the world once he knew that he was the murderer of the cold-blooded murderer of the mayor.
So anyway, but Dostoevsky has a big general view.
And it looks, it's sort of like this.
You could put it in kind of philosophical terms.
It's a kind of proof of the existence of God.
That is, he's if, it's a kind of syllogism.
If and only if God is dead, would all things be possible, or all things be lawful.
But all things aren't lawful.
Nobody can get away with murder and not be caught in the web of connectedness and finally suffer for it or have to kill themselves, be in the hands of a living God.
So it's so the universe is so set up that you can't break the chain of connectedness with impunity and just get away with it.
And the chain of connectedness is God, remember, that whole prayer of Alyasha's that God is catching up with Yvonne, the Yvonne who thought that he could just wash his hands of everything and leave the world at 30 or leave the town and go to Moscow because he isn't involved.
That everybody is involved, and if you break the involvement, then you will suffer for it.
That's the prayer, remember, an important prayer on 619.
I'm just mentioning it, but I'll show you, remember, that God in whom Yvonne disbelieved and his truth were gaining mastery over his hard heart, he refused to submit.
That means God is the connectedness.
That's the truth.
Nobody can break the connectedness and get away with it.
That would prove that there was a God.
That would prove that there was connectedness.
If it was true, that everybody who was a human being couldn't, no one could commit the crime and get away with it.
One, the most damaging thing you could do is make a movie like Woody Allen's Crimes and Misdemeanors, which I keep talking about.
Get it on DVD and watch it.
I mean, this guy actually takes, so to speak, takes back Dostoevsky.
I'm sure that's what Woody Allen had in mind.
He commits, he hires a hitman, gets his mistress murdered, begins to feel that he has to confess, practically breaks down and goes to the police to confess, like Rostolnikov, and then decides, well, why should I confess?
Nobody knows.
And he doesn't, and he lives happily ever after.
Now, that is exactly what Dostoevsky thinks is impossible.
That would show that God is dead.
I mean, if you could do that.
And maybe you can.
I mean, I think Woody Allen has got an interesting point there.
He makes this very plausible.
I mean, it's a question of whether you can make such a life plausible.
Dan White is on Dostoevsky's side.
He commits suicide, but the guy, the hero of the leader, don't die in crimes and misdemeanors is on the other side.
Yeah, yeah.
No, I gather it's a similar story.
I've got to see Matchpoint because, yes, how many have seen that poem?
A lot of you.
Oh, I've got to connect up.
Or you want to tell me, is it just like the story I told?
Very similar.
So Dostoevsky, Woody Allen and Dostoevsky are on a head-on collision, and he's doing it twice, taking on this thing.
But it looks like that, but then, so much for that.
Now the question is, I want to come back for a minute to what we've just been talking about before.
But Dostoevsky's got a problem.
How does anybody ever commit a murder and get away with it?
How could they?
And the answer is, one answer would be that they haven't got any self.
That the only person who could commit a murder with impunity would be somebody who had no understanding of the connectedness whatsoever and was acting on somebody else's orders because he was a kind of totally parasitical on them.
In other words, Smerzhikov.
Smerzhikov, he can commit a murder.
And he doesn't have to commit suicide because he committed a murder.
He commits suicide for an entirely different reason because he's lost touch with Ivan.
But I think Dostoevsky has to set it up so that nobody commits a murder in any Dostoevsky book gets away with it.
But there are killings in Dostoevsky books, and they're always based on misunderstanding, like this one.
In the possessed, lots of people get killed because they totally misunderstand the Smerzhikov-like character who's at the center of the possessed.
And in the end, well, and that person isn't even a person, and they're a kind of vacuum.
They end up wasting away.
So anyway, this is a kind of Dostoevsky picture.
You can either believe it or not.
But I mean, it's surely something Dostoevsky believes.
So now, I just want to look at.
Okay, I've done that.
I'm just seeing where I am.
Okay, somebody, did I see a hand?
Well, we've got ten minutes.
I'm going on.
There's plenty we should talk about.
So where are we?
Oh, yeah, I owe you an explanation.
I just found it, and I needed to tell you at some point.
Now it looks like we don't know whether Yvonne is going to live or die.
Let's just do that before time is done.
I've got to find it.
Okay, so Yvonne's position is unlivable.
And where now?
I don't even know where is Yvonne at the trial.
Well, I read that art, didn't I?
Where he asked for water and he looks like he's dying.
Okay, so we've got that.
So I, oh, but I didn't cry.
Now I remember.
I said that someplace we have evidence.
You see, this is not a deep existential point.
This is just something that I promised that I would use this time to do.
The promise was that we know that Yvonne is going to live.
And that means that somehow, we don't know how, he's going to have to suffer for his crime and expiate it and get back in touch with people in spite of the fact that Smerzhikov suicide.
Maybe that connected to the mysterious visitor, it occurred to me.
They don't have to believe Yvonne, as long as Yvonne has suffered and become a good person.
So Smerjakov doesn't get away with this trick, if that's what he's pulling, that Yvonne is now stuck for the rest of his life, knowing that he's a murderer and knowing that he can't tell anybody because they won't believe him.
Somehow, somebody, probably Alegashi, gets Yvonne to suffer the right way.
All we know is the following.
That when he goes and stands on the stairs, which remember I read today because it comes back at the end of the book, as the most disgusting thing he ever did in his life, but the first time it happens, it happens.
I mean, it really happens, is on 267.
So, remembering the night long afterwards, Ivan recalled with peculiar repulsion how he had got up and gone out and listened to his father stirring round, now skipping down a third.
That action, all his life afterwards, he called infamous.
At the bottom of his heart, he thought that it was the basis action of his life.
And that's it.
So, all his life afterward, and that he understood it as base.
That action was his total detached listening to his father.
And he felt no hatred for his father, but simple curiosity to know why he was walking around down there below and what he was doing.
Now, once you know that later, you know that he, Yvonne, also knew that thanks to Smerzyakov and Dmitry, as he thought about it then, this was his last night, because Ivan was just on his way to Moscow.
Smeryakov was going to sham a pit.
Dmitry was going to kill him.
So Ivan was listening like a detached spectator, like an eyewitness, outside the world to old Karamatsov, completely indifferent to whether he's going to be killed or not.
And that is the worst thing he ever did.
And somehow or other, he suffers for it.
I don't know how, because all his life long, though he had a long life, presumably, he remembers it, rightly he remembers it, as the most disgusting thing he ever did.
Namely, why?
Not accept the connectedness.
He's just related to old Taramatsov, like a curious bystander related to an interesting incident, and that's what he has to suffer for and realize you can't do that.
You've got to accept the connection.
Okay, now maybe I should stop.
I have to look and see if we should go on to the next.
Yeah, it's okay.
What we've got for next time, and you should definitely read it because it's just terribly important.
Now, now it's not important anymore for who did it, but it's absolutely crucial for every important question that's left open.
Let me just tell you that, and then you can go.
Remember that there are several unopened questions, unanswered questions.
We don't understand what it is to found a church.
The whole issue of community left over from the Grand Inquisitor is still open.
We don't know whether the church should be one individual in isolation or a universal ante, and neither one sounds right.
Well, is there a way to existentialize the church?
I'm going to tell you the question you should have in mind when you read the last chapter before the afterlog, the part about Alicia's, what happens at Alicia's stone, on page start on 722.
Here are the questions you need to keep in mind: What is the church?
Is there such a thing as immortality and eternity?
What's the true meaning of being a Taramatsov?
And how does the third stage of Christianity send Markle's love out into the world so that the star will rise in the East?
In one little chapter, Gostevsky is going to answer all those questions.
Try to read it with those questions in mind so we can work on it together next time.
So I can ask you what it's like.
Well, I just thought I.