So here we are, where we have the question, whether anybody entered Alyasha's soul at the moment when he had his big mystical experience.
He says that somebody did.
And if it were somebody, it would be Jesus, presumably.
But obviously something's going on that we don't understand, something that's being existentialized.
This mysterious finger that points the way both for Joshua to go into the monastery and then points the way for Alyasha to go into the monastery.
What is this mysterious finger?
And I asked you last time, does anybody know?
And nobody knew.
Does anybody know now?
He's in the background, so to speak, running this whole show, who would be the demythologized Christ figure in the book who directs the lives of Zasma?
And what's the other thing?
You don't know yet.
Oh, Koskovsky's really fooled you.
That's good.
But, and you can't, and he hits you over the head with it, but you don't see it.
That's typical.
I didn't see it for years.
But somewhere smuggled in is the story of the demythologized or de- or the existentialized Jesus and smuggled in at the same time the proof that it is really Jesus, that he's the existentializing.
So here we go.
It turns out to be Brother Markle.
So on 275, Zosima starts talking about his brother.
And he, at the bottom of 275, I'm surprised 275, that looks like 276 to me.
I see yes all around on 275, about two-thirds of the way down.
At the dawn of my life, when I was a child, I had an elder brother who died before my eyes at 17.
Later on in the course of my life, I gradually became convinced that that brother had been for a guidance and a sign for my time.
He had he not come into my life, I could never, perhaps, though I believe that he had become a monk on this practical path.
And turns out Alyasha reminds him.
Look, similar.
That's not the important thing.
The important thing is that Zosima thinks of him as guiding.
That's a long way from understanding what he's doing.
Okay, so we have to now look in detail.
Markle is really very, very important.
One of the ways you might get a glimmer that he's important, though, it's not the existentializing, it's just plot-wise.
Alyasha reminds Zosima of him on 275, a little further down.
Alyasha has some, though not a great resemblance in face, seems to me so like him spiritually that many times I've taken him for that young man, my brother, mysteriously come back to me as a reminder and inspiration.
And I wondered at so strange a dream in itself.
Well, in a way, there is a sense in which Alyasha is his brother, come back.
We'll see.
But Markle is also like Dimitri because he gets, he's very on 276, he's sort of brutal and frank and anti-religious.
At the bottom, he's at the very bottom of 276.
My elder brother Markle, he was eight years older than I was, of irritable disposition, but kind-hearted and never ironical.
Well, that fits Dimitri.
Certainly, Yvonne's ironical.
And so this guy has got to be sort of, well, you know, sort of Dimitri-like, passionate, hot-tempered, and so forth.
And he's also like Yvonne because he gets involved with a philosopher.
And that's bad for him, but he does.
He gets very interested in philosophy.
I have to find it now.
Now, hmm.
Should be in here, but I don't seem to have it.
Well, it's right in these pages, so I'll find it.
This secular socialist philosopher comes into the town.
Where is it?
At the top.
Okay.
Yes, right where I was, but a little further down, and I didn't mark it.
He made friends about six lines down with the political exile who had been banished from Moscow to our town for free thinking and led a solitary existence there.
The man was a scholar, but gained distinction in philosophy.
Bad news, of course.
Something attracted him to Markle, and he used to come to see him.
He spent whole evenings with him and so forth.
Well, yeah, being a philosopher, there are two kinds of philosophers in the book.
Both of them equally wrong-headed, but it's important to keep them separate.
There's a place you'll see before the end of the day where Zosima talks about how much he likes philosophy.
It's so spiritual.
Well, that's Platonistic kind of philosophy.
And it's evidence that Zosima has never completely outgrown, sort of institutionalized Christianity, and that the Russian Orthodox Church didn't completely avoid getting corrupted by Plato.
But this is certainly no spiritual philosopher who's coming into town to corrupt Marko.
He's a free thinker, a kind of materialist, naturalist, atheist kind of philosophy.
And that's also a branch, a tradition in philosophy.
So either, yeah, both of them are wrong in two extremes.
They're either too heavenly, that's Plato, or they're too earthly, that's, there are lots of them.
We could say Hobbes, who's got something right about human nature, remember, that everybody's nasty and selfish, but he certainly hasn't got anything spiritual to do about it or save us from it.
So, and that's a kind of modern materialism, let's call it.
There's the sort of tradition, there's sort of ancient Greek spiritualism and modern European materialism.
Both of them are blamed on philosophy.
But Markle isn't really corrupted very long by that because he ends up having what I would call a supernatural experience.
And that's by supernatural, I definitely don't mean against the laws of physics and chemistry.
Nothing in the book happens against the laws of physics and chemistry.
But it's a supernatural experience in that it's an experience of what the world would be like and human beings would be like, which instead of being selfish in this Hobbes materialist modern way, they were loving like the early Christian community once they had learned from Jesus that what it was all about was agape love.
And what's interesting about Marko is that he gets transformed from the natural, rude, inconsiderable, inconsiderate human being that he starts out in the chapter on him into somebody who is supernatural in the sense that he has become transformed into a completely unselfish, loving person.
How that happens is important because, as I keep wanting to say, but you'll see it, I just want you to keep your eyes open for it.
Markle is going to be the Jesus figure in the book because, what does that mean?
Well, in jargon, of course, he's going to show what the incarnation, that's the fancy word for God becoming man in Jesus, what the incarnation amounts to as an existential, not a kind of magical, event.
And we'll see that we have to keep our eyes open for what it amounts to.
I'm going to get there little by little.
So notice first that when he's in his materialist stage, he won't fast and do sort of the kind of magical and ritual things that the church requires.
It's important to see that because he never goes back to these ritual things.
Where is it?
He's where he's laughed at.
Oh, yeah, right after where we're reading still, right after the mention of philosophy on 277.
It was the beginning of Lent, and Markle would not fast.
He was rude and laughed at it.
That's all silly.
And there's no God, he said, horrifying my mother, the servants, and me.
That's Markle when he's the bad guy.
But then something happens to Markle.
He gets TB, tuberculosis, and that gives him a very high fever.
And he becomes crazy, delirious, but delirious in a very important way.
It's typical of Dostoevsky not to want to make a distinction between what you're sick with and what you discover when you're sick.
We'll see, I mean, maybe you remember the mysterious visitor also dies of some strange disease of the heart, which also affected his mind.
But the strange disease of the heart affected his mind, made the mysterious visitor a completely loving, happy father confessing and going to heaven on earth.
So Markle is sick, but that doesn't mean that he's anything, that he doesn't have a deep insight.
So let's look in the middle of that 277.
The doctor who came whispered to my mother that it was galloping consumption, that he would not live through the spring.
Consumption, fancy name for tuberculosis or an old name.
And so now we've got to see what happens to him as he gets sick.
He sees that he sort of begins to existentialize Christianity, though he wouldn't put it that way.
He doesn't know, he doesn't even care about Christianity, and he certainly doesn't know about existentializing.
But he says, instead of saying to that his mother and the nurse, don't light the light in front of the icon because that's all silly superstition, at the top of 278, he says, Let me light the lamp before the holy image, my dear.
He says this to the old nurse.
Before this, he would have not allowed it, would have blown it out.
Light it, light it, dear nurse.
I was a wretch to have prevented you from doing it before.
You pray when you light the lamp, and I pray when I see you.
So we are praying to the same God.
Now he's beginning to sort of say, yes, it's a fine thing to light the lamp, and what it means to you is different than what it means to me, but it all is something related to God, which we haven't understood yet.
And he hasn't understood yet, or at least if he has, he hasn't said it yet.
So now he's beginning to go crazy.
And, of course, remember that the mysterious visitor.
So, in Dostoevsky's reading of it, I think Jesus too.
All these people have to go crazy because they see something so supernatural, so alien to the way human beings normally are, and take it for granted that human beings always are, that they can't sort of find any language for this or any precedent for this or any way of relating to this other way of being.
Now, that sounds still mysterious, but it'll get clearer.
What, let's see who we are.
So, what's he see when he begins to go crazy?
Well, he's experiencing this overwhelming love that flows through the universe.
On 301, it says, I have my doubts why I say 301.
Yeah?
No?
Maybe that's the mysterious visitor's version of it.
When the mysterious visitor version of it, well, I might as well, I open to this page, it's no accident.
It's the other illness, but it's so peculiar on 301, what they say about the illness of the mysterious visitor.
The nature of his illness, I can't explain.
That's the sort of dumb narrator again.
They said it was an ailment of the heart, but it became known that the doctors had been induced by his wife to look into his mental condition also and come to the conclusion that it was a case of insanity.
So insanity means people are doing things and saying things that normal, natural, everyday human beings can't understand, couldn't say, wouldn't say.
And what is he saying?
Well, on 278, he's saying things like the middle of the page, don't cry, mother, life is paradise, and we are all in paradise, but we refuse to see it.
If we would, we should have heaven on earth the next day.
This is now he's beginning to really rave existential ravings.
So let's see here.
So anybody who experiences this love will look crazy to everybody, including themselves.
It isn't as if they understand what they're doing.
They're just raving.
But they are in touch with something absolutely crucial.
They're in touch with the connectedness of everything that Alyasha experienced when he fell on the ground and had the experience of all the threads connecting all of God's world, as Dostievsky puts it.
Now you may well wonder why Alyasha isn't crazy and raving if he had that experience.
Well, that's no accident that he is.
But I can't explain that yet.
By the end of today, you'll see why Dosima and the mysterious visitor and Jesus have to seem crazy to themselves and everybody else in a way that Alyasha doesn't.
That's important.
We just first we have to get what Markle says.
And I just repeat that they experience this love that selfish people like us can't understand, and there's no precedent, no language, no practices, no institutions for making it intelligible.
Now there are sort of Christian practices at the time of Markle, but you're supposed to think of it as if Markle has no knowledge of or use of or understanding of the Christian language and practice.
He's supposed to be like the Jesus must have been when he was in the early community, which wasn't even the Christian community because it hadn't been named yet, and nobody had any understanding.
And Jesus was going around saying that everybody should love each other in a way that nobody had ever said before in any culture at any time, this kind of agape love.
But they didn't have a word for it, agape love.
So, and this love is now what's coming through, so to speak, Markle.
And I want to find the place where he says it on page 310.
You've got to read that carefully.
My brother, this is Zosima talking.
My brother asked the birds to forgive him.
That sounds senseless, but it was right.
For all is like an ocean.
All is flowing and blending.
Touch in one place sets up movement at the other end of the earth.
It may be senseless to give beg forgiveness of the birds, but birds would be happier at your side, a little happier anyway, and children and all animals, if you yourself were nobler than you are.
It's like an ocean, I tell you, and so forth.
Let me go a little further.
Then you would pray to the birds too, consumed by an all-embracing love.
That's what's happening to them.
That's their craziness.
And treasure that ecstasy, however senseless it may seem to men.
It seems crazy, it seems insane.
This is this kind of ecstasy of connectedness to everything, but that's really what's going on.
Instead of threads of possible worlds here, it's called an ocean of love.
But the main thing is everything is connected to everything else.
And if you experience that connectedness, you experience it with this kind of ecstasy, and you show it by a kind of love.
Now, you could say then that Markle is the incarnation.
If Jesus is supposedly God, who has taken on a body in order to manifest sort of what he stands for, well, Markle has taken on a way of life to manifest what God, so Jesus is God, but God manifested a certain space and certain place in time as a human being.
So Markle is doing that.
Markle is, without knowing it or wanting to do it, manifesting in his life and now, when he becomes transformed from his fever, manifest in his life an understanding of what?
Of the connectedness of everything.
That God is the connectedness of everything.
Remember now, you've got to keep this straight.
This isn't the God of the Supreme Being, where Plato and Judaism got all mixed into Christianity.
Dostoevsky's God is a field, is an atmosphere, like in Kierkegaard.
They both get rid of the Supreme Being.
For Kierkegaard, God is that all things are possible.
For Dostoevsky, God is that all things are connected.
And how would you be an incarnation?
You'd be the manifestation, demonstrating in your life that all things are connected.
And Dostoevsky thinks that's what Jesus did, and he thinks an existential, and he thinks there'll be lots of these incarnations.
Every time somebody goes crazy enough to get in touch with this love and lives it for a while before they die of it, then you get another incarnation.
The special thing about Jesus was he was the first.
In that sense, he's the incarnation.
But Markle is another one, another instance where God becomes manifest in the life of and the actions of an individual human being.
So now we can put this together.
And let me just catch up.
So the Markle dies, the mysterious visitor dies, Jesus dies, none of these, and so does the idiot die.
None of these people can live in this sort of wicked and selfish and rational materialist kind of world because they are just raving mad by the standards of the world.
And that gets expressed in Dostoevsky by them dying of brain fever.
Yeah.
Boy, you're right on, yes.
Okay, well, the terrific question.
You're really with it.
Yes, something very important is happening.
Namely, it's just a different version of Christianity that Dostoevsky's got.
He thinks the Protestant Kierkegaard one is much too individual, that when you've got your one defining commitment, you care altogether about that person and don't pay any attention really to anybody else.
It happens to Alyasha.
While he's hooked on Zasima, he does no good deeds for anybody.
And then, so Kierkegaard, so Dostoevsky says that's not the real meaning of the Christian church.
That could have only happened after this big heresy with Luther and all that.
This very individualist, very anti-universal, as you say, understanding of Christian love.
The real Christian love, Dostoevsky will say, is agape, is universal love of everybody.
The way to put it in Christian jargon is love your neighbor.
And your neighbor changes, and it's not, you don't have an unconditional commitment to your neighbor, but you're ready to give everything you've got to help your neighbor, even if necessary, die for your neighbor, Jesus says.
And that's just a different story.
In the end, if you'll have to think about what to believe, you'll just have to figure out which one you believe.
It helps to have the right kind of mystical experience to go with it.
I don't think you can tell unless you actually have this experience that Dostoevsky is trying to show you and sort of put you in the position to have that Alyasha has in the middle of the book.
Then Dostoevsky will say, you see, that's the real Christian experience.
It is the universal church.
Or you can have the unconditional commitment experience of Kierkegaard, and it will seem to you like that's the central meaningful thing in your life.
The one thing they both have in common, interestingly enough, is that they give you eternity in time.
Kierkegaard's eternity comes from you love this person forever.
Dostoevsky's eternity comes from you live your life in terms of this mystical experience of the connectedness of everything forever.
Where forever means, remember, existentialized, as long as you live.
There's no other forever that they claim they know anything about.
Yeah.
What do they think?
Not to me yet.
That's true.
It's funny.
My favorite philosopher Heidegger says, yes, we all have the same now.
But I don't know if that helps any because the materialist, selfish people are having the same now too, and they're not loving anybody.
So I think that probably won't do it.
It has to be a special religious eternal and eternity in time kind of now, like the one we're talking about.
Okay, now comes the fun question: how am I making this up that it's demythologized Jesus?
Or is Dostoevsky going to hit you over the head or hide you, hide it like a sort of Easter egg somewhere in the text that he's doing that?
Well, good old Dostoevsky, it never fails that if he's up to one of these things, and you should remember that in your paper if you try to do the paper on mystery and authority, you only know you've got it right when you find out where Dostoevsky has sort of hid the answer that he's trying to give.
Okay, so here we are.
Markle's going crazy, and I've lost where Markle's going crazy, so we have to find it again on 278.
Here we are.
Okay, now after the middle of the page, where he says life is paradise, and then he says, Friends came to see us, Zosima says, middle of the page.
Dear ones, he would say to them, What have I done that you should love me so?
How can you love anybody like me?
And how was it I did not know I did not appreciate it before?
When servants came to him, he would say continually, this is where you have to pay attention.
Christians will notice, Dear kind people, why are you doing so much for me?
Do I deserve to be waited on?
If it were God's will for me to live, I would wait on you, for all men should wait on one another.
Do you recognize Jesus washing the feet of Mary Magdalene, and so forth?
If you're, I mean, you have to know the New Testament, but if you don't, you have to take my word for it.
That's a kind of quote: that everybody will be servants of everybody, and even, you have to realize how weird this is.
Jesus is God, Marco is God, in some funny sense, and this God, instead of being super powerful, supreme being, or a kind of weirdly, weird, powerful Greek God, Greek gods don't go around washing the feet of human beings.
Neither does Jehovah.
It's just outrageous that God should be coming around serving and washing the feet of the servants.
But that's, and that's the Christian, that's the sign that what Markle has got is the same vision that Jesus had, and there it is, planted in there for you to see.
And then I'll go a little further.
Mother, darling, he would say, there must be servants and masters, but if so, I will be the servant of my servants.
And that's the crucial line.
It's not an important part of the existentializing, not at all.
It's the clue.
It's in here because it's the clue about what's being existentialized, namely the incarnation of God, where it happens in this case for Dostoevsky, God is that all things are connected.
And Markle says it.
He says it goes beyond the Bible, I think, in saying it.
I've always thought it to him, I don't think Jesus ever says you should love the birds, does he?
And the animals.
St.
Francis got that out of it somehow.
Where he found it, I don't know.
But Dostoevsky doesn't have to stay true to the Bible.
He has to just have the existential structure.
That, here's the point.
In a selfish world, nobody can just understand this kind of unselfish agape love.
It has to be brought in, so to speak, from outside and demonstrated.
And whoever brings it in from outside and demonstrates it is a God, is the incarnation of God, and they will be sort of overwhelmed by the power that they have once they have this love.
And it's so overwhelming that they die of it in various ways.
They all go crazy.
They all die.
So, because, well, and I think I said just a second, huh?
Yeah, they're too crazy to live in the world.
Yeah, that's the Markle story.
Now, the question then becomes, and you should be asking it yourselves, or maybe I've sort of preempted it.
Well, how come Zosima and Aryasha and all these other Christians don't go crazy?
They're loving.
Zosima gives all this talk about the flowers and the birds and the bees and the animals and how we all love each other.
And they seem perfectly, they don't need brain fever.
Well, that's important, all right.
That's the next stage.
I want to tell you now, Dostoevsky thinks Christianity comes in three stages.
I don't, he never says it in so many words, but he says it in lots of sort of asides and stuff.
And he clearly says it.
I'll read you passages.
And what are the three stages?
Well, the first stage is there's this community of strange people around this completely strange character who are experiencing this supernatural love that comes into the world through him, and it's all too crazy for anybody to know what to do with it.
But what you have to do with it, and I already said this, you have to find a new language and new practices and new rituals and new institutions to preserve it and make it intelligible and make it manageable so it doesn't destroy the people like the idiot does.
Doesn't it destroy them by loving them in this overwhelming and unsort of controlled way?
Now, the question for you is: what is that?
What's in the book the example of the next stage of Christianity where it gets tamed and where people come to be able to talk about it and live it without being crazy?
How does that happen?
Where does that happen?
Huh?
Do we find people talking about it and not being crazy?
Yeah, sure.
Zasima.
The elders.
In fact, the whole institution of elders is a kind of existentialized second stage where the message of Jesus is preserved, or the message of Markle too, it turns out, is preserved by taking it out of this ugly, sinful, violent, brutal, selfish world, finding a language for it, finding chants and prayers and confessions and all the stuff that you can use to sort of nurture this new experience and not let it destroy you and not let the world destroy it.
That's the second stage.
But we haven't, I mean, I'm not ready quite for the second stage.
At least put it on hold for a minute.
Something important also happened that is another existentialized Christian thing.
This is a little bit magical, but not magical against the laws of physics and chemistry, but just sort of, I think Dostoevsky would say, mysterious.
But it's in the Bible.
He's going to demythologize the apostolic succession, that is the succession of bishops, the forming of the church.
Those again who know the Bible know that Jesus gives Peter, one of the disciples, the right to set up a church and to take confession and so forth.
He sort of gives him the job of institutionalizing Christianity, which hadn't yet become Christianity, but that's what his job is, to turn it into a manageable religion.
Well, it so happens that Marco also passed, and oh, and it happens, and this is sort of the seemingly magical part.
Peter lays his hands, sorry, Jesus lays his hands on Peter and gives him this power to found the church and sort of continue the love and so forth.
That's called the laying on of hands, and that's how the love is passed on.
And that does seem sort of, again, magical and mysterious how it gets passed on that way, but not against the laws of physics and chemistry.
Just strange.
But Dostoevsky has it.
There is a moment.
I said it wrong last time.
I said two or three times ago when Zosima picks up Alyasha at the vision that Alyasha has, after Zosima is dead, of Zosima at the feast of Cana.
And I said, that's how this love thing gets passed on.
Remember, I said, like, Spock touches and gives it to McCoy at one point, and then McCoy begins to act like Spock.
So that's what's happening.
And it's the same sort of thing.
It wasn't against the laws of physics and chemistry in Star Trek either, but it was pretty weird.
Anyway, what happens here is it happens not at that vision, because the vision would have been, you know, just a vision.
It really happens that Marko passes on the love to Zosima by touching him and putting, I think, his hands on his shoulders and looking into his eyes on 279.
About two-thirds down.
I remember I once went into his room when there was no one else there.
It was a bright evening.
Notice the sun was setting and the whole room was lighted up.
Whenever you get in touch with all the threads connecting the world, it's always the slanting rays of the setting sun.
It's never the sun at noon.
So there it is.
He beckons me and I went up to him.
He put his hands on my shoulders and looked into my face tenderly, lovingly.
He said nothing for a minute, only looked at me like that.
Well, he said, finally, run and play now.
Enjoy life, too.
That's how Mark passes this on.
And it's like, I mean, it's not utterly mysterious.
It's a childhood memory.
It's in the same business as how Alyasha got held up to the icon and it made a lasting influence and he went to the monastery, how Dimitri got the nuts from the doctor, and that made him a loving person too, and so forth.
So at this point, Markle is giving Zosima an experience which will make Zosima a loving person.
But it takes a long time to take effect.
That's the next thing.
So he passes the love on to Zosima.
I just read that.
Okay.
And you see, Zosima says going on, I went out then to play, and many times in my life afterwards, I remembered even with tears how he had told me to enjoy life for him.
But it's the childhood memory which is now going to come back and guide him.
It's the finger.
He's now sort of got the finger that's going to point him into the monastery when Markle does this to him.
So now let's see.
So Markle has now opened up a new relation to God as connectedness, and he experiences this love in an unbearable ecstasy.
It's too deep and too impersonal for him to live it.
But then Zosima gets a kind of ordination from him.
And that's the, and he now passes it on to Alyasha.
Only I don't see where.
Interesting.
I hope it's on page 84, because if it isn't, I have no idea where it is.
Yeah, there he is.
And he puts his hand, I think, on him, let's hope.
On 84, Zosima says, remember my words about three lines down and so forth.
And then he says, you're going to leave the monastery.
Leave me.
I must pray.
Go hurry.
Be with your brothers.
And not near only one only, but near both.
Faza Zosima raised his hands to bless him.
That's the moment when Zosima passes it on to him, the love that's going to...
What you want is that God's love comes through one person who passes it on to another person who passes it on to another person.
But of course, you're not going to transform the world that way.
Somebody's got to pass it on to a lot of people.
And you might, you can look at your chart if you want at this point, and you can see what's happening there.
The side of the chart called the chain of love, not the onion, but the one where Alyasha is in the center.
I don't have a copy, but you've got any extra ones?
Yeah.
Okay, so you can see the succession we're talking about, the apostolic succession.
But I would have been writing on the board if I knew how to write on the board.
So there you get the God field of connectedness.
Mark's the incarnation of it.
Now, we don't know yet about the onion.
We'll get there in a minute.
It goes from Zosima to Alyasha, which we just read on page 84.
And from Alyasha, it spreads to all those people.
And it's no longer a sort of private thing that the church has.
Everybody can get it, and anybody can pass it on.
It's gotten even further existentialized.
I mean, it was a private property of the bishops.
I mean, probably some of you know the difference between the Episcopal Church and the Roman Catholic Church is that the Roman Catholics claim to have been in the direct line of the laying on of hands since Peter.
But they claim that the Episcopal lost it when they broke with the Roman Catholic Church, and their bishops aren't really challenging channeling this love.
And Dostoevsky would find all that too magical to be interesting to him.
But what is interesting to him is that you've got to have, I think, through the child, through the special experiences, the kind of passing on, which he's showing you in this scene with Brother Mark.
Now, what happens?
Well, it's sort of like a time bomb.
It doesn't go off immediately.
Zosima doesn't walk out of Markle's sick room and immediately become a loving Christian.
Far from it.
You remember the Dostoevsky picture?
Why couldn't he just walk out of there and start loving the birds and the trees and everybody in total openness and complete channel for agape love?
Why would that not work?
Yeah.
Exactly.
That's right.
I mean, that's the problem of the idiot.
The idiot is like somebody who just got brain fever, got whacked by this whole new way of looking at the world, and didn't help anybody.
So what happens with Zosima?
He becomes a bad guy.
And that's on page 285.
He learns the dark side, as you put it, the middle of 285.
I spent a long time, almost eight years in the military school in Petersburg.
It's always the army that is the dark side.
In these new surroundings, many of my childish impressions grew dimmer, though I forgot nothing.
I picked up so many new habits and opinions that I was transformed into a cruel, absurd, almost savage creature.
I worry about the word transformed there.
I hope there are two Russian words, one for change and one for transform, because changed is what it would be.
Transformed ought to be saved for being reborn, a new, loving being, instead of a natural, selfish sinful being.
And that's so, so if I had a Russian, I've never yet found the right Russian person to tell me.
So I would, instead of transform, just put in change.
I bet those, even if the Russian word, even if there's only one Russian word, I bet it has both meanings.
And there is, and you've just got to keep these two meanings separate.
You could translate it the other way, too.
The transform seems more total.
Anyway, he got changed into, socialized into, a cruel, absurd, almost strange creature.
And then, and he becomes really, really bad.
I mean, he becomes brutal on 287.
He's got to experience all this dark forces in people.
On 287, in the middle of the page, in the evening, returning home in a savage and brutal humor, I flew into a rage with my orderly and gave him two blows in the face with all my might so that it was covered with blood.
Well, that's pretty brutal.
But by the bottom of the page, the sort of power of love that has been planted in him by Markle suddenly flowers and takes over.
At the bottom of the page, I hid my face in my hands.
I fell on my bed and I broke into a storm of tears.
And then I remembered my brother Markle and what he said on his deathbed to his servants: My dear ones, why do you wait on me?
Why do you love me?
Am I where's your waiting on me?
So he gets the Christian message and he gets the Christian love that's been put in him by this laying on of hands and looking him in the eye and demonstrating the love.
And so Zosima then goes to a duel, but he's already been transformed, so he doesn't shoot.
He throws away his gun and he says, two-thirds of the way on 289, Gentlemen, I cried suddenly, speaking straight from my heart, look around you at the gifts of God, the clear air, sky, the pure air, the tender grass, the birds.
He's being sort of taken over by Markle.
Nature is beautiful and sinless, and we only, we are sinful and foolish.
And we don't understand that life is heaven.
We have only to understand that, and it will be once, and it will at once be fulfilled in its beauty.
We shall embrace each other and weep.
Well, that's exactly what Markle said.
And that's what now Zosima is saying.
And we've heard Zosima saying it every once in a while, but now we know how come he's saying it.
He's saying it because he got it from Markle, and he's able to say it without going crazy, because for 2,000 years, the second stage of Christianity has preserved it in a way that is manageable.
So I'm just catching up with where I am.
Jumping on 310.
Well, Zosima, it's complicated here.
I don't even know whether I want to say it.
In the middle stage of Christianity, of course, it's not existentialized.
It's put in very religious symbols.
So, Zosima, who's in the second stage, still believes in a God who is a supreme being and accepts Platonic philosophy.
Dostoevsky's making a criticism of the church.
He thinks that in the original Christian community, it wasn't like that.
And once the church is sort of surmounted, it won't be like that.
And the symbol of the church being left behind, so to speak, is Alyasha leaving the monastery.
The love of Marko, which gets institutionalized as Christian love in the monasteries, finally goes out into the world.
And it's very interesting, but you've got to read very subtly to see how it gets changed.
Here's Zosima still being Christian and using the Christian language.
He says, the middle of the page of 310, my friends, pray to God for gladness.
I mean, praying, you can't really pray to the interconnectedness of it.
I don't think Dostoevsky, I'll show you.
I don't think Dostoevsky thinks praying is the appropriate thing to do.
What the appropriate thing to do is to love people and love the one you're with, whoever the neighbor is that needs it.
So let's go at the bottom of 310.
Zosima says, on earth indeed, we are, as it were, astray, and if it were not for the precious image of Christ before us, we should be undone and altogether lost.
And that, well, you can read it, you can either read it as he's still thinking of this in two sort of symbolic terms, or you can see that he's got the feel for it.
That if it weren't for the, but he doesn't say if it weren't for Markle, I'd be entirely lost.
He's put it in universal Christian terms there.
And then it gets, so to speak, I would want to say worse, finally, from a Dostoevsky point of view, because it's getting all too much tied up with philosophy.
He says, much on earth is hidden from us, but to make up for that, we have been given a precious mystic sense of our living bond with the other world.
The other world.
There's all these worlds, and they're all interconnected.
There is no the other world with the higher heavenly world.
Well, the higher heavenly world is here on earth, according to Markle and according to the mysterious visitor.
We are in paradise now.
We are in heaven now, if we would only see it.
Zosima is sort of losing it.
Higher heavenly world, and the roots of our thought and feelings are not here, but in other worlds.
That's okay if you hear it right.
That is why the philosophers say that we can't understand the reality of things on earth.
Well, that's Plato.
That what's real is something spiritual and eternal, and what's on earth are just reflections and imitations.
Zosima, I was going to say Zosima shouldn't be talking that way, but that's probably I shouldn't be talking that way.
Because Zosima should be talking that way, because that's what you have to do when you take over this experience and try to make it intelligible.
So the church goes around for 2,000 years, putting the Christian message into, maybe not 2,000, 1,500 anyway, putting the Christian message into Platonic form, and Zosima is part of that.
He isn't doing it as badly as the Roman Catholic Church is doing it, Dostoevsky would say, because the Russian Orthodox Church always preserves more of the original Christian community.
But Zosima hasn't got it.
He got it right, but he's a necessary stage.
He's the second stage in the three-stage Christian thing.
There has to be the incarnation where the love comes into this natural world and destroys the people who bring it in because it's so powerful and ecstatic.
There has to be the stage in which it withdraws into the monastery to be preserved and then it can go someplace else.
I'm still talking about the monastery.
So the church fathers had to make up a whole story.
For instance, the Trinity.
There's no mention of the Trinity in the New Testament.
There's sometimes a one God, and sometimes a two God, and sometimes a three God.
They had to work it out, make it consistent, and make it something you could understand.
It's pretty mysterious anyway, but they had an account of it.
And they have to make it livable.
That is, they have to make it so that through, as I say, practices of love and devotion and shared property and shared confessions, you can actually live in a way that's in touch with this kind of love.
And they do all that.
And that's good.
It just isn't good enough.
Because remember in the background that Vostievsky says the star will rise in the east.
That means that finally the Russian Orthodox Church is going to save the world.
And it's certainly not going to save the world if they all stay in monasteries and talk this kind of Platonic talk about the other world that Zossimeth does.
Now, I'm looking for something which I don't see here.
But I know we don't really need it.
But remember now, the crucial thing to read is any passage which tells you that institutionalized Christianity, which is represented here by the monastery, is a safe place where you don't have to go crazy and you don't have to fight off all these brutish people.
That's what he says on the bottom of 303.
And then this is a summing up of stage two, the top paragraph, the end of it.
Meanwhile, in their solitude, these are the monks.
They keep the image of Christ fair and undefiled in the purity of God's truth.
See, all that's still pretty much Christian, unexistentialized talk.
From the times of the fathers of old, the church fathers, the apostles and the martyrs.
And when the time comes, they will show it to the tottering creeds of the world.
That is the great thought.
That star will rise in the east.
So now we need to know what the third stage looks like.
And that's it.
The third stage is going to be when this love leaves the monastery.
So we readers are in on the third stage.
What's happening with Alyasha and what's happening with Dostoevsky writing the Brothers Karamatsov and you guys reading it and being existentialized is the third stage, where it's something that any human being, you don't have to be in the West and you don't have to be in the Christian church.
Dostoevsky wants to find universal human experiences that this Christian church has found and preserved and is now ready to go out in the world.
So the answer to Alyasha, why didn't Alyasha go crazy when he had this mystical experience of all connectedness and loving the animals and the birds and everything?
Because he was had, because the whole Christian, because for 1,500 years, the Christian community had been finding a language for it and rituals for it so that you could do it without being crazy.
And that was a very important stage.
But now we're ready for the third stage.
So the love that goes from Marko to Zosima, you have it on your chart, goes to Alyasha, and then it goes to the whole, it spreads to the world.
He brings the he he okay, let's put it that way.
And Zosima not only ordains Alyasha, that is, puts his hands on him and puts him in the succession of bishops, but instead of making him the next elder, he sends him out into the world.
And that's what he does on 83.
I've read this once before, I think.
Ten lines from the bottom.
When it is God's will to call me, leave the monastery, go away for good.
Alyasha started.
What is it?
This is not your place for the time.
I bless you for great service in the world.
And Christ be with you.
Don't abandon him, and he'll not abandon you.
Well, we know that means, in effect, Mark will be with you.
And don't lose the memory of Zosima, who's got the memory of Markle, which is guiding them.
Now we know who the mysterious visitor, the mysterious finger is.
It's always Marko's love coming to them as childhood memories.
It's guiding them.
And it's the existentialized Christ guiding them.
And so that's fine.
So Markle's truth, that his experience, which has been symbolized and Christianized by the monks, will be existentialized and brought into the world in a transforming but completely livable form.
Everybody will be able to love everybody and live in a kind of big bunch of Christian hippie communes.
Remember, the story is not that the church will become the state, but that the state will become the church.
That is, we'll have Christian socialism.
That's what he's saying is going to happen.
That means not that it gets secularized, that's the enlightenment, where you change, you believe in reason and science, and you think you can organize the world to satisfy everybody's needs and makes them happy.
That's the Grand Inquisitive.
But instead, it gets existentialized.
It becomes a supernatural, non-rational experience of love, and people go out and do it.
Now come these interesting little touches that I mentioned already.
Alyasha only becomes effective when he leaves the monastery.
He doesn't help anybody, I think.
I hope.
I don't remember any place where he does any transformation.
He only transforms Grushenko once he's been told to leave the monastery.
He hasn't sort of officially packed his suitcase and left, but he's decided to leave.
He's outside the monastery and he's doing his first miracle.
And he is sort of changed in an interesting way.
On 178, he looks altogether different.
He apparently, monks apparently had long hair and silk trousers, and it says two-thirds of the way down.
Monk in silk trousers, cried the boy, following Alyasha.
So while he was in the monastery, the boys, who turn out to be important later, sort of ridiculed him.
He seemed to them.
But when he gets out of the monastery, they don't ridicule him anymore.
And he turns out to be sort of a very good-looking young guy on 505.
The bottom, 505.
We may note here that Alyasha's appearance had undergone a complete change.
That's nicer than transformation.
I hope it would be nice if that was a different word.
Since we saw him last, he had abandoned his cassock and was now wearing a well-cut coat, a soft round hat, and his hair was cropped short.
All this was very becoming, and he looked quite handsome.
Well, there's a new Alyasha.
You can ask yourself, in the funny way that Dostoevsky is playing around with this, where did he get these fancy clothes, which must have cost a lot of money?
You know?
You don't know.
I don't think there's any answer.
I think Dostoevsky is demonstrating that we know that Alyasha will always find people who are happy to take care of him.
And somebody or other was happy to buy him his clothes.
Maybe his father.
I don't know.
But he's now, anyway, a completely handsome, secular, not secularized, remember, that's the Enlightenment.
But there's no word for it.
He's now Christian love out in the world.
He's the apostolic succession arriving at its conclusion.
Okay, that gets us to the onion chain.
The onion chain is the story of how this love does go out into the world.
And it's just an amazing and beautiful story, which I can't tell you all about until the very end of the book, where Dostios pulls off a big tour de force.
We can read some of it.
We should notice.
that.
Now let's just go, I'll go through the current supernatural love, which comes up, it comes out of Markle, Dezosima, Talyasha, goes to Grushenka, and she then becomes capable of self-respect and love.
And she, instead of going off at the pole, she loves Dimitri, and she's one of the people who inherit the love.
And she's also the person who tells a story, which is absolutely perfect for expressing this way, that this love goes through somebody and then out into the world on 339.
We've got to read the whole thing.
I mean, it's amazing.
I don't know what luck for Dostoevsky somehow finding this parable.
Because this parable is the story of the love going out into the world.
And it's in this chart.
So about two-thirds, about one-third of the way down on 339.
Once upon a time, there was a peasant woman, and a very wicked woman she was, and she died and did not leave a single good deed behind.
The devils caught her and plunged her into a lake.
So her guardian angel stood and wondered what good deed of hers, he could remember to tell God.
Remember that Dimitri says that God and the devil are fighting for the soul of man.
Every person has a God, or it really turns out to be an angel, an angel and a devil fighting for their soul.
You see that on the other side of this hand.
But I haven't got, we haven't quite got there yet.
You can actually map out who is the angel and who is the devil fighting for each of the characters in the book.
The angel is trying to bring out the best in them and make them able to be Christian or not even Christian, post-Christian, let's call it, and blissful, loving.
And the devil is trying to bring out their insecurity and their despair and put them in a situation where everything they do will be destructive of them and everybody else, like Rakitin.
The Rakitin and Alyasha fighting over Grushenka is typical.
But it turns out that in every case, the devil and the angel, and in most cases, I'm not sure about everyone, but I'll show you.
You always are told by Gostoevsky in so many words who is the devil and who is the angel, in this particular instance, fighting over this particular person.
But I can't tell you that yet, for one thing, you've got further to read.
Okay, so here's this woman.
She once pulled up an onion in her garden, he said, and gave it to a beggar woman.
And God answered, You take that onion in, hold it out to her in the lake, and let her take hold of it and be pulled out.
And if you can pull her out of the lake, let her come to paradise.
But if the onion breaks, then the woman must stay where she is.
The angel ran to the woman and hailed out the onion to her.
Come, said he, catch hold and I'll pull you out.
And he began cautiously pulling her out.
He had just about pulled her out when the other sinners in the lake, seeing how she was being drawn out, caught hold of her so as to be pulled out with her.
But she was a very wicked woman and she began kicking them off.
I'm to be pulled out, not you.
It's my onion, not yours.
As soon as she said that, the onion broke and she'd go back into the lake, and she is burning there to this day.
Well, up to the end, Alyasha is like the onion, except, or like the woman.
Well, no, sorry, Zasima is like the onion.
He's the way to pull everybody out by pulling Alyasha out.
I'm back with my chart.
But Alyasha, unlike the woman, isn't kicking all these people off.
He's taking them all on.
Wushenka, Dimitri, the boys who haven't come across yet, Ilusha, who haven't come across yet, or Kolya, all these people who you're about to read about over vacation.
Alyasha's helping them all come out of the bad world into the super world.
So let's see now.
Anyone want to say anything?
I've been talking and talking because there's so much interesting stuff to say.
But yeah, good.
Say something.
Yeah.
Tell me more.
He loses her back into.
Yeah.
Well, it has a common structure, but I think sort of the message is so different.
I mean, he doesn't look back out of selfishness exactly.
But anyway, don't bring it up because a lot of people don't know it, and we'd have to know the context more.
Anybody else want to say anything?
Okay, let's go on then.
We still have time to complete the first pass of the onion chain.
So Alyasha doesn't kick the others off.
He pulls them all out, except for Yvonne.
He pulls them all out into a better world.
Whether he ever doesn't manage to pull Yvonne out in this book, maybe he does in the next book.
We don't know.
He pulls them out of the selfish world into the loving one, out of the Eros world into the Agape world, from the hell of selfishness and isolation into the heaven of selfless love.
And that fits with what Dimitri says on 118.
I said it, but I show it to you.
No, I won't.
No, I don't have it on 118.
Well, oh, because it's on 112.
So Dimitri just says, sort of out of nowhere at the bottom of that long speech, God and the devil are fighting there, and the battlefield is the heart of man.
So this now gets turned out into the angel and the devil are fighting.
And the battlefield is each person.
And that's what Dostevsky is going to show you.
And now we can just go and look at some of them.
So let's, we've done Grushenko already, just to review real fast.
So Rakitin is the devil fighting, trying to bring Grushenka down, make her go to her pole, this Polish lover, either like a dog or with a knife, both of which will be disastrous and destructive for her and the Polish lover.
And she gets another possibility, and Rakitin still goes around saying the devil only knows as it's happening.
And she says every once in a while to Alyasha, I'm so glad you've come, you angel.
And the angel wins.
And then Grushenka goes off to her lover and just says, I'm not interested, and goes off with Dmitry.
So a weird, complicated one is the struggle over Lisa.
The person who is the bad person over Lisa, bringing out her sadistic, self-destructive side, who's that?
We've seen that.
Is Yvonne.
She writes a letter to Yvonne when she wants to tell him about her crucifix, her thinking about the crucified child and eating her pineapple compost.
And he comes and says, That's very nice.
And she says, Did he despise me?
And she wants to be told yes.
She wants to be despised by Yvonne and so forth.
So Yvonne is definitely trying to bring out the worst in her, or doesn't even have to try.
You don't have to try.
These devils and angels do what they do, often without even knowing they're doing it.
There's a sense in which Alyasha plays the role of devil with Grushenka.
There's sort of two Alyashas in that sense.
The Alyasha, who's in the monastery, he is the one who brings Grushenka down to the despair that leads her to this move, bad move of going to the pole with a knife or like a dog.
Remember how he does it.
Remember?
She, remember, he won't look at her.
And she thinks that he is this person she admires so much, and she is such a slut, he won't even look at her.
And that is what's driving her to despair, she says.
So there's Yvonne playing the devil role without even knowing it.
And I bet there are people playing the angel role without even knowing it.
I don't know.
I mean, let's see if I can, such a big book to run through just like this, but let me try.
Maybe Grushenka is for Dmitri.
Do I have, after all, I should look at my chart.
There are any of these people who are the angel ones, who are the playing, doing what they're doing without knowing if they're doing it.
Grushenka is doing her angel job with Dmitri.
I don't know if she knows she's doing it or not.
See, on my chart, Alyasha is the devil for Grushenka and the angel for Grushenka.
That's the sort of pre, that's the pre- and post-monastery Alyasha.
One is in the monastery, he's so afraid of her that he's playing the devil role without knowing it.
And after the monastery, he's saving her.
Does anybody you'll see later, I think, that Ilusha is playing the angel role to the boys, and he doesn't know.
Most of the people happen to know it, but it doesn't matter whether they know it.
It's the function of what they're doing to these people or for these people that matters.
So Yvonne's influence is to bring out the sadistic side of Lisa, 553.
So here it's all this crazy stuff I was summarizing where she once, where she says that the middle of 353, when he went out laughing, Yvonne did, I felt it was nice to be despised.
The child with fingers cut off is nice, and to be despised is nice.
And she laughed in Alyasha's face, a feverish, malicious laugh.
Do you know Alyasha?
Do you know I would like, I think that means I would like Yvonne to come and totally despise her and maybe hurt her and so forth.
And Alyasha says, and then she says, Alyasha, save me.
So there's clearly the side of him, the fact that she wants him to save her.
What's interesting on these pages, these are probably after you've stopped way beyond what you've read, but it's nothing about the plot being given away.
But, and I won't even tell you, I guess, about it.
There's, you can ask yourself when you get there, what is it about Alyasha's dark side that enables him to have enough empathy for Lisa to be able to save her?
Because if he's too nice, he's not going to explain her kinky, really crazy story of, well, well, I'll tell you this crazy story.
She's dreaming of devils on the bottom of 551.
And she gets them all to crowd around at the bottom.
And they want to come and grab me.
They are just coming.
But suddenly I cross myself.
They go away, stand in the corner.
And then I have a frightful longing to revile God.
And so I begin.
And then the devils come back, delighted to grab me.
And I cross myself again, and they draw back.
It's awful fun.
It takes one's breath away.
It's deep to try to figure out how that's related to her problems about the dark side of herself, but it surely is somehow.
And the next line is the amazing one.
I've had the same dream too, said Ali.
So he's got a problem with devils too.
And of course, it's because both of them haven't integrated the sensual side of themselves.
But anyway, so he shares her dark side, her problem with her sexuality, and he has a similar problem with his sexuality.
And both of them are dreaming of devils.
Now, I wanted to say one more thing about prayer just at the end because I've got only one minute.
But it's interesting if you look at it, that I want to show the three stages.
I'm going to summarize the three stages by showing what they think about prayer.
Markle prays to the birds, but there's no mention of God.
And he prays to the birds in the sense of asking them to forgive him.
Zosima prays to God as a person that connects people to others and asks him to intercede and help people, like on 309.
In other words, the normal Christian relation to God, which expects Osima to have.
So on 309, he says, I hope.
Okay, yes, at the top, you're supposed to pray to God to help people.
And God will look on you both more graciously.
This is about a third of the way down.
For if you have such pity on him, how much more will he have pity who is infinitely more loving and merciful than you?
Who is this one with pity, infinitely merciful and more loving?
Well, in Zosima, it's God, God, the Supreme Being.
That's because he's in the church stage, and God is for him like a person.
But for Alyasha, interestingly enough, God is not like that.
But I don't see where I say so in my notes.
Alyasha, here we are.
Last thing we'll read on 174 or 160, or maybe both.
I have to look and see which one I want to read.
160.
So when Alyasha prays, he doesn't pray to all the creatures to forgive him, which was the pre-church version.
And he doesn't pray to God, the loving, forgiving Jesus or Supreme Being.
He does a different thing at the bottom of 158.
As a rule, every evening after services, the monks flomped into the cell.
Where is it?
Uh-oh.
What have I got?
160, I'm supposed to say.
160.
The very middle.
He thirsted for the joyous emotion which always visited his soul after the praise and adoration of which his evening prayer usually consisted.
The joy always brought him untroubled sleep.
He's not praying to God to help people the way Zasima is, as if God could intervene.
He's praying to God as that joyous experience that he had of the connectedness of everything, and that gives him a kind of tranquility, and it totally existentializes prayer.
There isn't any person or object, but when Alyasha prays, and that's just what you'd expect, because he's gone out of the church way of thinking about it.
And it's so he doesn't pray for God's help, he does, but he helps everybody, as I wrote down.
God helps, but through Alyasha, not instead of Alyasha.
Okay, we start to stop.