But we got to the idea, which is, I'm going to sort of try to stress as we go what's existentialist about some of these ideas.
And at the end, I'll try to tell you something about what I think is characteristic of all existentialism.
But here's one, that it doesn't matter what you believe about what exists.
There is a question of what you do.
And if you have a childhood memory that lasts a lifetime, then there's eternity and time, there's a forever or you.
And if you're in touch with other, with all the other people and you feel like they are loving you and you're loving them, if you behave that way, like Alyasha, that's what counts.
And it doesn't matter, remember, what he believes or at all.
Okay, but then what matters is the way of acting.
And so Nietzsche, who, like a good any existentialist, understands that, is going to attack the Christian way of acting.
And there seem to be two big theses in the Course from the beginning that he definitely attacks.
I mean, and always has his own counter-way of thinking about it.
It's just, you have to keep realizing that what's fascinating about Nietzsche is he's reinventing a way of understanding ourselves and our culture and everything about human beings, what's the best way of life, and so forth.
He's sort of going against 2,000 years of how people have thought about it since the Greeks, and then making up a new set of values, as he would call it, a new table of values, a new idea of what the good life is.
So the two big ones that I want to sort of talk about briefly at least, how he's going against them, is the view about the self, which we talked about way, way back at the beginning, and the question of unconditional commitment, which we talked about a whole lot in the middle.
He's got very different views about the self and about commitment than the others.
But that's all within a certain existentialist way of looking at things, which we'll come back to at the end.
Okay, the self, remember, was for the Greeks a kind of disharmony, factors that didn't go together, the mind and the body, the eternal and the worldly.
And remember, for the Greeks, the idea was you get rid of the unessential part of yourself.
You cut it out, you repress it, and then if the essential part of yourself is the rational part of yourself, then you just devote yourself to that.
And then you have peace and harmony.
And the Judeo-Christian view, particularly the Christians, particularly according to Nietzsche, had the same idea that if something or other offends you, well, cast it out.
There was a limit to that.
One of the church fathers, Origen, castrated himself on this principle, and the church thought he had gone too far and did not make him a saint.
But there is a tendency, certainly, to repress and get rid of whatever doesn't fit in with the spiritual and loving side of the self.
But that's the Greek.
That's not the existentialist.
Starting with Pascal, you get the idea that to be a self is to be in constant tension, to stretch between the poles of being like an insect and being like an angel.
He already had that.
And to stretch between the poles and fill all the intervening space.
And that was tension.
And Kierkegaard gets the two sides of the self together and wants some kind of equilibrium.
But it's not a kind of equilibrium that's peace and harmony because it's going against constant anguish is the test of the Knight of Faith because he's always seeing the sword over the head of the beloved.
That is the vulnerability of his or her unconditional commitment.
And he's always ready to have to, he always knows that he may at any time have to suspend the ethical and do something which is terrible, even from his own point of view.
So, and now, Dostoevsky, oddly enough, on this, I wish it was more systematic, seems to not much have the notion of tension.
That is, Dimitri's in constant tension.
When he's falling into the pit headfirst and going towards Sodom, he's also singing a hymn to the Madonna, and the self is too broad, and he can't keep it all together.
But Dostoevsky thinks that he will eventually, Dimitri, through love, sublimate the dark side.
And everybody will be able to have a self when they've been properly loved and properly loving that sublimates all the evil dark side into this love, which makes him more like the Greeks.
I mean, I don't see when I read Dostoevsky the kind of tension in the self that Kierkegaard and Pascal have, and Nietzsche certainly has.
I'll read you quotes about that in a minute.
I don't think Dostoevsky has it.
He has it all right in Dimitri, but he thinks that it's not a good thing.
Somehow, if you look at the dark side enough, it will become part of the hooray for Karamatsov, because the earthly and the heavenly will go together.
And that means the self not only in equilibrium, but not in anguish, so forth.
Now, Nietzsche naturally, being Nietzsche, goes against all of that.
He wants to keep the dark side, and he wants to keep the tension, and he thinks that evil, that you should incorporate, not sublimate.
You don't cut out the evil part of you.
You don't sublimate it into something else, into purity.
Remember all this talk about the kind of purity that gets rid of the bad side, which is Ivan.
You don't even have the kind of purity that sublimates the dark side, like Alyasha.
You actually thrive on the dark side.
It gives you energy.
It gives you struggle, and that's all a good thing.
On 331, for instance, he says, We, this is aphorism 371, we keep growing and keep changing.
And then he says, we shed our bark like a tree and shed our skin every spring.
We get younger and fuller.
You recognize that whole Nietzschean constant overcoming in there.
We become younger with Dylan.
I was, what is it?
I was so much older then, I'm younger than that now.
It's a reflection of the new our version of this.
And we get taller and stronger and so forth.
And now comes the interesting one, the bottom of 331, the very bottom, page 331.
We push our roots ever more powerfully into the depths, into evil, while at the same time embracing the heavens ever more lovingly.
Now that's, you see, sounds more like Dimitri before he got Christianized and existentially loved and all that.
He wants to say you should keep the extreme contradictions in the self and spread yourself into them.
If you're a free spirit, you shouldn't even try to transform the passions which are chaotic and make them equilibrium-like and get peace.
Peace in your life is what Nietzsche just doesn't want.
That's weakness.
No harmony, no peace.
He just rejects the whole Greek and the Greek eyes Christian tradition.
The best you should do is organize your passions so that there's a kind of constrained, dynamic, unstable unity that you have to keep struggling to control.
That makes you powerful.
That makes you creative.
I think his favorite figure is certainly not the saint, but the artist who is supposedly always trying to take over more and more, which is evil, at least in the sense of original, and going against the way everybody did things before.
And in their selves, they have these powerful impulses which they don't want to get rid of, which are sort of fueling their passion in their work.
So just to see that, you show you see this in Twilight on 54.
And now notice, I mean, the self is a contradiction, according to Kierkegaard.
But it's a contradiction that you get at least into an unstable unity, but it's a kind of unity that you buy at a high price.
But for Nietzsche, the self is a contradiction, period.
You don't ever get out of the contradiction.
And it's a good thing.
15 lines down on 54.
One is fruitful only at the cost of being rich in contradictions.
One remains young only on condition that the soul does not relax, does not long for peace.
Peace is such a big deal in the Greek and in the Christian, and then in this sort of Judeo-Christian thing.
Now, I don't know about you, but I learned at various points two prayers, both of which were all about peace.
I think there's a pair that begins, grant us peace, thy most precious gift.
And I don't know how many know that prayer.
I don't know where I got that.
And what's another one?
Let's see.
Now I lay me down in peace, and so forth and so forth and so forth.
There seems to be this obsession with peace, as if that was such a big deal, good thing.
Nietzsche would say, that's just boring.
And what's exciting is, why don't you pray, grant me excitement and struggle and the strength to hold together all the most diverse parts of my personality.
Nobody prays that except Nietzscheans, but it sounds like a good thing to pray.
So we don't long for peace.
Nothing has grown more alien to us than that desideratum of former times, peace of soul, the Christian desideratum.
Isn't the end of the Mass about peace, too?
I'm thinking of that.
Yet, give us peace, right?
That's the very last lines of the Mass, I believe.
Anybody know?
Nobody must know.
When you hear music of the Mass, Dona Novis Pachem is the Pachem is the very last word of the Mass, I believe.
So it doesn't surprise me, and it wouldn't surprise Nietzsche.
But it doesn't make him, he certainly makes him feel that this is not a good way to go.
So, and in the Antichrist on 190, he talks about there's a lot more about struggle in the self and how to keep it struggling and how to make the struggle fruitful in other things by Nietzsche, other books that we don't read.
So, I didn't put them in.
But here's another funny thing which struck me just this morning for the first time.
I mean, just as I said, and I think it's so interesting that Dimitri is a Nietzschean, while he's going crazy at the beginning as a walking contradiction, trying to get this broad self into a peaceful balance.
Whereas, and Dostoevsky thinks you've got to overcome that, Nietzsche would like Dimitri at the beginning.
See if you can figure out who Nietzsche would like for this one, the middle of 190.
The most spiritual human beings, as the strongest, find their happiness where others would find their destruction.
We're 190 of Antichrist.
In the labyrinth, in severity toward themselves and others, in attempting, their joy lies in self-constraint, with their asceticism becomes nature, indeed instinct.
And now, this is the neat part.
They consider the hard task to privilege, to play with vices, which overwhelms others.
They consider the hard task a privilege, to play with vices, which overwhelms others, a recreation.
Who considers playing with vices a recreation?
I never realized.
And of course, from Dostoevsky's point of view, not a good thing to be doing.
Have you remember?
Who plays with devils?
No, no, Ricky is a devil.
But that's all right.
You're on the right track.
No, no, somebody, what?
Lisa.
Good, yes.
Remember, she has this game she plays where she dreams of devils or conjures up devils, and when they're just about to take her over, she crosses herself and they go away again.
I mean, a recreation of playing with vices.
And of course, playing with her sadism too, slamming the door on her thumb and so forth.
These are not things that Dostoevsky would admire, but if you took this definition literally, Lisa turns out to be able to play with vices that would overwhelm others.
But this is just how radically strange to the tradition Nietzsche is.
So, just to sum up that aria, is spiritualization is repression is in Plato.
The self denies half the self.
And that's one way of getting peace.
Spiritualization is sublimation.
That's Dostoevsky and purity, the right kind of purity.
And that gives you, again, I think, peace and joy.
I don't see any anguish in Father Zosima.
And then Nietzschean spiritualization, he would use the same term, I think, where it's controlled chaos and integrating evil at any level.
Okay, any comments about that?
I feel bad because I think that's such an interesting issue.
But I don't know where to find a, I was looking this morning where Nietzsche talks about it, but I know that he has this view that at any given time some passion or other is the dominant one, and it fits for this occasion, but on some other occasion, some other passion, which is absolutely incompatible with that one, is the dominant one.
And what you want to be is the kind of person who has a lot of passions and somehow manages to get the right one on top, controlling things in each situation.
Yeah.
Well, I wonder, you're right to ask.
So Kierkegaard, can somebody close that door back there?
That's going to get us eventually.
I hear people running by talking.
Well, unless it's too hot, you want it open?
Are you all right?
Let's close it.
If anybody gets suffocated, let me know.
So spirit does so Kierkegaard, the finite is the infinite, the temporal and eternal, the possible.
In Kierkegaard, you want to integrate them in an unconditioned passion.
Getting mixed up in Nietzsche, Kierkegaard, in an unconditional commitment, you manage to give fullest expression to the finite and the infinite, to the temporal and the eternal, to the possible and necessary, so that they support each other.
So that's integration.
He's got integration without peace.
That's what makes him interesting.
But I have trouble sort of getting them all together in any chart.
But the integration in Kierkegaard is total.
I mean, there's no contradiction anymore.
The self is...
stops being a contradiction when you get an unconditional commitment.
You get out of the despair that you were in when you were a contradiction.
However, you get it at the cost of anguish so that you don't ever get peace.
Kierkegaard talks about the self when its full self as constantly swimming over 40,000 fathoms.
I mean, that's just another strenuous idea that there's no ground and no rest if you're going to get yourself together at the best life that a person can have.
Does that help?
Okay.
I better go on because I'm not sure.
The next big deal, and we're right at it, so we'll do it, is unconditional commitment.
That's a big thing in Kierkegaard.
And he gets it out of already Jesus asking the disciples to be ready to die for him and saying if he'd be ready to die for them, does, and so forth.
And total commitment is something that goes all through the Judeo-Christian tradition.
I don't find much talk about commitment, I mean, or in Dostoevsky.
It's somehow you're committed to, so remember I said love the one you're with.
You don't want to get totally committed to any one person.
That takes you away from being able to love everybody.
Just as Alyasha's total commitment, he did have unconditional commitment to Zosima.
And when he did, he got so upset when Zosima was dying that he forgot to take care of Dimitri and then wasn't doing his angel job at all.
And so individual commitments seem not to be something that Dostoevsky thinks you should be stuck with.
You should outgrow them.
He sounds almost like Nietzsche there.
But there's something which takes the place of unconditional commitments, namely childhood memories, something which is settled, whose meaning is settled for the rest of your life, which you can't betray without betraying yourself.
That there's something that is forever.
It's just a peculiar something.
It's not a risky commitment to an individual.
So anyway, I can't make all these people neatly fit together, but they've all got this common concerns.
The important thing is to see that Nietzsche, as you would expect when you get used to it, totally overturns any notion of unconditional commitment, any notion of eternity and time.
All that is, of course, weakness.
It's weakness if you think that the highest thing in life is constant overcoming, outgrowing, and so forth.
The big enemy is an unconditional commitment, something that you are going to have to believe and do, act on, never mind believe, act on forever.
So let's look at it on Twilight 184 is where he comes down on his notion on commitments.
Here they're called convictions.
I think maybe convictions is a little more intellectual than commitment, but I think the idea is the same.
So I'm going to just call it commitment and read it that way.
I don't know.
I didn't try to go back and look at the German.
It would be fun to see if I could.
I'll leave this message to myself.
Go back and check the German, see if you could make it mean commitment.
Now, in the meantime, I'm just going to do it.
Okay, the middle of 184.
Freedom from commitments of any kind.
The capacity for an unconstrained view pertains to strength.
Grand Passion, the ground and force of his being.
Even more enlightened, more despotic than himself, than he himself is, takes his whole intellect into his service.
This is bad.
This kind of grand passion.
It makes him, no, well, maybe it isn't.
No, no, sorry.
The grand passion is fine, but it's what you get when you have freedom from commitments.
Grand passion, the ground and force of his being.
This is the free spirit.
Even more, ever, even more enlightened, more despotic than he himself is, takes his whole intellect into its service.
It makes him intrepid.
It gives him the courage for unholy means.
Evil again.
If need be, it permits him convictions and commitments.
That's important.
Remember, I said that in passing last time.
There's nothing wrong with commitments, except that you've got to treat them as means, not as ends, so that you can outgrow them.
I may have said this when my students came up with the slogan: stick with it, but don't get stuck with it for any commitment.
You stick with it for a while, but when it becomes time and you're strong enough, you leave it behind.
Let me go on here.
Commitment as a means.
There is much one can achieve only by means of commitment.
Grand Passion uses and uses up commitments.
It does not submit to them.
It knows itself sovereign.
And then, and the need for belief or something unconditional, so forth, that's a bad thing, it turns out.
It is a requirement of weakness underlined.
So you see what he's up to.
And now, yeah, that's.
And of course, I just said it, but I'll say it again.
And why does Nietzsche think that we should be strong and get over our commitments?
Well, why?
Well, it's built into what it is to be alive.
That's how he does it.
It's not a question of what we should do.
There's nothing in the universe on which to base an ethics.
It's just what any healthy person does.
And if you aren't doing it, you're weak and sick, and you don't even deserve to be alive.
That's that may that I don't know what to call that when you build your ethics into the universe like that, but that's how Nietzsche does it.
So I've told you now that having commitments is strong.
Now look on 127 of Twilight.
And I believe, I don't know why I've got that.
We read it.
It's important, but it isn't what I want to read right now.
Let's look at the Gay Science 100.
There are lots of places like this, but I've read this one too, but it's just important.
What is life?
Life that is continually shedding something that wants to die.
Life that is being cruel and inexorable against everything about us that is growing old and weak, and not only about us.
Life that is being without reverence to those who are dying, who are wretched, who are ancient, constantly being a murderer, and so forth.
That's Nietzsche, his outrageous.
And if you want something as firm and eternal as the vault of heaven, to talk like Dostoevsky, that just means you aren't strong.
You've got to, either you're just weak and you're hopeless, or you have to outgrow it.
At the bottom of 287 in gay science, number 347.
Believers and their need to believe, how much one needs a faith in order to flourish, how much that is firm, and that one does not wish to be shaken, firm as the vault of heaven, because one clings to it.
That is the measure of the degree of one's strength, or to put the point more clearly, of one's weakness.
That's pretty clear.
And once you're strong enough, you always see your commitments and convictions as errors, that you had them because they were necessary for you to believe in the past.
I mean, take the extreme case.
I believe you may need to believe in an afterlife, Nietzsche would think, because you're just not strong enough to face the fact that once you're dead, you're dead.
But if you get strong enough to face that fact, then you will need to believe in the afterlife.
And since there's no evidence one way or the other, you won't believe in it.
Convictions are necessary, and you have to, it's not a question of what you should do.
You have to hang on to them while you're weak and need them.
And you will give them up when you're strong.
You'll just outgrow them.
He talks about this on 245 of the gay science.
It's a funny quote.
I really like it.
It's so weirdly something at the bottom of 245.
Now, something formerly loved as a truth or probability strikes you as an error.
You shed it and fancy that this represents a victory for your reason.
But perhaps this error was necessary for you then when you were still a different person.
You're always a different person.
As are all your present truths, being a skin, as it were, that conceals and covered a great deal that you were not yet permitted to see.
What killed that opinion for you was your new life and not your reason.
You no longer need it.
And now it collapses and unreason crawls out of it into the light like a worm.
That is so weird.
I mean, that's that, you realize that it was never reasonable once you get strong enough to see it.
When we criticize something, this is no arbitrary and impersonal event.
It is, at least very often, evidence of a vital energy, evidence of vital energies in us that are growing and shedding a skin.
I mean, this talk about constantly shedding the skin, which has sort of now become too confining, is Nietzsche's main picture of this outgrowing of your convictions.
Okay, so that's the second big thing, a big doctrine or pillar of the Judeo-Christian tradition that Nietzsche is going after.
So, the self and the idea that you should achieve some kind of harmony and peace as the highest way to be a self, that seems to be absolutely solid in the tradition, in Dostoevsky, even, and he's shooting it down.
That was the first point I made.
And now that people should have unconditional commitments that give them forever, that give them eternity and time, that give them something in their lives as solid as the vault of heaven.
Now, Nietzsche is not only saying that's not necessary, he's saying that's positively bad.
That simply shows weakness.
And if you're strong, you outgrow it.
To put it in a funny way, what would Nietzsche say to Dostoevsky and Dmitry's childhood memory of the nuts that the old German doctor gave him?
Well, he'd say, Well, to Dmitry, yeah, that was a tremendously important experience when you were a lonely kid, but now you're a growing man.
Forget it, outgrow it.
What are you doing thinking that it's something that you should have so important in your life?
Now you're a different person, and so forth.
You're just two different pictures of what kind of stability you want.
Okay, that's the second unit.
Now, the third thing I want to talk about is what's happening in our culture.
I think all the existentialists share a common belief that the Enlightenment is a big mistake and is a disaster.
Whether you're, and that's what's in one of the interesting things that unites Dostoevsky and Nietzsche completely, and Kierkegaard, because the Enlightenment for him is in Hegel.
So that's a very interesting thing they have in common.
You don't have to be an existentialist to think the Enlightenment was a disaster.
It's a wider held view among some intellectuals.
But it's certainly central to all these people.
So what does that mean?
Well, one, they are anti-Greek, all of them.
They're anti-Plato, all of them.
But that's not the Enlightenment yet.
The Enlightenment is this time in the 1600s when Descartes comes along and declares that the self is autonomous, that everybody, and it sort of gets finished in Kant, I've talked about these people, where everybody should be an autonomous, free, self-sufficient person who decides on what's right and wrong and who takes responsibility for what they do and so forth.
That picture, and the whole culture should decide what's right and wrong and take responsibility for what it does.
And human beings progress that way.
They become self-legislating, autonomous.
They give the law to themselves.
They set up the institutions in the culture that they want to have, presumably democracy and free enterprise, and then progress and so forth.
So Nietzsche thinks, doesn't like any of that.
So you look at 339 in the gay science.
No, we don't need 339.
Look at 338.
This isn't something I've spent much time on because sort of political stuff isn't the big issue for most existentialists.
And it isn't something that Kierkegaard, oh, sorry, Nietzsche spends much time on.
But his view about the Enlightenment values comes out in the middle of 338, aphorism 377.
He says, we conserve nothing.
Neither do we want to return to any past periods.
We are by no means liberal.
We do not work for progress.
These are we free thinkers.
We do not need to plug up our ears against the sirens who in the marketplace sing of the future.
Their song about equal rights.
These are all the things that we believe in, which the Free Spirit doesn't.
Their songs about equal rights, a free society, no more masters and no more servants, has no allure for us.
We simply do not consider it desirable that a realm of justice and concord should be established on earth.
That is really amazing.
I mean, Nietzsche is just outside of everything, outside of that whole tradition that believes in democracy and progress and justice and equal rights.
The Free Spirit doesn't care about that.
That's just not what's important.
What's important is what?
To be able to reinvent yourself, to invent new worlds, to sort of destroy the current society and the current laws and the current institutions and set up new ones.
You've got to outgrow everything.
So that's a very powerful strange to us, most people, most sort of Western liberal humanitarian people, that Nietzsche is always coming up.
He's always taking the counter position.
And now, here's something, however, that he and Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard can all agree on.
That these Enlightenment values are coming to an end, they think.
That we're going into a period of nihilism.
That God is dead.
God supports progress and justice and equality and all these good things.
And the belief in them has been strong, but not anymore, according to them.
So for Nietzsche and Yvonne, and when the Enlightenment comes to an end, it will be a geological cataclysm.
Because all the values of equality and justice and progress and rationality and so forth will disappear because there'll be no God around to prop them up anymore.
That's the picture.
And so for Nietzsche and Yvonne, that's great.
The geological cataclysm is followed by what?
The men have to, the people have to become gods, invent their own values, and so forth.
So the idea is for Nietzsche and Ivan, the Enlightenment overcomes itself, and that's good.
Just like when Christianity overcomes itself and kills God, that's good.
And the Enlightenment overcomes itself, I guess, because belief in truth and reason and so forth finally comes to see that there is no basis for truth and that reasons are just always rationalizations, to put that story about what happens when you outgrow something that you thought was reasonable.
So all the values of the Enlightenment somehow would have to self-destruct.
And I bet somewhere in Nietzsche you can see how they undermine themselves.
But in any case, the Enlightenment is collapsing.
And Dostoevsky thinks, yeah, the Enlightenment is collapsing, and he thinks that's a good thing.
But not because the Enlightenment has then overcome itself and some new world of more struggle and more evil and therefore more exciting and more interesting is coming around.
He thinks that's because when the Enlightenment collapses, it's going to destroy everything and everybody.
Because people are not capable of being gods.
So, and Dostoevsky would say, Nietzsche, he's just part of the Enlightenment.
He's an individualist, a willful person, and sort of he's just part of this autonomous tradition.
He says, for instance, you should have the strength not to serve something higher than yourself.
All these religious people are weak because they serve something higher than themselves.
Dostoevsky would say, if you've got enough strength, I suppose, but that wouldn't be his main thing.
If you have enough sensibility to the way people are related, you will serve something greater than yourself, namely the interconnectedness of everything, namely God, in his particular understanding of God.
But he thinks that what Nietzsche shows, this is what Dostoevsky would say, is that natural human beings are just like Nietzsche says healthy human beings are.
They use everything to enhance their freedom.
They're proud.
They're evil.
They're selfish.
And Nietzsche is making a virtue of all that.
But really, that's what man is like if the Christian love that Markle experiences and passes on to Zostima and passes on to Alyasha doesn't come to change human nature.
Nietzsche is describing sinful fallen man.
And that's, from Dostoevsky's point of view, that's exactly what will take over when the Enlightenment ends, if Christianity doesn't take over, which is the only other hope, you know, the star that rises in the East.
Nietzsche would say that Dostoevsky's experiences of love and connectedness and eternity show weakness, and that's why Dostoevsky clings to them, that he should outgrow being a meaning at it.
And Dostoevsky would say, meaning, identity, love, forever, that is childhood memories, are absolutely crucial.
Without it, humanity would destroy itself.
That's the constant worry that he's got.
Okay, that's the other piece of what's important.
How they agree about the Enlightenment and how they agree that we'd better get out of the Enlightenment and how they're happy insofar as the Enlightenment's going to collapse.
But they go in opposite directions.
Total freedom and power and domination of your own instincts and everybody else and on the one hand in Nietzsche and openness to God's love flowing through the universe in Dostoevsky.
And Kierkegaard just doesn't think much about these political things.
He thinks only about what individuals have to do in relation to other individuals, so I can't really bring him into this.
Okay, now, where are we?
Well, where we are is that the question is, well, who's right?
I mean, I've just given you two complete, or are they both wrong?
They certainly can't both be right about all these things, about whether we need eternity in time, about whether we should sublimate evil or integrate evil in ourselves, and a million other things.
The interesting thing is that, or furthermore, here's another thing.
Who's right about the way to the future?
Nietzsche says we're all going to become, Nietzsche and Yvonne, and Yvonne's devil say the wave of the future is lots of free spirits, lots of super people who have become gods.
And Dostoevsky says, what is the way to the future?
It's alearchy teaching the boys.
We're going to go out into the world, and the star will rise in the east, and we will have a Christian society, a Christian socialism, which is that is the only kind of, you can only have that once everybody's human nature has been transformed.
So, how do you decide?
And or, let me just read some of the ways I kind of summed it up at one point.
Okay, for Nietzsche, now that God is dead, all things are possible if we only see it.
And for Dostoevsky, we're in paradise here and now if we'd only love everybody and see it.
But the question we're trying to figure out: how would you decide whether the current collapse of the old values is the first sign of a new freedom and a new man, where the new man is arising, or is it the beginning of the cataclysm which won't end until we get back in touch with love and connectedness, which is Dostoevsky?
Or is the Enlightenment doing fine, progressing towards global peace and democracy, like the Swiss in The Third Man?
And maybe you do have to give up Leonardo and the Da Vinci's and Michelangelo.
Maybe it's worth giving them up for 2,000 years of peace and democracy.
That's another possibility.
Three powerful interpretations.
Okay, now comes, I think, Nietzsche's most amazing and interesting move.
He's got one more move up his sleeve.
This is a philosophical sounding issue.
Well, who is right?
And where would you go to find out?
How would you decide who is right?
Particularly since they all question reason as going to tell you who's right.
Well, maybe not the Enlightenment people, the others.
But they can't agree on anything.
They are so different interpretations that they can't even argue with each other.
So what do you do?
Just flip a coin?
Well, that's possible.
Or just believe whatever you happen to believe.
Well, Nietzsche's got another move.
He sees that it's the kind of question to which you can't give an answer.
That is, there are different total interpretations, and there's no way to negotiate between them.
I mean, you can just fall back on revealing experiences and sort of pound on the table.
Dostoevsky's got his revealing experience that Alex Hawke has in the middle of the book.
And if you really, if that experience really gets you in touch with the connectedness of everything, well, then that's it.
Or Nietzsche has his equally kind of revealing experience, only it's metaphysical more than religious.
He experiences life as constant overcoming and as the highest principle that is the test of everything.
And of course, if you believe that, if you have some kind of metaphysical revelation of that kind of Nietzschean sort, then everything follows.
But that's not going to help.
So what's the last surprising move?
I doubt if any of you see it, because it sort of doesn't get a big play here, but it's so interesting.
Well, he just changes the rules of the game, the rules of the debate.
And he says this is not a question of deciding in some rational way or even appealing to some kind of revelation, finally.
It's an aesthetic question.
It's, oddly enough, not a question of truth, but a question of taste.
This whole big thing I've been telling you, what seems to be this huge choice, turns into in Nietzsche, and you can see why, that is, you're going to believe whatever you're strong enough to believe.
And that's going to be not because you argued it.
Remember the thing about criticism.
What we want to know is what can people, what truth can people stand now?
Something like that.
On page 106, number 39.
The change in general taste is more powerful than that of opinions.
Opinions, along with all proofs, refutations, and the whole intellectual masquerade are merely symptoms of a change in taste, and most certainly not what they are still often supposed to be, its causes.
So it's not that we're going to try to find out who's right and think that that's what's causing things to go in such and such a direction or belief to go in such and such a direction.
What we're going to find out is the change in taste, and that's going to be, in effect, a change in how strong an interpretation people can have.
Let me find, I'll show you another one, 186.
This just comes up every once in a while, but he really has, he really thinks the move is, in other words, just so you get it, is not whether the whole Judeo-Christian tradition is wrong, but whether people like it or not, whether it seems plausible to people, whether it seems sort of, I don't know what, I can't find a right word.
Honorable is too Greek, true is too philosophical.
Whether it's, and wonderful can't do either, that's Nietzsche.
Whether, I don't know, it's a good thing, whether it makes life worth living.
Let's try something neutralized.
To decide which of these views makes life worth living is a question of taste, he says, at the top of 186, aphorism 132.
What is now decisive against Christianity is our taste, no longer our reasons.
And that's the final Trump argument.
Now, you can't really see yet that it's a final Trump argument, but I'm going to help you see in a minute.
So Nietzsche says that given the way our culture has developed, we might go on believing in love, connectedness, and morality and meaning.
Or we might, if we're a healthy, strong culture, outgrow it.
And there is evidence that we've outgrown it, or we're beginning to outgrow it, the middle of 340.
I mean, this is in a way, partly we've become a secular culture, but it's still really off on the horizon that we've become an anti-enlightenment culture.
But this is about Christianity now.
So he says, the middle of 340.
We have also outgrown Christianity and are adverse to it precisely because we've outgrown it.
So it's not a question that's true or false.
It's a question of whether you need it.
And human beings have become sufficiently strong in the West, finally, that they don't need it anymore.
So they're going to stop believing it.
Never mind arguing about it.
As long as they need it, they're going to believe it.
And as soon as they don't need it, they're going to see that it's just a desire that they had, that they had to believe it.
And that's all that's going to happen.
Don 287, 347.
Didn't I just read that?
How much one needs a faith?
Did I read that?
That's what I thought.
Well, I'll read it again.
How much one needs a faith in order to flourish?
How much that is firm, that one does not wish to be shaken because one clings to it.
That is the measure of the degree of one's strength, or to put the point more clearly of one's weakness.
It was better to read it further.
I'm going to cross it out here.
Let's try 288.
Is that going to be something I also read?
No.
But it's not all that interesting either.
But I'll read it because it's got to do with, again, the faults of heaven and the firmness of belief and conviction, commitment.
Three lines down on 288.
The demand that one wants by all means that something should be firm, while on account of it, the ardor of this demand, one is easier and more negligent about the demonstration of this certainty.
This too is still a demand for support, a prop, in short, an instinct of weakness, which to be sure does not create religions and metaphysical systems and convictions of all kinds, but conserves them.
And the question is: have we outgrown it or are we outgrowing it?
So now comes the interesting move.
How would we find out?
Well, we find out in the sense that you already know the answer.
Each of you sort of individually, but mostly collectively, as a class.
That is, you are the answer.
That is the I've I've been taking this poll over 30 years and there is definitely a change in which of these views people like, people, what their taste is, which they find attractive, let's put it that way, and we try to find a new niche-like word, and which they don't find attractive.
So now I'm just going to take a poll, so to speak, and see where you are on this chart.
So, okay, we've got somebody will somebody come up here and write on the board for me?
You know that I can't write so that anybody could read it.
Thanks.
Okay, qu number one.
So how many would believe in traditional Platonized Christianity, which means with a Creator God and probably an afterlife and so forth?
I'm really interested in this one because I think it may be having a comeback, but we'll just have to get numbers.
So how many?
Help me count.
Let's really hide your hands because it's fascinating to see.
And if you don't support Christianity, it'll get voted against.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.
Yeah, okay.
So now we can't tell what that means yet until we see how it relates to the others.
So now we've got two kinds of existentialized Christianity.
And we want to see what's happening to them.
So how about how many think the Kierkegaard's right, that the highest form of life is an unconditional commitment to one other something or other, person or cause, and that is the only thing that can save human beings from despair, and that will give you a really rich, meaningful life.
Risky and anxious, but satisfying.
Okay, let's see.
Okay, when you kind of count the Kierkegaardians.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, I think.
What do you think?
Nine, maybe.
I felt I might be missing somebody.
Okay, and the other one, now the Dostoevsky one.
How about the unconditional commitment to all other human beings as the only lively, joyful way of life?
Aha, look at this.
Dostoevsky is doing.
Very well.
Come on, it'll take it, take a lot of counting.
Whoa.
Stabilize your hands.
One, two, three, four.
I got fifty.
Okay, fifty.
Wow.
This is interesting.
I think Nietzsche is losing to Dostoevsky.
Okay, but then we don't want to leave out the fact there may be people in the real world, don't let this course intimidate you, who believe that the secular Enlightenment values of individualism, autonomy, lucidity, peace, freedom, social justice, and progress are still the only way to go and that they will work eventually and there's what we should be working for.
How many believe that?
This is terrible.
I don't know what to think of that.
This is not how it was.
Yes, oh, you're going to a few people will dare to support the Enlightenment.
Why don't you?
What's fixed okay?
Do it again.
Question in the middle.
Question?
What do the GSIs and me think?
That's interesting.
I don't know.
Let's finish this and then we'll vote.
We never have before, but we will.
Okay.
We got six for them.
What?
Five.
That's what one of them was a question.
Okay.
But we haven't, oddly enough, got to Nietzsche yet.
Or is constant overcoming, danger, struggle, wonder, unstable selves, having different identities, a life that's a lot of short stories instead of a novel, or even bigger things like opening new worlds is what makes life worth living.
Those are the Nietzscheans.
How many Nietzscheans?
Ah, now I see.
I mean, that's what I expected, but I was worrying about it.
That Nietzsche wasn't winning.
So I think Nietzsche is winning the taste game.
One, two, three, four, five.
He got 50.
What did you guys get?
What?
60.
Ah.
Well, I'll believe Ian.
I'm not very good at counting any more than I am at writing on the blackboard.
So, okay, 60.
Well, now what does that show?
I guess that shows that Nietzsche, see, that's what I suspected, that Nietzsche, once he turns the game into not a question of what's right or wrong, but what's happening in the world, and that's all that really matters, according to him.
What's that?
Well, we don't know where I am yet, you mean?
Well, I ended with Nietzsche because that's how the course ended.
No, I don't.
I'm not a Nietzschean one.
I guess I'm Kierkegaardian.
I'm still way back in the unconditional commitment business.
I mean, maybe I could convert some of you.
As one of my TAs said last year, at the point when I was getting all these dossiers, all the Nietzsche votes, there were a lot of Nietzsche votes.
She said, Would you want your lover to be a Nietzschean or a Kierkegaardian?
And that changed the votes completely.
So I don't know what to do about that.
It shows that you've got to be careful when you take polls how you ask the question.
So, do the TAs want to tell where they're at in this?
If so, please do.
The students would like to know.
Ian?
But you could say you don't you, you know, you haven't got a stand yet.
That's true, too, possibly.
I would say that I am and more in the Nietzsche, but for all those.
Those are the two biggest camps, that's Christine.
Oh, I just ask you something very well.
Steve, what?
More Kierkegaard than Nietzsche.
Wait, wait, wait, wait.
What do you mean, more Kierkegaard than Nietzsche?
Not Nietzsche.
Okay.
Yeah.
I might have to see what it's going.
And can you hear him?
He's.
Okay.
Sonia.
One thing that wants to change or finally come.
That's that's that's like you do the job of my TA last year.
Okay, yeah.
Oh, well, it's good to have somebody defending the Enlightenment.
Now, what I want to finally do, just got a minute, is I've got to look at this and see.
I mean, I'll tell you what happened last time, and then we'll see, I mean, because it's hard to compare since the number of people, but then I want to see if things are going.
What's really important, if Nietzsche's right, is not the number, but the direction that things are going.
Because his claim is, if he's right, it ought to become more Nietzschean every year.
And I do think that what's happened at least is that it's gone, in my experience, from Kierkegaard to Dostoevsky.
And whether, and it did seem to me the last two times that it was getting more Nietzschean every year.
But let me just put the previous two times on the board, or one time, no, two times.
So what do we got?
We've got tradition.
Okay, it was 10 and 6.
You see, you've got to now, I don't even know how to do this, but you've got to see these in relation to that.
Somebody helped me do this.
25 and then 7.
I mean, this was, it went down from, it went down from 10 to 6.
This one really went down.
Kierkegaard's really going down from 25 to 7.
Romantic love is not a popular thing these days.
40 to 26.
So that went down pretty radically.
But it didn't here.
So Dostoevsky is staging a kind of comeback.
Let's see here.
This went, there was 4, and the next year 13.
So the Enlightenment was getting better.
And now the Nietzsche question.
Nietzsche was 40 and then 43.
Now, does that mean somebody helped me understand?
Yes, I think there's still a trend toward Nietzsche.
Just as he said, he will turn out to be right when everybody's going to have taste like his, and it may take 300 years.
Is there anything else we can conclude from that?
Dostoevsky is, this is the interesting one, that Dostoevsky is also, it's Dostoevsky versus Nietzsche.
If trend counts, it looks like taste is going in the direction for Dostoevsky.
Taste is going very much in his direction, even more than taste is going in Nietzsche's direction.
That is, what is it, the derivative of the curve or something?
I don't know.
At MIT, they would tell me what it is.
What's happening here, that the acceleration of this is going for Dostoevsky, that the velocity is going for Nietzsche.
I'm not sure how to say this.
I have to think about this.
But in any case, I think now I have to quickly do one more thing because people want to know what existential philosophy is.
I don't think that's a very interesting question, really.
I mean, what's interesting, what is interesting is the views that these people have.
But I'll try to give you some general characteristics.
First, if you want to find definitions, start by looking at paradigm cases, which is exactly what we've done.
Kierkegaard, Dostoevsky, and Nietzsche are really paradigm cases of existentialists.
It would be right to go also and look at Sartre and Heidegger and Pascal, whom I mention every once in a while.
Those six are the top guys: Kierkegaard, Dostoevsky, Nietzsche, Sartre, Heidegger, and way back at the beginning, Pascal.
And here's what I think they all have in common: one, there's no new, no human nature.
Pascal already said it when he said custom is our nature.
And Nietzsche says, so from the beginning, when Pascal says custom is our nature to the end, when Nietzsche says we're the undetermined animals, we have no fixed horizons.
And therefore, they all think human nature and the world can radically change, be transformed.
History is more important than having any fixed eternity outside of time.
That's the big deal Judeo-Christian move against the Greeks.
And then, of course, if you use the old categories I used, in ethics, the individual is higher than the universal.
And in epistemology, the involved point of view reveals reality and is more basic than what you get from detached reason and theory.
And Kierkegaard terms truth to subjectivity.
And finally, they all believe, and this is the metaphysical part, belief in an onto-theological God, that is a supreme being, is no longer plausible and no longer necessary, but they think, but it opens up the possibility of other ways of understanding the divine and the sacred.
They've all got their versions of the divine and the sacred, even Nietzsche with his polytheist claims.
So that's all I see that they all have in common, but that's a lot.
Did that go so fast that you didn't get it finally?
So I suppose it will show up on a podcast anyway.
And as I say, what's more important is to understand each of these people than it is to have what they have in common.
Okay, that's it.
I have to stop and we're going to hand out the forms, the evaluations.
That's a new vote, I must say that.
It's a pretty neat one.
Thank you.
Okay, quick.
Give out the evaluations.
Yeah.
What's that?
What's my unconditional commitment?
Teaching, I think.
So everything fits in, everything falls into place.
Here's another thing that somebody might ask.
If you like this course so much, you might, and if you have room in your schedule, you might be interested that I'm going to give Philosophy VI, which is sort of really the prequel to this, on next spring.
And that goes follows the culture from Homer and Aeschylus with Virgil and Dante to Moby Dick, Moby Dick being exactly contemporaneous with Kierkegaard.
So if you want to know where where how it got to where you started this time, then you should look into Philosophy VI.