The first page in front of you is sample final exam question one, two hours.
Identify as precisely as possible, give author, identify each speaker under situation or and or situation where relevant.
And I have to put that in because sometimes the quotes from Nietzsche haven't got a speaker and/or situation the way they would from the brothers or so forth.
Anyway, if it's the brothers, you should give the speaker and situation.
If it's Kierkegaard, you can say if you want to, who's the pseudonym talking, since it's always the same one.
However, that's not a big deal.
And state briefly the significance of 10 out of the following, 12 of the following.
Of course, it won't be these, but I'm going to just, to give you an idea of what kind of answer we want, which is roughly a page of a blue book, not a big essay, but enough to show that you understand not only where the quote comes from, but why we would choose it.
That is, why it's significant.
That's the important part.
If you got it completely wrong, but you got it wrong in an intelligent way where it could have, you might have well made the mistake, but you get the significance, that's the important part.
Okay, let's just run through them together and give you kind of practice and a sense of what's expected.
So here we go.
You are really angry with me for not having appeared to you in a red glow with thunder and lightning, with scorched wings and so forth.
You are wounded in the first place in your aesthetic feelings, and secondly, in your pride.
Those who come in late, come up front and take a copy of this, which is what we're reading together.
It's over here.
Okay, who's talking?
The devil, right?
In what book, of course?
And in the Brothers Karamatso, of course.
And I'm not sure myself.
It doesn't seem to me to have a very interesting significance now that I look at it.
But I can make up one.
I could make up an A answer.
That is that Yvonne has this kind of pride that his ideas are very valuable and his essay like on the geological cataclysm is very important.
And the devil is constantly making fun of the lofty side of Yvonne and his philosophical ideas.
And the devil is the external lackey or stupid or whatever side of Yvonne.
And Yvonne is, in a way, happy to externalize that.
On the other hand, it sort of wounds his pride that he's got this crazy lackey parody side of his personality at all.
I don't think that's a terrific good question.
And so therefore, my answer is to, what's wrong with my answer is that it's too far from the text.
But then the trouble is, I can't think of any answer.
Can any of you that's any closer to the text?
I wouldn't, I think we, I wouldn't put that on again.
Let's try this one.
Much better.
I came here to find a wicked soul.
I felt drawn to evil because I was base and evil myself, and I found a true sister.
I found a treasure, a loving heart.
She has pity on me now.
Who talking?
Alyosha.
In the brothers, to whom, or about whom?
About Grushenka.
And now, the significance of that one is a good, clear one.
Anyone want to volunteer a significance?
What would you say on the exam about that one?
Well, that's very clear and important.
Why is this episode where he goes to her?
What does he mean that he went out of being evil?
Well, he means that he went out to her out of lust and because he was rebelling against God and religion and everything because the Thasma had not performed a miracle.
And why is this so important?
That what's he saying?
He's saying, in effect, that instead of this situation, they love each other, agape love, and he doesn't say it in this sentence, but what's important is: why do we choose this sentence?
The significance of it is it's part of this episode in which Alyasha performs a miracle.
Namely, he saves Grushenka by way of his love and because she was feeling despised by him, and she saves him by way of her love because he was feeling rebellious and angry about the lack of a miracle.
If anybody has any comments or objections or anything, just interrupt, because this is going to help you get a grip on this.
So, okay, three.
No person who has learned to exist as the individual, no person who has learned that to exist as the individual is the most terrifying thing of all will be afraid of saying it is the greatest.
Who?
Kierkegaard.
And why is that significant?
Anybody want to try this one?
Boy.
Okay, I'm ready to take the whole example.
Anyway, here we go.
So, for Kierkegaard, being an individual means having a defining commitment.
And why would that be terrifying?
Well, there are really two, I think, answers.
I think grading it, I'd be happy with one or the other.
But it doesn't say two, so you aren't really required.
But there's two things terrifying about it.
What?
Yes, the sword hanging over the head of the beloved.
That is the vulnerability of it.
The fact that you put your whole identity and world on the line, and it's all now very risky.
And that's terrifying.
And what there's something, I think, in fact, if I went back and found this sentence, I suspect it means something else.
Yeah.
Good.
Say a little tiny bit more.
Why is that terrifying?
Not following the ethical.
That's right.
You recognize the importance of the ethical, and you recognize that you're deviating from it.
But you're deviating from it in a way that your deviation isn't a temptation to lower immediacy, which is where you should return to the ethical.
You're deviating from it in a way that the ethical itself is the temptation.
Remember the sort of gay example parallel: that if you were a gay person loving somebody in Copenhagen in 1850, the temptation would be to go straight, and the terrifying thing would be to do this thing, which everybody says is awful and unethical.
You're suspending the ethical.
You're going against the ethical.
And so, in Abraham's case, just to finish it, what's the terrifying thing that he's doing?
Yeah, but put it in his terms, and put it in the ethical terms that he would have to use if he talked to himself.
Remember?
He's a murderer.
Abraham can only say, when he talks to himself and makes it intelligible, he can only say he's a murderer, just like the gay person can only say, I'm a depraved, unnatural sick person or whatever.
So it's terrifying to go against the ethical when you respect the ethical, and you've got to respect the ethical because it's what enables you to make any sense of what you're doing.
Four, and if the suffering of the children go to swell the sum of sufferings which was necessary to pay for the truth, then I protest that the truth is not worth such a price.
Who says?
Good.
Yvonne, in what part of the book?
Now it's important to talk about the situation.
Rebellion, right.
And that's the situation in which he's telling Alyasha why he rejects the world.
And he's, then you have to say something about what does it show?
Why is it important?
Well, Yvonne's making a strong case that if you were outside the world and you had a strong sense of justice, you wouldn't join the world.
But what's wrong with that way of putting it?
That's right.
He's not outside the world.
It's not up to him to figure out, to decide whether to accept the world or not.
And I think that would be already a complete answer, but if you wanted to just go over the top, what's the right thing to do instead of condemn the world as unjust from outside it?
What should Yvonne do?
What does Alyasha do about the injustice of the suffering?
Exactly.
Try to fix them.
In your local, whatever bad things are happening around you that you could do something about, you should stop complaining about how unjust the world is and do something about.
That's certainly the whole answer.
Everything has been good except for the first question.
Let's try the fifth.
Unconditional and honest atheism is simply the presupposition, the way he poses his problem, being a triumph achieved finally and with great difficulty by the European conscience.
I wonder if that's in the reading.
Does that sound familiar?
I have a feeling that I took that out of Nietzsche this time.
It's Nietzsche.
That is, finding with great difficulty by the European conscience, being the most faithful act of 2,000 years of discipline for truth, in the end, forbids itself the lie in faith in God.
I mean, I had, there are passages like that.
So what's going on here?
That after 2,000 years of discipline for truth, they forbid themselves the lie of faith in God.
It's a very interesting idea, and we discussed it a lot.
Anybody, what's the point of this?
Yeah.
That's right.
So it's the we have killed God story.
We did it ourselves.
Christianity overcame itself by being determined to find the truth about our desires and about the world, so to speak.
And the truth about is that we would love to have an answer and a meaning to this world and the chaos of it, but there isn't any.
Okay.
What exactly but the person who gives up the universal to grasp something still higher that is not the universal, what does he do?
Can this be anything but temptation?
Well, actually, that's repetitious.
What's that about?
Kierkegaard, and what's the issue again?
It's another version of the teleological suspension of the ethical.
Number seven, why is it he still does not understand how much I'm really ready to bear for his sake?
Why, why doesn't he know me?
How dare he not know me after all that has happened?
I want to save him forever.
That's something we never talk about in lectures, but that's all right.
The quotes are not supposed to be what I talked about in lectures.
Who's talking to me?
Katerina.
Yeah, about whom?
About Dimitri.
And she's sacrificing herself for Dimitri out of pride, and she's suffering for it, which is the kind of suffering which I forget our translation calls lacerations or strings.
Lacerations, right?
Lacerations.
It's her kind of lacerations.
She wants to sacrifice herself for him to show that she's better than he is, better than everybody.
And that's her kind of pride.
Oh, and that's enough.
I mean, you could go on to compare it to Yvonne, her existential doubles kind of pride, but I think you certainly don't need to.
Okay, let's see.
We know it well, the world in which we live is ungodly, immoral, inhuman.
We have interpreted far too long in a false and mendacious way, in accordance with the wishes of our reverence, which is to say, according to our needs.
Hmm.
Sound familiar.
Who?
Nietzsche, again, it's really the truth thing again.
Because we couldn't face the way the world is ungodly, immoral, and inhuman, and we needed meaning.
We were addicted to meaning.
We lied to ourselves.
And remember, he says God is our, he says it as a question: could it be that God is our longest lie?
That's what he's, in fact, claiming there.
Okay, God has pity on me and is calling me to himself.
I know I'm dying, but I feel joy and peace for the first time after so many years.
There was heaven in my heart from the moment I had done what I had to do.
Now I dare to love my children and to kiss them.
That's a good one.
Who?
The mysterious visitor, right?
The mysterious visitor.
And in the brothers, of course.
And the situation is he's talking to Alyasha after he's confessed.
And the important thing about it is that once he's confessed, he can be joyful because he's now back in touch with his children and his wife and everybody whom he has been, in effect, lying to all these years because they didn't know he was a murderer.
Not that they really believe he is a murderer, but because he isn't really like that anymore.
But the important thing is he now feels that it's really him that they love, and that makes it heaven in his heart.
And that's important because that's to say, that's a kind of existentializing move.
To say what it is to be in heaven is to be feeling the joy of connectedness to the people you care about.
So you love that.
Now, 10, he is constantly making the movements of infinity, but he makes it with such accuracy and poise that he's continually getting finitude out of it.
And at a second, would one suspect anything else?
Kierkegaard, well, who's he talking about?
Yeah.
Well, there's some disagreement.
It's about both the night of resignation and the night of faith, but it's strictly the who's making the movement of infinity in such a way as to get finitude out of it.
The night of faith.
That is, he has an infinite passion for something finite.
He's got the actual embodied other person there to love.
And whereas, who's he contrasting it with?
The knight of resignation, who makes the movement of infinite resignation and doesn't get infinity out of it, doesn't get back in touch with the temporal embodied finite.
That's the lady in Hiroshima Monomur that illustrates what it would be like to make the movement of infinity and not get back in touch with individual finite people.
Okay, philosophy cannot and should not give us an account of faith.
It should understand itself and know just what it is indeed to offer without taking anything away, least of all cheating people out of something by making them think it is nothing.
I don't think I read that, but you did.
Anyone recognize any Kierkegaard?
What's he talking about?
What's wrong with philosophy?
But how does it cheat people out of something?
Yeah.
Okay, good.
That's absolutely right.
A little bit would be better maybe to say it says that faith is lower immediacy.
He's against the idea that there's something higher than faith.
And that's the sense in which you take something very high up and you make it seem the lowest sort of thing.
That's good.
Okay, next.
When we criticize something, this is no arbitrary and personal event.
It is at least very often evidence of vital energies in us which are growing and shedding a skin.
We negate, we must negate, because something in us wants to live and affirm something we perhaps do not know or see as yet.
Now, I'm not sure that's on the list of what you were supposed to eat.
Anyone recognize it?
It is.
Okay, good.
But who is it?
You look like, you know, you were nodding.
It's Nietzsche, right?
And it's Nietzsche telling us again that you ought to outgrow whatever your skin is.
You've got to, because life is constant overcoming, constant outgrowing.
And something that you thought you needed before, because you were too weak to face reality, you now have gotten strong enough and to leave it behind.
And that's what a human being at its best does.
Okay, that's any questions now about that overall?
It's supposed to have left you happier or sadder about the two hours you're going to have to put up with.
I hope it gives you a sense that you could do it.
And if anything, the quotes we're going to give you are going to be better, at least better than that first one.
That is, it should be clear where they come from.
It's not a trick.
And it should be clear what the significance of them is.
Ask yourself always, well, why do they put that on there?
It's not just any old quote.
Something important about the book is coming out in that quote.
Okay, anything else?
If not, I'm going on to the next on the back of what you've got.
The question two, one hour.
So we decided that the way to do it, after much discussion, is to give you these six questions in advance, and you can think about what you would have said to any of the six.
It's a way of reviewing and discussing the course with other people in the course.
And then we will choose two on each of the two exams.
It may be the same two, it may not.
We don't promise.
It may be one of them, but not the other.
So there's no way to tell which of the two you're going to get, but that's the point.
The trade-off is we save you from surprises, but you have to think about the whole course in order to be prepared for that question.
Any question about that?
Okay, we had to go through that at some point, and it's better to do it while you've got this in your hands than not.
Okay, so now I'm going to get my notes and talk about what we should talk about today.
I didn't give you guys the notes.
Now, I've got a big problem, and as I told you already, it's the brief habits problem.
I didn't call it that.
I'm going to have to review what I said at Mulford because when I came in, just before I left to come over here, I looked and it was still pending.
We can't wait because it's an important piece that goes into explaining Nietzsche at this point.
And it's so important that it's not a big disaster to have to do it again.
I'll try to do it a little faster than I did last time.
But because again, let me just ask and assure myself: so, how many people were not at the lecture at Mulford where I talked about this?
Well, that is just amazing.
Okay, well, I can understand why.
I mean, I switched the time on you, and it's not your fault if you couldn't make it.
So, we're going to do it again.
The interesting quote, which most people don't notice or pay much attention to, but which I think is very important, is on page 236, aphorism 295.
And I haven't talked about it, have I accepted on that day?
Those of you who weren't there that day, we haven't read this, I think.
Okay, then, is that right?
Okay, so let's read it.
I love brief habits and consider them an inestimable means for getting to know many things and so forth.
My nature is designed entirely for brief habits, and that's we don't need to read that either.
But now, at the top of 237, I always believe that here is something that will give me lasting satisfaction.
Brief habits have a faith, have this faith of passion, this faith in eternity.
Whenever you see eternity, you have to think about this is important.
This is something about forever.
And you also ought to be puzzled: what's Nietzsche doing thinking about forever?
So, we have to go on.
And that I am to be envied for having found and recognized it.
And then he gives a lot of nice, how much it's nice, and he doesn't desire anything else.
But one day, its time is up.
The good thing parts for me, not as something that's come to nauseate me, but peacefully and sated with me as I am with it.
It's as if we had reason to be grateful to each other as we shook hands to say farewell.
Even then, something new is waiting at the door, along with my faith, this indestructible fool and sage, that this new discovery will be just right and that this will be the last time.
Now that's amazingly interesting.
And what's he talking about?
Well, all sorts of things, but I think the simplest thing before we read his list is it's a kind of infatuation.
It's something which, when you're in it, seems terrific and seems to be something you will never want to give up and so forth, but it goes away.
And when it goes away, that's fine, too, because you will have lived whatever you can get out of it.
And he says, this is what happens to me.
And then you get this amazing list.
Dish it with dishes, ideas, human beings, that's the infatuation.
Cities, poems, music, doctrines, ways of arranging the day, lifestyles.
In any of those, you can sort of throw yourself into them as if they were the ultimate satisfying and fulfilling thing and get a great deal of satisfaction out of them for a while.
That's the brief habit.
And they even look to you like they are eternal, that they're going to last forever.
And you're foolish enough, and you'd have to be a fool, to take the next infatuation as if it was going to last forever since the last one thought you looked like it would, but didn't.
But that you can't get over that.
You are just a fool and sage.
The next one also looks like this is really it.
This is going to last forever.
I've never been in such a wonderful, satisfying relationship or whatever.
But you should know, and it will happen, that you will what?
Outgrow it.
That's what's behind all this.
It's the Nietzschean outgrowing story.
And then, and he, Nietzsche, being a free spirit, says, enduring habits I hate.
I feel as if a tyrant had come near me, as if the air I breathe would thicken when events take such a turn, as it appears that they will inevitably give rise to enduring habits.
And so that, so he's got an interesting position.
He doesn't want to be trapped in one relationship or gourmet love or love of the city like Berkeley, say, or Paris.
But he also doesn't want to think that every minute there's something new.
He says at the end, that most intolerable, to be sure, and the terrible par excellence would be for me a life entirely devoid of habits, a life that would demand perpetual improvisation.
I don't know whether he thinks that that's even better.
And you see in Breathless, in a way, Michel Pueka, who is the ultimate pop free spirit, doing perpetual improvisations, but you also see him in the middle of one of his brief habits, namely the one he's altogether involved in is with her.
She keeps wanting to know whether it's going to last forever, and she's afraid that it might, and that scares her.
She's afraid it might not.
That scares her.
He isn't scared at all.
He's enjoying every minute of it while he's in it, and he's not making any promises about the fact that it'll last forever, but he's planning it as if it would last forever.
They're going to go to Italy together.
They're going to steal cars together.
They're going to go to prison together.
So I don't know.
I think Nietzsche, I don't think Nietzsche has an opinion about this, but I'm not sure.
Whether you ought to have a lot of brief habits or a few or whatever.
I think he thinks that it's a good thing, I have a feeling, to get involved in a brief habit so you can outgrow it.
If you had total improvisation, if everything was like Michelle is in the background, sort of making up his life and his identity every few minutes, then you wouldn't really be able to outgrow anything.
So I think the ideal thing is to actually throw yourself into a brief habit and stay with it as long as it works and get the most out of it.
But when it isn't working anymore, then you have to be free to drop it and move on.
I say, look at page 88, so let's look at page 88.
He's talking about it again, the middle of page 88, the end of the top paragraph of aphorism 14.
Gradually we become tired of the old and of what we safely possess, and we stretch out our hands again.
Even the most beautiful scenery is no longer short of our love after we've lived in it for three months.
And some more distant coast attracts our avarice.
Possessions are generally diminished by possession.
It's the same point again, that that's a brief habit.
Three months, you love it on the Amalfi coast or on Lake Como, and then even something as gorgeous as that gets to be a habit.
Like maybe looking at the Bay and the Golden Gate Bridge.
I'm still dazzled after 30 years, but I know people who are totally glase and don't even bother to raise the shades on that side of the house.
They've gotten involved in something else, presumably.
So now, it looks when you read this, in this course, and me at least, coming out of Attita Guardian story, that a brief habit must be something like an unconditional commitment.
That it gives your life meaning, and it gives your world an identity.
But then there are several things that are peculiar about it.
One is, well, there's all one thing to feel peculiar about it.
There's no talk about grief.
If a brief habit were giving you an identity in a world, then you'd have to go into the collapse of that.
You'd have to go through grief in order to get a new identity and world.
So there's something very different about a brief habit than an unconditional commitment.
And we have to find out what that is.
That you have no sense of anguish and vulnerability because whatever it is that brief habits are, there's plenty of them around.
And another one is waiting at the door as soon as this one goes away.
You can see this on 337 in Aphorism 375.
We are cautious, we modern men.
Modern men is another, there are lots of names, by the way, for free spirits.
Modern men, it can be, we philosophers, that would really confuse you if I don't warn you.
Because philosophers are in general the Greek Platonic bad guys for Nietzsche, as for Dostoevsky.
But when he says we philosophers, he's talking about free spirits who are not really doing philosophy, just a way of talking.
So we philosophers, we modern men, are cautious about ultimate convictions.
Our mistrust lies in wait for these enchantments and for, well, let's go on, deceptions of conscience, that's like Christianity, that are involved in every strong faith, every unconditional yes or no.
There's even a term conditional.
And so, then only, but better skipping down is the jubilant curiosity of one who has formerly stood in his corner, but who was driven to despair by his corner.
I have to say something about that, and now delights and luxuriates in the opposite corner, in the boundlessness in what is free as such.
Well, remember, looking at something from a corner is looking at it from some perspective, some interpretation.
So you've got this corner, that living in some city is the most satisfying thing, or living with some woman or man is the most satisfying thing.
And then you get driven to despair in that corner.
Now, despair can't mean this kind of eternal experience, which is that my life never meant anything and would never mean anything.
See, that's just not a brief habit kind of experience.
There's another waiting at the door.
So it shouldn't be despair.
It should be, I don't know, sadness or something, melancholy.
I don't know.
Something that happens to you when you finally get bored with the person you're with.
Or I said, I remember in Mulford, an artist like Licaso paints in one style, throws himself into it, thinks painting everything blue in his blue period is just the right thing to do, and you can have such fun and so exciting, but then at some point gets tired of it.
Not nauseated by it, just tired of it, and maybe frustrated.
And then you want to get a new corner, say Cubism, or another city, or somebody else to live with.
And that's his idea of what it is to be free.
Let me see if I need to read more.
I don't think so.
No, that's the idea.
Now, now comes the interesting part to me.
So, how come the brief habits don't get you in the position of wanting to hold on to them forever, the way your unconditional commitment and your identity and your world do?
It took me years to see this.
Maybe I'm wrong, but I don't think so, because a lot of quotes more and more fall into place.
That is, if you're searching for meaning, and remember for Nietzsche, we're meaning addicts, then when you find something that gives your life meaning, you want to hold on to it forever.
It becomes who you are.
And meaning just brings with it the desire for stability, eternity, and so forth.
Well, what's he getting out of these brief habits if not meaning?
I mean, coming at it from Kierkegaard, it looks like the brief habits must be getting him meaning.
But if you describe them the way I've been describing them and you read his weird list of them, it looks like it's not meaning.
It's something else, which I'm going to call, and he sometimes calls wonder.
That is, you find, let's say, this other person exciting.
What else?
Romantic is dangerous.
That's going into Kierkegaard territory.
Exciting, surprising, whatever.
Let me show Poikard is.
What breathless, the whole movie is folks.
Full of surprises, making every day enjoyable, satisfying.
Any of those words will do.
Anything but meaning.
Meaning leads to grief when your word overcollects.
But wonder is something that you just enjoy while you're in it, but it doesn't last because what's essential to what makes it wonder is what makes it wonderful is that it's new and surprising and different.
And of course, it's built right into the wonder story in a way that it isn't built into the meaning story.
You're going to get bored with it.
I read you the passage.
After three months, any beautiful countryside, which is just filling you with excitement and every new perspective is terrific, is going to get boring.
And that's what happens.
In the wonder business, when things are fascinating and exciting and marvelous and so forth, then you will ultimately outgrow them.
And there's always plenty of other things in the world that will be wonderful and exciting and fascinating.
And you just, they are waiting for you at the door, you're waiting for them, and you just go into the new one.
And this is, for instance, on 346, number 382, The Great Health, where he talks about in the second paragraph, second sentence, we argonauts of the idea, with more daring perhaps than is prudent, have suffered shipwreck and damage often enough, but that isn't grief.
He said, I'll read you a passage where he says specifically it's not grief, but are to repeat healthier than ones like to permit us, dangerously healthy, ever again healthy.
This is all outgrowing talk.
And so let's skip down, and that you find a world so overrich in what is beautiful.
See, this is wonder talk.
A world so overrich in what is beautiful, strange, questionable, terrible, and divine, where divine means for him just more exciting.
Because the divine, even the divine, is something about which you can laugh, remember.
Not the sacred in the old meaning of that.
So, divine, that our curiosity as well as our craving to possess it has got beside itself and so forth.
This is just a description of what it is to go into one of these brief habits and find it terrific.
And it's what's meaning is deep.
That's another way to put this.
And that's this business of lasting.
And he's against deep.
Wonder isn't deep.
What's fascinating, but Michelle Poitard isn't deep.
When she looks at his face, she doesn't see deep thoughts and so forth.
There's nothing behind it except whatever is on the surface and he relates to whatever he comes across in terms of what's on the surface.
This is what the Greeks and the artists do, Nietzsche says on page 38.
Bottom paragraph.
Oh, those Greeks.
By the way, these are the Homeric Greeks.
Every time you read Greeks, you have to ask yourself, I hope you're learning to do it.
Does he mean the Homeric Greeks, which he likes very much, or does he mean the Athenian Greeks, who he dislikes, Socrates, and all those decadents?
These are the undecadence.
Oh, those Greeks, they knew how to live.
What is required for that is to stop courageously at the surface, the fold, the skin, to adore appearance, to believe in forms, tones, words, in the whole Olympus of appearance.
Those Greeks were superficial out of profundity.
And then skipping way down, they were artists.
Because I think artists are the ones who are most sort of out of serious, not into seriousness, not into meaning, not into deep, but into enjoying and throwing themselves into appearances, having brief habits.
That's all marvelous.
On page 76, just a short sentence at the bottom of 76, Alphorism 2.
Standing in the midst of, what does it say, discordant concord of things and this whole marvelous, uncertain, and rich ambiguity of existence.
So existence is marvelous, you could say, rather than meaning, if you want, for the free spirit.
So you find, in jargon, if you find a partner you like, you like them because they're wonderful, but not because they're adorable, technically speaking, because that's Beatrice.
Dante adored Beatrice.
That puts Beatrice in the center of his world forever.
And it's not, he didn't find Beatrice fun, exciting, marvelous, and so forth.
That was not his relation to her.
And that's the difference.
And Nietzsche is trying to do this amazing thing.
I mean, you just, sometimes it makes my hair stand on end.
It's so interesting.
I mean, for a culture that's been addicted to meaning for 2,000 years, he's inventing another way of life that's satisfying, but not meaningful.
You have to, if you're going to tell people to be free spirits, you've got to give them a new sense of what it would be like to live that way.
And he's coming along, he's discovering the fascinating, wonderful, marvelous, free meaning, early Greek way of life and trying to get people to appreciate that again.
So you want your partner to be endlessly surprising and fun to be with.
You want to be fun when you're with them.
But if you break up in the right way, namely when you finally get bored with each other, then nobody's got any recriminations.
You and this brief habit shake hands and say goodbye without anybody feeling bad, and you're ready for the next brief habit.
Yeah.
I couldn't hear you.
Talk, I have to talk louder.
Yeah?
Interesting.
Okay, wow, that's a very, very deep, interesting question.
And I think Camus is like Nietzsche, knew Nietzsche.
I think he is into appreciating what would it be sort of on the beach in Algeria and so forth, which you can't have an unconditional commitment to the beach, but you could certainly have a brief habit and enjoy it for a long time and then get tired of it and go to Paris.
But the interesting thing is that you're saying, why do I say that Nietzsche and Camus are existentialists, particularly since Nietzsche, since Camus said he wasn't?
Okay, that's a tough one.
I think that strictly speaking, you can use the words any way you please.
So here's, if you think, I'm going to talk about this in the last lecture, what existentialism is, for asking me to do it now.
If you think that existentialism is something inside the Judeo-Christian tradition, which has got a meaning and eternity and a monotheistic God at the center of it, and the question is really how to existentialize that, which is what Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky are doing, then Nietzsche's anti-existential.
But if you think that existentialism wants to, well, what am I going to say?
Let me think.
If you put them under a different umbrella, how do you live in the West after the death of God that is after the the supreme being Platonized kind of Christianity is over in such a way as to get in touch with your pre-Christian roots, that's the Homeric stuff, but also in such a way as to have profited from having gone through the Judeo-Christian.
That's Nietzsche's story, because that's the business of we are now convalescing from our greatest overcoming and that makes us stronger and more joyful.
Joyful, cheerful is more than joyful, is let's up.
I'll come back to it at the end.
I mean there is just lots of different definitions, but they're all in the same area.
But you reminded me of something I remember I said in Moper and I haven't ever said it before and I don't even know who cried, but I'll say it again.
I wonder if joyful isn't belonging with Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard.
Kierkegaard talks about bliss.
Dostoevsky makes joy the crucial thing.
I think it's probably important that Nietzsche had to talk always about cheerful.
Cheerful is a sort of a scale down, not forever, not serious, not having found the ultimate meaning kind of emotion.
And I think that's important for him that he's saying cheerful.
The gay science, it's, well, Berlisch in German, it would be, yeah, fun, cheerful, and so forth.
It's not Freud in German, which is this big deal joyfulness.
How many know Beethoven's Ninth Symphony?
That's the first word of the Ninth Symphony, Freude Schoener, and so forth.
That's, even though Beethoven isn't Christian, that's sort of, I think, this big mono vision of the modern world all heading toward better and better.
And it's therefore joyful.
Anyway, let's go back to this.
I'm off in a thing.
I'm just wondering always to myself.
And does Nietzsche ever say joyful?
Keep your eyes open.
And if you find him saying joyful, tell me about it.
Mostly it's cheerful that I know of.
Okay.
So and so when what's been wonderful leaves, your world doesn't collapse, so you don't go into grief because you never built your world around whoever or whatever made it rich or made it satisfying and so forth.
And if you don't demand deep, unconditional meaning, you'll find something wonderful and fascinating always at the door.
There's plenty of opportunity.
And if your love lasts a whole lifetime, this comes up, then that's just fine too.
It isn't something that you should be congratulated on, but you shouldn't be, you know, feel sorry for people whose love lasts a whole lifetime either.
If it stays fascinating and exotic and exciting and growing and changing and full of surprises for two people's whole life, I'm sure Nietzsche would say, Well, happy you.
You had one grief habit and it was a long one.
But it's not going to be any better.
That would be Christian to say, ah, yes, and it looked like that.
It was forever and that made it better.
Think of those poor people who have only, who have, whose lives are made up of, say, 20 short stories instead of one novel.
Well, Nietzsche would say, I think that either one is equally okay for a free spirit.
The important thing is to get into the non-meaning business.
And so, and it can happen in three months or three years or 30 years or whatever that you give up your brief habit, or you can have it forever.
No, sorry, not forever.
You can just have it for a long time.
And it might last your whole lifetime, but it won't have the eternity story in it.
So, and he says explicitly, I was happy to see, I didn't say this in Wilford because I hadn't found it yet, 231 that it's not got grief in it.
At the bottom, 231 Aphorism 289.
It's again about a brief habit.
Consider how every individual is affected by an overall philosophical justification of his way of living and thinking.
He experiences it as a sun that shines especially for him.
He said, remember that you can have brief habits for doctrines.
I think that means you can find some philosophy that makes you happy, and then you feel warm, and so forth, and so forth.
And let's see, it makes him independent of praise and blame, self-sufficient, rich, liberal with happiness and goodwill.
See, happiness is okay, like cheerfulness.
Incessantly, it refashions evil into good, leaves all energies to bloom and ripen, and does not permit the petty weeds of grief and chagrin to come up.
In the end, one explains, How I wish that many such new suns were yet to be created.
That's a neat one.
So you don't get caught in grief.
Many new suns is, S-U-N, is other beautiful experiences that shine on me and make me satisfied and make me feel warm and content and all that.
The more of these new suns, the better.
So I'm going to say again, whether I'm finishing it, but I want to sum up.
The really interesting thing is, I think that meaning is by definition stable.
Once you have it, you want to keep it.
Remember, he says, once you're a meaning addict, you'd rather suffer than give it up and find yourself in a meaningless world.
And I think wonder is by principle unstable because if it's exciting, then you could get bored and you would move on and outgrow it.
And Nietzsche definitely thinks that he wants to substitute wonder for meaning as what people really need to bring out.
And why do they really need it?
Because outgrowing is what everybody really needs, because that's what it is to be alive.
And meaning doesn't permit outgrowing, but wonder sort of requires outgrowing.
And once you realize in Nietzsche language that you posit the values that you've got, that is, there's no values in the universe, you make them up, and you can change the values, that they aren't grounded in sort of the Supreme Being or any metaphysical principles, then you, wow, this is wrong.
Oh no, I'm just reading it wrong.
So if no Supreme Being or metaphysics gives what you're doing a grounding, gives it stability and gives it meaning, then it becomes a source of power and excitement to you that there are no values sort of fixed in the universe, and you're free to change them, to make up new values.
That's one of the, that's the highest thing people can do.
I'm going to get to it in a minute.
That's going to be what differentiates us from animal, from a lower immediacy.
But let me get there bit by bit.
I'm on a new point now.
I've been talking about brief habits all this time.
I hope it hasn't been too boring for those who were there, and it's important, you can see, for those who weren't.
Anyway, onto new horizons.
That's what he calls the, that's what I call the next thing I want to talk about.
So the exciting thing is, and the important thing is, that you can always open up new worlds.
And that's, he talks about that at the top of 232, right where we are, at the end of 289.
There is yet another world to be discovered and more than one embark philosophers, that is, free spirits.
So, and that's be, and therefore, you can always go beyond the horizon.
The horizon is free, says, I think, on 242, let's hope.
No, it's right after the death of God.
I didn't think that looked right.
Where they're new, oh, where the horizon is open again.
Help me find.
There we are, on 180.
In the horizon of the infinite.
We've left behind the land, we burned our bridges behind us, and so forth.
And there's no more land, it says at the top of 184.
That's a way of saying that we go from a closed world, the monotheistic world, though not only the medieval world, but even the modern world thinks that it's got, in the case of the medieval world, the supreme being makes it a closed world.
God created it, and the rules are in it, and it's eternal.
For the modern, not the free spirit modern, but the modern people after Descartes, it's reason that gives all the fixed order to the world, that it's just as fixed.
And the new world is open.
It hasn't got any horizon.
It limits it.
I think, how many saw the Truman show?
The Truman Show is so great, the scene in which he actually discovers he's in a closed world, remember, and bumps up against the edge of it.
That's one of the amazing scenes in movies.
That movie isn't appreciated enough.
And then, remember, what happens?
The voice comes on and says, I'm your creator.
And that's the guy who designed the Truman show and says, don't go, don't open that door.
I mean, it turns out there's a door in this wall in the closed world.
Don't go out there.
It's risky.
Stay in here.
Everything is settled.
You'll be safe.
I'll take care of you.
And Truman goes out.
That's a Nietzschean move.
He leaves behind the closed world and he goes out into a world in which, to talk like Nietzsche, there will be new suns, new worlds, new perspectives, new gods, new everythings.
I'm going to talk about all the new everythings for a while.
I wrote here joyful, but I wonder if I really have a right to say that.
I think, I don't think the quote says joyful.
We'll look.
But I'm going to circle.
I didn't have this anti-joyful.
So let's look on 242.
He's talking about this new, wonderful thing you get when you finally accept the death of God, the end of monotony theism, the end of the closed world.
And then about five lines down, a strong, bold, audacious, to enjoy.
That's nice.
Enjoy is okay.
To enjoy a strong, bold, audacious soul, to go through life with a calm eye and firm step, always prepared to risk all.
That's like Michel Coitard, festively impelled by the longing for undiscovered worlds and seas, people, and gods.
Skipping down a bit, the most profound enjoyment of the moment and so forth.
And that was the happiness of Homer.
I mean, with you, back to the Homeric Greeks to get his, you can't just invent out of whole cloth, I think, a new set of values.
What you have to do is take something that's already in your tradition, that was marginal now, and make it central.
And then you transform the world.
And that's what he's doing.
He's trying, he's the ultimate sort of outgrower.
He's not only going to change all our specific values, like that untruth is as important as truth, and evil is as important as good.
I'll talk about that later, and so forth.
He says he's going to do what he calls the transvaluation of all values.
That's the subtitle of the world, power.
But that doesn't mean just that all particular values, he's going to try to turn them over.
That means he's going to sort of transform the very notion of values.
Because before, values were fixed.
And now, for Nietzsche, values are posited by us.
And we can change them.
And the most important high-level value is the value of life.
It's the value of constantly outgrowing, which is no particular value.
So he's done two things.
He sort of switched around a lot of particular values, but in the end, he switched around something much more important.
He's found a value sort of higher than all of the ones that we normally have.
And that's, I don't know why I'm saying that now, but sometime one has to say that, so I said it now.
So this is world creating, and wonder is now what you experience when you are able to invent new values.
Okay, let's see.
And the religion that goes with wonder is polytheism.
He talks about that on 191.
You can imagine why.
It's the anti-monotheism.
On 191, aphorism 143.
For an individual to posit his own ideals, see, that means you invent your own values.
To derive from it his own law, joys, and rights, that may well have been considered hitherto outrageous aberration, idolatry.
The few who dared as much always felt the need to apologize to themselves, usually saying it wasn't I, not I, but a god.
The wonderful art and gift of creating gods, that's polytheism, he says.
And what he's against, about eight lines from the bottom, there was only one norm, man.
That is, there was whatever it was to be a human being.
Different epochs had a norm, but it could be to be a rational animal.
It could be to be a creature of God.
Now I think it's to get the most out of your possibilities.
But there's always some view about what it is to be a human being.
And sort of we knew that somebody, when you discover it, you think, well, that's what we really knew all along, or should have.
So, but above and outside, in some distant overworld, one was permitted to behold a plurality of norms.
One God was not considered a denial of another God, nor blasphemy against him.
See, that's important.
The gods are different perspectives in Homeric Greece for Nietzsche.
There's the erotic perspective, and that's Aphrodite, and there's the warlike perspective, and that's Aries, and there's the domestic perspective, and that's Terra.
There's the sort of ethnological nerve perspective, and that's Hephaestus.
And they've all, they're just fine, all of them.
And they don't contradict each other.
In fact, they sort of complement each other.
The techie makes jewelry for Aphrodite and so forth.
But the picture is that for him, mainly that God doesn't, there doesn't have to be one God and one way of looking at things.
There are, at the top of 192, undermen, dwarfs, fairies, centaurs, sagers, demons, and devils with the inestimable preliminary exercise for the justification of egoism and the sovereignty of the individual.
See, it ends up with egoism because everybody can invent a God that justifies whatever they do.
And finally, they just don't need any gods anymore.
At the bottom there of that.
In polytheism, the free-spiriting and many-spiriting of man attained its first preliminary form, the strength to create for ourselves our own new eyes.
See, we've had new worlds, new suns, added to the list, new eyes.
Keep your eyes open for all the new things.
And ever again, new eyes, and even more, ever, that are even more our own.
Hence, man alone among all animals has no eternal horizons and perspectives.
That's interesting.
What does it mean to say that here, Kierkegaard says, this is so interesting and funny, that the lower immediacy is like animals, like butterflies and caterpillars.
They have no eternity.
They are changing all the time.
Nietzsche says, no animals have eternity.
They're stuck in their species.
All the butterflies, all the caterpillars turn exactly into all the same kinds of butterflies.
The interesting thing about nature is that it's that all the species go on doing their thing forever.
But we don't have any nature, that is, human beings.
They can give themselves new natures.
They can, as I say, give themselves the nature creature of God, or give themselves the nature of potential hero, or give themselves the nature rational animal, and so forth.
But they aren't animals.
They are flexible.
So it's just the opposite.
For Kierkegaard, change is the animal thing, and eternity is the good thing.
You want to get, you have to have eternity in Kierkegaard's unconditional commitment to get eternity.
For Nietzsche, eternal is his, or forever, is the lower thing where you're stuck.
And change, constant overcoming, brief habits and so forth, is the human thing.
And the ultimate change is that we can change our very nature and our world.
So that's what he's talking about.
Where?
The animal.
Where does he say?
Man alone among all the animals has no eternal horizons and perspectives.
You see what that means?
That's very existential.
It starts with Pascal, who says custom is our nature, which means we don't have any nature.
It ends with Sartre saying that our essence is our existence.
I mean, but Nietzsche's saying it in his own way.
We invent, we are the only beings who invent what it is to be our kind of, the kind of being we are.
So, and animals can't do it.
Man is the undetermined animal.
It has no nature.
And so we get new everything on 232.
There's a whole bunch of new stuff.
Where is that?
232?
I don't see it.
Oh, yes, well, I read it already.
There's more than one world to be discovered.
Okay, how about 265?
The game of looking for new stuff is endless in this book, but I'm going to just give you some.
So here we go at the bottom of 265.
Let us, this is aphorism 335.
Let us therefore limit ourselves to the purification of our opinions and valuations, to the creation of our own new table of what is good.
That means that's the table of values.
That is, we decide what's good.
And then the end is very niche and about eight lines down.
We want to become those we are, human beings who are new, unique, incomparable, who give themselves laws, who create themselves.
That's the whole, that's the same idea.
It keeps coming back and back.
And now, where are we?
So 265, 266.
Okay, I've made a list here that I know of.
New perspective, new suns, new worlds, new eyes, new gods, new selves.
For Nietzsche, the highest value is being able to establish new values.
He says that in The Antichrist, on the very end, 199.
How many of you have got your Antichrist book with you?
Not the gay science, but the other one.
I want to tell you now something I forgot to tell you at the beginning, but first let's just find it.
Remember, I talked about the revaluation of all values.
That's on the very last line of the Antichrist.
It's also in The Will of Power, but here you've got it right in front of you.
That's the highest thing.
Twilight 54, I wonder what that is.
That's not what I want to talk about.
Well, maybe I turned two pages.
It looks to me like I've gotten where I don't want to be.
Establish.
Okay, now I see where we are.
So how are we doing?
Okay, to change.
That's the end of that story.
I mean, the end of the story about what the highest thing we can do is create new whatevers.
And that's brief habits is the sort of minimal version of that.
And changing the world completely, which is what Nietzsche's trying to do, would be the ultimate thing, the most powerful, the most joyful.
I don't know whether joy and joyful are all that different.
I am worried about it.
But don't worry, nothing big deal hinges on it.
If we needed to, we'd use bliss for the Christian one and cheerfulness for Nietzsche, but they may get confused.
Okay, we have a whole new thing to do yet.
So try to, you're all looking alert, so that's good.
There's a whole story in here, too, which is just a different story now.
Another way Nietzsche wants to be anti-Christian, anti-Dostoevsky, anti-Kierkegaard, anti-modern and enlightenment, all of them.
He wants to say that somehow incorporating evil in your life is a necessary and good thing.
Now, oh, but I didn't say what I meant to say.
I want to say, bring this next time for sure.
Because next time, I want to start comparing Nietzsche and Dostoevsky and Kierkegaard.
And in here, particularly in the part about, which you should read, and it's assigned, about Nietzsche's view of Christianity and of Jesus is the clue to how to put them together.
But I'm not going to do that now.
What I want to talk about now is this evil business, which goes back to Orson Welles and the Third Man about how the Borges produced Michelangelo and the Swiss with their democracy and peace produced the cuckoo clock.
On 79, he says, What preserves the species, the strongest and most evil spirits, have so far done the most to advance humanity.
That's what Orson Welles is explaining.
And then I want to read more of it.
Again and again, they re-loomed, re-illuminated, that is, re-light ignited the passions that were going to sleep.
It's in a way related to the brief habits.
People were getting bored, people were getting complacent and sort of satisfied in their, what they were with what they were doing.
And these people, the evil people, woke them up.
So about 15 lines down, in every teacher and preacher of what is new, we encounter the same wickedness that makes conquerors notorious, even if its expression is subtler.
What he's saying is if you open up a new world, it's bound to look evil because it goes against the values of the previous world.
So modernity looked evil to the medievals, and Nietzsche looks outrageous to the moderns.
And so in every teacher and preacher, what is new, what is new, see, this is what ties what I said to, I mean, I've been giving you a whole story about new.
Now I'm going to tell you what it looks like for having new eyes, new perspectives, new world, new sons, and so forth.
Well, it looks evil.
In every teacher and preacher of what is new, we encounter the same wickedness that makes conquerors notorious, even its expression is subtler and does not immediately set the muscles in motion, therefore does not make one that notorious.
What is new, however, this is the crucial line, is always evil, being that which wants to conquer and overthrow the old boundary markers and the old pieties.
And only what is old is good.
The people who are in it, they think that's the right way to do things.
The conservative people, with the new people, are overthrowing them, are evil, like Michelle Poitard.
He's overthrowing everything.
I mean, and he looks pretty evil, all right.
It's hard.
You have to have a sort of, you have to be really sort of inside the overthrowing to see it okay to treat his girlfriend the way he does at the beginning of the movie.
The nice girl who wants to loan him money, so he steals it.
But she hasn't understood that she hasn't pursued the question why until it becomes, until he sees that there's no, that the why receives no answer, so she needs to be just taken, she can be just taken advantage of because he's seen a whole different way of acting.
The good men are in all ages those who dig the old thoughts, digging deep and getting them to bear fruit.
Deep is always a bad thing, like serious for Nietzsche.
The farmers of the spirit, but eventually all land is exploited and the plowshare of evil must come again and again.
Recognize brief habits again.
Eventually, whatever these farmers of the good come up with as new values finally get boring and people and conventional don't give life any excitement anymore and you have to find something new.
So and how does such a life look, a kind of life that lives inside of grief habits and is evil?
Well, he talks about it on 331.
On 331, the aphorism 371, we incomprehensible ones.
By the way, I may read from things I haven't assigned, and if I do, think of them as added to the assignment.
What happens is I keep changing my mind and finding things, and I'm not always sure what I've assigned, and I don't take time to go back and look.
Okay, so here we are on 371.
Have we ever complained because we are misunderstood, misjudged, misidentified, slandered, misheard, or not heard?
Precisely, this is our fate.
Nietzsche is talking directly to you.
Oh, for a long time yet.
Let us say to be modest until 1901.
That is, he thought that maybe people would begin to understand him in 30 years.
That was pretty accurate.
They started to translate him and to take him to French and English should take him very seriously about then, I think.
It is also our distinction.
We should not honor ourselves sufficiently if we wish that it were otherwise.
We are misidentified because we ourselves keep growing, keep changing.
We shed our old bark.
We shed our skins every spring.
We keep becoming younger, fuller of the future, taller, stronger.
We push our roots ever more powerfully into the depths.
Well, here, depths is okay.
When deep means meaningful and seriousness, Nietzsche is against it.
When deep means evil, he's for it.
So we push our powerfully into the depths into evil.
What would that be?
That would be our most primitive, perhaps, and destructive impulses.
I'm going to talk a lot about that.
How are you supposed to deal with the Karamatsov side of your personality when the Karamatsov side meant the insect, the lackey, the bad, the sensuous, the selfish?
I mean, Nietzsche wants to talk about how you should deal with this evil.
And I'm going to get there next time more.
But remember, Dostoevsky thought you should sublimate it.
Face it, and it would go away.
Nietzsche doesn't want it to go away.
He says we get, we push our roots into the evil, we embrace the heaven more lovingly, more broadly, and so forth.
Now, like trees, we grow.
And that is, in all directions and so forth.
Outward, inward.
Our energy is at work simultaneously in the trunk and branches.
We no longer feel free to do one particular thing to be only one thing.
I mean, this is setting up what I'm going to give you the basic clue for in a minute.
What I'm trying to do is not do the twilight and the antichrist till you bring them next.
How many have twilight and antichrist wisdom like that?
Lots of you.
Well, I could go on.
Let's see.
But on the other hand, I think it's better if I let me just see where I want to be.
What bothers me is I had a great quote.
Maybe it was that quote about evil.
Maybe that's the quote I already said.
Yeah, I think, anybody want to say anything?
I've been talking and talking, partly because I wanted to cram in a whole other lecture before into this one.
Let's, let me, I mean, if you can stand it, let's stay the last five minutes so I can hear some response from this.
I'm sorry, I talked so long without anybody thinking.
You're all done?
Yeah.
Yes, that's a puzzling thing.
Yeah?
No, no, no.
I mean, you might think that, but that's not so.
He thinks that he talks about the somewhere free spirits who dance on near abysses on unsubstantial ropes and so forth.
I think he thinks that you could be, I'm not sure, a free spirit constantly finding new wonders, constantly changing.
But I think that I'm agreeing with you that he thinks that that's as bad as being stuck.
He's trying to say the word, and that's why brief habits is so interesting.
You should sort of get, it's like you should sort of get rooted in something or get something stable so that you can use it to climb out into something else.
You can't really outgrow.
And I sort of said this already, and it's sort of what you said.
I mean, I don't think she represents the enemy.
I think the enemy is really something very post-modern.
Some people who think that they should sort of every day have a new way of looking at the world, that there is any such thing.
I think he's not for that.
Maybe there aren't any such people who want to be completely flexible.
But he doesn't want it, because as I said, and I say it again, you can't be outgrowing something unless you grow into it for a while.
So his idea is you take on something, you really live it to the full, you get all the enjoyment you can out of it, and then when it's no longer satisfying, you outgrow it.
That's the best thing.
That's what free spirits do.
Yeah.
I mean, that's like a review of where we were, which is a good place to stop.
So let's stop at that.
Hi.
Oh, wait a minute.