Well, I'm going to start by sort of placing Nietzsche with the other two people we've talked about.
And feel free to sort of interrupt and ask me things because this is not that I'm going to pose you deep problems, but just generally orienting ourselves is something that I'm not always sure where you're coming from, so I'm not always sure that I've got the right way to orient things.
But here's how I would describe it.
We've so far studied what seems to me to be, and I think a lot of people would agree, the two greatest Christian thinkers of modern times, Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky.
What's interesting about them, it makes them sort of very original Christian thinkers, is that they're going to save Christianity, they think, by leaving out the Platonic, metaphysical, theological aspect of Christianity, and even the Supreme Being as the most metaphysical and theological aspect, which is pretty weird and daring and interesting.
And they're going to save Christianity by going existentializing it, explaining some special experience that Christianity is based on, and claim that this is what the early Christian community was like.
They're going to say they're going to save Christianity from not only what I just said, theology and metaphysics, but another way to put it, reflective, detached, theoretical thinking.
And that takes the form of Kierkegaard being against Hegel, which was the culmination of the philosophical tradition up to him.
And I thought it's sort of the end of it, as far as a great tradition that made sense of everything in terms of its account of the Supreme Being and how everything else got its meaning in terms of that.
They're also going to drop not only the philosophical, metaphysical supreme being story, but the other aspect from the Greeks is natural science, which the Enlightenment took up.
And they also are going to not reject natural science.
I don't know what Kierkegaard thinks about science, but I think he thinks it's okay.
In fact, I guess I do remember places where he talks about it gets you objective truth, he says.
And if you want objective truth, he has nothing against it.
But you can't live your life in terms of objective truth.
There, he's very much against thinking that it's a good thing to be a kind of theoretical being.
You can do science, but he thinks it's a bad idea if you sort of identify your life with science and think that you should deal with your life according to the detached, objective, theoretical way that science rightly deals with the universe.
So I think Kierkegaard, and we know Dostoevsky, thinks science is fine.
I mean, you don't mess with physics and chemistry.
It's just a bad idea, however, to think that you can understand your life in terms of physics and chemistry.
And you mustn't get to the point, remember Dostoevsky, where you think you should understand, you could interpret the meaningful existential experiences of human beings in a way that either scientific psychology or chemistry or neuroscience with its neurons and so forth would have any relevance whatsoever.
So the way you live your life is one thing, and the scientific description of the objective universe and your objective body and your objective brain is something else.
And so they all share that.
Everything that's Greek, which I now want to say is again theology and science, they are against it.
They meaning all of them.
Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky, and now we're going to find Nietzsche.
Nietzsche also thinks science is okay, but it's meaningless, as he says.
And he definitely thinks that the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and the God of Plato, the supreme being, is a big mistake.
And you'll see in his language, our longest lie of the Western tradition.
And so behind it all, just to remind you, way back to the first lecture, is Pascal, who started all this modern or anti-modern.
It's modern in the sense that it's our current form of Christianity, I think, of Judeo-Christianity.
But it's anti-modern, if modern means the Enlightenment, which comes, which takes over the Greeks and thinks that science and philosophy have the answers to everything.
So, whatever you want to say about Pascal, he's the beginning of existential thinking.
And remember, he says the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob is not the God of the philosophers.
It's not even Jehovah when you get done with Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky, because for Kierkegaard, God is that all things are possible.
And for Dostoevsky, God is the connectedness of all beings.
And there's no place in there for a supreme being, and certainly not for a personal supreme being.
But Pascal already started describing the life of what it is to be a Christian.
That was what was important.
So you're going to get rid of everything in Christianity that in any way messes up the supposed joyful new experience that Jesus brought to people, or in Dostoevsky, then Markle.
That means dumping all sorts of things.
Magic, that is miracles that go against the laws of physics and chemistry, and Platonism, that is some God outside the world in eternity and outside of time, and Protestantism, you have to throw in, which is this isolated individual before God.
And the last on that list that we just finished with Dostoevsky, masochism of some sort, the idea that the basis of the message of Jesus is suffering on the cross and death.
And all they're interested in is all Dostoevsky's interested in.
And Kierkegaard, too, I think, is incarnation.
That is, that God got into space and time and showed up as a person.
And they're interested in resurrection, that everybody needs to be reborn and can be reborn.
Those are the big deal existential messages.
That will get you back to the joyful existential truth of the early, really Judeo-Christian community, because they were Jews who were Christians, and they combined insights from both.
And now, where does Nietzsche fit into that?
Well, as I said, he's just as anti-Greek and Socrates and Plato and philosophy as you can get.
But he goes one step further.
He rejects the metaphysical philosophical content of current Christianity, like Kierkegaard does and Dostoevsky does.
And he rejects also completely the Christian way of life.
That's the new move.
He doesn't want to go back to the early Christian community.
He thinks that's part of the problem.
You'll see, he thinks that there is this, I can tell you this, you won't understand it yet, but it's interesting.
He thinks that Christianity lost it from the moment it got started.
He says the only good Christian died on the cross, meaning you'll see when you get to the Antichrist few lectures down the line, he thinks that Jesus was very close to having things right.
But as soon as it fell into the hands of Paul and so forth, it was completely messed up.
And so that nobody even had a chance to live as a Christian.
He just does, I mean, the complicated thing is, I mean, Nietzsche has a very different idea of what these early Christians must have been like.
I think he would like the Dostoevsky picture of the early Christian community.
We could ask ourselves that when we get there.
He certainly wouldn't like anything in Kierkegaard.
You'll see that.
The Kierkegaard notion of unconditional commitment is something Nietzsche would find very confining or something like that.
We'll get to that.
He says conviction, he says commitments are prisons.
Confining is a good word for it.
But that's, you want to say something?
Good.
That's good.
Yeah?
Did he say that?
Where did you read that or hear that?
That's interesting.
Can you hear her?
The Pope recommends and likes the brothers Karamazov.
We have to take this into account.
Go ahead.
The Wikipedia article.
I see.
Okay, so now the news is from the web that the Pope likes the brothers.
What does he say about it?
Like the Brothers Karamatso?
Anybody else interesting on this list?
Sigmund Freud, yes, I've mentioned that to some of you.
I think after class, Freud thought that the idea that when Yvonne says every man wants to kill his father, this was very Freudian and had it.
He wrote a whole article about the brothers Kermatsov.
Yeah.
Okay, now why?
See, why would the Pope like it?
Let me think a minute.
But it's not, he does, obviously, he doesn't think he's the Grand Inquisitor.
But Dostoevsky thinks he's the Grand Inquisitor.
And so now what are we going to do about that?
Well, because certainly, I mean, from a Dostoevsky point of view, the Catholic Church is just as wrong for Protestants.
I mean, it's turning, but what's it got?
It's turned community into a bunch of a credo that everybody can believe.
It thinks that the whole world should be all converted to Christendom, or at least it used to.
I don't know what the current Pope thinks.
And it got rid of God.
That's pretty serious.
God as a supreme being.
But what?
Maybe he doesn't understand it.
Well, that's what I'm beginning to think as I talk out.
Or that's the uncharitable interpretation.
The uncharitable interpretation is he likes the account of agape and then the love and joy side of Christianity.
And he's ready to sort of forgive Dostoevsky for these other heresies because it is a wonderful defense of a version of the Christian way of life.
Certainly a good friend of mine, Charles Taylor, whom you don't know, but who's probably the most intellectual, philosophical, famous Catholic philosopher, loves Dostoevsky.
I have to ask him how he reconciles this.
I'll see what he has to say.
Because he does believe in the Supreme Being, but he likes, I think he just probably, they probably just think, well, Dostoevsky's wrong on that one, but he's right on so many other aspects of the Christian life.
Good.
Of course, he's against confession.
I mean, we can line up what he's against.
It doesn't leave all that much.
Just joy, maybe, which is a good thing.
Although, Pope Benedict doesn't strike me as particularly joyful.
I think we should stop discussing this and go back to your work.
I'm glad to hear it, anyway.
Anybody else have anything to say about this?
Okay, let's go on then.
Where is on?
So now we're going to do just a little, something I don't normally do at all, but I can't resist giving you some historical background and context for Nietzsche.
It's not the usual sort of existentialist thing to do.
It doesn't matter what the facts are.
It sort of matters how they live their lives.
So Heidegger, whom I mention every once in a while, or Kierkegaard too, sort of puts the facts of history just out of it.
I mean, Kierkegaard says that all you need to know about Jesus is that he, what is it, that he was a case of eternity and time.
Everything else is irrelevant.
What morality he preached, that he was a carpenter, that anything, according to Kierkegaard.
It's just that God became a human being at a certain place, at a certain time.
That's it.
And the who was that I'm going to say next?
Wait a second.
Besides, oh, Kierkegaard?
Oh, I was, it's, it's, Heidegger says himself that when he was teaching an Aristotle course, his courses, you can get them all, dozens of them, published.
Anyway, says about Aristotle, all you need to know about Aristotle is he lived, he did philosophy, and he died.
Now let's turn to the text.
So, and I sort of like that, but I'm so I'm apologizing for the fact that I'm going to give you a little bit of historical background.
They would consider it useless gossip, I think.
But so it turns out that Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky and Nietzsche all wrote at roughly the same time, around 1850.
And then, so Kierkegaard first, in 1850, that's when the time for fear and trembling, roughly.
Then Dostoevsky and Nietzsche, in a way, were at exactly the same time.
The Brothers Karamatsov is published in 1881, and The Gay Science in 1882.
You see, that's the kind of trivial fact that no one could resist mentioning.
And then the Twilight and The Antichrist are from 1888.
So this raises one interesting question, which you should keep in the back of your mind, and I'm ready to hear any suggestions you've got.
You'll see me worrying about it.
It is not, nobody knows how much Dostoevsky Nietzsche read, though it was available in German.
We'll come back to that.
Is there any evidence you should be asking yourself as you read the Nietzsche that Dostoevsky read the Brothers Karamatsov?
It's more likely, it looks like, that he read The Idiot, if he read any.
But it's fun to keep in mind.
There are hints, I think.
Maybe he did read The Brothers Kerenatsov.
So let's go on.
So, how much does Nietzsche know of his two greatest opponents?
Because he really, and Pascal was his third favorite opponent.
He really likes these people who share the whole anti-Platonic, anti-philosophical approach with him.
And so he feels that they're on the same wavelength.
And then he sees that they accept the Christian way of life.
That makes them the big existential opponents.
And so I'll read you some quotes about all that.
First, he'd heard about Kierkegaard, but he didn't have time to read him.
His best friend, Georg Brandes, wrote to him in 1888, that's when he's writing Twilight and Antichrist: quote: There is a Nordic thinker, Soren Kierkegaard, whose works would interest you if only they were translated.
See, unfortunately, they aren't in German.
They're only in Danish.
So that's a problem.
And he goes on, he is, in my view, this quote Georg Brandes says, one of the deepest psychologists on the whole there has ever, that there has ever been.
Where psychologist obviously doesn't mean somebody, existential psychologist who understanding of despair and being reborn and important things like that.
Nietzsche answers, for my next trip to Germany, I've resolved to occupy myself with the psychological problem of Kierkegaard.
Now, I don't know whether Nietzsche thinks he can read Danish or whether he supposes that by his next trip, he will be able to, that they will be translated.
But he doesn't get to, because Nietzsche, you know, you do know or probably know reading any of the introductions and stuff.
Nietzsche cracked up and went just totally crazy, but not in a dramatic sort of way first, raving and banging on the piano and saying that he was Jesus and Dionysius, and then sort of relapsed into a kind of coma for 11 years.
And that all happened so quickly after 1888, I don't know exactly the date, that he never got to read Kierkegaard.
But he did get involved in a way with Dostoevsky.
And you can see about that.
Maybe some of you noticed.
Has anybody noticed the notes in Twilight where they talked about Dostoevsky on 202 of Twilight in a footnote of a glossary of names when they decide to explain who Feodor Dostoevsky was, we have a quote from Nietzsche.
A few weeks ago, I did not even know the name of Dostoevsky.
A chance reach in a bookstore brought to my notice a work just translated into French.
Maybe that's how he's supposed to read Kierkegaard.
L'Esprit sout terrain, which is Notes from Underground.
The instinct of kinship, or what shall I call it, spoke immediately.
My joy was extraordinary.
So, and then it's skipping a little, whether he read all or any of the four great novels is unknown and so forth.
And on page 110 of Twilight, I assigned just this page 110 because I wanted you to just see it about two-thirds of the way down.
He says, Dostoevsky, the only psychologist, by the way, from whom I had anything to learn.
He's one of the happiest accidents of my life, even more than my discovery of Stendahl.
This profound human being who was ten times justified in despising the superficial Germans.
That's just an aside.
Kierkegaard, Nietzsche is Swiss, and German is his native language, from Basel, but he doesn't like the Germans at all.
I don't know if he likes the Swiss either.
I doubt it.
But there's probably no country, no culture he likes, but he dislikes Germans, particularly.
And so does Dostoevsky.
The only nice thing he ever says about Germans is Dr.
Herritzenstuck, the one who gave Dmitri the nuts.
Usually Germans are doctors in Dostoevsky, and usually they don't understand what's really going on.
They think it's brain fever, whereas it's really revelation.
Yeah.
Nietzsche.
The East is better than West.
I doubt it.
You have to show me that because at least Buddhism he can't stand because, of course, he's all for passionate involvement.
Non-attachment and meditation are just not his thing at all.
And so what he would find in the East, I don't know.
But of course, he doesn't like the West either because the West has been sold out since Homer, which he likes a lot, has been lost, so to speak, to anything good.
So, Nietzsche, Nietzsche has a hard time because he really sees through so much that other people accept.
And there's this, he has this line that he's doing philosophy with a hammer, which means not only that he's sort of hitting you over the head with what he thinks, you must have had this feeling when you read it, that he's sort of in your face, kind of screaming at you all the time and saying outrageous things, but he's, and that's his, so to speak, protest against the very style of doing philosophy, which was calm and ordered and reflective and impersonal.
For him, it's extremely involved and disordered and personal, and he just studies philosophy, but he doesn't really want to write that way.
Why am I saying this?
I get off of this strange tax.
Let me think of a minute.
Oh, about East and West.
Oh, yeah, just that he's against all of this, and that his style would be the furthest from any kind of serenity, which he would probably think of as Eastern.
And his style is also farthest from any kind of theoretical rationality, which he thinks of as Western.
So I was just saying, well, with a hammer.
Now I got it back.
When he says he philosophizes with a hammer, he doesn't really mean that he's hitting you over the head with everything, although he does that, and it's important that he does that, because he's so radical breaking with it.
But he says he's testing all the ideas that people believe in, and sort of knocking them to see if they're hollow.
And they all turn out to be hollow.
He's the most rectangular questioner that everybody believes that ever was, I think.
And after Nietzsche, it's very much harder to believe in a lot of the things that people believed in before he went around hitting them with a hammer.
So, where were we?
You want to say something?
Read your mind?
Go ahead, what?
By Socrates?
Yes.
He said, it seems like Socrates testing beliefs to see if they hold up.
And why is it so radically different than Socrates?
There's something way that Socrates tests them, which is something that he disapproves of completely.
What would it be?
I forget how many of you, I think I asked you this, have read any Socrates, have read the Apology and Prato and things that people do read in high school sometimes.
And okay, well, Socrates, you wouldn't know this then, but he's going around testing all these Athenian beliefs by rational means.
He's seeing how much they can be defended against any objections and how they can be self-critical and stand up to and be shown to be reasonable or else be rejected.
I mean, that's not how Nietzsche's tested.
Nietzsche's testing them in a much more what?
He would say genealogical way.
He's trying to tell you sort of how they developed, what needs that people had that they helped, and how they kept people from being strong and mature, and is what's wrong with them.
And Socrates, this is part of today's lecture, and Socrates is, after all, remember, you can read it, is the ultimate decadent, because Socrates needs rational arguments to defend what he's doing and tell him what to do.
Nietzsche thinks that's all wrong in the name of something very interesting.
We'll get to it in a minute.
So, where are we?
I'm just reading, okay, on 110, did I read it?
Yes.
Okay, so now it's funny what I'm reading is different than what I wrote here.
So I have to think about this.
Very interesting.
Where does he say what I have written down here?
I've written the following as if it was on Twilight page 110, but I don't see it.
If you see it, let me know.
And if it isn't there, where could it be?
But here is what I quote: Nietzsche says, ah, maybe that's what I just read on 202.
No, I don't know where it is.
It's interesting.
He says to somebody, I treasure him, that's Dostoevsky, as the most valuable psychological material I know.
I am in a remarkable way thankful to him, even though he always goes against my deepest instincts.
Similar to my relation to Pascal, whom I almost love because he's taught me so much, the only logical Christian.
That is, Pascal is completely wrong, but he's wrong in this very deep way.
Now, where?
I don't see that.
Do you see that?
Where did I get it?
Well, if I can't find it in a minute, I just go to you next tonight.
Okay, I don't know where I got it.
So, now, did Dostoevsky know any Nietzsche?
That's the next question.
No, but it's much more interesting.
Much more interesting than sort of history of influences, as far as I've been.
Dostoevsky was such a genius, he made up Nietzsche.
There's a character in the possessed named Kirilov, who's very Nietzschean.
There is a lot of Nietzsche talk in the brothers Karamatsov.
We haven't paid attention to it, but we're going to.
That's why you should bring the brothers back again.
Dostoevsky is making up exactly the position that, well, lots of positions that Nietzsche holds.
There was one just going across my mind.
I'm thinking.
No, I think it would get out of the order to do it now, so let's not talk about that yet.
So it turns out then that Dostoevsky and Nietzsche have a lot in common, Dostoevsky says, Nietzsche says, and I think Dostoevsky would agree in the sense that he made him up and knows his views without ever having read a word of him.
So we're going to look at what they have in common today for the rest of the time.
And I'm going to put off until later what it is they disagree about.
I've already said they disagree about whether it's a good thing or a bad thing to live, the kind of life that Dostoevsky thinks is the Christian life, and say whether it's nice to be like Alyosha, a good thing or not.
We'll worry about that later.
Finally, and then when we do, just to sort of show where we are, because we're so near the end of the course, trying to see how Nietzsche's like Dostoevsky, then we can see how he's not like Dostoevsky.
And in the end, you have to ask yourself, sort of which side are you on, because they're so radically opposed.
In the last lecture, we have to talk about how you would decide what's at stake who you like and think has important advice to give you.
But that's ahead of the story.
So let's go back.
We start with Nietzsche on the Homeric Greeks.
We're going to see later what Nietzsche has to say about the Athenian Greeks, philosophical Greeks, is going to look a lot like Dostoevsky.
But before we do that, we have to look at a distinction, which, if you don't know it, will confuse you very much, because Nietzsche talks about the Greeks, and sometimes he means the Homeric Greeks, and sometimes he means the Greeks in Athens at the time of Socrates, which is about 700 years after Homer.
And he's all for the Homeric Greeks, as you'll see in a minute, and totally against the Socratic Athenian philosophical Greeks.
And they're called Hellens, H-E-L-L-E-N-S, the Homeric ones.
You just need to know that sort of like code to follow what's going on.
And the next stage is called Hellenistic, because it's a sort of, it's a kind of copy or something, or degeneration of the Hellens.
So he's for the Hellens, but he's against the Hellenistic Greeks.
And that's just, I say that only just so you won't be confused as you read it.
I wonder if they're in this list of names at the end, whether we, I never thought to look, whether they tell you about that.
No, they don't tell you.
Nobody tells you.
It just goes by.
Why they're called Helens, I don't know.
It has nothing to do with Helen of Troy, the wife of Agamemnon and stuff.
I have no idea.
Does anybody over there know why these certain Greeks are called Helens?
Well, anyway, just keep your eye open.
So now we're going to read Nietzsche on the Greeks.
He thought these Homeric Greeks, how many read the Odyssey?
Hooray.
How many have read the Iliad?
Wow.
Ahead of me, practically.
I mean, I read the Odyssey over and over, but the Iliad is too much for me.
Read it once.
But anyway, I teach the Odyssey in Philosophy VI, but I dare do I teach the Iliad.
So, but in both books, you can see the Greeks being passionate, involved, and, and now comes this interesting Nietzsche way of looking at it, trusting their instincts.
That's what we have to talk about for a while.
Because it sounds like if you just use the normal word instinct, that it would mean something automatic, like birds had instincts for building nests and so forth.
But that's not at all what Nietzsche means by people's instincts.
It's not something that you are born with, something innate.
It's something you think you acquire by a long experience.
What makes it instinct for Nietzsche is that it's unreflective, spontaneous action.
And in all sorts of domains where, by lots of work and experience, you develop a skill so that you can just immediately, appropriately respond, then you've got that kind of good instinct.
For instance, in sports, if you're good at sports so that you hit the tennis ball exactly where you want to hit it, and just as soon as it's coming over the net, you're already running in the right direction.
That's your instinct for tennis.
Certainly, it isn't innate, you weren't born with it.
But what makes it an instinct is you don't think about it, you don't reflect.
If you stop to reflect, of course, you miss the point.
You can't reflect.
That's what's interesting about.
And the highest level of human behavior is instinctual in this sense: that people have all kinds of skills for dealing with other people, for sports, for music, for thinking, and reading, and so forth.
And when they are good at those, when they are at their best, they don't reflect.
They act spontaneously.
And if they do reflect, they're lost.
There's this baseball player.
I keep forgetting his name.
Somebody knows each time.
Noblau, something like that.
Who, what?
Yeah, probably.
What's his name?
I can hear.
Yes, right, right.
Exactly.
Who, I don't know what became of him, but I was fascinated from a Nietzschean perspective that he started thinking about what he was doing.
And as soon as he, he was, what, an outfielder?
And as soon as he's.
What's that?
I couldn't hear you.
I see.
And when he did, he started thinking about what he was doing.
Is that when it happened?
Well, let's go through this because I'm very interested in this case.
And could he do it from the outfield okay?
That's what I thought.
I think he was out of baseball as soon as he started thinking about it because once you start thinking about it, then you start trying hard not to think about it.
And that doesn't help a bit.
It makes it worse.
I think he just became reflective.
He just, it's a perfectly Nietzschean, wonderful thing.
It's as if he had suddenly become Socratic.
And any skill where you have this kind of instinct, if you start thinking about it and reflecting on it, you're finished.
You can't do it anymore.
You probably can't even think about how you ride a bicycle or riding a bicycle without falling over.
So Nietzsche's got this wonderful idea that the whole philosophical tradition has missed this interesting point: that the highest form of human activity has to be unreflective.
And you can't think about it.
And even if you did, you wouldn't do you any good.
I mean, not only, it doesn't do any good to think about it, there are no rules for how to throw the ball each time or play the beautiful, play the flute well or anything like that.
The rules, you may start with rules, but you leave them behind when you become a master or an expert.
And so there's no rules that you could possibly give somebody or find out.
So you wouldn't get anything positive from thinking about it.
But worse, you couldn't do it if you started thinking about it.
So Nietzsche's got onto something terrific.
And on 59, he says at the bottom of the page: everything good is instinct.
The bottom of that section, out of the page.
Everything good is instinct and consequently easy, necessary, free.
Effort is an objection.
There's this funny story, a colleague of mine told me that he didn't like, Nietzsche didn't like Beethoven's music.
And what he said about it was, to explain that he didn't like it, is that Beethoven's music sweats.
I mean, this is just another example.
I mean, it's too effortful.
He tries too hard.
He has to write everything over and over again.
I mean, Mozart just wrote it down easily.
So Nietzsche should like Mozart.
But in fact, his favorite composer was Bizet.
And you can make what you can of that.
Nietzsche actually composed music.
You can get a CD of Nietzsche music.
It's terrible, absolutely hopeful.
So we won't go on about that.
But on page 59, about five lines down, he says more of this.
A well-constituted human being, a happy one, must perform certain actions instinctively, shrinks from other actions.
He transports the order of which he is the physiological representative into his relations with other human beings and with things.
In a formula, his virtue is a consequence of his happiness.
Never mind that.
That's not going to help any.
But mainly, what you get is the idea, now what would it be to be a good person?
Now, not just a good baseball player at second bass or a good flute player, but a good human being.
Well, he has in mind what other people have called, Aristotle, in fact, called a man of practical wisdom.
It would be a woman or a man who had learned how to be an expert in their culture.
So that, as Aristotle put it, they always do the appropriate thing at the appropriate time in the appropriate way.
That is, and to some extent, you're all on the way to doing that.
You maybe once had to learn the rule, never tell a lie.
But then later you would learn, if you were, and I think Nietzsche's right, you learn that that doesn't work, that kind of rule.
You learn, as one of my TAs pointed out, a kid learns that after they've been at a birthday party in which the ice cream was melted and everybody was fighting and the parents kept saying, boys, it's dreadful.
As the parents leave, they tell the other parents, we had a wonderful time.
And then the kid thinks, but they told me I never should tell a lie.
And then he has to have a new rule.
Well, never tell a lie unless it makes people feel better, or something like that.
But that won't work either, because sometimes you should tell people the truth, even if it makes them feel bad, it'll help in the long run.
Or even if it doesn't, you should.
But anyway, finally, if you tell truths and lies enough in lots of different situations and you're willing to suffer the consequences and feel bad when you do it wrong, meaning that it leads to some kind of mess, and good when you do it right, you finally understand how to be truthful, which is not the same as telling the truth all the time or not telling the truth any other time.
It's being skilled, having an instinct, automatically, just the words come out of your mouth, that is either the hard truth that the person needs to hear or some kind of way of avoiding covering up the truth.
And that's what it is to become a person of practical wisdom.
And they are the best that the culture can produce.
There's another writer who calls them cultural virtuosos.
That is, you too can do this.
Maybe you are already to some extent able to do what in your culture is what is recognized, at least in retrospect, as having been the right thing to do.
And that's the person that Nietzsche admires.
And notice it's not a philosopher.
And it doesn't require passing through logic and mediation and reflection at all.
You may have to start with rules, probably not.
All kids don't have to learn rules.
And you certainly have to leave rules behind.
You can't get there by logic or rules.
You get there by experience, involvement, taking risks, and learning from your mistakes.
That's Nietzsche's picture of how you become a good person.
Now, let's see who we are.
That gives you perfection in living, as he calls it, somewhere here, I think.
Didn't I just read that, or did I just write that?
I guess that's my way of calling it.
Perfection in living is what you get when you do, if you're a culturo virtuoso.
And okay, here's what I was going to say next.
But notice that it's a higher immediacy of a weird sort.
That's really interesting to me.
I mean, both Nietzsche and Kierkegaard, and I'm sure Dostoevsky too, would be against lower immediacy, which is just sort of doing whatever spontaneously comes into your mind without having developed any skill, without having gone through the risks of telling lies when you should have told the truth in retrospect and vice versa, and whatever, learning to be a second baseman and not have to think about it.
Once you've done that, you're not in lower immediacy anymore.
Because lower immediacy is just giving in to your spontaneous, untrained impulses.
And Nietzsche's not for that.
That's not instinct.
I don't know what his word for that would be.
But you have to pass to higher immediacy, which is all this training that you go through by learning, but without reflecting, trying, and making mistakes, and getting wise in your whatever domain you're in.
But that's a kind of higher immediacy that you get to without going through mediation.
And mediation wouldn't help, and of course, mediation might stick you there if you were like the guy who, the second base person.
And if you get too reflective, you won't be able to ever get to this.
So Nietzsche's got this very interesting idea.
He can share the philosophical distrust of people who just act on their impulses and come up with a view that there is a higher way of acting instinctively on your impulses, which is the highest thing human beings.
And so you don't act like a child, not that kind of spontaneity, not just giving in to every desire and every impulse.
You act out of long experience, and that makes you focused and effective.
And that's what the wise people acquire.
And then they can just immediately, directly act.
Another example, by the way, how much, I mean, you might think that chess players at least have to think that that's reflective and mediated and analytic.
But some of you probably are chess players.
And if you are, you may know that chess grandmasters, after lots of chess experience, playing maybe a million games, because they have to play games sort of day and night, not only real games, but go through all the book games or now play the computer and so forth.
But finally, if you're a grandmaster, you can play chess, it blitz chess, at, say, 10 seconds a move and play at pretty master level.
Or you can play, you know, 20 people at once, which you couldn't have, you don't stop at each board and figure out what's happening and what happened up to now and what you were going to do next.
You just look at the board and your arm goes out and does something.
And that can, at the extreme, this is really Nietzsche would love this, blitz chess.
Yeah, you play at one second a move.
The masters are just, their arms are just going out and making a move before they can even take in what's on the board.
And they don't need to.
If you train your instincts enough, if you really get to this level of mastery, then you can, without any reflection, play better chess than anybody of us could ever play who was trying to figure out what to do.
Okay, so that's, I'm just a big pitch for Nietzsche on this.
I think it's a great idea that he's got there.
And now, again, if you're a good person in a culture and you're a kind of grand master of the culture, then so you take advantage of or get the most out of every situation, because that's just like making the master level move in that situation.
On 189, he's talking about this.
He's talking about how you could get the law, which would be, I'm back to saying the law might be something like never tell a lie.
But then what you want is you've got to live it.
You can't just take it as a kind of law.
It has to become unconscious, where unconscious means unreflective.
It's nothing sort of Freudian.
So that a complete automatism of instinct is achieved.
Again, that doesn't mean that you become like a machine.
It just means that you become totally unreflective.
It's the precondition of any kind of mastery and a kind of perfection in the art of living.
Oh, that's where I got the.
And I think that's all I need to say about that.
Yeah.
So that's more that I've said about all I want to say about instinct.
To sum up, noble instinct, which the Homeric Greeks had, is the source of impulsive, spontaneous, unreflective, but totally successful action.
Generally successful.
Something may be different than you realize that your past training may lead you astray.
But basically, you do the appropriate thing at the appropriate time in the appropriate way, and you, in a sense, win at whatever you're doing.
And now, so much for the Homeric Greeks.
Now we get to the Socratic Greeks.
They had lost it.
That's what he's talking about on page 43.
And this is typically radical new Nietzschean idea.
You've got to realize, and since most of you haven't been reading yet, Socrates' defense, Plato's defense of Socrates and what a great guy he was because he made all the Athenians reflect and justify anything they did.
That's the hero of our culture, Socrates.
Plato was a great, what does he need?
Who are the people you hire to put the right spin on what you're doing?
Sort of a press agent or what's agent?
There's another word for it, isn't there?
Yes, a public relations person.
Yeah, Plato was a great public relations person for Socrates.
He put this incredible spin on it, how great Socrates was for Athens, what luck they had to have him.
The Athenians were smart enough not to buy it.
They weren't completely decadent yet.
And they thought that he was a disaster for reasons that you ought to be able to figure out.
If you haven't figured it out, you think about it.
He's telling these people who presumably have at least some remaining instincts about what's the right and wrong thing to do, that they shouldn't do anything until they reflect on it and justify it.
He goes around stopping everybody on the three corners and asking them why are they doing what they are doing, which they thought they just knew what they were doing.
And they discover they can't explain what they were doing, and they sort of again become like the second baseman.
They aren't able to do anything.
By the time they leave Socrates, they're just in a kind of trance.
They know that he's taken away from them their ability to do what they were doing, and he hasn't given them really any ability to justify what they're doing, because it turns out Socrates is always, he's got this pure, critical kind of intelligence, which has nothing constructive to say.
And so Nietzsche thinks he's a very bad guy.
And interestingly enough, Kierkegaard wrote his PhD thesis on Socrates.
It was called The Concept of Irony.
And Kierkegaard thought that Socrates was an interesting case of somebody who undermined the values of the culture.
Because the values of the culture aren't rational.
And you can't define why it's rational to do what the ethics of that culture says to do.
It just is what the ethics of that culture says to do.
There is no right answer about what you're saying, Nietzsche thinks.
So the so, and Kierkegaard thinks.
So Socrates, by questioning the values, the morals of the Greeks, insofar as he succeeded, undermined their intuitive ability to do what in that culture was the appropriate thing to do.
So Socrates turns out to be dangerous.
And now we read a lot about Socrates in here, where Nietzsche is sort of taking him apart.
What he says is that in the essence of Socrates, the instincts had become, as he puts it, about six lines down on 43, the instincts, no, no, no, not the, four lines down.
Everywhere the instincts were in anarchy.
Everywhere people were but five steps from excess.
They had monstrous souls.
And that was the universal danger.
That means they couldn't count on what they just did spontaneously.
So now it's sort of complicated.
Instinct means acting just spontaneously without reflection.
If you're healthy, psychologically, that's good.
But if you've lost your healthy psycho estate, then just doing what you spontaneously feel like doing is back in lower immediacy.
So the Athenians, for reasons that he doesn't go into, but just so you can sort of see that this isn't just craziness on Nietzsche's part.
Thucydides, in his story about the Peloponnesian Wars, he sort of explains how the Athenians fell apart.
They were just wonderfully instinctive and had a kind of consensus about what to do, but then they had a plague which wiped out a whole lot of them.
Then they got in a war trying to be an empire.
And then they started sending out, you know, they had a direct democracy.
So every day they could vote on what to do.
And then they'd send out the generals to attack some country, say Iraq now.
And then they'd change their mind and they'd call the generals back and court-martial them.
And then they'd send some other general out to attack some other country.
They got completely confused and hopeless.
And they were in this confused state just at the time that Plato and Socrates came along.
Nietzsche just takes that.
We know that for granted when he says that their instincts were an anarchy, because that's what Thucydides says.
Nobody knows anything about it except what they read in Thucydides.
So, and he says at the bottom of 42, Socrates saw behind his aristocratic Athenians.
He grasped that his case, the idiosyncrasy of his case, was already no longer exceptional.
His case was that he had lost his instincts.
The same kind of degeneration was everywhere silently preparing itself.
The old Athens was coming to an end.
And Socrates understood that all the world had need of him, his expedient, his cure, his personal art of self-preservation.
Everywhere the instincts were in anarchy, and now skipping a little, the instincts want to play the tyrant.
We must find a counter-tyrant who is stronger.
And then when you go down a little more, where's the counter-tyrant?
Well, the counter-tyrant is on the next section.
If you go down to section 10, if one needs to make a tyrant of reason, as Socrates did, then there must exist no little danger of something else playing the tyrant.
Rationality was at that time divined as a savior.
Neither Socrates nor his embolists were free to be rational or not.
As they wished, it was driguer.
It was their last expedient.
The fanaticism with which the whole Greek thought throws itself at rationality, that means Socrates, Plato particularly, betrays a state of emergency.
One was in peril, one had only one choice, either to perish or be absurdly rational.
And that's so that's what happens according to him.
Let me just catch up.
Socrates is the prime example.
And on 43, we've got that already.
That makes him a pseudo-Greek in the sense that he's not like the good old Homeric Greeks.
And this is where you've got to keep track of who's what.
So in number two, on 39, about the very last line of the page, I recognize Socrates and Plato as symptoms of decay as agents of the dissolution of Greece, as pseudo-Greeks, as anti-Greek.
Well, you get confused unless you realize he means anti-Homeric Greeks, that they've lost it.
They've lost this wonderful sort of mastery and skill that the Homeric Greek had.
You can see on 41 that those are the real Greeks.
At the bottom of section 4, he says, I seek to understand out of what idiosyncrasy that Socratic question, equation, reason equal virtue, equal happiness, derives.
That bizarrest of equations, and one which has a particular, has in particular all the instincts of the older Hellens.
There you see it, against it.
That's the Homeric ones.
And these later Greeks used reason to control their instincts, and that was a fatal law.
On 43, he's talking about all that.
Read that.
I can read that.
Yeah, okay.
And all that he calls decadence on the next page, on 44, the end of 11.
To have to combat one's instincts, that's a formula for decadence.
As long as life is ascending, happiness and instinct are one.
Now you can see why.
I mean, if you could just spontaneously, skillfully, and generally successfully go through life as if you were a sort of champion, a master of whatever, that would make you, that would keep you happy.
And reason is not part of that.
Reason would undermine that.
Now, you might, and that means that philosophers, he now generalizes, because those are the first philosophers, and they started this thing about reason.
And that means that philosophers are decadent.
On 119, about 50 lines down.
But the philosophers are the decadence of Hellenism.
See, there, that's the Athenians.
The counter movement against the old, the noble taste, that is, spontaneously doing the noble thing.
Against the agonal instinct, that means the instinct for confrontation and combat of a good sort in games, in the Olympic Games, for instance, or in the kind of in their wars.
Agonal instinct against the polis.
That's against the city when it worked.
See, Athens, well, it worked for a while, and then everybody did have good instinct.
For those who know any history, under Pericles, then it was a perfect, perfect democracy.
They all voted and they all agreed, and everything went very well.
But they've lost it.
So, and they've lost the sense of the unity of the city, of the polis, against the value of the race, against the authority of tradition.
You've got to have a tradition, of course, if you're going to be able to learn to do things the right way, because what the right way is, is simply what's good according to the tradition.
And if you start questioning the tradition, the way Socrates and Plato did, saying, well, that's just, you know, what people say and what people think, we don't want that.
We don't want to know what's good, to put it in contemporary terms.
We want a theory of what's right.
We want a theory of justice, never mind what you just happen to intuitive justice.
That's what leads them wrong, makes them wrong.
So it's the against all that.
The Socratic virtues were preached because the Greeks had lost them.
Excitable, timid, fickle, comedians, everyone.
They had more than enough reason to let morality be preached to them.
Not that it would have done any good.
The big words and fine attitudes are suitable to decadence.
This is just an outrageous thing in the face of the 2,000 years of Socrates' worship.
This is Nietzsche taking on everything.
Let's see now.
Oh, yeah, I wrote here.
And why should we believe his view about what was going on in Greece?
Well, partly it doesn't matter.
He's making up his story.
They're against the other interpretation.
But at least you should realize that he was an authority on Greek culture.
He was a superstar of Greek philology, which means knowing the Greek language and everything written in the Greek language.
You can get everything written in Athenian Greek on one CD, I read somewhere.
And that's quite surprising.
Nietzsche knew it all.
And he was so smart that he got tenure at the age of 24 at the University of Basel.
He was an absolute superstar.
Then he just quit all that and went out and wrote these books.
So now, let me see where we are.
Okay, now back for a minute to Kierkegaard and Dostoevsky and how they deal with it.
Kierkegaard is still, remember I said, the last one who sees that mediation is a stage that it's a good thing to go through.
Because he understands that it's a good thing to question the rationality of your superstitions and your phobias and your fanaticisms and your desires.
And that it's, and if you use philosophy that way, it's a means to get rid of lower immediacy and make a place for higher immediacy.
That's Kierkegaard.
And that's interesting.
And Kierkegaard would say, but now why is Kierkegaard then not like a philosopher?
Well, why?
Does anybody know?
I mean, he likes mediation, but it's a means, not an end.
It's a means of getting rid of lower immediacy, thereby a means to sort of clear a space for higher immediacy.
But it's not something that you should build your life around.
And that's what philosophers do, according to Kierkegaard and Nietzsche.
And Dostoevsky, they're interested in people who just not, they're not upset with people who study philosophy.
They're people who they're people who live, like Plato and Socrates said philosophers should live, namely detached, theoretical, denying their bodies, denying any involvement with local concerns and so forth.
So, but Kierkegaard is the last of the existentialists that has any place of value for rationality and reflection and philosophy.
Because for Dostoevsky and Nietzsche, philosophy isn't even a meme.
Now, we haven't talked about Dostoevsky.
Dostoevsky doesn't directly attack Socrates, but he does certainly attack Western, detached, critical rationality.
And how does he attack it?
Well, who's the philosopher in the Brothers Karamatsky?
Who went to the university and studied natural philosophy?
Yvonne.
And yes.
And who's the detached one?
And the rational one, the theoretical one.
Well, Yvonne.
He's the incarnation of, well, that word is better not.
He's the paradigm case of a philosophy-minded person.
And what becomes of Yvonne?
Well, he's dangerous and sick and suffering, and there's nothing good you can say about it, but he's decadent in the Nietzschean decade.
He had one moment in which he did something impulsive.
He picked up the peasant.
And if he had gone on with something impulsive and confessed to the police, who knows what would have happened.
But he managed to.
There's this joke: if you have this intense desire to do something, you should lie down till it goes away.
Well, that's how Yvonne, when Yvonne has an impulsive, intense desire to do something, his attitude is, well, let's wait till tomorrow, it'll go away.
That's what happened.
So Yvonne, who was from the beginning a detached spectator, an eyewitness, denies his involvement in the world, denies his involvement in life, and that makes him sick and dangerous.
And now we get back, yeah, we just have time, to the way Socrates is decadent and how that's related to the way Yvonne is decadent.
I think I've got half of it done already.
Yes, so there was the decadence.
I'm just making sure catching up with myself with that.
Well, we've got to add something from page 39 because it's people, now we're switching to something specific.
How do philosophers and Yvonne relate to life?
And at the top of 39, Nietzsche says, in every age, the wisest have passed the identical judgment on life.
It's worthless.
He's being ironic about wises.
He means the people who we take to be wisest, like Plato and Socrates.
Everywhere and always, their mouths have uttered the same sound, a sound full of doubt, full of melancholy, full of weariness with life, full of opposition to life.
Even Socrates said as he died, to die that means to be a long time sick.
That is, his whole life was sick.
And now that he's dying, he's getting well.
He said, I owe a cock to the savior, Aescalabius.
That means that if you read the footnote, that you give a cock, a rooster, to your doctor as paying him off when you're recovering from an illness.
So, Socrates is recovering from an illness.
What illness?
Being alive.
And now that he's dying, he considers this being cured of being alive, and he says he's going to give the doctor a reward.
So Nietzsche says, even Socrates has had enough of it.
Always, what that proves?
What's the point?
Well, skipping a little, here at any rate, there's something sick.
That's our retort.
One ought to take a closer look at them, these wisest.
Were all of them perhaps no longer steady on their legs?
Belated, tottery, decadence?
Does wisdom perhaps appear on earth as a raven which is inspired by the smell of tarian?
Nietzsche just goes on and on saying marvelous things like that.
And now we get to where he converges with Yvonne on 40.
It's about the value of life.
Remember what Yvonne is up to.
He thinks that life isn't valuable, the world isn't valuable, that he's going to kill himself when he gets to be 30.
He'll kill himself sooner, but he can't quite get over the traction of the sticky green leaves on the one hand and cater katarina on the other.
But as soon as he does, he's going to get out of this life.
And so now we've got to connect this with this issue about the value of life on page 40, about 15 lines down.
Judgments, value judgments concerning life, for or against, can, in the last retort, never be true.
This is Nietzsche's view.
They possess value only as symptoms.
They come into consideration only as symptoms.
As judgments, they're stupidities.
And their symptoms, what, of sickness, decadence.
One must reach out and try to grasp this astonishing finesse that the value of life cannot be estimated.
Not by a living man because he's a party to the dispute.
That means, remember, that what I, Yvonne, didn't realize that he's just alive already.
He can't just join it or leave it the way you join or leave a fraternity, a sorority, or whatever.
So it's a party to it.
Indeed, its object, and not the judge of it.
Dead people can't judge life because they're dead, and living people can't judge life because they're too close to it.
For a philosopher to see a problem in the value of life, thus even constitutes an objection to him.
Well, that's exactly Yvonne.
He's a philosopher.
He's asking about the value of life, and it's an objection.
He's got a position, Nietzsche's saying, that nobody can have, namely, as if he was standing outside of life, judging it, weighing it.
He's making exactly the same objection that Dostoevsky made.
It constitutes an objection, a question mark as to his wisdom, a piece of unwisdom.
What?
And these wise men, they have not only been decadent, they are not even wise, and so forth.
Okay, so, and now, just a quick reference to the brothers.
On page 224, you don't have it with you because I didn't tell you to bring it.
You can look on 224.
They have a brief discussion, Alyasha and Yvonne, about the value of life.
On page 224, Yvonne is saying that he loves the blue sky and the sticky leaves and sins.
And do you understand?
He says to Alyasha, I understand, Yvonne.
One loves with one's inside, with one's stomach.
You said it so well.
I am awfully glad you have such a longing for life.
I think everyone should love life above everything in the world.
And then Yvonne backs off and says, Love life more than the meaning of it.
See, that's the wrong move.
So step outside now and ask whether you should love it, depending on what it means.
Because Alyasha answers, certainly, love it regardless of logic, as you say.
It must be regardless of logic.
It's only then one can understand the meaning of it.
I thought so for a long time.
And so it's the same point.
Alyasha is saying to Yvonne, you can't step outside and ask about the meaning of life and decide whether to be judging it, whether it's good or bad, whether you should join it or not.
You're in it, and if this is something that Nietzsche thinks too, if you get really involved in it, you will be joyful and appreciate it.
But if you stop and withdraw and ask yourself whether you should become involved in it, you're lost.
They both agree on that.
Now I just got time to finish.
So the philosopher is weak and decadent.
Otherwise, he wouldn't even try to step outside of life and become detached and judge it.
That's what Nietzsche says on 55.
And the way he says it is very interesting.
Look at this on 55.
Where?
55.
No, I'm not on 55.
Here we are.
Okay, and then in number five, on 55, it's about five lines down.
For a condemnation of life by the living is, after all, no more than a symptom of a certain kind of life.
The question whether the condemnation is just or unjust has not been raised at all.
One would have to be situated outside life.
So that's the same point again.
Now I want the punchline at the top of five.
If one has grasped the blasphemousness of such a rebellion against life as has in Christian morality become virtually sacrosanct, one has fortunately therewith grasped something else as well.
The uselessness, illusoriness, absurdity, falsity of such a rebellion.
Remember what Yvonne's chapter is called, where he gives back the world?
Called rebellion.
And this is the kind of little hint where you wonder whether this whole diatribe isn't about Yvonne, and maybe Dostoevsky has read it.
At least his name for stepping outside of life and rejecting it is rebellion.
So is Dostoevsky's.
And they both agree that if you step outside of life, it only shows that you're sick.
No, I think I don't need to read that.
I think I'm just about done.
Yeah, that's it.
Okay.
Next time, we're going to start with talking about the gay science.
So read the passages in the gay science that I tell you about.