We stopped last time just at the point where, if I hadn't run out of time, I would have liked to get a tiny bit further because the ending is such fun, if you can consider all this suffering fun.
That is, it's interesting that it looks like there's going to be a happy ending.
I mean, I'll go back one little step so that you know where we are.
Remember that they're having this debate because Orestes has asked Pylades what to do and to do it for the sake of whom the Furies or Apollo.
And Pylades says, as he naturally would, being a complete detached stranger spectator, the one sentence he has is: do it for the new gods, do it for Apollo.
So that so Orestes has to, at the last minute, shift out of the emotional outrage that he's worked himself up into to even consider splitting his mother's throat into a kind of cold logical frame of mind in which he's got to prove to himself and his mother that it is the right thing, meaning the necessary logical thing to do, that he kills her.
The right thing is, of course, all up for grabs, depending on all these other issues about what counts as right.
But whatever it is, he's got to work himself up into giving a logical defense, which means it's Apollo right thing, to kill his mother.
And they have this great debate.
By the way, I was telling the TAs three years ago, the Berkeley Rep people did the Orestea, and they obviously didn't understand what was going on.
And they felt that, of course, if he's working himself up to kill his mother, he must be getting more and more excited and frantic, and she must be getting more and more excited and frantic.
So they were yelling these logical lines: if this, if then, and counterexamples, and if and things like this one, which is where the last one, where she says, Take care, your mother's curse, like dogs will drag you down.
She screams at him in this version, and he says, How shall I escape my father's curse if I fail here?
But that's not the kind of screaming thing.
That's a debate.
He's saying, Well, if you want to discuss it on the level of fate and say, You couldn't help what you did, it was fate.
Then I can't help what I'm doing.
That's fate, too.
And that's the whole way it is.
He's become completely cold and logical, and he's done it for Apollo.
And now what's going to happen?
That's the question.
Well, one more line.
I said it, but I said it so fast that I'm afraid you missed it.
And the translation would get you way off track.
At the bottom of 126, Orestes says that indeed the terror of your green saw things to come clearly.
And she says, oh, clear, CCL, he says, you killed and it was wrong, now suffer wrong.
Now that can't be right because he doesn't think what he's doing is wrong.
He thinks that what he's doing is logically justified of killing his, killing the woman who killed his father.
And the translation is wrong.
It says, you did it.
The Greek says, as far as I can tell reading other translations, you did a terrible thing, now suffer a terrible thing.
That's okay.
And so he does it for impersonal reasons.
A student, I think last time, somebody here asked, what does it mean in the middle of 126 to say it will be you who kill yourself, not I?
I sort of messed that up.
I forget what I said, but it wasn't altogether wrong.
I said somehow it's fate and what you did that requires me to kill you.
That's right.
But the right thing to say is he's become identified in his mind with cold, impartial justice.
And so he's saying it will, that is, it amounts to saying, I'm just an agent.
I'm just an executioner.
I've got no emotional involvement in this thing.
It's all your fault that you got into it, and I'm just standing by and executing the results.
I mean, he's trying to make himself as cold, impartial, and impersonal as he can as he does it.
And so much for that.
Now let's go.
Now we're going on.
That was from last time.
Now comes, and this is where I would have started ended, the seeming happy ending.
As I say, this play is full of reversals, but I didn't get a chance to talk about this reversal.
It looks like it's happened.
I just described to you the way the killing looks to her and to him as if he did it with cold, impartial, Apollonian justice, and now the curse should be over.
He didn't perpetuate the fury-motivated killings that have been going on in the house of Atreus for three generations into the next generation.
He stopped it.
And that's what the chorus thinks, and that's what he thinks.
And everybody's happy.
This is the happy ending on 127, bottom of the page.
All that Luxius, you know who that is by now, Apollo, who on Parnassus holds the huge and deep cleft in the ground, shrilled aloud by guile that is no guile, returns now to assault the wrong done and growing old.
This is going to need a lot of explaining.
Divinity keeps, we know not how, strength to resist the power of the strength to resist surrender to the wicked.
That means, all of this means, look, Apollo's doing it right.
It's done out in the open.
It's done in a fair debate.
And we're resisting these bad guys.
The power that holds the sky's majesty wins our worship.
Apollo won.
Light is here to behold Apollo again.
The big bit that held our house is taken away.
Remember the bit goes back to the bit they kept had on Ephigenia to keep her from cursing Agamemnon when he killed her.
But then Clytemnestra says that she killed Agamemnon in the name of Ephigenia's furies.
So there's still curses going on, even though people are trying to muzzle them, they're there.
But when what is it to have the bit taken away?
Well, that's that logic I was talking about.
She gets to state her case out in the open, giving all the arguments for her position.
It's like a law trial.
He gets to, she's the defense.
The prosecution, which is him, gets to refute all of her arguments.
Nothing is kept secret, and she loses.
And then the big bit is taken away.
It's not a question of underground seething resentments and revenges.
It's a murder, and the murderer has to pay for it.
And I want to say one more thing.
I don't remember whether I said it last time or not.
There's a kind of bump in the story that Aeschylus can't fix, namely that Apollo, who for him is one of the sky gods, the god of light, the god of everything out in the open, has a priestess who lives in a cave underground, and that's a bit embarrassing, but he can't get rid of it.
So he says it, Luxius, who on Parnassus holds the huge and deep cleft in the ground and so forth.
And he tries to cancel this unfortunate thing in the next paragraph when he says light is here to behold.
He doesn't say, look, it's secret, it's dark, it's hidden, it's underground.
He just treats it as if it was out in the open.
And it's just a fact that they had this cave.
Any of you probably don't have time to listen to NPR.
There was just a big discussion of Apollo's priestess.
Did anybody hear it?
There's that hole in the ground happens to be a case where psychedelic g gases come out and the priestesses were all drunk, you know, not with alcohol, but that stoned out of their minds, and then they made these amazing predictions.
And it had to be there, because that's where two different channels of sort of laughing gas or whatever it was out of the ground come together.
But that's all something Aeschylus either doesn't know about or doesn't care about.
What matters is that Apollo won.
And that and that so we go on.
Anybody, nobody wants to, I don't think there's anything to say about any of this yet.
Oh, there is.
Go ahead.
That's right.
Yeah.
But the priestess seemed to live underground.
At least, I mean, I'm only worrying about, says the huge, the Alexias who won Parnassus holes, the deep cleft in the ground.
Well, maybe not.
Okay, good.
Beatrice makes it even better.
It isn't, there is this hole in the ground where the gases are, and they go down there, presumably, when they want to get into this trance, or the gas comes up and they get into the trance, Beatrice says.
And that's fine.
That's better, because the less we hear about Apollo being underground, in the dark, and so forth, or his priestess being there, is better.
Okay, but he has to mention it here and then just cancel it and drop it.
And we'll just cancel it and drop it.
Don't bother to even take notes about it.
It's not going to turn out to be important that his priestess is, wherever his priestess is.
What's important is that Apollo won out.
Clytemnestra stated her case and lost every round.
And we don't need to prevent any curses anymore.
She can't, she can't, she doesn't curse him as she dies, as I recall.
I hope not, because she just, it's all on the level of logic, and she had a chance to say her whole defense, and it was refuted.
So there's no place for secrecy in curses anymore, I think.
It was done with the hot passion, motivated him up to the last moment, and it motivated him then into icy reason.
And that's just what should have happened.
That's just what they hoped for at the beginning of the play.
But who would have thought that anybody could have brought it off?
Aeschylus has to use this trick of Pylades to get it to bring it off.
But on page 98, you hear at the very beginning what the chorus hopes will happen.
And it turns out, it's exactly what seems to have happened at the time.
It really did happen.
What really happened?
Never mind the scenes, too.
At the top of the page, Orestes is saying, I think, or Electra, it doesn't matter who's saying it, they all are agreeing to it.
Electra is saying, grant that I, Electra, be more temperate of heart than my mother, that I act with purer hands.
Such are my prayers for us.
So Orestes, too, then needs to be temperate and pure.
But for our enemies, Father, I pray that your Avenger come, that they who killed shall be killed in turn as they deserve.
Well, she's on both sides, the Avenger of the Furies.
But what actually happened is that Orestes did it temperate and with pure hand, I take it.
And that's why it looks like a happy ending.
It looks like a happy ending, and now at the top of 128, this is the statement of the happy ending.
Time brings all things to pass.
Presently time shall cross the outgates of the house.
After the stain is driven entirely from the hearth, by ceremonies washed clean, and cast out the furies.
The dice of fortune shall be thrown once more and lie in a fair, false, smiling up to the new indwellers come to live in the house.
The curse is gone from the house of Atreus, they say.
And what could be a happier ending?
And he comes out, then Orestes, and shows them the net.
This is still part of the sort of forensic legal thing.
It's a little odd that you show the murder weapon after you've already executed the criminal, but it's not, but he's showing that he did the right thing.
Here's the murder weapon on page 128, a line about 985.
No, more 980.
Behold, oh, Ottis, behold, O audience, of these evil things, the engine against my wretched father, they devised.
The hands entanglement, they tangled him up in this net in the bath, and then they stabbed him when he couldn't get out and defend himself.
And so he lays it out, and he says, it's a net who caught a man.
I think that's correcting his father.
He's not supposed to kill her, remember, because she killed his father.
That would be, you've got to keep your eye on that all the time.
Every time it looks like he killed her because she killed his father, it's either a mistake in the translation or a mistake in my reading.
And I'll show you several mistakes that are in the translation.
It's up to you to show me mistakes that are in my reading.
He's supposed to do it because she killed a man and because she killed a man of high renown.
That is, she killed a king.
He's not supposed to, that's all logical.
Anybody could have done it.
That's what I mean by doing it impersonally.
He's not supposed to kill her because she killed his father.
So then he says, and so he switches.
So the net that caught a man, then so shall not my father, but he's going to cancel father, but that great father who sees all, the son, that's Apollo, look on my mother's sacrilegious handiwork and be a witness for me in my day of trial, how it was right that I achieved this death, my mother's, for against this death I take no account.
Nobody cares.
It's in a play.
He had a seducer's punishment no more than law.
So that's the happy ending.
He lays out the evidence.
He cleans up his act and makes clear that he did it because of the bad man, not because of his father.
And it looks like, all by himself, he's freed the house of Atreus from the narrow alternatives of the destructive background practices of the culture.
That he, at least for himself and maybe for everybody, has saved them from this mess that they're in, in which the Furies and Apollo are always fighting, or to put it now in less mythical terms, in which the culture always has emotional vengeance reasons for doing things and rational logical reasons for not doing them, and everybody's caught in the crossfire, or sometimes it has logical reasons for doing things, but they conflict always with the emotional reasons, I presume, for not doing things.
But there's always this emotion-reason, conflict, but it looks like, single-handed, he's stopped it.
Now, do you see that that can't be right, that are the story I'm telling.
There's something wrong somewhere.
Why would this be not something that Aeschylus would possibly consider?
Can you tell?
Can an individual person, by having the right motives, fix the culture?
It's just a phenomenological question.
I mean, it's not a question about Aeschylus.
It's anybody ought to be able to tell.
Could you?
No.
I mean, it takes time, it takes suffering, it takes lots of doing to change the values of the culture.
That's what the play is about, and there's still an act and a half to go.
So there must have been something wrong with what I said.
Well, we'll see what's wrong with what I said.
What's wrong with what I said is right after the speech where Orestes claims that he's made it all okay now, he killed her in the right way, and everything is fine, he starts to crack up.
In the middle of 995, the chorus says, I think I don't need to read anything of that.
Yeah, starting with the chorus, ah, but the pitiful work.
This is the chorus.
Dismal the death that was your ending.
He has left alive paying flowers for him.
So dismal the death of Clytemnestra, that doesn't matter.
Good riddance.
But what's happening to poor Orestes?
He looked like he had just, you know, single-handedly saved the culture, and now it looks like he's in deep trouble.
Yeah, he's certainly in deep trouble.
He's in trouble because he's going crazy.
And he's not just going crazy in any old arbitrary way.
He's going crazy in a way that makes perfect sense.
In the next speech at the end, I'll just go to the very end.
I grieve for the thing done, the death of all our race.
I have won.
That's what we just heard.
He did win.
He did it right.
But my victory is soiled and has no pride.
Well, why?
I mean, why is he cracking up?
Why didn't he just win?
Is he guilty of having done something wrong?
No.
That's a trick question.
No, he's not.
He did it right.
He exactly did what had to be done.
He killed the Clytemnestra, who had killed his father, who had killed a man of high degree, who had let herself be seduced by the brother and all of that.
She was definitely to be killed, and he did it, and he did it in the right frame of mind for the sake of Apollo.
So what's happening?
Well, he's not guilty.
Aeschylus is very subtle and clear about this, but he has tremendous guilt feelings.
There's a big difference between being guilty, which is a legal thing.
And if you're guilty, you're guilty for all the crime, and there's nothing you can do about it except go to prison and expiate it, like Reskolnikov at the end of Crime and Punishment.
But if your problem is that you have guilt feelings, that's a whole different story.
Picture the thing.
Just really picture the thing.
He slit his mother's throat face to face, a mother who he presumably loved up to the age of 11 when she sent him away, and maybe even afterward.
And once that's happened, you can't just walk off and say, well, hooray, now everything's done.
We fixed it.
And he can't.
Yeah, that's easy, but I mean, well, hard maybe, but doable.
But a good question.
Suppose, I'm trying to explain it right now.
He's not guilty because he hasn't done anything wrong from Apollo's point of view, which is the legal point of view.
He has done what it was right to kill quite a mistress.
She deserved it for over-determined reasons.
A bad lady.
But it doesn't keep you from feeling terrible that you've done, as the translation, or my earth translation says, a terrible thing.
You feel the horror and the terribleness of slitting your mother's throat.
You feel that you've done something terribly wrong, even though you know that what you did was exactly right.
That's the feeling you could, and maybe not very often does anybody have it, but anybody who has to kill their mother because that's the proper legal thing to do and the God demanded it and helped isn't going to feel good about it because nobody can feel good about killing their mother.
So that's it.
And it's very important, this distinction to Aeschylus.
I'll jump ahead just to suppose because I see that people are looking somewhat incredulous.
Okay, the test is, one more thing, and then good, good, yes.
I was thinking a while back of Kaczynski.
You know, remember that maybe it's a little before your time, the Unabomber.
Were you conscious at the time of the Jungen bomber?
So his brother turned him in.
That was the necessary right thing to do.
He was a dangerous, mad criminal killing people.
But he must have felt terrible turning his brother in.
And that's the kind of split you have in mind.
Yeah, okay, that's a helpful example.
But I'll give you also a kind of philosophical point that's related to it.
Remember, I said that if you feel, if you're guilty, you're guilty forever.
You can go and do your time in Siberia, like Reskolnikov, and that means you expiate your crime, but you're still, you still did something, and you're still guilty.
And in the United States, you're a felon forever, right?
Once you're a felon.
They want to change that, I think.
But right now, I believe that's how it is.
But if it's guilt feelings, and this is for you back in the corner, if it's guilt feelings, then gradually you'll get over them.
Because you'll begin to drift into the past how awful it looked when your mother's blood was all over you and so forth.
And you can get over guilt feelings.
And that's what happens.
He gets over the guilt, which means it couldn't have been legal guilt.
So let's go now and look at that.
He's beginning to hallucinate on way back here.
So on 129, we still are.
This is what's happening to him.
Now you just got to read a lot.
So I'm still reading on 129 because you've got to get used to this issue of why Orestes, who did it temperately, logically, purely, is now being pursued by these loathsome old ladies who are the furies, who are the forces of revenge.
And so the chorus says, there is no mortal man who shall return unhurt, his life's course to the end, not marred.
There is trouble here, there's more to come.
And Orestes says, I would have you know, I see not how this thing will end.
I am a charioteer whose course is wrenched outside the track, and I am beaten.
My rebellious senses bolt with me headlong.
I mean, that's a way of saying I'm going crazy.
It's not that anything objective is going wrong.
His senses, his brain, his perception is going wrong.
And so, let's see.
And the fear against my heart is ready for the singing and dance of wrath.
Wrath is always associated.
In Greek, it's atte, and that means the same kind of thing that Achilles had at the beginning of the Iliad.
It means getting very angry and upset.
And that's how the furies are.
Wrath is always associated with the furies.
So I've got to stop here and tell you something.
I made my mind up to tell you at the beginning that I was too busy getting all the microphones and stuff.
Students asked me in office hours, and I was worried myself about this talk about wrath with a capital W, what is the else?
Fury with a capital F, and justice with a capital J.
And it even says in one place, whoever came, I think it was him maybe, to complain, that the daughter of Zeus is, was it you?
Was wrath?
It says on 41, and you thought maybe that was Athena because she's the daughter of Zeus.
But it's not.
It's not really the daughter of Zeus.
That's just a metaphor, that Zeus being behind everything.
He's also behind wrath, justice, and what's the other one again?
Now we've got DK, Ate, wrath, justice, and Fury.
Those are the three.
Maybe I should just write them on the board.
You shouldn't worry about this.
I'm telling you this so you won't worry about it, not so you will sort of pay attention to it or write it down or anything, because it doesn't lead anywhere.
But there is wrath, there's justice, and there's furies.
And there's a Greek word for each of these, Ate.
I don't know how to spell it.
Is that how do you spell it with an accent or something?
So I think something like that.
Justice is DK, right?
Who, and Barry, how do you spell it?
D-I-K-E with a D-I-K-A-E.
Just E.
Okay, DK.
And that's sometimes translated as fate, right?
That's the same.
Right.
No, that's another one.
Okay, here's another one.
Right.
Oh, that's the same.
So it is the same as fate.
DK is fate, or is justice, or is right.
Not fate.
What's fate in Greek?
Oh, yeah, Moira.
Let's not get Moira into this, right?
And this is Aranes, which I certainly can't spell.
Somebody spell it for me.
Something like that.
I mean, since it's going from Greek to English, there's no absolute, you can't call me wrong, because I can transliterate it as I please.
Anyway, the main thing is that the that wrath, justice, and furies, there is a Greek word for each of them that really does mean wrath, getting all upset and angry.
That means that it's the way that means that means justice okay and that is another name for the furies sometimes they're called Irenees in the text here and sometimes they're called furies and now then it's not a people and they're not actually children of Zeus and well I don't know why they're capitalized in the Greek we've never came out with the answer to that one but they are and it's just a way of describing the relevant emotions or situation and that's that so don't worry about it that's all so I'm not going to worry about it and if there's something to worry about let me know so now he be where are we again so he he admits where are we 129 okay at the top of 130 he's he's going crazy he says my rebellious senses bolt with me headlong and fear against my heart is ready for the singing dance of wrath oh yeah that's what got me into it and sometimes it's capitalized in translation and sometimes it isn't but while i hold some grip on my wits that is he knows he's going crazy i say publicly to my friends i killed my mother not without some right that is i'm not legally guilty i did the right thing my father's murder stained her father's hmm where's my greek did i not bring it with me we don't have it do we uh i think i that's not going to be father everyone every time so far that he has said father and i looked it up.
It turns out to mean, as you you've all read Shakespeare and seen this word sire or lord, it means something like sire or lord, my superior.
And there are two words in Greek apparently.
There's one for father and one would get translated sire, and which is something like father, but not blood, not blood father.
And every time I've looked up father in the wrong context, like this, it's turned out to be the Greek word for sire.
So now I just have to make a note.
I missed that one and see if that is too.
If not, I'll bring back the bad news next time.
Let's see.
Father, page one thirty.
Okay, I'm going to go out on a limb.
I want to say he isn't saying father.
He's saying sire there.
Or if he's saying father, he's not saying it in a way that means blood relative.
My father's murder stained her and the gods disgust.
As for the spells that charm me to such daring, I give you in chief the seer of Pytho, Luxius, again, Apollo.
He declared I could do this and not be charged with wrong.
So he's just asserting again and again, legally he didn't do anything wrong, and he isn't guilty.
And then he says he's going to go off and now he has to somehow do some rituals, which is sort of like therapy, that will get him over this feeling of guilt, which he doesn't really deserve and he doesn't want, but he can't just say, Okay, I'm I'm not guilty, so I stop feeling guilty.
He's got to go, he's going to go armored in leaf, branch, and garland on my way to the centerstone and sanctuary and Apollo's level place, the shining of the walls, and so forth, to escape this blood that is my own.
That is, to escape the guilt feelings of having killed his blood, his closest blood relative, his mother.
Okay, and then he tells you how awful they look.
All of this I'm just giving you so the context here.
Or the bottom of 130, he says, women who serve this house, they, that is the furies, come like gorgons, whatever they are, more, I think gorgons have snaky heads, and these furies also seem to have snaky heads, you'll see in the next thing.
And they are reading, yeah, in a tangle of snakes.
Okay, I can stay no longer.
And they say, and it's interesting now, by the way, notice that in this play, Aeschylus is being very modern.
And he's not telling you that there are walking around objectively in the world these kind of creatures.
It's not like in Homer when I will call it magic realism, where if enough people believe that they saw a god, then it counts as actually seeing a god.
And you don't ask the question, was it really a god or was it a hallucination?
That's just not relevant.
If the appropriate emotion mood is on and you get attuned, Athena's there.
But here, he's got a sharp distinction, Aeschylus.
It's 500 years later.
And the rational forces in the culture are getting stronger than they were in Homer.
So Apollo and the new gods, particularly Apollo, who represents the newest of the new gods, rationality, theory, and so forth, is making a distinction between whether those are actually out there or whether he's just seeing them.
And they say, Orestes, dearest to your father of all men, what fancies were you?
That is, you're hallucinating.
They don't see them.
The audience doesn't see them.
They're not on the stage, but they're real in the inner sense.
It's really psychological, in the psychological sense that he's experiencing them.
Now, if I'm right, Aespelus is not going to leave us with that, but that's the current situation.
They are the bloodhounds of my mother's hate, he says.
And then he says, Oh, Lord Apollo, how they grow and multiply, repulsive for the blood drops in their dripping eyes.
And then he says to the audience in the middle of 131, You can't see them, but I see them.
I'm driven from this place.
I can stay no longer.
Okay, so it didn't work.
One individual can't overthrow the culture, the practices, the idea that you can't just get away with murdering blood relatives.
You can do it legally, murder your blood relative or kill them if it's required, like by Apollo.
But you can't get away with feeling good about it.
And so finally, the chorus goes around and sees we haven't won after all.
This is not a happy ending.
That's one of these reversals.
It just sounded like the God had been, you know, light was there, truth was clear, everything was out in the open, everybody did what they were supposed to do.
And now it turns out, I'm going to read the starting on 1065 on page 131.
Here on this house of the kings, that's the house of Atreus.
And where are we?
The third storm has broken with a wind from the inward race.
That's the furies in the house.
And gone its course.
The children were eaten.
That's Thaestes.
Thaestes' children?
I still try to get it straight.
Okay, Thaestes' children.
There was the first affliction, the curse of Thaestes.
He cursed Atreus.
Next came the royal death when a man and lord of Achaean armies went down.
That's Agamemnon got killed, killed in the bath.
Third is for the Savior.
The Savior is Orestes.
That's what he should be doing.
He should be saving them from all this.
He came, shall I call it that, or death?
Did he really come?
I mean, was he a savior?
Where, presumably not, they think now.
Where is the end?
Where shall the fury of fate be stilled to sleep, be done with?
So in the end, the culture is as bad or worse off than ever.
That's the end of the play.
So then everybody goes out and has drinks and popcorn or something.
I don't know how they managed to sit through all these three plays in a row and comes back and we get the next play.
And we're now, you should have, I told you last time to start reading it.
So we're not going on to talk about it now for a while.
But I think I ought to stop here.
The Eumenides is done.
Do you want to say something about it or ask something about it?
I'm ready to follow your lead.
Yeah.
No, that's not.
The good.
I really like it that you are ready to say things.
And they don't come together in a nice way, the way you at least look like you wanted them to come together.
They collide.
Their world's in collision.
The two cultures just don't get together.
Apollo said killer.
Now he's going crazy because the furies say you shouldn't have killed her.
The two cultures are totally in opposition.
And Orestes is being batted back and forth like a ping-pong ball between the two forces in the culture.
Whatever he does, it doesn't work.
It can't work because it's the cultural practices are messed up.
If you are a revenge culture, then you're bound to have revenge after revenge after revenge and never be able to get out of it.
And if you're a culture in which emotions, if they only have two possibilities in the culture, viewing what you're doing always with sort of family emotions, that's part of the revenge culture.
Or this new God stuff, viewing everything everybody does with logic, rationality, and principles, and universal laws, if you believe equally in both of them, it's not coming together.
It's crashing.
And the interesting thing, keep your eyes open for this.
Not only does perhaps not each person in the culture believes equally in both of them, though everybody believes somewhat in each of them.
But the interesting question to ask yourself is: is it 50-50 in the culture, or what percent of the people believe that the Furies are right, and what percent of the people believe that Apollo is right?
You would think that there wouldn't be any evidence of such precise mathematical sort, but there is.
Keep your eyes open if you can see the point where you're told by Aeschylus just which group outnumbers which group.
You should expect the right, you should guess the right answer.
How many how many what do you what do you think the right answer is?
Yeah.
Well, the exact number is crucial, yeah?
I can't hear you, but I think you're saying the right thing.
What about the jury and then she's got it and he's on the track of it.
The jury splits 50-50.
The jury is the citizens, and they choose at random the twelve jurors, and they split six to six on this for the Apollo side and the Fury side.
That just shows that the culture is split 50-50.
Then there's got to be a new big new problem.
And Athena casts a sort of completely wacky seeming vote for very weird reasons and settles that.
The important thing is you get a clue that this is a really split culture.
You want to say something?
Oh, I thought I was going to end.
Okay.
Well, now you've said interesting things.
We can go on to the next round.
So where are we?
So three questions are left at the end of the humanities.
How can Orestes be cured?
And we're going to find out.
You know, cured of his guilt feelings.
That's like a sickness.
How can the splits in the culture that cause this sickness be cured?
And that has two sub-questions.
What are you going to do with the Furies?
How can you somehow turn them from being a negative and destructive social force into some kind of positive social force?
How could you possibly do that?
And how can you redefine reason and Apollo so that the emotions, namely the Furies, don't run into a head-on conflict with reason, namely Apollo, but somehow they support each other.
That's what you want.
But can you get that?
And how would you get that?
And if you can, then Athens has developed a really wonderful culture in which they've integrated emotion and reason in a positive way.
And we have to see if and how that can be done.
So, next, now I have to prepare you for the reading of the humanities.
I really should have prepared you last time, but it's really all right to let you see what you see on your own.
You probably realized if you started when you started reading it, the Furies are now on stage, really there, jumping up and down, lying around, looking awful, and so forth.
And the interesting thing is that that doesn't mean that Aeschylus has changed his mind and sort of gone back to Homeric realism.
It means that we're on a different level now.
The cultural forces are just personified.
I mean, the Furies represent the fact that in the culture, everybody has to avenge everybody and is always in a state of emotional excitement.
And Apollo is on stage now, and he represents the extreme force toward rationality which is taking gaining ever since Homer.
I mean, Homer already was trying to read the Furies out and make the culture more rational.
And it's now gotten 500 years further along, and Apollo is a lot more rational than he ever was in Homer.
And they're all on the stage, and what they say represents these various cultural forces.
Okay.
And the way you can tell that they're switched around is that everyone now sees the Furies.
It's not just Orestes anymore.
And the audience sees the Furies, which they didn't before.
So now the Furies, not that that means that there really are Furies running around and Apollo running around, but it means that this is an objective truth about the cultural practices that everybody sees.
And in a metaphorical sense, sees them, and in a literal sense in the play, they see them.
Okay.
Now, that's easy to say.
What's hard to understand, and I wouldn't expect you to understand it on your own, and I'm not sure I got it right, but the Furies say some pretty peculiar things, and for years I've tried to make sense of them.
I never know whether I've succeeded.
But what's wrong with the fact, what goes on that's puzzling, is the Furies have redefined their domain.
They're no longer just the forces of wrath and revenge and emotional outrage.
And you see this in a puzzling way at the bottom of 144.
And who's talking?
The Furies.
You must give back for her blood from the living man, red blood of your body suck, and from your own, I would feed with bitter swallow drench, turn your strange, turn your strange limp, what your strength limp, while yet you live and drag you down.
This must be really sort of, remember this, and you have to realize this is sort of sung and encanted by these dancing, awful creatures.
Where you must pay for the pain of the murdered mother and watch the rest of the mortals stained with violence against God or guest or hurt parents who were close and dear, each with the pain upon him that his crime deserves.
What's strange about that?
Jolt, you in what I was just reading?
You've got to be very sensitive to being jolted because you learn something or you run to the translation and then, if you can't fix it, you learn something.
Don't you see anything strange?
They're going to be in charge of hurt parents and guests.
Guests?
What is that doing on the list of the Fury business?
They're the blood relative business.
They're not in the Fury business.
That's very upsetting if you're reading it closely.
And it's not, I mean, I went to the translation.
No, that's what it really says.
And moreover, that's not the only place they say it.
They say it again on page 154 at the top.
Let man see this and take care to mother and father and to the guest in the gates.
Welcomed, given all rights that befall their position.
They're really doing a kind of a new god, Athena, Hermes, and Zeus, insofar as he's a new god thing there.
That's not their job.
It's not their business.
Well, I wish I could just tell you clearly what's happening, but I can't.
But if you read the play, I think you'll see that what's happening.
As I say, this is only my speculation.
If you think it's wrong, it's a good paper topic to say so.
The furies are being generalized into something that's recognizably like what they were, but it covers a lot more than just family feuds.
And how I would define it is something like the furies, and it's got to be emotional, and it's got to cover more than family feuds, but it can't be sort of rational like Apollo.
I take it to be, I think, any moral outrage at something which strikes you as wrong.
That is moral outrage, not just moral condemnation or disapproval.
But they are what they are that in the culture and in each person raised in that culture that makes them just furious when somebody does something wrong.
And they just generalize the job.
And even if that means running off with your guest's wife or throwing a stool at an old beggar, the kind of bad things that people did to guests in the Odyssey and got in big trouble for it, they still get in big trouble for it, but they don't get in big trouble for it because Zeus is a friend of guests or because guests go from world to world.
They get in big trouble for it just because it's in the culture that they get upset when guests get badly treated.
That's the only way I can see it.
If you I see a hand, I would love to you want to say something.
Oh, I don't know why the people down and why we don't get that enough for them.
Okay, well, good, good.
I see what you're saying, and I think you're making a kind of objection to what I said, which is interesting.
And I may have to, I don't know, I'll try to squirm out of it.
Let me repeat it.
So on 156, there is this interesting discussion where Orestes says, why weren't you upset when Clytemnestra killed Agamemnon?
You should have been.
Instead, let's see now.
Let's just read it on 156.
She murdered her husband and my father, too, and there he means father.
And the chorus says, of this thing, death has set her free, that you're still alive.
But when she lived, why did you not descend and drive her out?
That is, why didn't the Furies punish Clytemnestra for killing Agamemnon?
See, Clytemnestra says it's her Furies and Phaginias that are causing them to kill Agamemnon.
But it should be, Agamemnon's, the Furies should be trying to get, it's complicated, the Furies should be trying to get Orestes, who is the son of Agamemnon, to kill Clytemnestra, right?
But we don't hear anywhere in the book that the Furies are the ones who wanted to kill Clytemnestra.
It's that it's Apollo who wants him to kill Clytemnestra.
And the Furies say, well, we don't have to worry about her.
The man she killed was not a blood congenital.
That's very interesting.
That means that the Furies don't care about marriage, which is just a question of an institution and an oath.
They only care when blood relatives are hurt.
Now, that's true about the Furies.
And then the whole conversation is, but am I then involved with my mother by blood bond?
Because they are upset that he killed his mother.
And they say, Yeah, she is.
How else could she have nursed you, and so forth and so forth?
Your mother is your blood relative, and you killed a blood relative, and so you're in trouble.
And Agamemnon killed a blood relative named Ephijania, so he's in trouble.
But Clytemnestra didn't kill any blood relative.
She just killed her husband, so she's not in trouble.
That's the argument of the Furies.
Now, but her objection to me is that you've got a good objection.
I mean, everything so far we have to agree on.
That's how it is.
That's what the Furies are saying.
They only punish blood relatives.
But then, how did they get generalized into guests?
You're a very smart question.
I don't know.
That's why I said with such hesitation that I can only understand them as moral outrage.
But why don't they have moral outrage when a wife kills a husband?
Well, I don't know.
I mean, there's sometimes, I wish I could be clearer and better about this.
It's as if the Furies sometimes are like the old Furies, and sometimes they've got a bigger, newer job.
And unless somebody comes along and helps me out, maybe Beatrice, I'm stuck.
Aha!
I like it.
Well, no, it won't work.
I'm sorry.
I liked it for one minute.
But no, it won't work because it isn't a question of family, but of blood.
See, fathers are certainly part of the family, but from the Furies' point of view, you don't have to kill a father because, I mean, sorry, husbands are part of the family.
And if you just kill your husband, the Furies are not upset.
That's what just came out with this thing.
Clydemnestra, after all, she killed Agamemnon.
Who cares?
They're not blood relatives.
So and if their husband isn't part of your family, then I don't think the guests are going to become part of your family just by coming to dinner.
That's not going to help.
So I'm still stumped.
Anybody else want to help?
Okay, I'll have to say something absolutely weasly until somebody comes up better.
That culture is confused.
I'm confused, and Aeschylus is confused, but I think it's mainly he's sort of saying here's a culture in transition between, I guess, really narrow Furies who only worry about killing blood relatives, which is their sort of original, primitive, barbaric status, and a more general kind of fury, which is moral outrage, as I say.
This is like the 60s.
There used to be lots of dogs in the lectures in the 60s.
I once told, I don't think it'll work anymore.
I once told a dog, my brother's also a professor here who loves dogs, so he was in the wrong lecture.
He should go to my brother's lecture.
Go to my brother's lecture.
I don't think it's going to help because my brother retired.
Anyway, back to, this is a way to avoid facing the problem.
The problem is it looks like the Furies are in transition from a very narrow construal of what they're up to to a broader construal of what they're up to.
And this mention of guests is a sign of it.
And so, anyway, that's the best I can do.
Come and see me in office hours if you've got a solution.
Anybody who can really explain this gets an A-plus on their paper, no matter what else they say.
Okay, now let's see.
Where are we?
Okay, we've got they get very general.
The culture's getting, ah, he's off to my brother's lecture.
Good.
The Furies say that they've been excluded and so forth.
Okay, yes, a very important line.
Very important.
It's going to turn, it's sort of snuck by here on purpose by Aeschylus.
He's going to need it later, but we can see it now on page 147.
Part of the thing that we have to explain is why the Furies are so upset about everything, but particularly about the new gods.
They've got this total outrage about the new gods.
What did the new gods do to the Furies that they're so upset about?
Well, it comes out in the middle of 147.
I have chosen overthrow of houses where the battle god growing within strikes near and dear down.
That's the Fury saying.
Isn't that interesting?
That's part of the same thing we're talking about.
The near and dear seem to be different than the guests.
If you can think of guests as near and dear, maybe you're getting somewhere.
Anyway, I don't want to go back into that.
I really want the next quote.
Here we stand in our haste to wrench from all others these devisings.
Make the gods clear of our counsels so that even appeal comes not to them.
Now comes the crucial line.
Since Zeus has ruled our blood-dripping company outcast, nor will deal with us.
What they're really angry about is that Zeus, qua representing now the new gods, won't even deal with, won't talk to, won't make treaties with the Furies.
It's like the United States and North Korea.
I mean, Zeus just considers the Furies the empire of evil, and they can't stand it.
It's that rejection by the powers that have the power that is making them furious.
And it's going to turn out to be very important, that that's really deeply their problem, that they're not accepted, they're not integrated, they're not appreciated by the new gods and the new practices.
Now, why that's going to be important, I can't tell you yet, but remember it.
We'll come back to that little quote later.
But what's happening is clear.
The cultural horses are getting more and more rational all the time.
And that's, and more and more, they're being disapproved, ignored, denied, repressed.
My one word for it is: the culture is repressing the emotions.
It's repressing the feelings of moral outrage.
It's repressing all feelings.
It's getting to be the logic freak.
It's tending in the direction of the craziness of rationality in Apollo.
And if any, I don't forget how many, I don't know maybe I ever, how many read any Socrates or Plato in there?
Well, that's where it's heading, where everything is really logical and debatable and emotions.
How many read the Euthyphro?
That would be the first thing to read for this.
Well, the Euthyphro is where Plato says that piety, which means love of the tradition, is a bad thing.
I mean, that's where they're heading, and the Furies see it's coming, and they get they're very, very upset.
So now we're there, let's see.
So, oh, yeah, now we get a fun thing, and there's plenty of time.
And now, let's see it from the other side.
Why are the Furies so upset?
Well, you can see it by looking at what Apollo's priestess says when she sees the Furies, and what Apollo says when he sees the Furies.
I mean, to say that they're not appreciated is an understatement.
And where does this happen?
Okay, on 136, at the beginning of the play, you see exactly how far it's gone in the non-appreciation of the Furies.
The priestess of Apollo comes staggering out of the temple and says, things terrible to tell and for the eyes to see, terrible drove me out again from Luxius' house so that I have no strength and cannot stand on springing feet that run with hands help and my legs have no speed.
She's crawling out.
It's complicated, Aeschylus way of saying.
And why is she crawling out of as fast as she can from the temple?
She's just been knocked over by what she saw.
And here's what she saw at the bottom third of 136.
In front of this man slept a startling company of women lying all upon the chairs.
And this is the first real description we've got of the Furies.
Or not women, I think.
I call them rather gorgons, only not gorgons either, since their shape is not the same.
I saw some creatures painted in a picture.
Let's skip that.
They are black and utterly repulsive, and they snore with breaths that drives one back.
From their eyes drips the foul ooze in their dress is such as not right to wear in the presence of the gods, statues, or even any human house.
I've never seen the tribe that owns this company, nor know what piece of earth can claim with pride it bore such brood without hurt, and so forth and so forth.
Well, from the priestess point of view, she doesn't even know what they are.
That she just can't recognize them as anything that she's ever heard of or seen, and she finds them just incomprehensibly repulsive.
But now, on the other hand, Apollo recognizes them and thinks they're just terrible.
I mean, you could have it either way, that they are just so repulsive and so alien to the current rational tendency in the culture that Apollo's priestess doesn't even know what they are, just that they're some ugly, awful thing.
Or on 137, Apollo knows perfectly well who they are, and he has a lot of very nasty things to say about them.
On 137, about a quarter of the way down, I will not give you up.
He's talking to Orestes, though to the end standing your guardian, through to the end, standing your guardian, whether by your side or far away.
I shall not weaken towards your enemies.
So now I have caught and overpowered these lewd creatures.
That's his view of the furies.
These repulsive maidens have been still to sleep.
Those gray and aged children, they with whom no mortal man, no god, nor even any beast will have to do.
Well, I want to stop to say for one thing: furies fall asleep and they get overpowered, and that's because, remember, I said emotions, after a certain amount of time, just sort of wear down.
You can't keep yourself into a constant state of guilt feelings or outrage or anything else.
You've just got to go relax and go to sleep every once in a while.
And that's what happens to the Furies.
They just sort of not standing guard, they're falling asleep, and that's going to be important too.
That's how they're losing their grip on Orestes.
And why are they aged children?
Do you understand that?
The funny thing to say.
Well, why are they aged?
Why are they old?
Because they go way back to the beginning of the race, to the beginning of all culture.
Remember, I said they come from the blood of the fact that in the first generation of gods, Uranus, I think it is, castrates Kronos, and from the blood comes the Fury.
So they're very old.
And why would they be children?
Have you got an idea about that?
Well, they're very primitive and irrational and emotional, like children are.
They're not going to be making logical arguments like Apollo.
So Apollo thinks they call them aged children, primitives, you could say, in one word.
And now comes another interesting thing, with whom no mortal man, and that would mean woman too, presumably, would have anything to do, Apollo says.
Is that true?
Can you think of a counterexample to Apollo here?
He would be sensitive to counter example.
Can you think of anybody who does have to do with the furies?
Well, Clytemnestra.
She calls on them.
Ophiginia is Furies.
She's all for them.
So it isn't as if, and half the population, we discover later at the trial, is whoever it is, said, will have plenty to do with the Furies.
And the same problem with the gods, only you don't know it yet.
And he says no mortal man, no God would have anything to do with them.
Well, it's going to turn out, I don't know how many read far enough, how many know what God is going to have something to do with the furies?
Only a few.
Okay, well, Athena does, so that's wrong too.
And then you get this funny story about why they're there.
It was because of evil they were born, because they hold the evil darkness of the pit below, earth, below earth, loathed alike by men and by the heavenly gods.
Well, not all men, not all human beings, and not all gods.
But now there's a kind of funny, not funny, but crazy kind of pun in this.
They were born because of evil.
That is, they were born to punish evil.
But Apollo puts a different spin on it.
He thinks that they're born to perpetuate evil because he can't see that they've got any positive function.
So that's, so I'm just reading that so you can understand why they would be upset.
They're lewd, they're dark, they're evil, they're indecent, they're primitive, and they are, sort of, because they are irrational, extreme outrage, and sort of a very sharp distinction between good and bad, and very much against what they think is bad.
And Apollo can't stand this darkness, and he doesn't see any value in being underground in the earth.
And so, and so and he thinks they're born of evil in this bad way, and so forth.
And that's it.
And Apollo takes credit for the way Orestes killed Clytemnestra.
In case you had any doubt whether he did it in a cold, rational, detached way or not, you look at the bottom of 137 and you see Apollo say, for it was I who made you strike your mother down.
And that's just sort of baiting the Furies into more outrage because Apollo is protecting him in the temple for having done what the Furies think is the worst thing you can do, kill a blood relative.
Okay, any comments about that?
There's I still could go one more unit of understanding.
Okay, let's do it.
One more unit of understanding.
So they're asleep, and we hear more about why they're asleep at the middle of 139.
But I've already said it, but I'll show you.
So Clytemnestra, who's trying to get the Furies back to work, meaning trying to make sure that Orestes is still feeling completely horrible guilt, says to them, sleep and fatigue, two masterful conspirators, have dimmed the deadly anger of the mother snake.
She understands.
And she wakes them up, and they get up and they start, get him, get him, get him.
They're back after Orestes again.
And she says a little three lines down in her next speech, Let not work's weariness beat you, nor slacken with speed, so that you forget my pain.
So, and forgetting her pain, they're supposed to not let Orestes forget his pain at killing his mother.
And he isn't guilty, but he feels guilty.
But he doesn't feel guilty anymore, you'll see.
He's getting over it.
But first, there's a debate between the Furies and Apollo.
So we have to do that.
We'll see what's happening in that debate.
They're going on the usual thing, but you get it from lots of different angles.
And every time you do, it's a little clearer.
Here's, I mean, they're telling again why they're so upset.
Remember, one of them is that they're repressed.
They're not appreciated anymore.
And so halfway down, roughly line 149 on page 140: shame, son of Zeus, robbers is all you are.
The young gods, you have ridden down powers gray with age, taken the suppliant, though a godless man, who hurt the mother who gave him birth, yourself a god, you stole an apricot away.
Where in this act shall any man say there is right?
So she's doing her things and their things.
And they're making, I'm going to read you two sort of extreme statements from the point of view of Apollo and the Furies.
And you're supposed to think that they'll never be able to get reconciled.
So here on 163 is one of them.
Here's the Furies talking.
Such are the actions of the younger gods.
These hold by unconditioned force beyond all right a throne that runs reeking with blood, meaning that there's all this blood among the gods.
After all, they're constantly killing each other up to the new gods.
The new gods have finally, I think, put an end to this craziness where the gods are killing each other.
Uh but the throne is reeking with blood from the past.
It runs re blood at the feet, blood at the head, and so forth and so forth.
And mainly they have at the bottom of one hundred forty blighted age-old disab distributions of power.
That means, again, that they used to have equal power, or well, first more power in the primitive times, and then presumably equal power at the time that this is happening.
But they're things are getting worse and worse, and the distribution of power is switching over.
So now that's their side.
Now we hear Apollo's side.
And that's with one hundred forty-one, line one eighty-five.
This house is no right place for such as you to cling upon.
The the the Apollo says, get out of my temple, in effect.
But where, and now this is why you guys are so bad.
By judgments given, heads are lopped and eyes gouged out, throats cut, and by the spoil of sex, the glory of young boys is defeated.
That's castration or circumcision or something.
Where mutilation lives in stoning and the long moan of tortured men spiked beneath the spine and stuck on pails.
I mean, this is really primitive warfare and retribution and weird rituals, which we now find disgusting, and Apollo already finds disgusting.
So he thinks this is just barbaric stuff.
And that's what I just read.
Anything, for him, anything primitive is bad.
Reason is always right.
It's all that matters.
Everything that's irrational, all emotions, because they're irrational, are bad and should be banned and should be banished, put underground, repressed.
And the idea that that they could have a positive role strikes him as completely wrong.
By the way, we should look at page 142.
Here's one of those places where I did catch the translator getting it wrong.
The top of 142, Apollo says, the word to exact price for his father.
What of that?
What's going on here?
Chorus, the Furies say, you gave this out slander the word to kill his mother.
Apollo says, to exact price for his father.
What of that?
Now, that sounds sensible to us.
But remember that he's being, that she had every, it was okay for her to kill Agamemnon.
Remember?
Why?
He's just her husband.
Husbands don't count for the Furies.
Only blood relatives count.
So he doesn't understand why didn't you exact price for the father?
Only he wouldn't say father because that's a blood relative thing.
He says sire or Lord, that is, but he means, they both mean Agamemnon.
It's just how they describe him.
And he says, why didn't you, wait, no, yeah, why didn't you punish him for killing the king, in effect?
And they say that's because he wasn't a blood relative.
And let's see.
And they say in the middle of the page, and yet we have our duty.
It has to do, it was to do what we have done.
And he says he's very surprised, Apollo.
An office, that means a job.
You, you, you know, foul monsters, found forth your glorious privilege.
And then they say to drive macricides out of their house.
And that's fine.
That's their job.
And then he says, very logically, we're back to that again, but what if it be the woman that kills her man?
And they say such murder would not be the shedding of kindred blood.
Marriage doesn't count.
I just wanted to read that because, in case you thought I made it up, it's there.
And Apollo then says, and this is interesting, and this is a nice way to see the difference.
I mean, when a man and woman get together, the Furies think that that's just irrelevant.
And Apollo thinks that's marriage, that that's a very beautiful institution.
So read that.
You have made into a thing of no account, no place, the sworn faith of Zeus and Hera.
Notice sworn faith.
It's not blood relatives.
They said, I do, and they married each other.
Hera, lady of consummations, and Cyprus, that's Aphrodite.
By such argument is thrown away.
Now, it looks like Aphrodite is not exactly the one you want to invoke for marriages.
She just broke up the marriage of Agamemnon and Helen.
But things have changed, and Aphrodite has changed.
She's no longer the goddess of wild, erotic passion, married or not.
She's the goddess of domestic long lifetime love of a husband and wife.
You can see this.
So the an Cyprus of such argument is thrown away, outlawed.
And now this is Apollo, new god talk.
Yet the sweetest things in man's life come from her.
That is, love and marriage.
For married love between man and woman is bigger than oaths, guarded by right.
And then it says of nature.
And I thought, of nature, what's natural about marriage?
Nothing.
So I went back to the translation.
There is no of nature.
Cross it out.
It's a question of oaths, of swearing to be stick to each other in sickness and health and all that.
If when such kill each other, you relent so as not to take vengeance nor island in wrath, then I deny your manhood, Orestes goes with right.
I see that one cause moves you to strong rage, but on the other, you clearly unmoved out.
See, what's bothering him there is that they're not impartial.
They're not rational.
They're not saying.
They're saying, well, if he kills his mother, that's terrible.
But if she kills her husband, we don't care.
And he finds that unacceptable.
So do we, because we're rational too.
And Apollo thinks that all killers should be punished equally and totally.
Where are we?
Yeah, it's okay.
Just about where I want to be, which is good, because we just have about three minutes.
So we got Aphrodite, we got marriage.
We can't we can't, Apollo can't stand the fury's partiality.
Remember, I want to just read it again on 157.
You don't hear it but once, but I keep coming back to it.
Apollo is totally impartial.
He says, You must have marked it already because I read it already: I shall speak justly, I shall not lie.
Never for man, woman, or city, for my throne of prophecy have I spoken a word except that which Father Zeus of the Olympians might command.
This is justice.
He's just saying again, he's completely impartial.
Doesn't matter whether there's blood, doesn't matter whether they're family.
If you kill somebody, that's bad.
And he will, and you're guilty.
And any emotions that are partial are unjust and dangerous.
And the Furies, in effect, say, we may be not be impartial, but we're consistent.
We understand exactly what we're up to.
And we're the primitive moral outrage of the passions.
And that's more basic than your law and order.
That's what holds society together.
And we're not interested in your arguments.
And the situation looks hopeless.
That's my last comment on 143.
Where is the situation looking hopeless?
Oh, yeah.
They don't even believe in arguments, as they say.
Even if Apollo said exactly convincing things, like, look, you're inconsistent.
A revenge culture has contradictions in it.
You can't be a rational being and have contradictions.
They would say, so much the worse for being rational beings.
We know what matters.
So they say it in the second chorus, little speech on 143, don't try to dock my privilege by argument.
So don't try, you can rationalize anything they're saying.
It's strong feelings, that's what matters.
Okay, I got that there.
Now, why do I stop there?
Because the question, it looks hopeless, and you've got to have some something besides these two crazy opposed fanatical forces, the emotions and reason in their pure form.
Who could do that?
How would they do it?
Well, finish reading the humanities for next time.