And so now, we were in the middle of my list of Melville's understanding of what kind of meaning we can find in a godless world, where I mean godless with a capital G, that is, a world with no supreme being and a world with no onto theology, that is, because Buddhism doesn't have a supreme being, but it still has one total view about the true nature of everything.
And once you give up on that, and it becomes more and more implausible to the people in our culture, and probably gradually the West takes over everything, and science takes over everything, and it becomes more and more implausible in all cultures, then what have you got left as possible sources of meaning?
And the only one I did last time talked about was the pagan, which is represented by KweQ.
And that's got to do with some kind of saving understanding in the culture.
And part of that saving understanding, I don't, it isn't spelled out enough to be able to say just exactly how this works, is carved on Kwiquweg's body.
That is, there's a tradition, and that tradition is sacred because, to put it in a Pascali way, I think I may have said this, custom is our nature, so that we are the kind of human beings that the tradition in our culture makes us, and things show up for us as the kind of things they are because of this tradition in our culture.
So, in a way, the tradition is doing the job of the Creator God.
It's making us, it sort of creates us and the things we deal with, and that's why it's sacred.
And just preserving it is some way preserving the saving power of that tradition.
And to preserve it, you don't have to do much because it's carved into your body anyway.
But you do seem to have to have a sense of its importance, and that's why it gets carved on his body explicitly and why he copies it onto his coffin.
The nearest thing I can think of it is Judaism, where there is a supreme being, but the supreme being, the creator God, doesn't seem to be nearly as important as the tradition, which is what is sacred and what you've got to keep.
And the pagan is just that same idea, but without the supreme being.
Okay, I don't have more to say about that.
I do have one more thing to say.
I think I said something wrong last time, or at least if I don't remember whether I actually said it or just thought something wrong.
But when on page 400 we see Quique dying, which he doesn't do, but what?
I've somehow got my page number wrong.
Where is Cuique dying?
Queque in his coffin.
Help me find the chapter.
Here we are.
It's chapter 110.
It's page 460.
I read this passage where I won't read the whole thing again, but he's dying and his eyes deeply looked out at you there from his sickness, a wonderful testimony to that immortal health in him, which could not die or be weakened.
I can't remember exactly what I said, but I think I said something like: well, nobody gets healed of whatever it is that's basically incomplete and needy about human beings, the way that they are, quote, cracked about the head and in need of mending.
And that's wrong.
I mean, Melville thinks there are ways of getting healed.
That he didn't say that people are cracked about the head and in need of mending and that they're unmendable.
And I don't know.
Did I give the impression that even dying Queque was still somehow sick?
It's not true.
He's physically sick, but he's got immortal health in him.
That's to say, his way of relating to the sacred in the tradition, in his culture, has healed him.
And it was easier in his culture because it wasn't corrupted by onto-theology, so that people wanted something more, namely total experience of total God that made everything intelligible and gave you eternal fulfillment.
When that gets in the way, as it does in Dante, everything, as we saw, else gets lost.
So Quiqua didn't have to worry about that, and therefore his sacred tradition, as appreciated and carved in his body, healed him.
And so he can die physically, but he is no longer sick with whatever it is that human beings are sick with.
I think I wasn't clear about it, but I am now clear about it.
And now, unless anybody wants to say anything more about it, I'm going on from the pagan story to the next story.
I'm sure the weirdest chapter in the book, maybe the weirdest chapter in any book, I don't know, which is The Squeeze of the Hand, chapter 94.
It's a very important chapter.
I mean, it's important to the people who try to read it psychologically, who try to worry about whether Ishmael is or is not gay, and who try to see if this is Freudian or Jungian or what.
I mean, of course, that's not why I think it's important to me, or I don't know if this is how it was to Ishmael, but we've got to read it and see that lots of interesting things are going on here, starting on 402.
So, starting at the third paragraph in chapter 94, he's talking about the new job he's got.
It was a little way down.
It was our business to squeeze these lumps back into fluid.
So, there they had this big tub of the sperm out of Moby Dick that they were, why I don't know, he doesn't tell us, squeezing it back into liquid.
But on 403, he tells us that it completely changed his mood.
He'd been in this mood of monomania that he had taken over from Ahab, and Ahab's curse and search had become his.
And now he gets rid of that on 403 and gets switched into another mood, not again by choosing, but by being drawn in, he's drawn into the mood as far from Ahab as you can get, about 15 lines down on 403.
For the time I lived as in a musky meadow, I forgot all about our horrible oath.
That's the other mood, when Ahab dipped the harpoon in blood and made them all swear to go after Moby Dick.
In that inexpressible sperm, I washed my hands and my heart of it.
I mean, in other words, I completely got out of that mood, and I completely got into this mood.
So he was in sync with Ahab.
What's he in sync with now?
Well, he's in sync with all the other people who, or the other subgroup of sailors from the boat.
I don't know how they got picked or who they were, who were doing this job together.
So in the middle of 403, I squeezed that sperm till I myself almost melted into it.
I squeezed that sperm until a strange sort of insanity came over me.
This was this very strange mood.
I found myself unwittingly squeezing my co-laborer's' hands in it, mistaking their hands for the gentle gobules.
Such an abounding, affectionate, friendly, loving feeling did this avocation beget.
And this is sort of friendship at its best.
And it's related to this friendship he has for Quequeg.
That's the only other time we hear about this kind of special loving mood that you can get into that's very important.
It certainly seems to be erotic, and it certainly seems to be sentimental, but he quickly gives it a broader and very interesting meaning.
And that's at the bottom of the page.
Remember, the subject we're interested in is: can you find meaning in a world without onto theology, without the supreme being and the total order?
In short, without Dante.
That's the guy in our course that stands for this.
And the answer is yes, but only if you don't insist on total, eternal fulfillment the way you're supposed to get it if you stare at God at the end of the divine comedy.
So here's what he says.
Second line at the bottom paragraph.
For now, since by many prolonged or repeated experiences, I have perceived that in all cases, man must eventually lower or at least shift his conceit of attainable felicity.
That's a mouthful.
His conceit of attainable felicity means he's got to lower his demand for what happiness is.
What kind of happiness you can attain.
That is, you can't have total, eternal, unconditional, and absolute fulfillment.
So you have to place it, not placing it anywhere in the intellect or the fancy, but in.
And now comes a whole list of particular, temporary, sometimes short-term, sometimes long-term, local-ish forms of satisfaction.
The wife, and I'll keep giving you sort of, just so you see what's going on, each of these is going to be a mood, and each of these is going to be related to some goddess or god in the pantheon, roughly the Greeks.
It doesn't map completely, but there's the wife, that's the domestic mood, that's Hera.
The heart.
I take the heart is the friendship that he's been having because it's this kind of warm, very affectionate feeling that you can have for your fellow human beings.
The bed, I take that to be sex and Aphrodite and the erotic.
The table, it's not, of course.
Have I talked about this already?
I suddenly, no, good.
I remember something that I thought to myself.
The table isn't, of course, a kind of special relationship to tables like this.
It means food.
It means being concerned to make good meals and to take the trouble to get the meal set up and cook the food and get the people together.
I did talk about it in some other connection, didn't I?
Where, how?
I don't know either.
But it's all right.
I'm talking about it again.
It's another one.
It's more short-lived, but it's a local, temporary world around the dinner in which all these people are brought together and they're all brought out in their best.
Heidegger has this idea that you can make these self-contained worlds which have their own meaning and bring things out in their own most, as he puts it.
So fathers and mothers and children and vegetables and all are brought out at their best when the dinner comes out right.
And that's another one of these things.
It's not like staring into God in the divine comedy, but it is a kind of happiness.
The table, the saddle, that's for horse people.
My daughter was one of them.
And that goes, Captain Kirk obviously was one of them.
We talked about how that's when he went to his sort of retirement.
It was some beautiful horses.
The fireside.
The fireside is a funny one.
I'm having this deja retreat that I, oh, I talked about this in another lecture.
I gave it another state in another week.
I don't think I did.
I tell you about the foyer?
Okay, the fireside is interesting because it's the example of these kinds of focal practices.
Focal practices is what a guy named Borgman calls them.
There's no reason why you should know about Albert Borgman, but he did write a very good book, and it was about the way focal practices are different than what he calls the just enjoying commodities, where you just get the result and you don't have to do any work and you don't have to have any skill, and it always gives you just the thing you want, and nothing more or less.
So, fast food is the commodity version of the cultivation of the table.
And in the case of the foyer, it means in French, fireplace.
The fireplace is the foyer.
It's the focus because once it was the focus of the family, in which they had to have the skill for cutting the wood, for keeping the fire going, and they had to sit around it to keep warm and to cook and presumably to read the Bible or whatever they did in those days.
And therefore, the fireplaces are sort of the model or a kind of focal practice.
And they turn into commodities in a funny way.
That's what I suddenly stopped and remembered that I told this to some other group, and I'll tell it to you too, because it's sort of pathetic and funny.
My daughter shows up in this again.
I mean, the idea that sitting in front of the fireplace is the way to sort of be when you're at home, she had that.
Unfortunately, we didn't have any fireplace, but she instead always did her homework and petted the cat and talked to her friends sitting on the hot air vent in the floor in the living room.
And that's what's left of the fireplace as it's turning into a commodity, where the heat just comes there and it doesn't have any focus and it doesn't take any skill and it doesn't unite anybody around it.
And the last pathetic thing I thought was, well, the next generation is going to have radiant heat in the floor and not even any hot air coming in through a vent, and that's the end of it.
Heat will have turned completely from the spokes of the family into something so much of a commodity that nobody will even know.
The room, the thermostat will do its job, and the room will stay the same temperature summer and winter.
And there's a danger that all of these can be gotten rid of by being turned into commodities.
The next one is the country.
That means patriotism, I suppose.
You could think of that as the Aeneas, or you could think of that as what Athena brings about in the Orestea, where the pride in Athens is the meaningful thing.
So all of these, that list, is a list of somewhat meaningful practices which could still make your life worth living, but you can only have them if you lower your standards and don't insist that it be a complete knockout of the traditional Dante story.
Okay, then that's what's so interesting about that particular chapter.
And what's, I realized just yesterday that he's prepared you for this, or I mean, that would give much too much of a sense that he knows what he's doing.
But something in him came out earlier that is related to this when on 102, when you get another one of these absolute people, the guy who doesn't think, who isn't insisting on an absolute relation to God, in fact, he's thinking about an absolute relation to nothing.
That's Balkington, standing in the howling gale of the infinite, in the indefinite and the ungrounded, and not asking for any meaning.
But for him, he doesn't want the port, the land.
But here there's a good story about the land on 102 at the top.
In the port is safety, comfort, hearthstone, there we go again, the fireplace.
Supper, there's the table again.
Warm blankets, friends, there's the love again.
All that's kind to our mortalities.
And it's not, notice, talk about the slavish land here and how nobody in their right mind would go and walk around on that turnpike earth with its landmarks all over and no indeterminate, no mystery.
There is the side of Melville which really does appreciate a kind of much lowered but nonetheless satisfying and meaningful way of life.
And it comes up there, and it certainly is, for him, a kind of sacred.
So the fireplace and cultivating your dinner and all, and the Aphrodite erotic and all that can be sacred.
And the way you can see it in this funny way on the bottom of 403, after he lists all these local moods, I keep wanting to say two of these, there is a mood, of course, I keep forgetting to say, which goes with each of these, whether it's the erotic mood or the domestic mood or the aggressive mood and so forth.
All of this, he says, where is it now?
I am ready, and after I perceived all this, I'm ready to squeeze case that is sperm eternally.
And then the sacred.
In thoughts of the visions of the night, I saw long rows of angels in paradise, each with his hands in a jar of spermacetti.
I mean, instead of getting a total contemplation of God in paradise forever, you get the opportunity to have, in this case, this sort of sensuous, loving, friendly relation to other people around this job.
So, okay, so that's what there is to say about that.
That activity gathers together the people and the angels, and in Heidegger jargon, that is the mortals and the gods, and so forth.
And it creates little worlds.
That's certainly a world for a while around the squeezing of the sperm.
So much for that.
Now, it's interesting to contrast this.
Melville is really wonderfully sort of complicated because he always sees all sides of everything.
And there are happy moods where people have lowered their, what is it, something, demand for felicity, that is their sense of happiness, and they've lowered them too much.
You wouldn't think he would have a story about that.
What would it be like to have a wrong version of this?
Well, this will make do with friendship as a kind of mood.
And what would be wrong with it?
Well, what would be wrong with it?
Well, let's see if you can figure out what's wrong with it.
The example of it is the Samuel Enderby, the ship, where he meets Boomer and Bunger, the two happy captain and ship's doctor, which who live in an ordinary, sort of happy, seeming kind of domestic or whatever, I mean, friendly, no, it's a really friendly mood.
And it turns out that he starts making it look very attractive, but by the end, it's not attractive.
And you have to understand why he doesn't like it.
Okay, so it starts out looking attractive on 421, where he describes one of them, which one?
I don't remember.
It doesn't matter which.
I think it's Boomer.
But the middle of the top paragraph, he was a darkly tanned, burly, good-natured, fine-looking man of 60 thereabouts.
And he had one empty arm.
Yeah, that's Captain Boomer.
Moby Dick took the other arm into his jacket.
But he seems like a really attractive guy.
As I read it, it reminds me very much of the description of Bulkington.
But you could think of him as the absolute anti-Bulkington, who is so a heroic nihilist.
These people are neither heroic nor nihilist.
But not that Nelville wants you to be heroic and nihilist, after all, Bulkington got dumped into the sea almost immediately.
But there's something wrong with these people.
We have to figure out what it is.
And on 425, you get a feel for it.
You could have jumped into the story anywhere.
I'm just jumping in the middle of 425.
Boomer says to Dr.
Bunger, Bunger, you dog, laugh out.
Why don't you?
You know you're a precious jolly rascal.
Oh, heave-ahead, boy, I'd rather be killed by you than kept alive by any other man.
And you can just see the sort of goodwill and jolliness that goes through all this, the constant banter between them.
And, of course, they're not interested in chasing Moby Dick the way Ahab is, because they're happy as they are.
You see this on 426, the middle of the page, where Boomer says, with about five chasing Moby Dick, don't want to try to.
Ain't one limb enough?
What should I do without this other arm?
And I'm thinking Moby Dick doesn't bite so much as he swallows.
I don't quite know what that line means.
Maybe he thinks that the next time he encounters Moby Dick, he might be swallowed altogether.
I don't know.
But he does say something very important because you want to keep in mind all the interpretations of Moby Dick.
And here he's got one, he says, a little below that.
What you take for the white whale's malice is only his awkwardness.
It's not his song.
Good.
It's only his awkwardness, for he never means to swallow a single limb.
He only thinks to terrify by feints.
So there's just another view.
By the way, here I will stop for a parenthetical remark.
As I told you already, I can't keep from discussing the final three chases that make up the exciting ending of the book.
And I am putting it off till Tuesday by running out of here and giving you the evaluations.
But read like mad over the weekend, because you're going to have to read it sooner or later anyway to write a paper on it.
And because it's such a great book, and I would rather you, for your fun, that you read it through to the end before I have to tell you the end.
But of course, what's going to have to become clear in the end is what is Moby Dick really up to?
What is the meaning of Moby Dick?
And of course, the answer is not going to be anything simple.
But I won't tell you even a hint what.
But keep your eye open every time they chase Moby Dick, whether who's got the right interpretation of what he's up to.
Is he a dumb brute, which Starbucks says?
Is he a moral avenger, as he is in the story of Steelkilt, which you'll read in here, where the bad guy gets knocked into the sea and swallowed up by Moby Dick and so forth.
Okay, back to where I am.
These guys sit around and they laugh and they have fun and they give you that perspective on Moby Dick.
And Boomer doesn't feel any need to get revenge or ultimate answers or recognition that he's important in the universe.
He's just happy to sit and drink and make jokes with his old buddy Bunner.
And they sound like a kind of vaudeville team and they're full of good cheer.
So what's wrong with it?
Anybody know?
There's two things wrong with them in the Melville world.
Well, anybody?
How many moods do you think they've got?
Don't you have the feeling that they're locked into one mood?
That they've been in this kind of joking, drinking, backslapping, funny frame of mind forever.
And that's bad.
The idea is to get the rainbow of moods, not to get stuck in one mood forever.
I think that's half of what's wrong with it.
And the other half of what's wrong with it is it's somehow a shallow mood.
I don't know what to say about that, except that it doesn't somehow gather enough.
It doesn't gather the divinities, and it doesn't bring out mortality.
There's something certainly, from Melville's point of view, superficial.
And you can get the contrast when you see because Melville earlier before he presents them, in a way tells you what's wrong with them.
And I'm going to read it.
And this time it's your turn.
See if you can tell.
You better be able to tell what this says is wrong with it.
Besides, there's simple-minded mono-mood is it's something wrong with that mood.
And here, here it is, on page 410.
Complicated things are happening.
It's not just about Boomer and Bunner at all, but they're implicated.
But keep your eye open for the big, important thing.
So starting the first full paragraph, two-thirds down on page 410, when it turns out that he's been in a very strange mood, looking into the fire, and he looked into the fire so much, and he thought he saw devils dancing around in the triworks, when they were cooking the fat.
I think that's where we are now.
No, the cassock.
Yeah, the triworks.
Okay, that's when they cook the meat and render out the fat of the whale.
And he's had this feeling that they're devils dancing around the fire.
And he says, look not too long.
And he gets in that mood.
And then he almost capsizes the ship because he gets so hypnotized that he forgets which direction they're going.
Look not too long in the face of the fire, O man.
Never dream with thy hand on the helm.
Turn not thy back to the compass.
Accept the first hint of the hitching tiller.
Believe not the artificial fire when its redness makes all things look ghastly.
Now, why not?
Well, not because you shouldn't be in that mood sometimes, but tomorrow in the natural sun, the skies will be bright.
Those who glared like devils in the forking flames, the morn will show in far other, gentler relief, the glorious golden-clad, glad sun, the only true lamp, all others but liars.
So he flips you from that night moon to the how it's really the truth is that everything is terrific.
The sun is shining and everything is bright.
Anything wrong already?
If you're reading carefully, you see, even if this was in some other translation, I would say, uh-oh, look at the translation.
What is that?
The only true lamp?
I mean, there isn't any only true in Ishmael and Mel.
What is he talking about?
Well, it isn't a mistranslation, of course.
He goes on, nevertheless, and here we go in the other direction: the sun hides not Virginia's dismal swamp, nor Rome's accursed Campania, nor wide Sahara, nor all the millions of miles of deserts and of grief beneath the moon.
The sun hides not the ocean, which is the dark side of this earth, and which is two-thirds of this earth.
The brightness of the sun is rapidly being cut down to one perspective, and not even the biggest.
So, therefore, that mortal man who hath more of joy than sorrow in him, that mortal man cannot be true, not true or undeveloped.
Okay, now, can you relate that to Boomer and Bunner?
If it's a no-brainer, if you can't figure out why, now you understand, presumably, something about what's wrong with their totally constant jolliness.
Well, they have no sense of the dark side, of the grief, of the fact that it isn't always sunny.
And he says it next right away: the truest of all men was the man of sorrows.
The truest of all books is Solomon and Ecclesiastes.
In the fine hammered steel of woe, all is vanity, and so forth.
Now he switches over to that.
And now he's going to say what's wrong with them and everybody else who's in a constant jolly mood.
He who dodges hospitals and jails, walks fast across graveyards, and would rather talk of operas than hell, calls Cowper, Young, Pascal, and Rousseau poor devils, all sick men.
And there, and throughout a carefree lifetime, swears by Rabelais, who is in sort of a jolly mood, too, apparently.
I haven't read Rabelais, but I think I've liked Boomer and Bunner.
Swears by Rabelais wise and therefore jolly.
There's the key.
Jolly is what they were.
And it's all right to be jolly sometimes.
But it's not all right to be any mood all the time.
And it's particularly not all right to be jolly all the time.
So not that man is fitted to sit down on tombstones and break the green damp mold with unfathomably wondrous Solomon.
But.