Two big subjects for today.
Both of them very interesting, as interesting as anything in the book, but there's so much interesting in this book.
But anyway, the one is his Dante's reaction to the incontinence, as the chapter is called, as the canto is called.
I don't think that's the right name for it, that that's all right.
We will rename it when the time comes.
And I explain why it shouldn't be called that.
But it's called, oh, it's called the Carnal.
Why did I get the idea?
It's the incontinent.
I don't know.
That's not my name for it.
It's not, and it's not Charlie's name for it.
Anyway, it's Canto 5 that we're going to be reading.
And I think we'll see that Virgil calls it incontinent, and Chardi, the translator, calls it carnal.
I want to call it the committed, but these are the people who are, so to speak, the opposite of the uncommitted outside of hell who don't get sort of committed to anything.
The people in this level of hell are totally committed to something, something which is not going to give them a joyful life if they get committed to it.
I mean, you can be committed to, say, smoking with all your might, but that doesn't mean that you're going to have a good life.
But so Dante's interested in these people because he admires them as committed, and he somewhat identifies with them in the kind of commitment they've got, but he also knows that it's got something wrong with it.
And that's all going to turn out to be very interesting.
Why I call them incontinent is, and why Virgil calls them incontinent, is that literally means incontinence, you've lost control.
And these people have lost control of their lives.
And this is a very good example of the kind of punishment that is the good kind, not the contrapaso, where you did something and now something nasty is going to happen to you, but where what happens to you in hell is what happens already through in your life, which what you couldn't give up even if you wanted to, and what's revealed in hell is the dark side of it, and that's what you're stuck with for eternity.
But I think I mentioned before, but if I didn't, I want to say it now.
When Dante says that when these souls are ferried over to hell, I don't want to try to look it up right now, their fear turns to desire.
Did I mention that?
Oh, I wish I could open my book to it, but I don't want to spend the time.
But anyway, what that means, what I would take that to mean is that they both fear the consequences of this kind of commitment that they've got, but they wouldn't give it up.
It's like telling somebody who's a smoker that if they go on smoking, they'll get emphysema, but the next hour or so, when they're ready to smoke, their fear of emphysema is trumped by their desire to smoke.
So these people, even though they know the dark side, can't give up the desire.
And now we'll, and they turn out to be not smokers in Dante's time, but in the circle we're going to look at, the carnal, according to Darty, these are sex and love addicts.
And some are just sex addicts.
I don't think any of them are just love addicts.
And then there are gluttons and people hooked on material things.
And oddly, the angry.
I spent a long time trying to figure out what it is that the angry love and desire.
I mean, the love addicts love people, and the gluttons love food, and the materialists love things like BMWs.
But what do the angry love?
Well, all you can say is it's sort of, it's almost like a pun.
Well, what they loved was getting angry.
They loved hating people.
That's the only way to understand their kind of addiction.
There are people who just are sort of can't control the fact that they are always in a state of outrage, and those are the ones in the angry.
Now, we're only going to talk about the ones in the circle of the lovers, because those are the most interesting to Dante, and their relation of their, I don't even want to call it crime, the relation of their addiction to their punishment is the most interesting.
All these people love the wrong things.
Other people's bodies, food, material things, and getting angry.
Those are all the wrong things.
And what's wrong with them?
That's where it begins to be interesting.
It's not a kind of puritanical rejection of them.
It's the only thing wrong with loving one person with all your might is it is not fulfilling and it has certain painful consequences.
And the same for food and the same for material things.
These are all people who loved something too much, more than it could satisfy them.
One more thing, Papers.
And you've got to resist this puritanical tendency.
It's fun to have Chiardi in here just to see how sort of hopeless our culture has become.
And a Catholic he is, too.
I mean, it sounds like Puritan Protestantism to think that somehow loving bodies and sex too much is so terrible.
In fact, you've got to realize that for Dante, it is the least serious sin there can be.
Because up to now, all we've seen is the people that aren't really counted as sinners because Dante made up the category, namely the uncommitted, and then the people in Limbo who aren't sinners because they couldn't help it, what they did, but they've got lives where they have no relation to Jesus or God.
And now we've got the first of the sinners who, that is, knew about Christianity, were Christians, and loved something too much.
But it's the sin for which Dante has the most sympathy.
It's practically admiration he has for them, as you'll see.
And that's because what they love is the most fulfilling thing short of the fulfilling something that you could love.
We haven't really talked about what that would be yet, but we won't for a while.
But it's obviously, I mean, in some version or other, it's got to be what Jesus was telling the apostles to love, to love each other and to love him in some way which is different than what the lovers in this canto have to each other.
The lovers in this canto are examples of romantic love.
They are a kind of total commitment for another individual, or sort of mixed in with them, is also people who were just totally committed to sex and made phallic idols and so forth.
This woman we'll hear about.
And you have to sort of look up in the footnotes the various people who are in one of these stages of the inferno to try to figure out what the unifying feature is.
And I'm sort of reading into it my version of the unifying feature: uncommitted addicts for sex and/or romantic love.
That's what that covers them all, and only then.
Now, Viakas.
Oh, great.
Let's hear it.
Yes, okay.
This is what I'm trying to explain.
I want to get my pen so I can write it in.
But what I'm trying to explain, okay, what I want to explain is what is it, I'm trying all the time, we should be thinking all the time about what it means to say that as these souls approach the inferno, which is full of all kinds of unpleasant things, to say the least, they nonetheless desire it.
That's what I was trying to explain.
It's all passed over eagerly from here.
Divine justice transforms and spurs them so that their dread turns wish, they yearn for what they fear.
That just continues.
You can think of smokers and emphysema if you want.
That's part of divine justice.
It's just built into the way nature works.
That if you love the kind of things that are in this first four stages, again, love beautiful bodies or food and good food, I mean, gourmet food, even, and beautiful material things, and getting angry, this funny category, which, by the way, sort of fits Dante.
He's angry about an awful lot of things by the end of the book.
I mean, he's angry about politics, he's angry about popes, he puts the current Pope in hell already and says there's only a kind of ghost of the Pope actually on the throne.
So he knows that anger is a big, big temptation.
Okay, where are we now?
So they're seeing what they find attractive in their life now unglamorized and unattractive, but still irresistible.
They haven't got any of the illusions anymore and the rationalizations and the social support that covered up the downside.
The way being a glutton looks like being a gourmet when you're eating in a nice restaurant with people you like and so forth.
But that covers up the fact that if that's the most satisfying thing in your life, you're in trouble.
And if it's if it's, I had a neighbor, that's what I'm talking about, he had a white BMW convertible, and every weekend he cleaned and polished and shined and washed this beautiful white convertible.
And Dante would have felt sorry for him and said he'd be better off if he had gone to Che Panis or even better off if he had a girlfriend.
But there are all these levels of getting addicted to things that aren't really satisfying.
So now what else here?
Let's see.
And the sins, of course, get worse as you go down.
That's what I was just saying when I said, you've got to realize that sort of structurally.
That's how you know that the carnal ones, the romantic love one, is the least serious because it's the top of this going down that funnel, which is the inferno.
When you get to the bottom of the inferno, you get the worst sinner of all.
Obviously, Satan is going to be down there.
And so now you see that.
So things get worse and worse.
And now we're going to look at the circle of the committed lovers.
Because Dante is so close to them.
Because after all, they were influenced by the chivalric love stories.
Powell and Francesca, who are now the people we're going to talk about from now on, who were the big stars in what would be something like, it isn't People magazine, what do people read to find out what the latest stars are, who's involved with whom, and so forth.
That was the big news in Florence, anyway.
Powell and Francesca were lovers, and lo and behold, they were caught by her husband and he killed them.
And that was pretty sensational.
And they became lovers from reading one of these chivalric stories about Lancelot.
And Dante, his love, his lady Beatrice, one of the things that saves Dante from a fate similar to this is that Beatrice is dead.
So Dante isn't tempted to run off with her and commit adultery or she run off with her husband.
But his kind of addiction to Beatrice is very similar.
And if it's different, we won't find out for a long time how it's different.
Now, and what is their punishment?
Well, their punishment, now, what do you expect?
It ought to be whatever, the dark side, which they tend to overlook or just accept of their way of life, of their character, of what the main thing is for them, is.
And having read it, can you tell?
I mean, Dante's very subtle.
He doesn't just hit you over the head with what's wrong with that form of life.
He sort of embodies it in the punishment.
Do you remember what's happened?
What's their problem when they're in this circle?
What's their form of torture?
Well, I'll explain it, but I mean, this is how you have to ask yourself as you go.
But I'll give you a demonstration.
Their problem is that they are swept around in a kind of constant storm.
At the bottom of 58, this is now in Canto 5, line 27.
I came to a place stripped bare of every light and roaring on the naked dark like seas racked by the war of winds, their hellish flight, of storm and counterstorm through time foregone, sweeps the soul of the man of the damned, whirling and battering, it drives them on.
So that means that he's taken up a kind of metaphor about passionate lovers.
And it's that it can be like a storm.
It can be very full of ups and downs and jealousies and fights and making up and so forth.
It's definitely not a peaceful way of life.
And he's dramatizing that passion is a storm.
You can see that on page 59.
Three cantos from there, he says, well, let's start at the top of 59.
And this, I learned, was the never-ending flight of those who sinned in the flesh, the carnal and the lusty, who betrayed reason to their appetite.
Now, there's so many things going on at once in Dante.
People write books and books about how there's a symbolic level and a biblical level and a literal level and a, I don't know, that's just a waste of time.
Dante did write about that.
What's important going on is that you're getting a description by Virgil of something Virgil doesn't really understand.
Because all of these things look different once Jesus has come and you have the creation as your perspective.
It would take me a while to explain little by little how they look different.
By the end of today, you will understand.
But it is a very Virgil thing to say that they betrayed reason to their appetite.
I mean, that's what he might say about Dido.
That's his stoic view that you should always be rational and have self-control and never let your base desires get out of hand.
You've got to keep them under control and then pose a form on that unruly aspect of what it is to be a human being.
Okay, so, and now we say, skipping a stanza, here they are up, down, they whirl, and whirling string with never a hope of hope to comfort them, nor of release, or even of less pain.
So their pain is simply their being battered around.
They have no repose.
You'll see, they have no peace.
They know it, and they are not happy about that.
But they wouldn't give each other up for peace and repose.
So they're stuck in this.
It's wrong to say, as Virgil did, and when we get the Italian, which we're about to do, we'll find out.
Beatrice, note this one, on tanto 5, line about 42 or something, the tanto just above the one of we're up and down.
As the wings of wintering starlings bear them on in their great wheeling flight, just so the blast wearies these evil souls through time foregone.
You see anything funny about that?
Are they evil?
Are our sort of knights and ladies who are totally committed to each other and constantly in a turmoil?
I don't know where knights and ladies are because they don't get together very often.
But I mean, say romantic lovers then.
Are romantic lovers evil?
Well, they are to Chiardi because carnal lovers, oh, but not in marriage.
Oh, good grief.
But that's not Dante's problem.
The translation I gather is not evil but unhappy souls.
And of course that would make perfect sense, but we're going to check it out.
Now, so any questions yet or any objections?
I'm just going to go through this so you can see what it's like to read one of these cantos.
Yes, yes.
And that's how it is in Limbo, too, already in Dante.
It's a continuation of what their life was.
But it isn't always, and then it's sort of unfortunate.
But when he's doing his best, it is.
And this is one of his best, because he feels so close to it.
So let's go on here.
They really have got sinners at a certain point on the way down.
And before the end of today, I'm going to tell you where sin starts.
Sin starts where the city of sin starts.
And we haven't got to, we're in the suburbs of sin right now.
That is, we're in the fields and marshes and winds and swamps.
If you look at these punishments, they're all out in the suburbs or in the fields.
We haven't actually got to Sin City yet.
We get there eventually.
So now we're going to concentrate on the lovers.
They're being swept about in their ups and downs, elations and depressions that Dante thinks goes with romantic love.
And the question is, so what exactly have they done wrong to get them into this?
Well, Virgil's version we just heard was they lack self-control.
They've got reasons of their appetite, a very stoic answer.
I don't think that's Dante's answer.
I think Dante's answer is that they worshiped each other.
Or they either worshipped sex or they worshiped or adored each other.
It's a question of putting something in the place of God that they've done, but in a very wonderful way, I mean, because they're at least very committed.
So you find this out on 59 further down, the middle of the page, roughly, line 40-something.
I can't read it.
Line 50, maybe I've scribbled over it.
Line 50, roughly.
He's talking about the various people they saw.
I just want to show you that there's the people who actually worship sex, and then there are the people who actually worship each other, I think.
But here's one of the made idols.
For the first of these, of whose history you should know, he answered, was empress of many tongues, mad sensuality corrupted her soul.
And then the footnote says she was a queen and she made phallic idols and so forth.
And that's, and that's Cimmeranus, it says.
And so we're skipping down now to 60.
The other is Dido that he sees, faithless to the ashes of Scythius.
She killed herself for love.
Well, I guess that's in there.
We should look at the Italian, but I can't believe we're going to get our way out of this one.
It makes it look like Dido's problem was that she wasn't loyal to her husband, who was dead.
I mean, that seems to be asking an awful lot of, I don't know, any system of ethics that would condemn somebody just for not being faithful to their dead husband.
I mean, I don't know what Dante's thinking here.
Well, oh, it's Virgil talking.
Ah, well, that helps.
Virgil does say that, does condemn her for that in his amazingly sort of Puritan Protestant way, but you can't say that about Virgil, but his very moralistic story.
He does say that he shouldn't have, I mean, he says at least that she shouldn't have had sex with Aeneas until they were married.
I mean, this is not a Dante-ish frame of mind.
So it's not that she was faithless to the ashes of Sicius, but she did kill herself for love because she let herself get out of control over total passion for Aeneas, and that's a life that leads her to running around the streets of Carthage.
Is that the name?
Raving lad with bloodshot eyes and so forth.
She was definitely caught up in a kind of storm.
And Cleopatra gets into it, and Helen, from whom such ill arose, which is interesting.
Helen didn't die for love.
She was swept away by Paris.
And Virgil just condemns her for the bad effects.
Virgil hasn't got a very sensible, worked-out ethics, I don't think.
I mean, and charting always makes it worse, so let's not worry about that.
But on the top of 60, we get the people we're interested in.
And Paris and Tristan, I mean, these, funny, he's got this, Paris, I take it, is the one who ran off with Helen, but then Tristan goes with Isolda, and those are part of the chivalry kind of love.
The romantic, they're the beginning of romantic love.
And they whirl about, and all of these people are torn from the mortal life by love.
That's interesting.
Not Helen.
That's very strange.
Helen's doing fine, as we remember.
So what's going on here?
See, Helen, this this is Virgil talking, isn't it?
And I, yes, it's Virgil talking.
I've never noticed this before.
He just got it wrong.
He's always getting it wrong.
I'm going to show you in a in a minute where he really gets things wrong.
But let's go on.
I stood there while my teacher was teacher one by one named the great knights and ladies of dim past.
There it is out there.
That's the really important thing.
There are all the romantic lovers.
And I was swept by pity and confusion.
Notice the difference between feeling pity for them and condemning them as evil souls who betrayed their reason to their appetite.
It doesn't sound like courtly love, like knights and ladies to portray their reason to their appetite and be sinners.
No, he feels pity for them because they got swept away.
And that's in the next stanza.
And as I spoke, and then at last I spoke.
Up to now, it looks like Virgil's been speaking, though why was there no end of quotation marks?
I'm very puzzled.
It starts quotation marks from the middle of 59.
Where do they end?
60 that ah, Paris, I see, good.
It ends after Tristan.
Well, who says a thousand shades of those torn from immortal life by love?
Dante, I guess.
But he's got Helen in him.
I doubt if the Italian's going to fix that, but it isn't a big deal.
I mean, it's not something we should worry about, although you'd think after, you know, thousands of years of worshiping this book, people might have noticed and done and worried about it.
Anyway, I'm not going to worry about it.
So there are the great light knights and ladies.
That's the crucial thing.
And then at last I spoke.
Poet, I should be glad to speak a word with those two swept together.
Remember the storm again, and Helen was swept off by Paris?
That's part of our our vocabulary still that's being put into the wind story.
Those two swept together so lightly on the wind and still so sad.
Lightly on the wind.
My eyes are being opened for the first time.
I've read this over and over, and I don't know what to make of all the contradictions in there.
Lightly on the wind, because we've heard how they are battered and squashed around and storm and counterstorm on 58, and whirling and battered, it drives them on.
And now we discover lightly on the wind.
Anyone got any help there?
I don't know.
Dante can't seem to.
I think, you know, what I want to say about it is Dante is so confused about it because, on the one hand, he's condemning them and showing that this life is not a life anybody would want to live for eternity.
And on the other hand, he's so attracted by them.
You got to help me?
Ah, so weightless on the wind.
Wow.
Good.
You fixed it.
I mean, every time I suspect that if you look carefully and you discover that it doesn't make sense, it's almost always the translator.
It isn't as if I could find a better translation.
There would be just different mistakes.
Translators don't seem to understand what they translate.
It seems to be a requirement.
But anyway, that would help a lot, because then they can be battered all they want.
Thank you.
Okay, I'm still back to where I am now.
So where am I?
Can we look at this language?
So constant turmoil of two people who have only each other as their whole world.
They have nothing else than their commitment.
And that makes their relation their lives unstable.
And so it's a different, and it's all got to do with the sort of total dependency on each other.
They have no freedom, no peace of mind.
And I guess, I don't know about no fulfillment.
I've written that in my notes, but I think that's wrong.
They have fulfillment plus suffering.
So they have no, I mean no peace.
That's what their problem.
I mean, they really love each other, and they really love blowing around in the wind, hugging each other.
There's some kind of fulfillment in that, but it's a kind of life that you wouldn't want to lead uninterrupted for eternity.
And Dante admires them very much.
So I'm going to go back at 59.
We've looked at all the places where they get admired.
And 60, we've looked at that.
No, here's the middle.
Again, this is like the weight list.
I mean, Dante is certainly less hard on them than Virgil, about line 80, as mating doves that love calls to their nest.
I mean, look at the metaphor.
Gliding through the air with motionless, raised wings, borne by the sweet desire that fills each breast.
How does sweet desire relate to appetite?
Well, that's not a mistake.
Virgil is the one who says, sort of, that their appetites were driving them.
Dante says their sweet desire still leaves breast.
That's a very different story of romantic love.
It doesn't fit Digo either.
Sweet desire didn't fill her breast.
It was sort of furious passion.
And so, just so those spirits turned on the torn sky from the band where Dido whirls across the air, such was the power of the pity in my cry.
And then he says this sort of prayer for them: O living creatures, gracious, kind, and good, going this pilgrimage.
Would they say that to him?
There's the power of pity in my cry.
Who's talking?
A living creature, gracious, kind, and good.
They are talking to Dante.
But do we know that?
It's definitely them.
How do we know that?
And they speak to him.
He says, does he say, speak to me?
Where?
Uh-huh.
Oh, weary souls, pause and speak to us.
Good.
Dante says that.
And then they say, O living creature, of course, that's Dante.
He's the only one alive in the whole poem.
O living creature, gracious, kind, and good, going this pilgrimage through the sick night, visit us, visiting us who stained the earth with blood.
We're the king of time.
And again, I don't look.
We want to see the Italian of that.
I don't know why they're calling God King of time.
We're the king, that's God, our friend.
We would pray his peace on you who have pitied us.
That's important.
That's the thing.
If you ask them, what would be the nicest thing you could ask of somebody?
What would they say?
Peace, obviously, because that's what they lack.
They're in this constant whirlwind of passion, and they never get a chance to even relax and enjoy it in any kind of serene way.
So when they want to pray something really good for Dante, they say they're asking peace of him.
As long as the wind lets us pause, ask of us what you please.
And then she says these sort of touching things.
Again, you keep Virgil in the background.
This is not carnal lust.
This is not losing your reason to your appetites.
She says, Love, which is in gentlest hearts will soonest bloom, seize my lover with passion for that sweet body from which I was torn untriven to my doom.
Love, which permits no loved one not to love, took me so strongly with delight in him that we are one in hell as we were above.
See, that's what I mean.
You can hardly say that they haven't got any satisfaction.
It's very, they're very tender and very happy to be together.
And that's okay, because they also are very unhappy because they're being battered around and never have a chance to rest and relax and enjoy it.
And it's all because they loved each other somehow so totally.
And now, oh, and when we have to say something quick about how Chiardi, in his Puritanism, gets it wrong on page 64.
Because there they're talking about how she had this passion for his sweet body.
And Chiardi gets all excited about that and says, ah, yeah, but that's exactly what's wrong with their...
Well, that's how the punishment takes effect.
They want each other's bodies, but they can't have them because they don't have any bodies.
That's what he says on page 64.
They can't, he says in footnote 102, find any pleasure in the presence of another.
And at the bottom, he says, as of that paragraph on 64, as insubstantial shades of the bodies for which they once felt such great passion.
I have them can't come in the middle of the sentence there, can I?
The temptation is to interpret this line romantically.
Indeed, I'm falling for that temptation, and I'll show you why.
That is that the love of Powell and Francesca survives hell itself.
It sure does.
The most Dantean interpretation, however, meaning Chiardi, not Dante, is that they add to one another's anguish as mutual reminders of their sin.
I haven't seen them doing that.
And as insubstantial shades of the bodies that once felt such great passion.
Now, why is that dead wrong?
Last time, if anybody is here who was there last time and listening, you ought to be able to figure this out.
That Chiardi is saying that because they don't have bodies, that's part of what makes them suffer.
Because it looks like they're sort of hugging each other, but they can't really hug each other because they haven't got real bodies.
And that's their punishment.
You see any problem?
What's going to happen in the Day of Judgment?
They get their bodies back.
And what's Chiardi going to do about that?
Well, their love, that we discover that their pleasure and their pain will be more intense.
And so that's what's going to happen.
They're going to have great joy having their bodies back, but they're going to be more blown around and upset and turmoiled and restless than ever.
That's the Dante picture.
It has nothing to do with Chiardi's constant gripe against bodies and sensualities and so forth.
Okay, so now we're just also there.
We are.
They're still in love.
Chiardi doesn't admit that, but it's perfect from the obvious from the one lines I just read where she talks about how her lover was seized with passion for her sweet body.
Dante's feeling just that way about Beatrice.
And Virgil says something on 68 that I want to talk about.
Well, that's where, just in case you didn't write it down last time, 68, Canto 6, line 105, is where Virgil says, because he's quoting Aristotle, and that look to your science again, where he's written, the more a thing is perfect, the more it feels of pleasure and pain, and when those souls get their bodies back, they'll have more of it.
See, as for these souls, though they can never soar to true perfection, still in the new time, that is, after the Day of Judgment, they will be nearer to it than they were before.
Okay, that's just to show you where I get this story.
Oh, I just see, I used another metaphor here.
They'll still suffer from the, they'll suffer even more from the tempests of passion.
I mean, these are the kind of things, these words that Dante's taking up to make literal in his punishment.
And they will still be tempestuous lovers.
They will be better and worse off.
I've said that.
And it's important to notice, again, Country Chiari's footnotes, that they're not being punished because they committed adultery.
That's, again, sort of the our modern view, maybe, but not Dante's view.
You notice that it isn't even mentioned that they were committing adultery when her husband came in and killed them.
That doesn't interest Dante a bit.
What's good about them is that they loved each other, and what's bad about them is that they loved only each other, and that's that.
Her husband just doesn't matter.
They're being punished for their whole way of life.
That is romantic love addiction.
And there's nothing that's bad enough and good enough for Dante.
Even if they were, and when I go back to their fear turns to desire, even if they were offered salvation at the price of never seeing each other again, but only adoring God Himself, they wouldn't give each other up.
That's not their nature.
Their eternal nature is to be the lovers of each other.
And that's it.
That's their essential feature.
Just as Dido comes up as one of the lovers, not as the suicides.
It's not her essential character to commit suicide.
It's her sort of essential character to lose control over Aeneas.
She had already lost everything, control, and sort of total, she was totally dependent on her first husband.
He's a case of a woman who loves too much.
And that's what she is, whether she remains faithful to her first husband or Aeneas and so forth, that's not the issue.
And they pray for peace for him.
And what is Dante's reaction to all this?
Seeing both the beauty of their love and the sadness of their punishment and identifying with them so much.
Then let's hear what happens when he, at the end of the canto, starting about line 130.
For when we read, she's talking, how her fond smile was kissed by such a lover, he who is one with me, alive and dead, reads on my lips the tremor of his kiss.
That's already very, very nice.
That book, and he who wrote it, was a pandara.
That's the chivalric romance they were reading.
And that day we read no further.
That was their undoing.
And as she said this, the other spirit who stood by her wept so piteously that I felt my senses reel and faint away with anguish.
I was swept by such a swoon as death is and fell like a corpse might fall to the dead floor of hell.
In short, Dante just fainted.
He couldn't.
This very conflict that I've been saying sort of lurks in this, the attraction of it, how much he would like to be one of those lovers, and the sadness of that kind of love finally can't fulfill you.
That he's so caught in that, that he's so identified with that, that he just faints.
It's the only sin that he faints for.
Or it isn't even a sin.
The only, if you're strictly sticking to sins as what's going to be inside Sin City, then we have to find another word for it.
It's the only wrong way of life that's getting punished that he faints for.
Okay, now, anybody anything to say about that?
Well, we got this question I want to leave you with.
How is Dante's story any different from theirs?
He's so close to them.
Is he just saved by the accident that Beatrice, lucky for him, died?
There must be something better than that to be told.
He said, you have to keep your eyes open through the whole book.
And if you don't have to read the whole book, I'm giving you the excerpts to read where you will find out.
Anything else?
Okay, I certainly want to do one more thing, and now I'm going to do it.
I'm going to talk about the.
I'm going to skim quickly.
I'm not even going to read to you, just to me, the rest of the incontinence.
I don't think I want to talk to them.
They talk about them.
They're the gluttons.
They're the collectors of material things.
There's bigger spending eternity doing that.
Okay, now that's the end of that.
As I was rereading it, I hate to interrupt myself and you all, but there's a puzzle bothering me that I can't imagine why I never worried about it before.
It's going to be all over the place.
What kind of love is this?
I mean, we say it's romantic love.
That's right.
But that's not agape love.
That is overflowing Christian love.
It's got something to do with agape love, because if you have agape love for your neighbor, you're willing to do anything, including even die for your neighbor and they for you.
But it seems this is not sort of overflowing, fulfilling love, but it's got a lot of arrows in it.
A lot of, remember, arrows is desire for something you absolutely need and lack.
So it seems to be, and maybe romantic love is.
In fact, as I talk, and I'm beginning to think I understand it, romantic love turns out to be an interesting mixture of some aspect of Eros and some aspect of agape.
And it's sort of made up by the troubadours, the chivalric, out of sort of these pieces left over from the Christian practices.
But keep your eye open.
Every time there's talk about love, ask yourself, what does love mean?
Is it desire?
Is it charity?
That is, is it giving?
Is it the totalness of the commitment that Dante cares about?
That's what I really think, and I'm thinking as I talk to you.
I think romantic love is, for Dante, important, not because it's agape, not because it's Eros, but because it is total commitment, where these people are ready to die and go to hell for each other.
That's the crucial thing.
That's a new thing.
That's what the chivalric people invented.
And that's what Dante got.
That's what they got out of the New Testament.
And it's something different than either of the alternatives that were around before, I think.
Ah, yeah, Chuck.
No, you're not, Chuck.
Okay, that's all right.
Go ahead.
To die for the other.
Yes, I think it is.
Right.
There is agape love in there.
But it's agape love sort of mixed in with the sensuous, erotic love, at least in the chivalric story, at least in the way Dante's telling it.
And what do you see his reaction to, well, I won't even tell you.
But anyway, yes, there's got to be this erotic thing.
It's as if somehow agape love got fused with erotic love, and out of that came a new conception of a romantic love.
See, agape also has the side, not of total, it is, agape love isn't at all the total commitment to one other person, or even to one other sort of thing, like material things or food.
Agape love is love your neighbor.
That's what it is, it's love for everybody.
Love the one you're with and who needs you, whoever.
So that's the funny thing.
Agape love is getting switched into romantic love and right in front of our eyes those in Dante.
And then naturally it's sort of hard to follow because it's a moving target.
But our Dante will come, and you'll see it more next two times from now, a new idea of love that's just not that put together out of pieces from the New Testament that is something that isn't in there until you put it together.
Okay, don't worry about that yet, except keep it in the back of your mind.
I want to go to the next piece of paper here.
Oh, here it is.
Okay, the rest of the time, we've got to do something entirely different, but it's very important and lots of fun, which is what happens to Dante when he finally gets to the city of dis, which I've been calling thin city, or he calls it the translator at one point, Hell's Metropolis.
Because all, up to now they've been in the woods, remember.
All these people punished, the wrathful, and so forth, are all in the swamps.
And then comes the fact that they finally get to the city of Dis on page 82 here, Panto 5, line 61, or no, it's more, yeah, 65 maybe.
My son, the master, said, the city called Dis lies just ahead.
This is the Roman name for Hades, who was the god of the underworld in Homer.
So this is the city of Hades, only now translated into Latin.
So the city called Dis lies just ahead, the heavy citizens, the swarming crowds of hell's metropolis.
And I, that master, I already see the glowing red of its mosques as if they came hot from the fort to smolder in this valley.
And my all-knowing guide, well, that was a shock when I found that, because good grief, me, Virgil has hardly got a grip on this.
And surely Dante realizes that.
Well, it wasn't in the Italian, according to, we'll write down and make sure.
When I last got to ask somebody about this, this is about line 70.
My all-knowing guide, it just says, and my guide, I hope, says, they are eternal fires of lower hell.
And as he spoke, we entered a moat.
And then we come up to hell, and guess what happens?
At the entrance, there is above the gates.
There are gates.
There's a wall.
There's gates.
I wouldn't make a big fuss about the wall and the gates, except everything's going to turn on that in a minute.
Above the gates, more than a thousand shades or spirits purged from heaven for its glory cried, Who is that that invades death's kingdom in his life?
Now, everything is already in there, but it's packed in there.
Who could these creatures be who are on the wall and who are said to be purged from heaven for its glory?
You know who they are?
The fallen angels.
The fallen angels have taken up and got ticked out of paradise and they have set up their own city, namely the city of Dis, with Satan who got taken, who was the leader of the people, the angels who got ticked out.
That's all got to be there.
And they take this as an invasion because they are defending themselves against God.
Now, you've got to know why they would be doing that.
And the answer is sort of complicated.
Milton understood it well in Paradise Lost, where Satan says at one point, better to rule in hell than serve in heaven.
So what is it?
These are the angels who, even though contemplating God on his terms, gets you complete bliss, they would rather be autonomous, interestingly enough, free, able to choose the terms on which they love and what they love and how much they love, and not be, in effect, sort of just homing missiles aimed at God.
I put it in that funny way because Augustine says that God has created us so that, quote, our soul is restless until it finds rest in thee, namely God.
So it's part of this creation understanding of being, that God has created all these creatures, us, and he's built in us a need.
This is sort of anagape.
This is sort of more like Errow's talk.
He's built in us a need for contemplating God, and we won't, we'll be restless like Paul and Francesco or in any other way, until we find peace.
And the only way to find peace and fulfillment is to contemplate God.
But you've got to do it on God's terms.
And the fallen angels would rather be free and making up the meaning of their lives on their own terms, that is, autonomous.
So they went and set up city where Satan rules and everybody rejects God.
Now, now comes the fun part.
Virgil wants to get into this fortress.
But Virgil has no understanding that autonomy and self-control and sort of giving the law to yourself is a sin.
Because you have to have the whole framework of the creation to see that.
It's only if, one, we're created with a need for total fulfillment, and two, God's created us so that He satisfies that need for total fulfillment, that then self-control and autonomy becomes a sin.
But if, as at the time of Virgil, there's nothing satisfied in the universe, and if you've got a lot of desire, you can't just satisfy it by contemplating God.
You have to curb it, control it, and bring it down to whatever it is that you desire can fulfill.
So you get a middle-sized desire for sex and romantic love, and maybe an even smaller desire for food, and a little desire for material things, because they can each fulfill you somewhat.
But the idea that you should have no control, but be totally open through contemplating God, that's only possible once God creates you as a need for him.
That's what I call he creates you as a homing missile, which you flounder around for a while.
Beatrice explains this later, until you finally manage to point just directly toward God, because the things that you go after when you're a child and so forth don't satisfy you, and even your lover doesn't satisfy you.
But finally, you get honed in on God.
You were made to be satisfied by God, and he will satisfy you.
All that's in the background.
But Virgil doesn't know any of that.
So what does Virgil do?
He goes up to the wall and he says something.
This is the fun where Dante's having fun.
And where you get the impression that Dante is really very smart and knows exactly what he's up to, playing Virgil off against Christianity.
The most important moment that happens is right now at the wall.
Because the interesting issue is, what's a wall of?
Is it a wall of a fortress to keep God and angels and everybody else out?
Or is it a prison that is there to keep the bad guys?
Virgil thinks it's a prison.
But the shades on the wall have said, which are the fallen angels, who invades this kingdom?
So now Virgil goes up to the front door of this something or other, which has a wall, and says at the gate, something, but we don't know what.
And then funny things happen.
The bottom of 83, Canto 110.
My sweet guide leaves me, and I stay in doubt with yes and no, dividing all my heart with hope and fear poor Dante's been abandoned by his guide.
I could not hear my lord's words.
That means Virgil's words.
It's not God with a capital L.
But the pack that gathered round him suddenly broke away, howling and jostling and went pouring back, slamming the towering gate hard in his face.
That great soul, that's Virgil again.
I don't know why all these capital letters, stood alone outside the wall.
Then he came back.
His pain showed in his face.
His eyes were fixed on the ground.
His vows sagged from its assurance.
And what did he say?
Dante leaves you with this little puzzle.
Virgil said something, and it had a big result.
Bang, they ran in, they slammed the door.
He's completely confused.
He didn't know what to think.
What did he say?
Somebody must be able to figure it out.
It's totally stand up.
Well, let's look at it this way.
What is Virgil's understanding of what he's doing, leading Dante around?
Who sent him to lead?
Beatrice sent him to lead.
And under whose authority did Beatrice do it?
Well, God's, of course, but it's particular of the Virgin Mary, I think.
I forget the details.
But anyway, what Virgil said was: we're on a divine mission.
We're sent here by God.
And boy, did that not produce the results he expected.
They produced exactly the opposite.
To say that he's sent there by God and they all slam the door and run in, and Virgil can't understand what went on.
And he says that, well, we don't need to know what more he says right here.
Let me go on to where they are.
They're blocked.
And then, so Virgil's very confused.
By the way, I'm telling you this all because you can see that Virgil doesn't understand the architecture and landscape of the inferno.
That is, he doesn't understand the big divisions, like this wall between this and what's outside and what's inside.
Virgil hasn't got the categories.
Even when he brings in the Stoics and when he brings in Aristotle, he still hasn't got the right distinctions.
Because there's this distinction, this crucial distinction, between the people who love too much, whose love is misdirected, and the people who reject God, who are sinners because they're trying to set themselves up as independent of God.
That's a hugely important distinction.
That's the difference between the incontinent outside and the real sinners in Sin City, in the city of this.
But he doesn't understand any of that.
But Dante, and Dante doesn't even really understand it, because he's just a pilgrim.
He's reporting what he experienced at each stage, not what he understood later.
So, because he's telling the story of his experience.
So, there's three possible things.
There's Virgil's point of view, which has got it all wrong.
Dante's point of view, that sort of suspects that Virgil's got it all wrong, it doesn't know what's right, and the landscape of the inferno, which is written, built by God, and reflects exactly the right distinctions, because those are God's distinctions.
So, and Dante can't understand that.
He can't understand the Christian world, can't understand creation, he can't, that is, he can only understand production, reason, duty.
None of those explain why these people are trying not to let Dante into hell.
He can't understand rebellion against the divine.
That's a Christian category.
Yeah.
Yes, that's right.
They have chosen to, it's odd, and of course, again, in real life, it didn't look to them so awful, or they wouldn't have done it, I suppose.
But they have chosen to substitute for the goods that God has strewn all around the world instead of getting their desire in exact proportion to how fulfilling things are, so that bit by bit they will finally be led to contemplate God, because then they will have total desire for what's totally fulfilling.
That's Dante's picture.
They have rejected all that and substituted their own desires for those.
The extremist example, which we don't have time to look at, is what happens to the homosexuals in hell.
The homosexuals in hell are a perfect example of having freely and autonomously rejected the natural sexual impulses.
That's how it looks to Dante, and substituted something that they have freely chosen as what they're going to get satisfaction from.
And therefore, they're inside of hell, and they're punished with a sort of stupid punishment, running around on sand because it's barren, they don't have any kids, and stung by falling flakes of flame because they're all sort of excited, and running around in sort of crops, because I think Dante thinks the homosexuals in hell are all promiscuous.
What's interesting about Dante is there are more homosexuals at the top of the Paradiso, homosexual poets, and mostly, and at the top of Paradiso is near a paradise as you can get.
And they are lovers.
And Dante just loves lovers.
It doesn't matter what sex they are, or the same or opposite.
And in fact, Dante knows all the names of the famous homosexuals, knows personally all these famous homosexuals, which has led people to suspect that maybe Dante himself was bisexual.
But there's a certain kind of homosexual, anyway, which Dante does not approve of, puts in hell because they have substituted their own understanding of what's fulfilling with what's natural and fulfilling.
And so that's sort of an answer to you.
And all of them, you have to understand that all of them have substituted something that they've chosen for what is naturally satisfying.
And it gets worse and worse as they go down, what they substitute, and how unsatisfying it is.
Any questions?
Because that was important.
Okay, I'm going on, Dave.
So there are these fallen angels guarding the city.
Virgil slips up.
He doesn't understand what's going on.
Okay.
These are the angels and the sinners who rebel against God.
And Virgil doesn't understand the very concept of rebellion.
He doesn't understand that it's actually sin.
So he thinks that hell is a prison.
I mean, we've already seen that, that's what he thinks.
But he says it explicitly in Canto 6, line about 20.
He's explaining to Dante those who are on the other side of the wall.
And he says, you must understand their sins at sight.
I will explain how each is imprisoned and why.
So that's the very middle of page 104.
So Virgil really thinks that that's a prison, even though it's clearly a fortress.
After all, think again how their fear turned to desire.
If they were imprisoned, it would mean that they would want to get out.
And I'm glad Vikas found this line because it's very important.
They don't want to get out.
They want these people from God to get out.
They've chosen the situation they're in.
Again, the homosexual, just as an example.
They've chosen to make, to choose for themselves what satisfies them and to pursue it.
And that's not being imprisoned.
They just want to be left alone to do it.
Okay, so now we've got to see where I am again.
So Virgil, well, then comes this funny little tactful thing that Dante says, back to 88.
Dante's really having fun with this, and this is the most fun place I know in the whole three themes.
Dante tactfully begins to realize that Virgil doesn't know what's going on.
So on page 88, Panto 9, line 15, he says, Tell me, Master, does anyone, this is very cute, does anyone ever come from the first ledge, that's from Limbo, whose only punishment is hope cut off, into this dreary bottom?
He doesn't say, he's too tactful.
Do you know where we are?
Have you ever been here before?
What right do you have to be a guide?
He's done it in this sort of impersonal way.
And Virgil understands that he's asking for his credentials, and he says, Yeah, once before, it's true, I crossed through hell, and how did he get away with it?
Conjured by Erictho, who recalled these spirits to their body.
Her dark spell forced me, and so forth and so forth.
Erico, it says in the footnote, his own witch.
Well, he was on a, on a, not on a divine mission, but on a witchy mission, whatever the right word for that is.
And so, when he went to the gate of hell last time, what happened?
The gate of Sin City.
He said, I've come here and I have the authority to come here because I'm sent here by a witch.
Do you think they ran in and slammed the door?
No, they said, yeah, come on in.
That's nice.
And it's interesting that what's cruel about Eric, though, I only noticed that this time through, is that he recalled the spirits to their bodies.
Well, that's a funny thing for somebody to say.
But it's not a funny thing for Virgil to say.
Because remember, they don't want their bodies.
They wish they were dead in the Aeneid.
They're sluggish bodies.
Here, instead of the blessing that you get on the day of judgment, hooray, you get your body back.
There's a curse.
When somebody puts a curse on you and puts a witch after you, this witch can make you have to take your body back.
It's just, everything is upside down.
Okay, we've got that now.
So he says he has a right to be there.
He knows what he's doing.
He was sent there by this witch.
and so forth and they say, yeah, come on in, and so forth.
So he doesn't get the difference between being on a mission sanctioned by the Virgin Mary and sanctioned by a witch.
I think that's pretty far gone.
He does see that it has a big difference in effect, and that's what happens.
But he doesn't understand the significance of the law.
Now, this much I think is clearly in the book.
If you think I'm over-interpreting, you should come and complain in office hour.
It's a big temptation in Dante.
If you read any of the literature on Dante, because he says it's got four levels of interpretation and he's happy that he's talking literally and biblically and morally and philosophically all at the same time, people read in all sorts of stuff.
Well, now I want to read something in.
Now, I don't know whether it's really there or not, but I think it is.
But first, I see I have to say one more thing.
Finally, just to finish the story, how do they get into the city?
It's not all that exciting.
On page 91 of Guitar, the only way to get in, an angel comes from God and breaks down the door.
At the top of 91, this is Canto 9, 90.
Outcasts of heaven, this is the angel says, you twice loathsome crew, he cried upon that terrible sail of hell.
How does this insolence still live in you?
You see, they're always rebelling.
Why do you set yourself against that throne whose will none can deny?
And which times past has added to your pain for each rebellion?
Well, there it is.
I mean, it's clear it's a prison, not a fortress.
It's a fortress that they built to keep God out, and they can't do it.
And again, where it says 105 in the margin line, 105, Dante says, I'm eager to learn what new estate of hell that burning fortress walls enclose.
Dante understands it's a fortress.
Virgil never really gets it.
That's perhaps just how it should be.
Okay.
And now this is a place where I say I may be going too far.
That is, they actually start talking about the meaning of the wall.
Is Dante or isn't Dante seeing through Virgil at this point?
I'm not sure.
I mean, we know, so to speak, that Dante sees that hell is built in a way that Virgil doesn't understand.
Dante is at this stage a pilgrim who has got sort of two authorities: the way the wall looks and the way Virgil's talking.
I think he understands that Virgil's not making any sense, but I'm not sure.
So look on Tanto 11, line 16.
Virgil's going to explain to Dante what's going on.
My son, he began, there are below this wall three smaller circles, and then accordingly, you have to understand, I skipped a little, their sins at sight.
I will explain how each is prisoned.
See, he's still got that and why.
And then he goes into a whole bunch of stuff which adds nothing.
Don't waste your time trying to memorize or understand that.
Malice comes in two kinds: fraud and violence.
And God loath violence more because, oddly enough, with the stupid reason that violence is something that only humans do, whereas, you know, fraud is something that only humans do, but violence is what even animals will do.
So fraud is worse than violence.
I think really for Dante, or for God, anyway, for the Inferno itself, fraud is bad and way down because it's a betrayal of trust.
But Virgil hasn't got any of these categories.
And so then, so violence he's got in here are for people who blaspheme.
Notice again, and probably something wrong with the Italian on 105, line 476.
Violence may be offered the deity in the heart that blasphemes and refuses him.
Beatrice, I hope the refuses isn't in the Italian.
It better not be.
Because that's refusal.
That's rebellion.
Virgil hasn't got any concept of refusal.
And then there's all kinds of stuff.
I'm not going to read it.
Stuff, stuff, stuff, which doesn't connect up with any of the architectural landscape distinctions.
It's just stuff that Virgil brings in from Aristotle and so forth.
That's why I'm not going to read it, and you shouldn't worry about it.
But then comes the interesting line.
What are you going to do with this at the bottom of 105?
Line about 70.
Master, I said, the clarity of your mind impresses all you touch.
I see quite clearly the orders of this dark pit of the blind.
But tell me, this gets really funny, but tell me, though, we're going to find out whether Dante is stupid or smart now.
But tell me, those who lie in the swamp's bowels, those the wind blows, you know who that is.
That's the incontinent out there in the suburbs.
The wind blows, those the rain beats, those are the gluttons, and those who meet with clash and mad howls, those are the material people.
Why are they not punished in the rust red city?
Dante wants to know what's the point of the wall.
It's pretty significant that there's a distinction between the suburbs and the city of hell.
What is it?
And he says, Virgil gets very huffy.
Why does your understanding stray so far from its own habit?
Or can it be that your thoughts are turned some other way?
Have you forgotten your ethics?
That's Aristotle.
That states that the three divisions of hell are so-and-so, and upper hell, and lower hell, and so forth.
When you understand that, he says, lying about 89, you will understand at once why they are confined.
And that's apparently not in the Italian.
But of course, if it were, that would be because Virgil thinks they are confined.
You'd understand why they are confined apart from those fierce race and why less anger beats down on them than from the eternal mind.
I mean, this is not getting very helpful.
And then Dante says, I mean, Virgil has said nothing.
The interesting thing is, Dante says, why the wall?
Virgil makes a speech that incontinence is different than malice and vestiality.
And one side of the wall is incontinence, and the other side is malice and vestiality.
And he says, incontinence offends God least.
But why?
He hasn't got any concept there about rebellion or anything.
He hasn't got the distinction that St.
Thomas has between, let's put it in here right now, loving the wrong thing and rejecting God's love.
And that's what the wall is: it's between the people who love the wrong thing, sex, food, materials, getting angry, and the people who reject God's love altogether, like the homosexuals, but all of them.
Okay, so, and what does Dante say?
He says, where now?
Hopefully you'll understand all that, all that.
And he says, Dante at 91, on page 106, O sun, which clears all mists from troubled sight, such joy attends your rising that I feel as grateful to the dark as to the light.
I wish I saw that in a pattern.
You see what a kind of pun that could be.
I mean, I want him to say something nice to Virgil, which, if you really understand it, says you haven't clarified a thing.
And maybe that's what he's saying, and maybe he isn't.
Maybe he's being ironic.
Maybe he's just being a pilgrim who doesn't know anything yet.
Maybe he's stupid.
They can't really tell.
But I would like to think that Dante, having cleverly set up this whole little episode at the wall where Virgil's got everything wrong, thinks that Virgil's got everything wrong and isn't going to accept an explanation from Virgil that doesn't explain the law, which is what Virgil has just given him.
So I hope he's just trying to be nice and yet, you know, say, I didn't really get it, which you were just saying.
It didn't enlighten me a bit.
Anyway, that's the way it ends there.
All you get from Virgil is these ad hoc explanations.
That is, ad hoc, meaning whenever there's something different from something, then Virgil makes up some kind of distinction of some kind of sin to some other kind of sin to fit it.
But it doesn't have any unity.
It doesn't really get at anything deep.
Virgil, Heidegger has a funny way of talking when he says about people like Virgil, what they say is correct but not true.
By which he means they are described, Virgil's right, he describes all these distinctions.
There really are distinctions between malice and fraud, but it's not true in the sense that it doesn't give you any deep insight.
If it helps any, the philosophers like Aristotle would say it's the difference between getting the proprium of something and the essence of something.
You don't need to know this technical terminology.
But they give examples like approprium is a general property.
So for instance, you can say of human beings, man is a laughing animal, the only animal that laughs.
Or man is a featherless biped.
It's the only featherless, two-legged thing.
Too bad there are birds, too distant.
That's why you have to say featherless.
But anyway, those are general properties.
But those aren't essences.
The essence of man is to be a rational animal.
That's what explains all that's important about man, Aristotle would say.
And it doesn't explain why men laugh or why human beings walk on two feet, but it doesn't have to.
It tells you what's crucial.
Virgil never gets the right answers.
He only gets these ad hoc kind of answers.
And now, one more, just in time.
And now, when I said I was going to say something too clever by half, maybe, is what I'm going to say now.
I sort of jumped ahead.
What I think now is probably still okay.
But if you ask yourself now, where is Virgil sitting when he's explaining all of this?
And getting it sort of raw and getting only the ad hoc.
He's in Canto 11, Circle 6.
And what is Canto 11, Circle 6?
It's the place where the heretics are punished.
Heretics are people who get it wrong about Christianity.
I think, but now I say, this might be overinterpreting, that Dante there is saying that Virgil's account of the meaning of the law has just not got the truth about Christianity.
And he puts it all there.
He doesn't say anything about it.
He just puts it within the circle of the heretics.
And I think, I don't know.
I hope he does it on purpose.
Now let's see.
I'm almost done.
So the heretics involved are the Epicureans.
That's a philosophical sect.
We still talk about being Epicures and Epicurean.
They believed that they wouldn't accept the idea that love could be total devotion.
They would certainly think that that, they don't understand that at all.
So the Stoics think that what do the Epicureans, now I'm getting confused.
What do they do?
Okay, on page 100, the footnote says that the aim of philosophy is to achieve happiness, absence of pain.
Doctrine thought it meant the denial of eternal life.
No, I don't think that's important.
I don't know why I'm even saying it.
So I'm going to skip it.
The other thing, another one of the people in the heretics, let's try that, is Faronata, who's a Stoic.
And Virgil is also a kind of Stoic.
They all think that self-control and temperance are the highest virtues.
And they think that trying to get bliss out of the world is a terrible mistake, like Guido made.
And so Virgil can't understand the shakeup, he can't understand the importance of love.
He can only think, I'm going to stop with this, that love is always a mess.
It causes Paul's guido to go crazy.
It gets Paula and Francesca into trouble.
And there's a funny place where, page 112, Canto 12, circle 7, line about 40, he's describing what happens when Jesus comes down to hell to get out the Hebrews.
There's something like a big earthquake.
And that's not important.
What's important is what he says about it.
He says, if I'm not mistaken, it was just before the coming of him who took the souls from limbo that all hell was shaken, so that I thought the universe felt love.
Jesus is love, all right, and love is breaking in on 112, where three stanzas down.
So I thought the universe felt love.
Now that you think, would be nice, wouldn't you?
Everything attracted to everything and everything held together.
So that I thought the universe felt love and all its elements moved toward harmony, whereby the world of matter, as some believe, is often funged to chaos.
And so, and that's it.
A very peculiar view of love.
But a view that follows that whatever kind of love, agape love, eros, romantic love, it all only causes trouble according to the view that Virgil holds.
Now I think I really have finished what I want to say.
Just let me pass.
So I just want to say again, St.
Thomas understood the distinction between turning towards the wrong things, which is what happens outside this, and turning away from God's creation, which is what happens inside this.
Virgil can't understand that.
He doesn't know anything about that.
And now we're ready to go on to the lower part of hell.
And the next thing we want to read, next time I'm going to do two things.
Talk about Canto 26.
Before we read Canto 26, which is interesting to us because Odyssey shows up in hell, pretty far down, in Canto 26.
And then, besides that, we're going to look at the bottom of hell, which is where Satan is.
And that is Cantos 32, 32 to 34.
And we may get to purgatory.
And that would be Canto's Can you read what I'm writing?
If not, I'll read it I'll find one, like four does it sixteen.
I tr I would hope to cover all of that next time.
Can you see what I wrote?
Or should I read it?
Can you can you see it?
Oh, okay.
That's it then.