Then we're on to the divine comedy, and we skip a thousand years.
And I'm going to give you a really quick run-up to where we are.
There was Jesus, and then there, which, at the year zero, so to speak, where he changed the world so much that we count before and after him as the pagan world, the ancient world versus the Christian world.
And then there were the articulators, the Gospel of John, and the person I keep mentioning is Saint Augustine, who at about 300 A.D.
tried to make sense of the Jesus story using the Gospel of John and all the other Gospels and the letters of Paul too, but particularly the Gospel of John, standing on his shoulders, tried to write a completely Platonic, that is, the philosopher Plato, account so that he said, well, what Plato called the good, which was this abstract, eternal, immutable something or other that gave everything its intelligibility and was very closely related to the logos, which is the word in John, that that was God and so forth, and tried to map everything onto the Platonic understanding.
But that didn't work very well because Plato thought, like also Virgil, that the body was a bad thing, and therefore, and the good was very abstract and didn't have a body.
But this was, but the sentence of the Jesus story is, after all, that the word became flesh, and Augustine couldn't make any sense out of that.
I heard lately, a student told me, to my amusement and happiness, when I was teaching the brothers Karamatsov, that Augustine is not a saint in the Greek Orthodox Church.
I'm all for that.
I think they're onto something there.
Augustine certainly didn't make it work, and things would have been in bad shape.
Where bad shape means they wouldn't have been able to find a language and a philosophy in which to state the meaning of all these weird sayings and parables and miracles and stuff that seems so hard to make sense of.
And then, in an old basement in North Africa, they found the lecture notes of some professor whose name happens to be Aristotle, and that brought about a whole revolution in people's thinking because Aristotle was sort of the Athenian anti-Plato.
He thought that bodies were important.
He thought the soul, in fact, was the form of the body.
He was just so anti-Platonist that he was a kind of materialist, which is sort of falling too far over on the other side.
But at least it was better to say that individual things and animals and people were more real than abstract ideas.
And starting with that and sort of running with it, St.
Thomas Aquinas, I'll write that on the board.
That's a new character in this that I mention occasionally.
St.
Thomas Aquinas, who people just call St.
Thomas, took on the big job of mapping all of Christianity onto Aristotle concepts.
And that became a big hit and just took over and eclipsed Augustine and the Platonists.
And by 1300, a thousand years after Augustine, Christianity got put into its, so to speak, final Catholic medieval form by St.
Thomas, mapping it onto Aristotle, and Dante lives at just that moment.
In fact, the time that the Divine Comedy takes place is 1300.
It doesn't really, Dante wrote it later than that, but the story, the adventure, or whatever you want to call it, that he's describing in the Divine Comedy, namely, his going to hell in purgatory and paradise, he dates as 1300.
That enables him to make predictions in the adventure he's telling, in this experience.
I see, I'm trying to find the right words for it.
People thought at the time that Dante had actually done this.
People pointed at him and said, that's the man who's been in hell, and so forth.
And I don't know whether Dante thought he'd actually done it or not.
It's not clear to me.
So I'm just calling it Dante's adventure, whatever it is, that it's supposed to take place in 1300.
And that's at the time when Aristotle was considered the master of those who know, to quote the translation.
I mean, when every once in a while, Dante appeals to Aristotle to prove something.
As soon as you show that Aristotle said it, there's no more discussion.
Aristotle was the thinker who was right about everything, except that there were things about the revelation, like that Jesus was God, that Aristotle wouldn't be able to understand, or that the soul was immortal.
But generally, Aristotle, insofar as he tried to understand anything, he got it right.
And Dante has a little bit of a problem, which you just have to get used to.
You'll see it a lot.
Virgil knows Aristotle's work.
I suppose.
I never thought about that till this moment.
How would he?
Well, you'll see when we get to limbo that Virgil and Aristotle would certainly know each other and talk to each other a lot in the afterlife because all the wise pagans were together in a part of the, it's not the inferno because it's not heated up.
What would be the general name for it?
The no, there's the inferno, there's purgatory, there's the paradiso, but then there is limbo, which is a special thing outside of, maybe it's still part of the inferno, I guess, though it isn't heated up until you get a certain distance down.
We'll worry about that later.
The geography of all this is important to get straight, but not yet.
In limbo, which I'm going to talk about today, the virtuous pagans, that's where they are in their afterlife.
And Aristotle is there, and Plato, and Virgil, and so forth.
So Virgil, presumably, could know about and even know the doctrine of St.
Thomas Aquinas, and he does, because every once in a while he says to Dante, when Dante asks the question, well, if you read your St.
Thomas, you know that.
And then Virgil announces things that he could in this life never have known.
But although couldn't he have?
He could have.
He just, I mean, I guess he was around, but Virgil.
No, well, I don't know, Aristotle?
What?
No, couldn't have known Thomas, right?
He never quotes Thomas, I think, because Thomas isn't in limbo.
Thomas is in paradise once he dies.
He quotes, he, but I think Aristotle was completely forgotten.
These lecture notes that happened to survive in this musty basement and been there a long time, and Platonists sort of ruled the intellectual world, I believe.
These are things we'd have to sort out more.
The Aristotle got translated by Arabic scholars.
Veroaz is the main one.
And they get mentioned everywhere, occasionally.
I think that they're in limbo too.
And once it gets translated from the Greek into Latin, and from Arabic into Latin, that's when it takes over.
Okay, now I'm going to just, then that's all background.
And now, but I'll give you an example.
If you look at, hmm, maybe I haven't got it with me.
I wonder, I've written 86, page 868.
That doesn't make any sense.
So let's look and where would we find it?
We'd find it in the probably in Paolo and Francesca.
There's a place, I'll read you the quote, and then maybe we can find it later.
Dante asks, I mean, this is an example, an important example of how Aristotle gets into Christianity, and also an example that Virgil knows is Aristotle.
And here it is, only I don't know the page.
Masters, I said, when the great clarion fades into the voice of thundering omniscience, what are those agonies, bodily agonies?
He's talking about the suffering of the people in hell.
Will they be the same or more or less after the final sentence, that is the day of judgment?
And he, to me, that's Virgil, to Dante.
Look to your science again.
Science is always Aristotle.
Where it is written, the more a thing is perfect, the more it feels of pleasure and of pain.
That's very interesting.
You finding it?
That would be great.
Where are you?
Anybody found it?
68.
Oh, I see why I had 868.
I knew that couldn't work.
68.
Oh, but that's wonderful.
You also answered an important question I forgot to ask.
Stop and immediately ask it.
All right, let's correlate our page numbers because remember what happened last time?
They weren't the same for the Aeneid.
They just like to cause you all to buy the book again.
So let's go.
Where does your Divine Comedy start?
Mine starts on page 28.
Yes?
27.
Oh, maybe 27.
I can, I'll, I'll, I'll, I'll, well, yes, call it 27.
That's not Dante.
That's, by the way, you should know there's so many things I'm trying to say at once.
It's the translator who puts in these explanations at the beginning of the canto.
And I'm pretty sure, though I would love to have somebody find out who knows more about this, that it's the translator who puts in the headings for the particular.
I'll tell you why, because the heading for the first place where people are punished turns out to make no sense.
And therefore, I doubt if it's Dante's.
Now, there's only one question.
Surely Dante didn't write little excerpts at the beginning of each canto, nor, I think, did Dante give the cantos names.
I just don't know whether the names are traditional and have been around since 1300 when some other guy put them on, or whether each translator gets to put his own names.
But I'm pretty sure each translator gets his own names because I've looked in other translations and they can toes have different names.
Okay, I'm saying all that, but first I'm correlating pages.
I'm trying to do 10 things at once.
So 27, is that the answer?
That's where it says canto one.
Is that right for all of you?
Everybody?
Hooray.
Well, that makes life simpler.
Then let's go back to what I was reading until somebody, and now I found 68, that's very reassuring.
So let's go there.
So, okay.
Now, here, here we've got it.
And the guide to me at the bottom of 68.
No, no, not quite yet.
Yeah, the bottom of the very bottom of 68.
And he to me, look to your science where it is written: the more a thing is perfect, the more it feels of pleasure and of pain.
If you read carefully, what do you discover about the body?
He's talking about what will happen when these souls, so I have to explain that.
These people are all dead in hell, obviously.
And they must be sort of ghost-like, the way they are in Homer, and the way they are where they have to drink blood even to talk.
They're just exhausted.
And even in Virgil, where Aeneas, isn't it?
Aeneas tries to embrace his mother and his arms go right through.
Is that right?
I think so.
Or is that a little, or is it?
He tries to embrace his mother.
Okay.
How sort of diaphanous are the shades in the Aeneas?
Do we know?
Anybody?
Ah, I thought something like that.
Okay, good.
So these shades are still pretty insubstantial.
But bodies are so important in Christianity, and they get this already from the Hebrews.
Bodies are so important that the Hebrews don't have a problem.
When you're alive, you've got a body, and it's important.
And when you're dead, you're dead, and that's that.
But the Christians have what what's going on in the afterlife with these people whose bodies are in tombs someplace?
Well, they get sort of loner bodies.
And Virgil explains that at some point.
Bodies that feel pleasure and pain and are substantial enough so that they can hug each other, as Paolo and Francesca do in the reading for today.
And those, and now we can go ask.
Dante wants to know what's going to happen.
And the Christians believe that on the day of judgment, all these bodies will come forth from the tombs and the people will get their bodies back.
That may cause a certain amount of problems, I think, probably in some cases.
But in general, and with a few miracles, that's what's supposed to happen.
Every soul gets its body back.
And now Dante's asking, and how about that?
When the day of judgment comes, this is a little on Phil in 58, each soul will come and hear the Edict of Eternity, and then that's when Virgil says, well, and Dante wants to know how will these punishments be after that.
And now you can really see the difference that's happened between the Platonist, Augustinian, anti-body people and the Aristotle people, because he says, look to your science, Virgil says, meaning Aristotle, where it is written, the more a thing is perfect, the more it feels pleasure and pain.
Now, what do you learn from that?
That getting a body makes you more perfect, which is a good thing to say if you've got a religion in which God has got become flesh.
And everybody gets back their flesh, and thereby they are more perfect.
And one of the things that happens if they're more perfect is that the ones who are suffering suffer even more, and the ones who are having are happy are happy even more.
And that's what he says.
All these souls, though they can never soar to true perfection, still in the new time, they will be nearer to it than they were before.
These souls means the ones in hell can never get true perfection.
That's because there's something wrong with them, or they wouldn't be in hell.
So when they get their bodies back, they're just going to be suffering more.
But their bodies, they will be more perfect.
Okay.
I say all that just to give you a sense of where things have gotten thanks to Aristotle and St.
Thomas and the funny way that Virgil knows where they've gotten.
Now let's see what else.
And I want to say just a word here before this.
Well, and what, I mean, I want to say one word: that St.
Thomas seems to me to lack something very important, though I've only read a few pages of St.
Thomas, and for all I know, it comes up somewhere.
There doesn't seem to be a place, a central place for love, but he couldn't ignore the commandment that you should love each other.
And Paul says the most important thing is adopting love.
What does St.
Thomas do about that?
I asked Dane because he knows about these things.
Well, he is.
And does he just have much to say about it?
Okay, well, good.
Then I'm wrong about.
I was going to say that St.
Thomas doesn't do much with the love part, but I'm glad he does.
But there's a certain kind of love that St.
Thomas knows nothing about, that Dante cares a lot about, and we'll hear a lot about in a little while, which is chivalric love, the love of the knight for his lady.
That's not obviously, it's maybe in there somewhere, but it's not what anybody saw in the Bible until much later.
But I'll get to that.
I want to say one thing about the understanding of being, which somebody's bound to ask.
And it doesn't, again, it's not so clear what to say about it.
One thing is sure: that the understanding of being is now createdness.
That means we're all creatures, and animals are all creatures.
Everything's creatures because they're all created by God.
And that's, as I said in passing, that's the Roman idea of production carried from lots of people producing lots of things, like bricks, from bricks to empires, by imposing form on somewhat reluctant matter.
That's the whole Roman Aeneas picture.
Now you've got a super emperor kind of creator who actually produced everything and imposed all the order on it.
And what kind of, and how would that look?
What difference would it make if you thought about things that way?
Well, the difference it would be is that the world would be intelligible through and through because a good, intelligent, intelligible being had produced it.
And you see this clearly in Dante, where everything is intelligible down to the tiniest detail.
And it's all hierarchical.
That's the kind of intelligibility.
Everything is ranked so that the sins are all ranked.
No more sinners.
There, I don't know, I'd like to be fun to count them.
I would say at least 25 different kinds of sin, and they are clearly ranked.
As you go down in hell, they get worse and worse until you get to Satan, who's at the bottom.
Then you go up and up in paradise, and they get better and better until you get to the highest saints.
Even saints are ranked.
Not every saint, not all saints are equal.
You go from sort of nuns to mystics with a lot of shades in between.
So the whole world is ranked.
Gold, for instance, is a higher, more, what would you say, worthy element than, say, iron.
That's ranked.
When God created the world, it was just created intelligible and morally judged in terms of its value through and through.
And that understanding of being permeates everything Dante's doing.
Another thing is, I'm not listing what happens when you get a good God that produces all this, the supreme being creates it all.
Well, everybody gets what they deserve morally.
The bad people get suffering, and it's in proportion to how bad they are that their suffering is.
And the good people get bliss, and it's in proportion to how good they are, how much bliss they get.
So it's intelligible and morally structured through and through.
That's it for the understanding of being, as far as I can see it.
And, okay, so next thing.
We're ready.
Well, I'm going to stop for questions.
That's the background, as far as I'm concerned.
We're going to go on to Dante.
Yeah.
That's true.
Good.
Beatrice says, gets rid of the distinction between nature and culture.
That's right.
Because even nature is produced and intelligible.
And that's where we get the idea of the book of nature, where God has written everything, sort of morality into nature.
And so there are these books that tell you, sort of, rank the animals and how virtuous they are.
And they are virtuous in order to show us things.
I mean, the only one I know is another author, Foucault, who is always interested in the kind of Puritanism of Christianity.
The elephant supposedly has sex a minimal amount of occasions or times or every few years or something, and then immediately goes and washes itself.
And that's a kind of the elephant is there to sort of illustrate something.
Everything is there to illustrate something.
And nature is to be read like a book and see what it illustrates.
And another example is the planets you will see are ranked because each planet corresponds to some virtue.
So Jupiter is a war planet and Venus is a love planet and so forth.
And the order of the planets as they are in heaven is again an example of the sort of value of the virtue that's associated with the planet.
So you can get this picture.
It is intelligible through and through in a way that the world never has been for any other culture.
And everything has grown into it to talk like Nietzsche.
So that the whole of nature and culture and psychology and biology and astronomy is all one integrated hierarchical, intelligible whole created by this perfect God.
That's something so bizarre and amazing that we get used to it, but I'm sure it's unique in the history of the galaxy and maybe any galaxy.
So now we're ready to go to Dante's situation in this, unless there's any other questions.
Okay, to Dante.
So Dante is a Florentine.
That is, he lives in Florence, Italy.
He's the ultimate articulator, we'll see, of this medieval hierarchical Christian total mono vision.
St.
Thomas had already articulated it, but he articulated it in Latin, and it wasn't something that you could sort of hold it up for everybody to see and share.
Dante wrote it in the vernacular, that means in the vulgar language, that means in this case in Italian.
So it's a lot more lively, a lot more illustrations, and a lot more people can understand it.
But and in a way, that's Dante's role as articulator.
That makes his book seem to be, and makes it a work of art working if everybody thinks that he has held up to them this created world that they're in.
Now, somewhere I marked, okay, yes, on page 13, if you still have the same everything as I have, it's as if the author writing the introduction of this, whoever that is, has set it up just for us as a work of art working.
Here's what he says: on 13 is the introduction, right?
Anybody there?
13?
Okay, bring your books to class.
That's important.
Okay, I'm going to read from the introduction starting in line 4.
Before the author's death, that's Dante's death in 1321, for the first two parts, including the Inferno.
Well, I can't begin in the middle.
Fame might indeed be said not to have awaited its completion, that is the divine comedy.
Shortly before the author's death in 1321, for the first two parts, including the Inferno, were presented, including the Inferno, here presented, had already, in a few years, this is the important part, achieved a reputation tinged with supernatural awe.
This is what happens with works of art work.
Remember, the people also worshipped the Aeneid.
And so within two decades, a half dozen commentaries had been written.
50 years later, it was accorded the honor of public readings and exposition.
Remember, Aeschylus gets the honor of the Aristague being performed every year.
An almost unheard of tribute to a work written in the humble vernacular.
And it was finally, just as the Aeneid was given shrines, the divine comedy was declared divine.
Dante only called it the comedy.
About the middle of 13, Roman numeral 13, it was the atheist mid-16th century, which, in spite of certain reservations, first proclaimed divine the work of its author.
The work that its author had simply called comedy.
Okay, so that's just to say, yes, but in Dante, Dante wrote a work of art and it worked.
That seems clear.
There was something more I wanted to say about it, just a second.
But I don't know, so I'll go on.
So that's what Dante wrote, but that wasn't what Dante thought he was doing.
He didn't say, I'm going to write a work of art that works.
I think Aeschylus did.
Homer certainly didn't.
But anyway, Dante had an entirely different job in mind.
He was influenced by the chivalric tradition, which was a certain offspring of Christianity, focused by the troubadours, and those are the poets who invented courtly love.
And Dante is right inside the courtly love, knights and ladies, chivalric way of looking at things.
And he is going to write a poem about his lady, Beatrice, a girl he's seen three times when he was 13 and she was 11.
I mean, it's as chivalric as you can get.
You don't have to know the person that you set up as your lady.
You just have to organize your whole life around your devotion to her.
He had a wife and kids, but all he thought about and wrote about was Beatrice.
And he said he was going to write a poem about her such as no one had ever written about his lady before.
And that's the divine comedy.
What makes it a poem such that nobody has ever written one like it about their girlfriend before or after won't become obvious until next week.
It isn't obvious until the end of the purgatory.
But he did it, and it's pretty impressive.
And one more thing, I know, I remember now what I was about to say when I suddenly forgot, is namely, you might wonder, if I waited, maybe somebody would ask, is there any burning question on your mind about any of what I've been saying?
Yeah.
Or Beatrice?
Good question.
That isn't the question I thought you were going to ask, but I think it's an interesting one.
I have no idea.
Do anybody know?
He was still around, I suppose.
That's like she died young.
She died in her 20s.
That's right.
So, okay, so she, so, no, and he, he, he, of course, she could still be around in paradise and appreciated.
I think, in fact, he did write it for Beatrice, even though she died, because he knows that Beatrice is in paradise, and he knows that Beatrice, and now we have to tell you a little bit more of the plot.
Beatrice is the one who has sent Virgil to guide Dante through all the realms of the afterlife.
So she's watching over him, so she must know that he's writing a poem about her.
And that's how it looks to him, I think.
I thought somebody was going to ask, well, why is it called a comedy?
Why in the world did he write this book and say, the comedy?
Do you all know?
I mean, I wouldn't have known, but so somewhere in high school, I was made to memorize the little bit of definition that in a comedy, all conflicts are in the end reconciled.
Whereas in a tragedy, there is sort of everybody learns through suffering, and to suffering that the conflict that caused the suffering doesn't necessarily get fixed.
So this is a comedy because everything works out just as it should.
Again, it's a comedy because the bad people suffer and because the good people are in bliss.
That's now.
We're ready to go further, unless somebody has any question.
Okay, a little bit more you need to know about the geography of things.
I think it's already in here, and I don't have to go into detail drawing it, but just in case.
The world at the time of Dante looks like that.
It's round.
Doesn't that surprise you?
In 1300, in 1492, we're told that Columbus was doing this big experiment to see if he went off, whether he'd fall off the edge of the earth.
Columbus may have been the only person who didn't know because everybody else seems to know it's round.
Dante certainly knows it's round.
And for a long time, they probably knew it was round, partly because they could see the masts of the ships coming up top first when they saw the ships on the horizon.
Partly because they could see the shadow, I think, of the Earth on the moon.
In any case, it is Perdante round, and Florence is down here in Italy, and underneath Florence, with an entrance in Florence, is this big cone, empty space, and that's where all the inferno.
That's where all the bad guys are kept.
And when they did this, they seem to have had an awful lot extra dirt, so they built something here, which is purgatory.
And that's where the souls are who are purging themselves and who have had rather bad lives, but who want to be good, and they have a long time to suffer and pray, and eventually they get from purgatory up to there, up there, which is paradise.
And Dante's trip consists in going into Inferno here at Florence, going all the way down to the bottom where Satan is here at the bottom, and then crawling up this little path to the bottom of purgatory, and then climbing up purgatory.
That's just to keep your head while you're going through all the details.
And Jerusalem is here on this map.
The exits here when he gets up there.
So now let me see.
And around the Earth, I can't draw it up there, are lots of spheres, in which you'll hear more about when we get to the Paradiso.
There's the sphere of the moon, and then the sphere of Venus, and the sphere of whatever other planets they knew, I forget which ones.
And finally, in the final outer, outer sphere is heaven.
And in a very peculiar sort of science fiction way that Virgil manages to bring off, God, who is in heaven, isn't so is both everywhere at the final outermost sphere, but he's also the center of everything.
So there's a part of the trip where Dante sort of turns inside out the trip, which has been going further and further out.
It becomes further and further in because it's got to finally get to the point where Dante gets to see God at the center of everything.
Now we've got enough of that, I think.
Let's see where we are.
Yeah, finally, we get to Dante's adventure.
And now we're on page 28.
And we stay inside.
That was all background, which I think I had to give you.
But from now on, it's important that we stay inside this and read at least some of it.
By the way, the assignment for next time is on the syllabus.
Just keep your eye on the syllabus, which is in here.
And we are reading, well, wherever we get, we want to get by next time to the bottom.
But you don't have to read all of it.
Just read the cantos that I've listed there.
And that's all the ones I'm going to talk about.
So now.
So Dante on page 28 now has lost his way in life.
He's depressed, confused, tempted by all kinds of bad things.
And that's it at the top of 28.
I'm sure it's beautiful in Italian.
It's famous.
Midway in our life's journey, I went astray from the straight road and woke to find myself alone in a dark wood.
And he was very frightened, and he didn't know how to get out of it.
And then he saw, he saw, where are we?
So by the end of the valley of evil, he sapped my heart with fear.
I found myself before a little hill.
I'm in the middle of 28 and lifted up my eyes.
His shoulders glowed already with the sweet rays of the planet whose virtue lends men strength on every road.
And the signing strengthened me against the fright whose agony had racked the lake of my heart through all the terrors of that piteous night.
And then just all the books that we read talk to each other, as you will notice, sort of.
You'll see more of that.
But Dante, of course, knows his Homer.
And what does he say next?
Just as a swimmer who with his last breath flounders ashore from perilous seas, does that sound familiar?
You've heard that twice in the Odyssey.
That's what happens when Odysseus comes out of the water and gets into the olive tree to sleep.
And that's what happens again when he finally gets home into his own bed after all his adventures.
And now it's Virgil's taking it over.
I mean, Dante's taking it over.
And he is saved.
And we have to get to where he so swimmer and so-and-so might memorize the wide water of his death.
So did I turn my soul, still furtive from death surviving me, to stare down the path that none had ever left alive.
He's looking down toward the bottom of that of hell.
And then he sees we just jumped to 30.
Okay, at the top of 30.
And as I fell to my soul's ruin, fell into what?
Let's see.
He died from hope of ever climbing out of it.
And he was falling back into the sunless wood at the bottom of 29.
And as I fell to my soul's ruin, a presence gathered before me on the discolored air, the figure of one who seemed hoarse from long silence.
Who is that?
Somebody better say, because I get very discouraged if I don't believe that anybody is listening or doing the reading.
Who does he see?
Virgil, hooray, yes, who is hoarse from long silence.
And well, he might be, because he's been silent for a thousand years since the time he wrote the Aeneid.
And he, when he talks about Virgil, well, Virgil says when he asks, Who are you?
Not man, though man I once was, and my blood was Lombard.
Both my parents met too, and these are all Italian references.
I was born, though late, sub Julio, and bred in Rome under Augustus in the noon of the false and lying gods.
Now that's interesting.
That means that Virgil has figured out that Christianity was right and that the Augustinian God was, as he sort of hints maybe in the Aeneid, an illusion, a false dream.
At least he now knows that this was the time of the false and lying gods.
And then, so Dante is 35 years old at this point.
The time is 1300.
And we now can skip ahead if.
And later, he's going to be the guide, he says.
And then at the bottom of 31, he's going to take him a certain place to the bottom of purgatory.
And then he says, to which, if it is still your wish to climb, that's the mountain now up there, if you wish to climb, a worthier spirit shall be sent to guide you.
With her shall I leave you.
Who's that?
Beatrice.
Yes, Beatrice is going to come and guide him, and Virgil's going to leave at a certain point.
And I leave you for the king of time who reigns on high forbids me to come there, and so forth.
Now there's something I don't like in the next paragraph.
It's all very well that he thinks that God is a kind of emperor or a kind of king who reigns on high.
But there's something I can't understand, and it doesn't seem to be helped by looking at Italian, though I'm going to take one last look.
Virgil says, I rebelled against his law.
Virgil didn't rebel against anything.
He didn't know the law, and if he had, he wouldn't have rebelled against it.
I don't know what Dante is thinking.
Maybe he's just tired at that point.
Or maybe we can make the Italian mean something different than rebel.
Rebellion is a very serious thing.
It it's sin with a capital S.
It's turning against God.
Virgil couldn't have been doing that because Virgil isn't in the part of hell where the rebellions against God people go.
So I don't know what's going on.
The truth is, Virgil missed out on Christianity, but he didn't, but and that's true.
But it isn't as if there was Christianity around and Virgil knew it and he didn't like it.
So we have to just go on anyway.
Now, Beatrice is going to help him out eventually.
Beatrice sent Virgil.
I'm just getting you up to where we need to go into more details.
On 36, I was a soul among the souls of Limbo.
Limbo is this outer, outer edge of the inferno where the people who are not sinners because it was pre-Christian, the virtuous pagans are there, the virtuous Hebrews are there.
I was a soul among the souls of Limbo when a lady so blessed and so beautiful, I prayed her to order and command my will, called to me.
Her eyes were kindled with the lamps of heaven.
Her voice reached through me, tender, sweet, and low, an angel's voice, and so forth.
Of course, and she said at the top of 37, it's I, Beatrice, who sends you to him.
You see, go take pity on poor Dante.
He's lost.
And she says, I come from the closest heights for which I yearn.
Love called me here.
So that means she wants to get back to paradise as soon as she can, but she had to go get Virgil in Limbo first and send him off to Dante.
And that's what she did.
And okay.
Now, we're getting ready to start looking at the punishments in the Inferno.
All that was still, in a sense, background.
That was background inside the poem.
First, I had to do background outside the poem.
But finally, we're getting to actual punishments, actual story about what goes on in the Inferno.
But before I do, I have to tell you there are two kinds of punishment in the Inferno: an interesting kind and a very boring kind.
That is, on page 41, Piarti, who understands very, very little of what's going on, although he's a good translator, gives you one of the kinds of punishments, the boring kind, in the middle of 41.
The law of Dante's hell is the law of symbolic retribution.
As they sin, so are they punished.
Now, that's called contra paso in Italian, I gather.
I don't know where I've written it so I can spell it, but it's in effect, yeah.
It says, as they did, we're going to turn it against them now.
How many know of the Gilbert and Sullivan opera, The Mikado?
Anybody?
I won't help to use that as an example.
But there is an opera by Gilbert and Solomon, which is a perfect example of contra paso, where the emperor devised all kinds of very funny things that drive people crazy, who, when turned against them, the one I remember is the people who are totally obsessed with playing billiards are all given twisted, curved billiard cues for eternity.
They're trying to hit the ball, but they can't ever hit it straight, and so forth.
Dante has sort of punishments like that, where it looks like you're turning the tables on the people.
Just to show you what it would look like, there's a punishment in here where we'll get to sometime.
Maybe I think, in fact, you don't need to read it.
The schismatics, the people who split the church, are punished by being cleaved in half from top to bottom by devils with swords, and then they grow back together again, and then they're cut again because they cut the church in two, now they're being cut in two.
Very boring sort of punishment.
The interesting punishments are, and we'll look at them, the punishments where the punishment is the crime.
That is, you get a description of the life of the person who, while they were living it, wanted to live that way.
But after they die, they see sort of the truth of how miserable they were, even though they hid that from themselves and sort of glamorized what they were doing.
So the gluttons, for instance, in real, in life, thought they were gourmets and hated Chpanis, but in the end, they're sort of shown that they're more like pigs, that they are sort of wallowing in food and it's no fun at all, but it's supposed to be what they were doing all along, only they just didn't admit it to themselves.
So we've got to look at both kinds of punishment.
Oh, by the way, the fortune tellers I wrote here, if I tell you the following, which is it?
The fortune tellers, is which kind of punishment?
The fortune tellers have their heads turned around so that they look behind them, and when they walk around, they bump into things because they used to see in front of them, now they can't see in front of themselves anymore.
What do you think about that?
Is that contrapaso or is that the punishment is the crime?
Right.
I mean, this is no, this doesn't give you any insight into a fortune teller's life than to see that they're being punished by not being able to see the future anymore and thereby constantly bumping into things.
That's just uninteresting.
So what would an interesting one be like?
Well, we're going to look at two interesting ones, I hope, before time is up today.
The second kind of punishment can be described in a way as the punishment in which they long for what they fear.
That is, where is it?
45.
When he says, what about all these souls?
How did they get in hell at the bottom of 45?
They all pass over eagerly, for here divine justice transforms and spurs them so their dread turns wish they yearn for what they fear.
It's really more like they fear for what they're yearning for.
It is that what they most desired, they are what they were addicted to, whether it was sex, you'll see, or love, no, sorry, not love, or food, or material things, whatever they were addicted to, they're still addicted to it, but now they see the dark side, the cost of that addiction, the misery that's really involved in it.
But they yearn for it and fear it.
That's the interesting kind of punishment.
So let's do two of them.
One of them, one of each to begin with.
Here's, and you can try to figure out which.
So now we're going to look at the people who Chiardi on page 41, showing utter lack of understanding, calls the opportunists.
They're not opportunists, you'll see.
But we have to see what's happening.
They are people who have not taken sides on anything.
They are, I want to translate them as the uncommitted, not as opportunists.
The clue is for on page 47, where you hear about one of these people, namely at the top, the footnote, the great denial.
Who made the great denial?
This is certainly intended to be Celestine V, who became Pope in 1294.
He was a man of saintly life, but allowed himself to be convicted by a priest named Benedetto, convinced by a priest named Benedetto that his soul was in danger since no man could live in the world without being damned.
In fear for his soul, he withdrew from all worldly affairs and renounced the papacy.
Does that sound like opportunism?
It does certainly not.
It sounds like somebody who should have had a commitment to do his job as pope, but put his own interests above that of a pope, and instead of tearing through on his commitment, sort of back out of his commitment.
And that's what these people are, I think, are people who don't stick to what they are committed to when it gets tough.
And their punishment is that they are following all sorts of different banners, and the only reason, and changing, I think, from banner to banner, and only follow them because they're being stung to follow them by bees.
Now, is that a story about how their life really is?
I don't think so.
I mean, that's again sort of if you were somebody who didn't follow any banner with any kind of enthusiasm, but simply look out for yourself as an non-committed person, then you get a kind of reversal, a contrapasto of life.
You are stung and forced into running after banners as if you were committed to them.
And something like that is going on.
It's pretty obscure, I must admit, but it's certainly not opportunism, whatever it is.
So that is a, I think, a kind of punishment that isn't like their life.
I don't think this Pope was running after various banners in his life.
He wasn't running after anything.
He was withdrawing from everything.
And so the punishment is the opposite.
He's now forced to run after all these banners.
Whereas, as it says on 47, he withdrew from worldly affairs and renounced the papistry.
And now, this is the punishment he gets.
And I think all I can say is it's a very peculiar kind of punishment.
And now, but I don't want to spend much time on it, except as a revelation of Dante.
Now, why would this?
Not every punishment tells you a lot about Dante, but the two I'm going to talk about today do.
And this is the first one that does.
What's peculiar about this punishment, very peculiar, I'm reading the footnotes, and there are all kinds of facts that I wouldn't normally know.
There isn't any place in the normal Christian view of hell for the uncommitted.
Dante made it up.
And there isn't any place for it, literally, in the geography of hell.
So it's called the vestibule of hell.
It's sort of stuff on the outside of hell where these people are punished this way.
Now, why is that interesting?
Because it tells you that Dante thinks it's such a serious crime to be uncommitted, to not take a stand and stick to it, that he's ready to go against in a kind of heretical way the story about hell and change the geography and build a space just to punish this kind of person.
And Dante, look at Dante, talk about uncommitted or committed.
He's utterly committed to Beatrice.
He's living his whole life in terms of Beatrice, or a lot of it, but you don't even know, and all the footnotes tell you in boring detail, and you should just glance at them.
He was also a very committed person in politics.
He was taking sides between the two big political parties, the Guelphs and the Ghibellines, such that when the wrong party won, he was exiled from Florence altogether.
I mean, he was definitely someone.
Why didn't he just stay home and renounce his politics?
Because he thought that was the most awful thing in the world.
You should take a stand on love and a stand on politics, and you should stick to them.
So he expresses his outrage at these people who are not opportunists but uncommitted.
And that's interesting about him.
And it's a kind of, well, that's it.
Now comes the interesting one, because it's the right kind of punishment.
And that is limbo.
Limbo is in the tradition.
Limbo is in the tradition way back to Homer, where it was the fields of Aspodel.
Remember where Menelaus was going to go, where life, or in this case, death, was a dream of ease, and everybody who was sort of laid back and had nice, comfortable life and had parties and talked to other people and so forth, nice sociable lives.
They could go on like that forever.
Well, that's where the virtuous pagans are.
Limbo is a nice area where nice people gather and talk and so forth.
You can see, and this is on the bottom of 50, two-thirds of the way down.
No tortured wailing rose to greet us here, but sounds of sighing rose from every side, sending a tremor through the timeless air.
A grief breathed out of untormented sadness.
Who does that remind you of?
Who was sort of seen to write a poem full of sadness?
Well, Virgil.
People thought, remember, that people were so sad that they didn't even want to be born.
It was better never to be born.
And what could be better than being dead is the moral of the sentence of the Aeneid.
So they are, like Virgil, sad.
There's nothing joyful.
There's nothing blissful, ecstatic, fulfilling, meaningful for them, but they lead calm lives.
And so naturally, you're going to find Virgil at home in Limbo, because that's where he normally is.
And so he's going to, because all of the other virtuous pagans.
And Dante asks, and the master said to me, sorry, he says, you do not question what souls these are that suffer here before you.
I wish you to know before you travel on that these were sinless to the bottom of 50.
That's how we know that Virgil isn't a rebellion against anything, that these were sinless.
And still their merits fail, for they lack baptism's grace, they weren't Christians, which is the door to the true faith you were born to.
Their birth fell before the age of the Christian mysteries, and so they did not worship God's Trinity in false duty.
I'm one of these.
For such defects are we lost, though spared the fire and suffering of hell in one affliction only, that without hope we live on in desire.
That is, they don't know what they're missing.
They just have, they're just sad and they wish they were dead.
If they knew what they were missing, they'd already be a step in the right direction.
But as it is, they, without hope, in fact, that seems wrong.
Gotta look at the Italian there.
Shouldn't be without hope they live in desire.
They don't even desire.
They're just sad.
Who, without hope, lives in desire?
Who would?
I'm thinking the Hebrews, waiting for the Messiah, lived in desire, but they had hope for the Messiah.
These ones, the virtuous pagans, had no hope and no desire, it seems to me.
I don't know whether that's what's going on there, but what Virgil, they're missing something.
Whether you call it desire when you feel that you're missing something, but you don't know what, I wouldn't call that desire.
The sadness is better.
But anyway, they are in limbo.
So he says, I thought how many worthy souls there were suspended in that limbo and so forth.
And now, let me see.
So now they'll never be able to have a fulfilled and blissful, joyful life because they never even wanted one.
And the afterlife is just a continuation of this life, like it was for Menelaus.
They get the life exactly that they wanted.
The life in which they walk around and talk to each other and sigh and discuss, and presumably that's fine.
There's no commitment, there's no risk, there's no bliss.
And all human beings need total fulfillment, joy, bliss.
That's what they were made to have, to be able to contemplate something that's totally meaningful and fulfilling and satisfying.
Whether it's Beatrice for Dante or whether it's God for the contemplatives or whatever, they don't have it and they'll never have it.
And human beings were meant to have it, so they were in a sad state.
Now the question is: I wonder if anybody has a question.
So there they are, condemned for eternity, and what is their crime?
They happen to live before Jesus.
That doesn't seem fair, yeah.
Ah, good.
Well, that's because you don't get to purgatory unless you're the kind of person who is living your life trying to get over whatever sin you've got.
They are the people in purgatory are sort of the kind of people who would be recovering alcoholics, for instance, who have got into the grip of some sin, who have to struggle to get out of it.
And that doesn't fix the speaker.
You can't put them into purgatory.
All you can do is put them into where they were, and that's where they were.
They get exactly what they want.
Well, want isn't right.
Yes, I guess what they want, because they want to be left alone, they want to be calm, they want to be without any risk and so forth.
And that's what they want.
And they got it.
In fact, one way to put it is as Stoics, they want moderation, self-control.
We had a word the other day discussing what kind of thing they had, that poets had, according to Dante.
But that's enough to do.
So they didn't get in the right relation to the possibility of agape love and fulfillment that Jesus brought.
And now we're back to your question.
But the punishment isn't unfair because they had no such choice.
There was no revelation.
There was nothing that told them that there was a better thing that human beings needed and could get than human beings than they desired and couldn't get.
They had no choice because there was no revelation.
And the question is, is that fair?
And the answer is it's not a question of fair.
That's why you've got to see this.
The afterlife isn't a kind of arbitrary punishment.
That's why that contrapasto looks is so confusing.
The afterlife is just the life you lived, now given its eternal significance and stuff forever.
It's like Menelaus.
And it's that Menelaus people aren't, as I just realized, breathing sadness into the air because they lived active, happy lives.
And even, well, now I be careful.
Achilles is an active one and he's unhappy.
Menelaus, I don't know.
Let's not worry about it.
Yeah.
Yeah, we've got to get to that.
I'm going to get to that in a minute.
Okay, anyway, they never wanted out of it, and they are simply living the lives they lead, all of them.
I mean, the crazy punishments sort of mess it up.
But you'll see another one next time, that is, maybe even this time.
But let's go on with them.
So they didn't know about love.
They were happy to be safe and sad and do their duty.
And their love, they didn't have any love and so forth.
So, and there they are.
I mean, you can't ask sort of, was it fair?
You could ask maybe sort of, well, it's too bad for them that Jesus came so late and that there's so many people in the world that he didn't get in touch with.
Well, that's true, but that doesn't, and maybe you could blame the Creator for that.
But once Jesus comes at the time he comes, and there's no answer to why he comes when he does.
He comes in the, quote, in the fullness of time, according to John.
And once he does, then everybody who isn't in touch with him won't just be in limbo.
They'll have some other story, which we haven't got to yet.
But we have to get to what Dietrich said.
What about Jesus coming down and taking a bunch of people out of limbo?
Who did Jesus take out of limbo, do you imagine?
I take it, let me put it as a puzzle, that for Dante, who solved it.
I don't know whether the Christians already solved it or he made it up.
There's a puzzle.
If you say these people got what they wanted, then nothing you can do to fix that.
That's the eternal meaning of their life.
Jesus can't come and retroactively give them joy.
But there are people who wanted something, namely total happiness and joy, but unfortunately they lived in the wrong place at the wrong time and didn't get it, though they understood that it would happen sometime.
It didn't happen while they were around.
Who were those people?
The Jews, the Hebrews, exactly the Messiah.
They understood that the glory of God would finally come.
And then, so what does Dante have to do about them?
Going to leave them in limbo?
No.
Then Jesus has to go down and get them and expose them to his truth and take them all out.
He took the Hebrews out.
And you get this on 51.
He takes out all these biblical figures.
So the mighty one, the middle, descended here among us, crowned with the sign of his victorious years.
I wonder whether I think there's a sort of joke in here, but I'm not sure.
Did Virgil mistake the crown of thorns for a kind of laurel wreath when Jesus came down there?
That's what I think is happening.
Here, this person, this mighty one, came down with a sign, namely something on his head, crowned with something, and he took from us the shades of our first parent, of Abel, his son, of Noah, of Moses, the bringer of law, the obedient, Abraham, David, his father, and so forth, Rachel, and so forth and so forth.
And do you want to say, why those only?
And then Dante says, and many more.
I think that means all the Hebrews, all the Hebrews who weren't sinners in some respect.
All the virtuous pagans are stuck in limbo, and all the virtuous Hebrews are taken up and exposed to Jesus and thereby got the joy and the bliss and the Messiah effect that they were wanting.
That's how it looks to Dante.
And the all, let's see, where are we?
Okay, yes, he visits, he takes out the figures, the other, all the Hebrews, and leaves behind the virtuous pagans, which include the philosophers on 53.
Well, it's funny, of course, they didn't have a clear distinction between literature and reality.
He leaves behind, I mean, he takes, yeah, he leaves behind near the bottom of 53, Electra, Hector, Aeneas, Caesar, all these sort of mythical and historical figures mixed together.
And at the bottom of 55, Dante sees on high, that is on limbo, in limbo, on a hill, Aristotle, the master of those who know, ringed by the great souls of philosophy, Plato at his side, it's on top of 54, before all others, before all others except Aristotle, and then a whole lot of other ones.
And then remember, I couldn't spell it, so I didn't write it on the board, but thank goodness there it is on 54, the people who translated Aristotle.
So besides Euclid, Ptolemy, Hippocrates, there is Avancena and Averroes, the Arab translators of Aristotle.
Those are all there.
That is both the Greek and the Arab philosophers.
And now, just the last interesting punchline, really, and who else?
Well, the great poets, and particularly the very, very great poets who wrote works of art that worked.
So you get that on 52.
And the middle of the page.
There's an honor, about five stanzas on 52.
And as he spoke, a voice rang on the air: Honor the Prince of Poets, the soul and glory they went from us.
The soul and glory that went from us returns.
Here he is, here he is, the crises.
I saw four mighty presences coming toward us and neither joy nor sorrow in their bearing naturally.
And who was that?
Well, if you skip down to the very bottom, and after they had talked a while, no, let me see, where's Homer in there?
I'm sure Homer is there, just a second.
Oh, yeah, I just didn't see it.
It is Homer, singing master of the world.
Next to him, Horace, and so forth and so on.
So Homer is the great poet.
He's the first reconfigurer.
He's certainly the one that Dante most admires.
And then, and now comes Dante, which does an amazing move.
You can think about sort of yourself whether this is incredible pride or what, that he says at the bottom.
And after they had talked together a while, they turned and welcomed me most graciously, at which I saw my approving master smile.
So Dante writes a poem in which the great poets of all time, including Homer who made a work of art work, says, You're one of us.
And they honored me far beyond courtesy, for they included me in their own number, making me six in that high company.
Well, what do you make of that?
Well, on the one hand, you could say amazing self-confidence and self-promotion.
Or you could just say, well, he was realistic.
He knew that he was writing a work that was going to be at the level of the greatest possible poets.
That Homer would say, he had a good job, Dante.
And he congratulated himself.
And he was right.
You can't be very annoyed at him for having put himself among the greatest poets of all time, since he was one of the greatest poets of all time.
And he somehow knew it.
Anyway, that we can stop with that.
Dante's now congratulated himself and he starts down into the inferno.
Be sure and read two things I want you to read: the part on Powell and Francesca, and let me just tell you, because it's very, I'm going to read it very carefully.
I don't know where it is, but I've got to find it.
You can start packing up, but I'll tell you where what I want to read is.
Where is Tanto V toward the end?
Now that's Paula and Francesca.
Definitely read that one.
But then I want to talk about what happens outside the city of Dith also next time.
It's very, okay, here we are.
So, and Tanto 8.
Whatever else you read, more, because there's more in the assignment.
Definitely Tanto V and Tanto VII for next time.
Okay.