So let's just do the gods one more time.
So starting at the bottom of the chart, we did Gods Last last time, didn't we?
Does anybody remember?
Okay, so starting at the bottom, I won't go, I'm going to go real fast.
There are these forces that everybody is under and which are sort of very basic, the earth and the heavens and time.
And then that's not anything we can say anything interesting about, I think.
And it's not even anything that the people in the culture have anything interesting to say about.
It's just some very basic structure that shows up in all sorts of myths.
The second one is a cross-cultural kind of structure, too, but it's got its own, each culture makes its own interpretation of, for instance, nature, death, need for shelter, the seasons and the fact that you need to eat.
All of that is in the gods of Poseidon for nature, Hades for death and the underworld, Hestia for the hearth and shelter, and Demeter for the seasons and the harvest.
Then one of the children of Kronos, which is the way basic time god, who never shows up and talks to people, by the way, these basic gods that we've just been talking about, Gaia, Uranus, that is earth and heaven, Cronus time, and the four I just mentioned who are children of Kronos, they are such impersonal kinds of cultural, or personal kind of forces, or general, such general cultural forces, that they aren't personified in people.
There are people there, but they don't show up and talk to human beings and stand on human, next to human beings when they do things like Athena does when Telemachus does his coming from a child world to a man's world, or as Aphrodite does when Helen leaves the domestic world for the erotic world.
These other basic general forces, even though they are represented by people, aren't interacting directly with people.
But then come the ones that we're really interested in.
And that is, Cronus gives birth to Zeus, and Zeus, I'll come back to this later.
If you ask yourself, well, what's Zeus' job?
His only job description really is protector of strangers, which is pretty weird.
And I won't tell you, I have a lot to say about that, but I'd rather get there by talking about all the other gods first.
So let's go.
There are all these gods that represent something like three different things that I haven't distinguished very well, as somebody in office hours was convincing me of.
You could say that the gods like Aphrodite, who is the erotic love god, goddess, the sort of golden Aphrodite, there, Marilyn Monroe.
And when you could say that she represents the mood, that when she shines on you, anybody, they're in the mood for sex or love or something, and that is somewhere in that dimension.
And then, but that's, there are also people who are just generally in that mood and particularly sensitive to that mood.
And Helen is like that.
I mean, she doesn't just happen to be in this mood when Paris goes by, presumably, but she's a kind of person who is very sensitive and open to the attraction of the opposite sex and of all the beautiful romantic, well, romantic is later, but beautiful ornaments and situations and shared experiences that go with that.
So there's the mood, the goddess shines, and anybody's in it.
There are people who have a tendency to be in that mood.
So that they're exactly, Athena is the only goddess who's with Odysseus, and she's always around, or almost always, accompanying Odyssey.
I presume Aries, the war god, is the only god that Achilles ever interacts with, except when Athena pulls him by the ponytail to stop him from killing Agamemnon at the beginning of the Iliad.
And so then there are, so there are these people sort of associated with a particular god because they have a tendency to get in a particular mood.
And then there's something else which is, let me see how to put it.
Well, that's when I talk about worlds.
I mean, there's the world of Aphrodite, which is all that goes into having a kind of life in which the erotic is the main thing.
And then there's another, and let me say more about that for a minute because I skipped it last time, and now I regret it.
There are certain general characteristics of worlds.
So when you're thinking of the goddess like Aphrodite, you're thinking of a certain mood.
You're thinking of a certain kind of person that's in that mood a lot of the time.
And you're thinking about, or she represents, a certain world.
And what is a world?
Well, first let's just look at the things that we call worlds, and then we'll try to see what their common features are.
There's the business world and the what else?
The theater world, the academic world, and so forth.
And then there are these bigger things like the ancient world and the modern world.
But the kind level we want to talk on is where there's a plurality of worlds, and you use the term all the time.
You just don't ask yourself, well, what is it to be in the business world or the theater world or whatever?
It's not some spatial kind of end.
Being in the theater is ambiguous.
If you're just standing around in the theater, you're not in the theater world.
Being in the theater means, if it's a world story, being involved in theater things.
And if you're in the business world, then your main energy and so forth is involved in business.
And if you're in the academic world, then, like us, then your main energy is focused in the academic world.
But what do these worlds have in common that we talk about all the time?
Well, there's at least two features that Heidegger finds in them.
There's always equipment for doing whatever it is that you do in that world.
So you can have props and costumes and theaters and so forth.
And you can have whatever business needs, computers and cubicles and CDOs and so forth.
And you certainly know what kind of equipment you've got.
I see it all over the place.
Computers.
I would have thought digital recorders.
That just shows how surprising things can be.
But there's plenty of other things, books and pens and pencils.
And that's always in a world that it has its own kind of equipment.
Take the Aphrodite world.
Apparently, she has the beautiful dresses and Helen too, her long-robed Helen that we hear about.
And there's, I don't know, what sort of the gifts that you give people when you're in that world and so forth.
I mean, they don't have Valentine's, but I'm sure they have some equivalent thereof.
And in each of these worlds, then there's equipment.
Of course, the Aries world of war and aggression and belligerence has got its swords and spears and helmets and horses and chariots and generals and foot soldiers and so forth.
So, okay, so now you can, so that I'm going to now distinguish three levels or three, I don't know, aspects, let's call it, of what it is that a god like Aphrodite, say, is in charge of.
A mood, the life of a person who has a tendency to be in that mood most of the time, and the world that goes with being in that mood.
Meaning, oh, I forgot I knew there was another, besides equipment, put this back in the world, roles.
There's all, I named them, but I didn't call them roles.
There are generals and foot soldiers, I said.
And I said they're CEOs and the people in the cubicles and so forth.
And here, there are professors and teaching assistants and students and deans and so forth.
It's part of a world that there are these various jobs.
Okay.
Anybody want to say anything about that?
I think I owe you that a lot from way back when I hadn't distinguished those.
Okay, well, now that I have, yeah, yes, of course.
Good.
Good point.
That's very important.
Right.
A world is a kind of, in Heidegger jargon, it doesn't have much disclosive space.
It is an opening in which things can show up for you and offer you possibilities for action.
In fact, that's true enlightenment, as if it was up to you to make a choice, draw you into certain possibilities of action.
When the war world shows up, they all march off to war full of energy and aggression and so forth.
When Aphrodite shows up, they all rush off to bed, full of energy too.
And in every one of the worlds, it opens up a lot of possibilities and draws you in.
And each world has its own bunch of possibilities.
I mean, you don't find mixing of Aries in Aphrodite, at least not in their culture or our culture.
There could be a culture where aggression and sex were very much tied up, and they had different gods and so forth.
But they certainly don't seem to be interrelated in this story.
I think I mentioned this: what does get interrelated between, well, it's interesting.
There's this crazy thing in the middle of the book, which I always sort of think of as a kind of sitcom, where Aphrodite goes to bed with Aries while Hephaestus is away.
That's sort of interesting in this, in what we're talking about, in terms of what possibilities show up to what it makes sense to do.
I didn't put it that way, but that's another phrase.
What it makes sense to do depends on what world you're in.
But in that crazy story, there are two things that are interesting.
One, why is Aphrodite with Hephaestus, who is sort of portrayed usually as he's a cripple, and he's sort of ugly, and he's just a brilliant craftsman who makes very beautiful things, but it's a funny couple, golden Aphrodite and ugly Hephaestus.
Well, the answer seems to be, at least as far as I can tell, there is an overlap between the worlds, which I was talking about without naming.
The erotic world is tied up with beautiful things, beautiful earrings, beautiful clothes, beautiful gifts, and people who are at least trying to look their most beautiful and so forth.
So there is something between the artifice of Hephaestus and the craftsman and Aphrodite.
And so they are there together.
But they're not a terribly happy couple.
And as soon as Hephaestes goes away, Aphrodite goes to bed with Aries.
And that's not surprising either that you've chose Aries because he is the aggressive, sort of, I suppose, somewhat brutal side and sort of raving crazy.
He's described as crazy, Aphrodite.
He's sort of out of his mind in an aggressive way, and she's sort of the goddess of people out of their mind in a passionate, erotic way.
And so naturally they get together.
But as you know, if you've read, how many have read?
You got that far already, haven't you?
I don't want to give away the sitcom plot.
But so Hephaestus makes this net, and he catches them, and then naked in his bed, and then all the gods come around and watch and laugh.
And I say that just because I want to point out different relations you can have to that.
And it'll get me to the next people I want to talk about.
So we've talked about Athena.
We talked about Hephaestus.
Let's talk about Apollo because his reaction to the sexting in the middle of the book is so typical of Apollo, I think.
Remember, he's the far-shooting lord of distance.
These are phrases that apply to him.
And his fields are prophecy, medicine, and music.
All of that has in common detachment.
And he's going to turn into the god of sort of theory and rationality when you get to Aeschylus.
He's always wanting to get the arguments straight and show that the reason is on his side and that what he sees is some kind of universal truth because he's never got passionately involved.
That's why he's the god of distance.
Well, when Aries and Aphrodite are in bed together there, and all the gods are laughing, there's only two gods that aren't laughing.
But one is Apollo, who is just, I think, too detached.
And he turns to the god next to him, and that's, we'll get back to him next time, Hermes, and says, would you be willing to be so humiliated to go to bed with golden Aphrodite?
And Hermes says, in effect, of course.
But Apollo, it would be totally wrong if it was the other way around.
If Hermes said to Apollo, as if he was the spectator, would you be willing to go to bed with Aphrodite under those conditions?
Well, Apollo would be appalled, I think.
Wouldn't think of it.
So we'll see that Hermes is a kind of, well, among other things, a very important kind of swindler, operator, thief.
And so he's ready to take anything he can lay his hands on and appropriate it, so to speak.
And he regrets he's not the one.
But, okay, so now we've got done Apollo.
We won't do Athena yet.
And Aries, there's nothing more to say except that he's the ferocious, crazy, sort of out of control, lerserk, war god, and Hephaestus, the craftsperson.
The other ones are people that Artemis doesn't make any big show in this.
She's the hunter, the virgin, the with a bowbo and arrow.
I don't know what life was like then, but I think she would now be the goddess of horse people.
My daughter, for instance, was definitely an Artemis horse person.
And now she still loves animals and is now an environmentalist.
I'm sure Artemis would be the goddess of the environmentalists at this point.
The green goddess.
I don't know what she looks like.
And Persephone, she's sort of running things in Hades, but I don't know anything about her.
And I mentioned Dionysus in here too, but it's funny, he never gets mentioned, as far as I remember, at all by Homer.
Homer just doesn't care about Dionysus.
Yeah.
Now we need our question person.
We're going to test this and see if this theory works.
I was just mentioning that Dionysus was a newer god after Homer's time.
He was sometimes believed to be an imported god from foreign countries.
So good.
Thanks.
Well, that works too.
Thank you.
Just keep the microphone.
Don't take it home with you, but hold on to it.
It helps.
Do you hear me?
Okay, then I'll keep it.
There must be a better way, given all this high tech.
But for the day, I'll have to do.
Okay, so that's interesting.
Well, good.
I printed Dionysus in a funny font because I suspected something.
So he isn't even around yet at Homer's time.
You know anything about Persephone?
No, nobody knows.
You know something about Persephone?
I see.
Okay, that's I can see why she doesn't interest Homer very much because those aren't really worlds.
There's no sort of equipment, really, for being summer or winter.
If there is, there's certainly no roles for me.
And it doesn't define a kind of life, a tendency to be summer or winter.
So it's not a, she's not a good person.
See, all these other people, there are roles for doing their kind of thing and equipment for doing their kind of thing run through it.
Aries, the war person, the craftsperson, the theory person, the hunting kind of person.
She's sort of marginal and that's how she gets treated.
And the erotic person, those are really whirls.
Okay, some question.
I saw a hand over there.
I swear I saw something.
I know I did.
Doesn't answer the question?
Well, okay, whatever.
So let's go on.
So let me, I'm going to now sort of run through what I've written here and see if it corresponds to roughly to what I said.
So far, yes.
And then there are these very peculiar ones that for various reasons I don't know what to do with.
By the way, I should say, I can't make a story that fits everything in the Odyssey and in the Iliad, that gods do all kinds of weird things, particularly in the Iliad, where Apollo, for instance, makes the what, who somebody's horse talk to him and tell him not to go into the battle.
That just doesn't fit in my picture of what gods are supposed to be doing.
But I'm trying to construct a kind of ideal polytheism because Homer's got the best polytheism, the most worked out, the most interesting around.
And we just have to sort of extrapolate it and clean it up.
And I mean, there are all kinds of elements in it that probably are really folk elements in it, and they aren't fully integrated in it.
And there are also stuff probably that was put into it because it was an oral tradition for a long time before it was written down.
And when it was written down, things probably were written into it that weren't there all the time.
But in any case, we don't care about that.
I mean, that's a very interesting question, no doubt, for people reading the Iliad and the Odyssey in a classics course.
We want to get sort of what the basic insight of this kind of polytheism is, what a life inside this kind of polytheism is.
So there are people, this was all to say, there are people, I don't know how to deal with them.
Hera, I think Hera would be great as the goddess of domesticity, which she seems to be.
Married to Zeus seems to be her main thing, and being jealous of his affairs seems to be her main jobs.
But we don't really get a full picture in her of what a domestic god just would look like.
She would plan the big banquets on Olympus, and she would take care of the family and so forth.
But that doesn't seem to be a job for anybody on Olympus, and so we don't care about Hera.
There's another person in there who Hebe, who I don't put on the chart, who serves drinks and is in general and sort of takes care of cocktail parties and stuff on Olympus.
But it just doesn't get worked out.
And Poseidon is a very special problem because he's not a world.
He's the god of the anti-world, so to speak.
Why isn't it a world?
Because he's the god of nature.
And there aren't roles and there aren't equipment to be nature.
And he's the overpowering force of particularly the ocean, which is the most overpowering force the Greeks knew and still is.
Did I mention my movie last time?
Did I talk about Poseidon last time?
I've gotten dependent on my own podcast to remember what I've said.
So anyway, did I ask how many have seen Castaway?
I probably didn't.
How many have seen Castaway?
Good, good.
If I had time, I'd show it in the course just to show what the...
When I saw that movie, I felt for the first time, now I know what it was like to be Odyssey on a raft in the face of this overwhelming force of the ocean.
It's brilliant for that.
And so he is that.
And Odyssey suffers from him.
But he doesn't have the normal features of world-defining gods.
He really looks like he belongs down in that lower level where I put him.
And he's, and it's important.
Homer doesn't have this all figured out in his head, I don't think.
But the sense of the people, sort of certain stories obviously stick and certain ones don't.
And like certain metaphors, like up a title or something, all the funny things that people say, that one takes off or laid back and so forth.
So the the kind of wisdom of the people sort out all the stuff about gods and some of it comes around.
I agree, but Poseidon isn't one of those gods of possible Greek worlds on the chart.
He is the brother of Zeus.
He's one and he's he's not a father of all those human world gods.
He's and that's and they have to treat him.
He's on Olympus with the pantheon.
The pantheon is the name for all the gods that are on Olympus, and he's on Olympus, unlike Demeter and Hestia and Hades.
But he's certainly in an ambiguous position because he's the brother of Zeus and he doesn't have to do what Zeus says.
And every once in a while, when he gets upset at people, he goes around and beats them up.
Because the Cyclops is a child of his, he gets very annoyed at Odysseus, who then that's where you get all this heavy beating up from the water when he comes crashing down on him.
And the other gods can't do anything about it because it's as if it was the force of nature against all the other forces with your culture.
All the other forces are roles and worlds that you can only have in a culture.
And then there is Poseidon, who's outside of the culture, and the Cyclops, who's pretty much outside of the culture, too.
We'll come back to the Cyclops later in another connection.
So, so much for the God story, I believe.
Yeah.
I just wrote down here, but I've sort of said it.
Cyclops is a sort of a minimal fourth generation God.
Not even a god.
Never mind.
He's, why do I have him on my chart?
I think we should cross out the Cyclops.
You know, because all these others are gods, but is he a god?
Demigod or something.
That's another thing, by the way, I don't hear.
I don't know how to cope with, but if anybody does, they should think about it, tell me about it, write a paper about it.
The demigods, are they very peculiar?
Probably Poseidon too.
They're half, I mean, they don't immortal.
They're not part of the pantheon.
That's why I don't like Cyclops up there, because he's something, I don't know where to put him, but down lower, because everybody up at the top is in the pantheon, is a cultural archetype or whatever the right word is, paradigm.
I don't like archetypes.
The reason I don't, archetypes are thought of as definitely cross-cultural things.
Cross-cultural heroes.
And I think that's just a very bad way of thinking about it.
It levels all the important differences.
What heroes are.
So I want to say paradigms.
Gods aren't cross-cultural.
About all human beings that they can discover.
Some of them.
Anyway, so the story goes.
But I want to say the important thing is that each culture's got a different shape on it.
A lot of them don't even have heroes.
And some of them have very different kinds of heroes.
What the gods are aren't cross-cultural.
That's the third generation.
You know, there is the Gaia generation, and then there is the Hades and company generation.
And then there is the second what do what what do I call it?
The second or third generation?
The generation, anyway, with Hades, Poseidon, and so forth.
Those are the cross-cultural ones.
The s c the cultural ones, each culture has its own paradigm.
The uh Apollo is not the archetype of of of intelligence.
We're the only culture with theory.
A Athena's not the only form.
Well, Athena's so special.
Only, only.
Let's say Artemis is a is a spe is not the same the paradigm with a certain above and not like any all any other culture, if you spell it out, I think.
Okay, somebody in back, can you say something very loud?
You can't hear me.
What am I going to do?
What's that?
Oh, okay.
But good.
Thanks for telling me.
Because I sound very loud to me.
I wonder why there must be speakers all around here.
Yeah, they're I guess they're very near me.
Okay, here we go.
Again, another test I just see I've written here is whether the all the gods in the in the pantheon can be a way of life.
You can have a theoretic a theory life, you can have a love life, you can have a worry about the environment and love horses life and so forth, but you can't you can't have a cyclops kind of life.
That's is that's just not a not a cultural possibility.
Cyclops is really a minimal amount of equipment to help in the stars.
And he also, what else?
And he's really just a part of nature.
The Cyclops is really a volcano.
I mean he kind of he's related to volcanoes.
That's why he has one eye and then that eye gets fiery and smoke volcano.
When when he just yells, I'm I'm the one who blinded you Polyphemus.
Then Polyphemus starts throwing big rocks that they're almost sink the boat well because that's a volcano erupting so there's he's really still in the in the Greek god world and really just a piece of nature but anyway that's that I don't want to get into that we should get into the next part so how are the various good lives related I mean given that those there are all these different possible lives which I was just naming and won't name again you could list the goddess and that list of lives okay talk louder we're gonna have to throw the microphone at you what are I think all the Cyclopses are probably Poseidon's children is that what you ask yeah I don't know I mean I don't know if it says anywhere you have any idea I suspect they are because they're still because I mean all the volcanoes are and I think they're still pretty closely related to volcanoes just as Poseidon is pretty you don't picture them much Poseidon sort of running around like a person although he does do that a little bit likes them best okay so let's go let I'm going to talk now about the interesting way and cyclopses can be brought right into this discussion so I'll jump to that probably what I wanted to do anyway okay there's I want to say that in in the one of the things about polytheism and is that there's appreciation of lots of different kinds and and this is the interesting find sort of incredible and sort of congenial well you'll see when I get there uh th th it does Homer does not want to rank the lives.
Lives are better than those lives.
Like saints are better than sinners.
Immature people are less are m mature people are better than immature people.
We've got lots of ranked people.
That's what it is to be probably.
You're having trouble hearing me?
Okay.
I don't know what to do about this.
Anyway, okay, just keep telling me, and someday I'll figure out how to deal with this.
Oh, one of the ways to growth over.
I won't try to do it now, but I know that inside that cabinet is the volume control.
Let's see what happens.
No, then I have to take this one off.
I give up.
This one.
Okay, like that.
Is that better?
Okay.
It isn't worse anyway.
I don't have that kind of microphone.
But I don't have that kind of phone.
I only have three microphones.
I don't want to.
Yeah.
What?
Hold it.
No, I can't.
That's too distracting.
Okay, I'm going to go.
You convinced me.
We're trailing this over here to see about whether we can use this microphone.
I'm looking for the key.
There's the key.
We don't even know whether this key opens this thing, but let's try.
Aha, that's a start.
Now, microphone one, microphone two, microphone.
One, two, they're all turned up full.
Great.
What else?
That settles that.
But I'm looking more.
The wireless we can turn up, maybe?
No, it's full.
It's full.
Well, there it goes.
I'm glad I tried.
And look at that.
That's switched to off.
I bet that's what happened last time, too.
After the first 20 minutes, if it's there's no way to lock it on, is there any way to put it on hold?
Everything has a hold button.
Everything but this one.
Well, I'll put it back in my pocket.
There'd be some new disaster.
Okay, so I want to start by contrasting, to show you how radically Homer does not want to rank wives.
I'm going to talk about the relation of the Phaeacians to the Cyclopses.
We just talked about the.
Am I ready?
Well, no, I'm not ready to talk about that.
No, I want to start with the life of Achilles as the Aries warrior one, contrasted with Menelaus, who went off to fight, after all.
Paris took his wife.
But he's not mainly a warrior.
He's very good at being a host at banquets is where Telemachus finds him.
And I don't remember him doing anything very memorable in the Trojan War, in the Iliad either.
His life is kind of la dolce vita.
He's ease, no risks.
He's nearly immortal.
Because he doesn't want to make himself vulnerable.
And the interesting question is, what will happen to him in sort of the final kind of judgment whether this is a good life or not?
And it turns out, well, it's a great life.
And Homer approves of it.
And he's told when he captures the old man of the sea and gets him to tell him what's going on about things on page 69.
You get an idea of what's the kind of life he leads and the relation this has to what happens to you after you die.
So here he's about two-thirds of the way down on 69, about 600 in the margin.
As to your destiny, Prince Menelaus, you shall not die.
Sorry, you shall not, he does die.
You shall not die in the bluegrassland of Argos.
Rather, the gods intend you for Elysium with golden rhadamanthus at the world's end, where all existence is a dream of ease.
That's the crucial phrase.
Snowfall is never known, neither the frost of winter nor torrential rain, but only mild and lolling air from ocean bearing refreshment for the souls of men, the west wind always blowing.
The gods hold you as Helen's lord, a son of Zeus.
The important thing is that his life is a dream of ease.
That's where you see him at the banquets.
And when he dies, he'll go to Hades, and it'll just be a continuation of that.
Now, the question I'm asking is: how does Homer rank that life relative to Achilles' life?
Now, you haven't read the Iliad, but you all know that Achilles is the glorious fighter, and you don't maybe know that it's important that his mother, who was a goddess, a demigod, which is probably important, but I don't understand how, so I won't try to explain it.
Anyway, the important thing about Achilles is that he's given the choice between a short and glorious life and a long, comfortable life like Menelaus.
And he chooses a short and glorious life, a different way of life.
He wants to do great deeds and have people sing of him at wonderful banquets.
That's what, and be by far the fastest runner and the most enduring fighter on the field at Troy.
And what happens, and it looks like you want to say, well, the whole Iliad's about him, and Menelaus only has a bit part in the Iliad, and not even a very big part in the Odyssey.
It must be that Homer and the Greeks that he represents choose the short and glorious life, which when you get sung about as a hero, over the laid-back life of somebody like Menelaus.
But Homeric polytheism does a very strange move on Achilles, which I think is just fascinating.
That is, when, how is he going to deal with that?
Is he going to show you Achilles being a better life?
Remember what happens when they go to Hades?
They go, and Odysseus sees Achilles, and they have an interesting conversation.
Where are we now?
On 200.
So, 200, here we are.
On about very near the bottom, when he sees the spirit of Achilles in the middle of the page, he sees the spirit of Achilles at the middle of the page.
Then, in the next chunk, Odysseus makes a speech to Achilles.
Son of Laertes, that's his father, Achilles' father, and the gods of old.
That must be because his mother is a demigod.
Odysseus, what?
Who's talking?
Sorry about this.
Wait a minute.
Sorry, sorry.
It's Achilles talking.
Just a second.
Yes, I'm completely confused.
Son of Laertes, I should have known better.
Laertes is Odysseus' father.
And I don't know the gods of old.
I have no idea what he's doing in there, or they're doing in there.
But so when Achilles sees Odysseus, he calls out to him.
You see where we are now.
Son of Laertes and the gods of old, Odysseus, master mariner and soldier, old knife, what next?
What greater feat remains for you to put your mind on after this?
How did you find your way down to the dark where these dim-witted dead are camped forever?
The after images of used up men.
Now that's the first question we have to deal with.
It turns out, remember what we have read, what the old man of the sea described.
Now I've lost the old man of the sea.
Where are we?
69.
Okay.
What is Hades like?
You get very confused.
Here, Hades is a dream of ease.
Everybody would love to go there.
It's sort of the, it's like going to Hawaii.
The weather's always terrific.
And then you hear here that it's a terrible place where the dim-witted dead and the images of used-up men.
What's going on there?
Well, I guess, my story would be, Homer thinks that the afterlife is the perpetuation of what you had in this life.
In that sense, Menelaus's life stays the same.
But it can't perpetuate any kind of life where there is power and risk because they're all dead already.
So, what I'm trying to say is, from the point of view of Menelaus, the afterlife is just fine, and when he's dead, he's going to be just as happy as he is now, or even happier, because he's even going to be more comfortable.
But from Achilles' point of view, the afterlife is a disaster because you can't have the kind of energy risk-taking once you're already dead.
That's why these people are dim-witted dead, used-up men.
Now, the question is: does this fact that Menelaus can go on and have a great life even after he's dead, show that it's a better kind of life to live comfortably like Menelaus than to have a life in which you lead a short and glorious, energetic, risky life, and know you're going to have to die young?
Well, it looks like there's a problem, and it comes to a head at the top of 201.
Odysseus answers Achilles, but was there ever a man more blessed by fortune than you, Achilles?
This looks like this is the best possible life, you see.
Can there ever be?
We ranked you with immortals in your lifetime.
We Argaves did.
Here, your power is royal among the dead men's shades.
Think then, Achilles, you need not be so pained by death.
Okay, so this must you must be okay, Achilles.
You led what looks like the best possible life.
So you must be happy with that.
What difference does it make now that you aren't able to risk your life anymore?
And the answer is, let me hear no smooth talk of death from you, Odysseus, light of counsels.
Better, I say, to break sod as a farmhand for some poor countryman on iron rations than lord it over the exhausted dead, the used-up men, remember?
These people with no energy.
Remember, they even have to drink somebody else's blood, a cow's blood, or I forget where they get the blood, to have enough energy even to have this conversation.
So, let's see.
Okay, then he says, well, let's stop with that.
It looks like he says, my life is not a good life.
I've been deluded because there's nothing worse than death, and I've risked my life and shortened my life, and it would have been better to be living as long as possible.
And he's very unhappy about it.
So now it looks like Homer has taken what looked like the best possible life and shown that it's got these tremendous limitations that being alive is a very good thing.
And if you're going to be risking your life and dying young, that's not a very attractive life.
So you'll see, there's this, but now comes a really surprising thing.
Sometimes Homer is so surprising and subtle.
What happens next?
He switches right from complaining, Achilles, to saying, Tell me what news of the prince, my son.
Did he come after me to make a name in battle?
Or could it be he did not?
Do you know if rank and honor still belong to Peleus in the town of the Myrmidons?
That's his island, what he's king of.
Or now maybe Hellas and Pythias burn him, seeing old age fetters him, and so forth.
Okay, now, so now it looks like Achilles, even though he sees that his life, how do I put it here?
I like what I said.
Just a second.
If you make your life a ferocious warrior life, then of course you're going to get old and lose your physical strength and die, lose all your force altogether.
Achilles regrets that he chose a short and glorious life, and that's amazing.
And Odysseus is shocked.
And it looks like Homer has gone so far as to go from overvaluating the life of Achilles to now under-evaluating the life of Achilles.
He doesn't seem to be able to get it right, or to get any middle view.
But even though he thinks that, even though it looks like, this is what I wrote down, the life of a superhero is really not the life of the best, not the best life, but an inferior, deluded life, that's what I'm trying to say.
Then, then what's the reversal?
Well, the reversal is he's he believes, however, that what he wants his son to be is just like him, a soldier doing great deeds in battle.
And he's asking about that, and he hears that his son was great, that nobody could do better.
This is the bottom of 202, than his son, Neopotolemus, who ran out of the Trojan horse bravely before it while everybody else was scared.
And when we had pierced and sacked Prime's tall city at the bottom of 202, he loaded his plunder and embarked with no scar on him, not a spear grazed him, and so forth.
Aries, in his mad fits, notice he's Aries, he's crazy, as I said.
Aries, in his mad fits, knows no favorites.
And now comes the punchline.
Achilles has discovered that his son is like him.
And he regrets it looked like being a soldier who's likely to die young, or at least get older and not be able to go running around waving his spear anymore.
But that isn't what happened.
What happens is, but I said no more, for off he had gone, for he had gone off striding the field of Aspodel, the ghost of our great runner Achilles, glorying in what I told him of his son.
So finally, the glory of the heroic life looks so good that Achilles is even able to, you know, now he's not going to say, my son is being deluded.
It would be better if he were, what did he say, a farmhand, that he's going around risking his life as a soldier.
He doesn't say that at all.
He says, isn't that wonderful?
What's the moral of all this flipping back and forth?
Well, I think the moral of it is that Homer doesn't rank lives.
You can't ask who's got a better life, Menelaus or Achilles.
To do that, he has to sort of cut down the life of Achilles first so that you don't think he's just a natural superhero who could be as good as that.
Because there is this problem of dying, and Achilles is not, and the soldier is going to die young.
See, so he's getting, what I want to say is, Homer sees the trade-offs, the pros and cons of all these lives.
Menelaus has a soft life.
He has no glory, but he's not going to miss anything when he dies.
Achilles has a soldier life.
All he cares about is glory and fighting and risking, and he's going to miss all that when he dies.
But which life do you choose?
Well, they're equal.
That's the important thing.
But I've got a bigger surprise if you doubt that.
I hope you do, that he thinks that all these lives are equal.
There's a point where Homer goes sort of off the chart in equality.
You'll see that in a minute.
Where are we?
The different lives I wrote down here are incommensurate.
You can't compare them.
There's no common standard.
There's something good and something wrong with every life.
Another interesting place that happens is on 87, where Calypso tries to compare life with her.
Remember, she's the perfect sort of erotic partner.
I don't know how to describe her, sort of acacia kind of person or something, because she's good at everything.
She sings, she's good at conversation, I'm sure she's a good cook.
She's very good at bed and everything, and everything.
And everything, and the whole thing is that Odyssey, how could anybody want to leave?
And Odysseus is sitting there crying because he wants to go home.
And the interesting thing is, he's been there a year with her.
He wasn't in any hurry to go home.
She was so attractive.
It was only when the men said, Look, we're supposed to be on our way home, Odysseus, don't you remember?
That he got out of this mood of being totally seduced by her and started wishing he was at home with Penelope.
Moods do that.
They wear off.
Remember Helen's mood of always being with Paris happily, and it wears off, and she regrets that she's not home with Menelaus.
So he's now sitting there every day, crying, wishing he could go home.
And she's feeling bad about that.
She says on 87, son of Laertes, versatile Odysseus, after these years with me, years.
I wonder how long.
I said a year.
No, I'm talking about Calypso.
Did I say, Certain Steve?
I did.
And he's staying with Calypso here.
And he's, okay, how long with Calypso?
Many years, apparently.
Yeah, so there he is, so seduced by this super sexy, super intellectual and everything woman, he doesn't even think of leaving.
He forgets home and everything for a while.
Then he got bored.
And that mood wore off, and homesick mood took over.
So there he is, crying on 87.
But she says, After these years with me, you still desire your old home.
Even so, I wish you well.
If you could see all before you go, all the adversity you face at sea, you'd stay here and guard this house and be immortal, though you wanted her forever.
Who?
What?
Stay here and guard this house and be immortal, though you wanted.
Is he talking about Penelope already?
Does anybody understand that line?
Something go on.
Okay, let's let me go on then.
That bride for whom you pine.
Yes, it is Penelope.
Okay.
Yes, he's missing Penelope.
That bride for whom you pine each day.
Can I be less desirable than she is?
Less interesting?
Less beautiful?
Can mortals compare with goddesses in grace and form?
And to this, the strategist Odysseus answered, notice this very smart answer.
My lady goddess, here is no cause for anger.
My quiet Penelope, how well I know, would seem a shade before your majesty, death and old age being unknown to you while she must die.
Yet it's true, each day I long for home, long for the sight of home, presumably long for her too.
If any God has marked me out again for shipwreck, my tough heart can undergo it, and he's going to try to get home.
So what I want to say is, he won't compare Penelope to Calypso.
They are each, for sort of immortal perfection, Calypso wins.
But for being his wife with his home and his son, that's winning out.
And he doesn't say in effect that one is better than the other.
He just, in effect, when one mood was on, that dominated his life.
And he was pulled into that, kept in that.
Now, this other mood has taken over.
He wants to get home.
Okay, so what's one of the things, by the way, you should notice, everybody seems to think that Odysseus is always just interested in getting home.
That's just wrong.
And in case I don't get a chance to say it someplace else, you should notice that for years he's happy to stay with her.
And he doesn't even get out of the mood of staying with her until his men sort of revolt and say, well, we're not having such a good time, and we want to go home.
And the point is, I think, not just that he is so happy to be with her.
That's not the conclusion that interests me.
One interests me is he doesn't try to compare her to Penelope.
But the other thing is, he's interested in seeing all these other ways of life.
He's more interested in going where no person has gone before and just observing everything from, even if it's very risky, like when they go to see Circe and when they go to see Polyphemus, that his men almost get wiped out.
He's always manages cleverly not to get wiped out.
But his more interesting to him than going home in the beginning, anyway, is seeing other things.
I can't prove it with this because he stays there for all those years instead of running around and seeing other things.
But when he gets to Circe, I won't try to find the pages.
His men say, oh, let's not go there.
We see the smoke over there.
Somebody lives over there.
But we're on our way home.
And Odysseus says, oh, we've got to find out what it's like over there.
Who lives over there?
What is this person doing?
And then they almost all get killed, or turned into animals, to be exact.
And then again, with the Cyclops, they say, oh, no, we've had it, you've done it again.
We don't want to go see the Cyclops.
We want to go home.
And Odysseus says, no, we've got to see who lives in those caves.
His real dominating thing is to see and experience as many worlds as possible, I think.
And we'll get back to that too, but I may forget to say it, so I'll say it now.
I wonder what I say on 179.
I say there's something relevant to what I'm talking about.
So let's see what it is.
What is it?
Ah, look at that.
There seems to be a contradiction.
Because this is still with Calypso, isn't it?
This is Cersei.
I see now.
That's what you're saying.
We should notice on 179, he stays with her a year.
That's what you said, didn't you, Beatrice?
At the bottom of 179.
So day by day, we lingered feasting on roasts and wine until a year grew fat.
And when the passing months and wheeling seasons brought the long summery days, the pause of summer, my shipmates one day summoned me and said, Captain, shake off this trance and think of home.
And so then he's launched again into some new adventure.
But he's in no big hurry to get home.
Okay, now I want to do my punchline about Homer refusing to compare ways of life to the point of mind-bogglingness.
You're going to see that the two most extremely different ways of life in the book get, we're in effect told they're equally okay.
They're good lives.
So here we go.
It starts with the Phaeacians.
The Phaeacians are the most civilized of any of the people he meets.
They're even more civilized than the people back in Argos, not Argos, Ithaca, and then the Mamenelaus banquets.
They've got even better banquets.
They've got the best meals, the most quality craft productions, the best harpers, the best sporting events.
They have the good life.
They know it.
Everybody knows it.
They are closest to the Olympian gods, they say.
They are, let's read it about five lines down.
And now they, that is the Olympian gods, have shown themselves in glory only after great hecatomes.
Those figures banqueting at our side, throned like ourselves, or some traveler met them when alone they bore no least disguise.
So anyway, so they are so well off that they dine with the gods.
And the next line is amazing.
We are their kin.
The cyclops rank no nearer gods than we.
So he's refusing to even rank this absolutely civilized society of the Phaeacians as more or less near to God than the absolutely bruty cyclopses.
I mean, I can't defend it.
I think it's absolutely crazy, but I think it's something that the idea behind it is don't rank lives, don't rank cultures, don't rank ways of being human.
And this is the extremist refusal to rank them.
You're looking worried.
It is worrisome, I admit.
I didn't write it.
Not ranking the same as ranking them all of equal work.
I'm ranking them all?
Yeah.
Not the same as saying they're all of equal rank.
Well, no, that wouldn't be enough to say they were of equal rank, just that they are all to be explored with curiosity.
That would be the Odyssey thing.
But I think the Homer thing, you could say something more.
There seems to be a kind of implicit anyway, refusal to rank them.
I mean, the important thing isn't just that Homer looks with equal eye on all these lives.
There is no place where he tells you that one life is better than another.
But it's a kind of negative argument.
But I mean, I think it's important.
I mean, I can say one thing, then Beatrice.
I mean, in the back of my mind, I'm thinking this kind of polytheistic openness to all ways of life is what makes this a comedy and not a tragedy.
As soon as you think that you've got to rank them, then you have to, then you get fights between the people who are for this kind of life over against that kind of life.
The Aeschylus is a tragedy.
Aeschylus is a fight, the Orestea, about which is the better way of life.
And another thing, I guess it's in Homer somewhere.
Somebody tell me, where is the story about the golden apples that's behind the Trojan War?
Was it Juno, that is, Hera?
Who has to give the apple to the sort of prize winner?
Hera?
Paris?
Paris has to give it to, and he has to choose between Aphrodite, Hera, and Athena, the three ladies.
Who gets the Oscar or whatever he's got among these three stars?
And the answer is: never ask a question like that.
That's going to lead to disaster.
That leads indirectly to the Trojan War.
He should have refused to rank them.
The way this is smart, Odysseus refuses to rank Penelope and Calypso.
But he does.
Who's he now?
Who has to make the choice?
Paris.
And Paris gives it to Aphrodite, right?
And she gives him the power to run off with Helen, and there you go.
So there's something very interesting and attractive about Homer's implicit, and I take it that Greek Homeric culture's implicit suspicion of ranking anything.
And that's going to turn out to be important and interesting, I think, already.
Yeah.
Although I see, yes, let me find it.
Because it would be good to look at the Greek, right?
It is so mind-boggling that one wonders whether it really says what I think it seems to say.
Well, let me find it.
117, line 220, according to this.
Cyclops ranked no nearer gods than we.
Who would have thought that there were in the in the, who would have even tried to find out who was nearer God?
Neither one of them are like our gods, neither the Cyclops nor the Phaeacians.
And I think Homer wants us to see that neither one of them are nearer gods.
But that's, I think, amazing and weird.
Okay, let us go on.
I want to get up to why I like this kind of polytheism so much.
Let's see.
I go into a whole thing about the Cyclopses here, but why do I have to do that?
So I just say they're barely human.
They're savages.
They're brute natural forces.
They're like volcanoes.
I don't know why I'm telling you all this, particularly since I've told you once already.
But at least I can find where we are.
On 148, there's the Cyclops.
They see the Lotus Eater, another life of ease at the top of 148, but they go on.
And then they find the Cyclopses.
And they neither plow nor sow.
They're their hunter-gatherers types.
They are not even into the agriculture business, nor till the ground.
And wine grapes in clusters ripen in heaven is rain.
That is, they make wine, I think, but they do.
He has wine, but they don't cultivate wine.
They just go out and pick the grapes when they get ripe.
And they have no muster and no meetings.
That is no politics and no culture.
Then they each dwell in his own mountain cave and so forth.
So that's their thing.
And they are, on 151, line 230, he's a towering brute, outward power, a wild man, ignorant of civility.
And yet, and now, he says, let's go see them.
That's why I'm reading this.
Because I want to tell you that he's always ready to take any risks to see some new form of life.
And they all say, no, let's go out, let's go to sea again as soon as possible.
And he says, yet I refused.
I wished to see the caveman, what he had to offer.
And so they all, most of his crew ends up breakfast and lunch and dinner for the Cyclops.
And now where are we?
But he wants to see all forms of life.
Now, I'm ready to talk about why I like this multicultural way of this polytheistic non-ranking.
I think that it's very close to us.
And first you have to see how close it is to us, and then you have to see how different it is from us in order to see why Homer's got something that we lack.
And as if he were somehow the stage after us instead of the stage way before us.
Well, to begin with, he's close to us.
He seems to think that you ought to be able to choose all the different forms of life.
They're all interesting.
They're all worth coming, lingering with for a while, and then you can always go on to another.
But then you are free, it looks like.
Remember, in the Enlightenment, it looks like Homer's sort of after the Enlightenment, because it looks like Odysseus is free, self-determined, as to whether he goes and sees these people.
He freely chooses to see the Cyclops.
He freely chooses to see Calypso and Circe and so forth.
So he's really pro-choice, like we all are, in this sense that you have the choice.
You are free to choose the kind of life that you want.
That's liberal democracy.
That's where we all got there, thanks to Kant and people after Kant.
And you don't rank them, and you don't get stuck with any of them.
You can go from mood to mood.
You can go from one kind of life to another, from one God to another.
Even Helen has two major moods.
She has the runoff with Paris mood and then come back and live happily with her husband and kid and have nice banquets mood.
And that sounds good.
Yet what it looks like, the moral is get the most, have the most diversity.
It's beginning to sound familiar, doesn't it?
Have the most diversity.
All these different cultures are all these different moods, all these different lives available, and freely choose among them and even switch among them.
And don't try to rank them, because then you'll get stuck.
You'll be told that saints are good and sinners are bad, that monks and nuns are better than lovers and so forth.
Dante's got them, I was reading sort of Dante ranking.
Dante's got, even in paradise, the souls in paradise, you'll see, are ranked.
And so that you can, they go, so that they go from monks and nuns to lovers to theologians, to church warriors, to rulers, to contemplatives, to those who just stare at God.
And nothing about the pros and cons in Dante.
You'll see.
He knows which life is best.
But we don't believe that.
We think that there are all sorts of possible good lives, and that we shouldn't be ranking them.
And so what has he got that we haven't got?
I just have time to talk about it.
We like the idea that he wants to have respect for all ways of life.
That's the diversity side of him, the multicultural side of him.
And we'll see more about that when we get to Zeus, Athena, and Hermes.
They are the very multicultural side of Homer.
But there's something he's got.
I just want to leave you with that thought.
There's something he's got that we don't have.
And it comes from the fact that there are the gods.
And the gods are the attuning ones.
And the attuning ones are moods.
Now, you need to contrast what I'm going to call our laid-back, ironic relativism from Homer's relativism.
In our kind of relativism, all these different lives are equal.
All these different cultures are equal.
You have the right to do your thing, and I'll have the right to do my thing.
We don't have to take any of them as better.
We don't even have to take any of them as something that has any particular serious authority.
It's like being in a kind of smorgasbord of various uh cultural and personal possibilities.
That's then everybody then everybody should do their thing, and nobody should criticize anybody else doing their thing.
And there's no reason to do this thing rather than that thing.
You do, you know, whatever, as I said earlier.
And then and there's something missing in that.
What's missing in that is a kind of seriousness, a kind of what gives uh a life serious meaning.
It's too sort of experimental and open.
But you don't want to go to Dante where it's all settled and you know which life you should be leading, and you just better do it because that's what God, how God ranks things.
But so what's the middle ground?
Well, in a culture in which moods are taken very seriously, there is something like being pulled into these various worlds.
We saw that.
Helen does has that, and Achilles has that.
They're being pulled into these various worlds, and they are serious.
The interesting thing is when you're in the mood, you can't have a sort of laid-back, relativistic, well, whatever mood about it.
Helen can't laugh at her affair with Paris, Paris.
Nietzsche says that every culture has something about which you're not allowed to laugh.
That means something sacred.
That means something that has authority, that your free will and choice can't mess with.
And if you had a culture in which moods were as important as they are in the Homeric story, you could be culturally, a cultural relativist, but not a kind of laid-back, ironic, whatever relativist.
Because when you were in a mood, you wouldn't think that that mood was what everybody should be in.
That's Homer never would want you to think about.
But that mood has authority over you.
You can't freely choose it, and you can't get rid of it.
When you're drawn into it, you're in it.
And it is unquestionably meaningful.
And when you are, when it leaves you, like Helen gets tired of Paris, then it's just not meaningful anymore.
But the whole point is, what Homer has is these worlds, which are tied up with the tuning ones and the moods.
And he has a kind of seriousness and authority that we don't have.
The Enlightenment has sort of wiped out for us anything but our free, arbitrary choice which we make and unmake by our own willpower.
The idea that there is a power outside of us which grabs us, gives our life meaning, tells us what's important and not important, casts its makes everything show up in its light, and as it's talking about like Dave did, what opens up a certain bunch of possibilities as the important ones.
That's what Homer's got that we've lost.
That's what he's got that's better than total enlightenment relativism and total arbitrary choice.
Okay, time is up.
But I hope this is recorded somewhere.