And death the same way, and so forth.
So that's the next level.
Now, one of Cronus's children, no, sorry, not Cronus, who's who's the one who's having yeah, Cronus' children, are there three of them, Hera, which is a funny problem, which I'll mention later, not important, and the Cyclops, which is another funny problem, not very important, but we'll come back to them.
But Zeus, the head god, and the main epithet for Zeus is protector of strangers.
That should be a clue.
Strangers are people who come from other worlds, into your world.
And one of Zeus's jobs, it seems maybe his main job, it's the only thing, sometimes he's the wielder of the Thunderbolt, so forth.
But his main job seems to be to make sure that people from other worlds get treated with respect and helpful and so forth.
And everybody always says Zeus will be very angry at you if you violate, if you don't take good care of your guests, and very angry at you if you're a guest and you violate the special relation between them.
So, and now we have to jump to Athena at the top.
The interesting thing is, Athena is Zeus's favorite person.
And what they have in common is that she is a cross-world person, too.
She doesn't protect strangers.
She's able to help Odysse go from world to world and get in sync with each.
But no wonder she's Zeus's favorite.
That's another aspect of what you need and admire if you're a multi-world, if you have a multi-world culture and a multi-world understanding of being, you need somebody who protects the people going from culture to culture and helps them get in sync with each world they're in.
Yeah.
I couldn't hear you.
Say it again.
Or is she also in trouble?
No, neither.
I mean, he asks, is she a goddess that helps you go from mood to mood or different moods in different worlds?
She's not a, she's the other member, she's the un she's the mood of cool persons.
She never gets in any particular mood.
She cools people like Odyssey and Helen off when they're losing their wits from passionate openness.
And she does help Odysseus go from world to world, but not by getting into the right mood, but by getting in sync with all of them, each of them, in due course.
That is her job.
And that's why she's always there, helping him, except one place where he's totally outside of all the worlds.
And that's when he gets captured by the Cyclops, who's really a piece of nature, practically, a minimal world.
And then he's, interestingly enough, Athena can't help him, I think, and doesn't help him.
But in any kind of human, normal human world, she can help him get the feel for it.
And then, like James Bond, he is the best at all the things that people in that world do.
Their kind of games, connoisseur of their kind of food, and what else?
Anything, getting the names of all the people at the dinner party, in general, completely adaptable to whatever civilized world he's in.
Now, let's look at these others.
I jumped to Athena.
A really funny one is Hermes.
When I got Hermes figured out, then I thought I really understood something.
Hermes is the other favorite of Zeus, besides Athena.
Now, that is really weird.
We can see why Athena is his favorite.
She gets you in sync with each world.
What is Hermes up to?
His job is to be a thief.
He's a thief, and he's a person who leads people from world to world.
He leads the living to the dead.
He leads Odysseus away from Clyta, gets him away from Calypso and so forth.
And what's interesting is Hermes, I think, is, what does it mean to, why is it important that he's a thief?
He's a trickster, too.
I mean, you can see, again, there are things Odyssey likes.
Odyssey says when he gets home and finds that they've eaten all the cattle and depleted his stores, he'll go, he's a pirate.
He says, well, I'll go to other islands and I'll steal them.
I'll steal them.
He's a thief, too.
I don't know how to fit that into a mood story, but it's okay to be a thief.
But at an ontological level, what would it be to be a thief?
Well, it would be to take practices and ways of understanding things from one world and bring them over into another world.
And Hermes does that.
He does it when they're visiting Calypso.
He takes her world of drugs.
Is it Circe?
No, it's Circe.
He takes her world of drugs and uses it against her to cancel her drugs.
I mean, it's not a perfect example, and there may be others.
But I think Hermes is a very interesting something or other who is able to take things from one world and use them in another world.
I mean, nowadays, that would be somebody who discovered, for instance, the telephone.
I see somebody with a phone, and it reminds me.
When Graham Bell invented the telephone, he thought it was only for businesses.
He thought, who in the world wants this thing ringing in their homes?
And it took a while for that to happen.
And then, of course, now everyone wants one ringing in their pocket, even.
And Hermes would be the kind of person who would be able to see that, to see that you could transplant the practice of businesses using phones to families using phones for utterly different reasons, not to bid on stocks and hire people, but to keep track of where the kids are and so forth.
So anyway, Hermes, I think, is a kind of very interesting, possible cross-world way of being.
Now, the other ones are pretty straightforward, but I want to just mention them anyway.
Okay, so Aries, you don't hear all that much about Aries in here, but of course in the Iliad you do, those of you who know, because Aries is the god of ferocious war, of going completely berserk and killing hundreds of people in an afternoon when you're in the Aries, when Aries is shining on you.
Apollo, I've already said, is this kind of almost got theory already, because he's the lord of distance.
Hephaestus, you should know these things probably just to follow the book well, because all these gods coming and going.
Hephaestus is the craftsman.
He makes all the beautiful things.
And one of the wonderful things about these Homeric Greeks is they loved sort of craftsmen.
And, you know, Homer stops to comment on the tables, on the jugs, on the chairs, on the well-hung doors, on all the beautiful gold goblets and silver goblets and so forth.
And Hephaestus is the craftsman behind all that.
One of the funny things is, this is hard to figure out, and I may have to push things.
Hephaestus is married to Aphrodite, which is odd.
Hephaestus is lame and presumably a kind of rough character, he's a kind of blacksmith, among other things.
Why is he married to Aphrodite?
Well, the only thing I can think of is that you could have a culture in which the question is: how do you understand the erotic in your culture?
And if you understand it as, say, violent, I had some other example in mind, but I can't think of it now.
It doesn't matter.
There are all kinds of ways to understand the erotic.
But what I think the Greeks do is they understand the erotic tied up with the artificial.
That is, with beautiful clothes and beautiful jewelry.
The last thing we hear about Helen is that she in this her beautiful long robe.
She's lying next to Menelaus.
So there is some kind of connection between making beautiful things and ornaments and so forth and the woman who is the most sexy of all in the world, golden Aphrodite.
So anyway, they are linked for the Greeks, and I think that's really quite fascinating.
I don't know what Prosophany does.
If anybody has a theory about it, they can come and tell me.
And Dionysus, for some reason I don't understand.
Homer hasn't, Homer's not interested in Dionysus.
He hasn't made it into the Homeric pantheon.
I don't know why.
And Hera is a funny one.
Hera should be the goddess of domesticity.
That is a different kind of emotion, mood, and so forth.
But she isn't.
And it's tied up with the fact that Homer sort of plays, has to have a problem because she's both the sister of Zeus and the wife of Zeus.
And I don't know if that's all very well in Egypt at that time.
Marks married their brothers and sisters.
But it's not all right, I think, for Homer.
And so he doesn't know quite what to do with Hera.
And Hera shows up mostly just being jealous of Zeus running off with other women, which is not very illuminating as far as I can see.
And the Cyclops is a funny case, too.
He turns out to be the minimal form of human life.
Now, let me see.
Oh, you can look at this while I look at my notes to see if I've told you what I want to tell you.
So, finally, that in the fourth generation, that is, Cronus is the second, Zeus is the third, all these children of Zeus at the top, that's what I'm calling the fourth generation, those are the gods of the various Greek moods, the various Greek ways of life, the various worlds that you can get into.
As I put in that little box, they're the possible Greek worlds.
Now, let's see.
Ah, yeah, I have written something here.
Let's see.
Oh, yeah, it's the missing line about why is Hephaestus married to Aphrodite?
Well, different cultures interpret the erotic differently.
I said here, it could be thought of as aggressive, for instance.
It could be thought of as extremely receptive, for instance.
But to think of it as something that is a kind of can be made, is beautiful and could be made more beautiful, that seems to be the way Homer thinks about it.
Each of the gods of the different worlds get people in tune with different ways of acting, different situations by shining on them.
They make all these ways of life possible, in which they are the attuning ones, remember.
And the only thing to say finally is the person who's interested who makes all these attunings possible is Athena and Hermes.
That's why they're the favorite children of Zeus, because it's polytheism, but somehow it values the plurality of worlds.
So, Zeus and Athena and Hermes are the expression of that.
I think it's funny that people never talk about that, and maybe there's some other way of understanding it, but I don't see any other way.
The way Zeus, Protector of Strangers, links with Athena cross-world and Hermes.
Does anybody want to say anything?
The time is almost up, but we've got three minutes to get one reaction.
Yeah, Beatrice.
Also interesting that both Aphrodite and the final Really?
Huh.
Oh, yeah, she comes in from the ocean, doesn't she?
From the blood of castrated whoever, Kronos.
And Hephaestus, who's he?
I see.
Well, that's interesting.
I I'll just repeat it for those who didn't hear it.
It's interesting that the two puzzling ones that I'm making up interesting to hope interesting stories about, namely Hephaestus and Aphrodite, are neither one of them Zeus' children.
They and therefore they must have some special powers, but I don't know what it is.
We should think about it.
Okay, that's it.
We'll go back to again to on on Thursday.
Read read up to page two oh six for Thursday.