We got up to Father Mapple, remember?
And we can't go back over.
I'll go in the super fast review.
We talked about lots of things, mainly the opposition between the land and the sea, and how the land was for what was solid and marked off, and the sea is indefinite.
We talked about Balkington, who only can live at sea.
He can't stand the slavish land.
He always immediately leaves on another boat.
And he stands in the howling gale of the infinite.
That is, he stands out in the unmarked nowhere and then apparently falls off the boat.
So Balkington is not a little, he's sort of heroic nihilism, but he's not a form of life.
Uh-oh, there's too much wind now.
Yeah, why don't we close this one, David?
It's easier.
They're just a rock.
Yeah, ah, thanks.
Okay, so those are the two main things we've talked about.
Now, and we were ready to talk about Father Mapple as another version of how to deal with the uncertainty, indefiniteness, non-representableness of life and meaning.
And so we turn to him, which is on page 36 of this rare book.
And I'll read you things carefully.
Okay, we're in chapter 8, page 36, a little below the middle of the page, about Mapple.
He's also a sea person.
He had been a sailor and a harpooner in his youth for many years past, but for many years past had dedicated his life to the ministry.
So the interesting question is: is there a kind of way of having a land at sea, having something definite that gives meaning to your life, even though you're not on the land where the roles and the practices and the institutions and all that for giving meaning are, in effect, sort of boringly and slavishly and vainly settled?
Is there any third possibility?
Something definite and out in the indefinite.
And there is.
And he tells it as a story about Jonah.
On page 40, it starts.
The important thing about Jonah is, one, that he got swallowed up by a whale, so it's a natural thing to be talking about as these sailors are about to leave for a whale hunting voyage.
But the reason he got swallowed up is what's interesting.
On 40, Father Maple says, shipmates, and then he goes on.
I just start with shipmates because, again, I want to say he's a sea person.
And Melville wants to make that clear.
But he says, about a third of the way down on page 40, we're in chapter 9.
But what it is, see, but what is this lesson that the book of Jonah teaches?
Shipmates, it is a two-strand lesson, a lesson to us all as sinful men, and a lesson to me as a pilot of the living God.
We don't know yet what that means, but he says more.
As with all sinners among men, the sin of this son of Amate, that's Jonah, was in his willful disobedience of the command of God.
Never mind now what that command was or how conveyed, which he found a hard command.
Already he's telling you that God had a vocation for Jonah, a job, a plan of what the point of Jonah's life was.
And he says, don't worry about how Jonah found out what his calling was.
Don't even matter what his calling was, that he had a calling and that it was hard is all that we need to know.
And he says, God oftener commands us than endeavors to persuade.
And if we obey God, we must disobey ourselves.
And it is in this disobeying ourselves wherein the hardness of obeying God consists.
That means that your vocation is not going to fit easily with the rest of your life, with your fan having a family, for instance.
Jesus says every once in a while, I don't have any mothers and brothers and sisters when they come and say, What about your family?
Because he's on his mission.
In general, your vocation is going to require you to give up some of the things you desire.
It doesn't matter what you want.
This is what you need.
You need to do what this command says you need to do.
Think of Ferrara, we have all sorts of examples.
Think of Gandhi or Martin Luther King, the kind of people who have a command and are willing to sacrifice everything that they might like, including finally their lives, to do it.
That's the kind of person, an issue, that Jonah raises.
So now we have to see what Father Mapple makes of that.
So it looks like every person is called to some vocation.
And it looks like already we're getting an extreme Protestant kind of religion.
It looked utterly different than Dante losing his identity and getting swept up in the will that moves the sun and the other stars and losing his commitment to politics in Florence and Beatrice, all in the light of this absolutely satisfying, completely impersonal supreme being.
That's the extreme version of the Catholic view.
The Protestant view, which I mention every once in a while, reaches its extreme in Kierkegaard, is that each person has their own unique vocation.
It starts, I presume, with Luther saying that every man is a Pope.
You don't need any intermediate things, any intermediate people or between you and God.
God has a particular plan for you, and you can only be an individual and have an identity if you take on that command.
That's what it is.
And Kierkegaard calls that subjective truth.
That means it isn't an objective fact, for instance, that Beatrice is adorable and worth sacrificing your life.
What is happening?
Osabundo is gone icy.
Well, how are we going to deal with that?
Well, maybe we can't.
I know one way we can deal with it.
We have to close the door.
Sorry.
Thanks, Dad.
That's all kinds of adventures.
So there's no objective truth that Martin Luther King should give his life for equality for African Americans.
There's no reason why the knight should die for his lady.
It's a subjective truth.
That is, it's true insofar as you totally commit yourself to it.
Beatrice being adorable and savior totally depends on Dante's commitment.
If Dante wasn't committed to Beatrice being adorable, she wouldn't be his Savior, and she wouldn't be adorable.
And it's that kind of subjective truth that Mapple is on to.
On 47, I read more.
This is all in the same chapter.
He says, Jonah did the Almighty's bidding.
And what was that, shipmates?
To preach the truth in the face of falsehood.
That was it.
I don't find that, that's not what I wanted to read.
That does not cast any light on my, doesn't disagree with me.
That's just his vocation.
So here he is on the top of 47.
Delight is to him a far, far upward and inward delight, who against the proud gods and commodores of this earth ever stands forth his own inexorable self.
That is, who has his own identity, who does his own thing, whether it be romantic love or some cause, or you could do it even by dedicating your life to science.
But it has to be, science is a little funny because it has to be something that has the quality it has only as long as and because you have totally devoted your life to it.
I don't know.
I think science can't be a subjective truth now that I think about it.
It's a funny one.
You can certainly devote your life to it, but it doesn't depend on your devoting your life to it.
Science doesn't care.
That's an interesting problem to think about.
Kierkegaard certainly thinks that science is done from a disinterested point of view, and that this kind of commitment is the ultimately personal, interested point of view.
So don't think about science in there.
So, what's happening there in Mapple?
He says, One more, I'll read you one more.
Delight to him who gives no quarter in the truth and kills, burns, and destroys all sin, though he pluck it out from under the robes of senators and judges.
Delight, top gallant delight to him who acknowledges no law or Lord, but the Lord is God and is only a patriot to heaven.
And no law, and his God doesn't give you any ethical principles, any universal principles.
This God just tells you what you have to be committed to.
And since it's subjective, and since it has, in Schiffegaard's language, no objective validity, it makes no sense to go around proselytizing, proselytizing for it.
Sort of getting everybody to adore Beatrice wouldn't make much sense.
In fact, it would show, Kierkegaard talks about how Don Quixote tries to get everybody to admit that Dulcinea, this peasant girl that Don Quixote in his craziness has taken to be his lady, is the, and she just a normal, plain old peasant girl, but he wants them to swear that she is the most beautiful and lovable lady in the world because he won't, it won't, it won't be true unless he gets it sort of objectively accepted.
That's the wrong way to think about it.
That she'll be adorable if he adores her, and that's all you need.
But that's also very unsettling because that means there's no foundation for this commitment.
You just get this calling.
It's an experience.
It's sort of, I guess, like a mood, a god calling you, except whereas the moods of the gods come and go.
Aphrodite shrines on Helen for a while, and then she stops shining on Helen, and then Helen gets bored, but with Paris.
But this is once in a lifetime for your whole life and with your whole life kind of commitment, with nothing to back it up, but that you have the experience that it's your commitment.
Kierkegaard calls that starting to emphasize the ungroundedness of it, that it's like swimming over 40,000 fathoms, which is interesting because there it is.
Even Kierkegaard, who has necessarily not read Moby Dick, which was written the same year as Karen Trembling, the book of his that everybody reads, Kierkegaard also has this ocean picture of this bottomlessness of this kind of commitment.
And the question only left is, I mean, and there is Melville inventing in a way.
I'm putting a lot more into it than he actually says, but it's in here.
He's inventing a Protestant Kierkegaardian, not the infallible Presbyterian church, which is for every which tries to be true for everybody, a special individual truth, and the riskiness of it is all in there.
And the question is, Ishmael can invent it.
What does Ishmael think about it?
What does Melville is Melville a Kierkegaardian?
Is this the answer to the problem of how to get meaning and keep the indefiniteness of the sea and not the slavish banality, everybody doing the same thing, following some job or other and so forth, which is the land?
Well, it is an answer.
It's an interesting Kierkegaardian answer, but it's not Melville's answer.
And he gives you his judgment on it in a funny way.
Right, the next chapter 10 begins.
Returning to the Spouter Inn from the chapel, I found Queque there quite alone.
He had left the chapel before the benediction sometime.
In other words, Quequeg, who is in a certain way Melville's hero of strange other sense of religiousness and the sacred, Quequeg's walked out on Father Mappel.
And Ishmael sat through it, but he doesn't seem to be affected by it.
It's just not Melville's answer.
Remember, I mean, it's no secret.
I wouldn't be teaching this book at the end of the course.
I'd love to teach the book at the end of any course because it's the greatest book ever, greatest American novel anyway.
But it goes in this course because Melville is a polytheist.
It just isn't clear yet.
But if you were a polytheist, you would walk out of such a thing that said, well, there's one God and He has one mission for you.
And it's sort of multiple monotheism.
That, I mean, it covers your whole world for your whole life and tells you what's meaningful and what's not.
You don't go around trying to convert other people to it.
And you don't go around, but you don't go around either questioning it.
It gives you a world.
It gives you one unified, lasting world to find your vocation.
And that's not open enough.
And that's a Melville.
You miss a lot of religions and a lot of sacred if you're going to get a Kierkegaardian vocation.
I think it's pretty impressive.
And when I teach Kierkegaard, I fight for it altogether.
But it's not in this book.
It just comes and goes like Balkington's heroic nihilism comes and goes.
Melville is good at making up exactly the kind of things that people will understand, say, roughly 50 years later.
Well, yeah, Nietzschean things like Balkington, or things that are exactly contemporary, like Kierkegaardian things going on in Denmark.
But Melville makes them up, and he doesn't accept them.
So where are we?
Well, Ishmael wants something that allows him to take seriously Quequeg's religion, Yo-Yo 2, and any other religion, as you'll see in the book that he visits.
He thinks that Christianity is too narrow, and it's irrelevant to his problem.
And Yo-Yo knows it's irrelevant.
On 84, which is the end of chapter 17, there's this strange thing where it turns out, did I say Yo-Yo?
I mean Kwequeg knows what, that there's, Quequeg's a funny figure.
Quique is, as you'll have, strictly in his religion.
I mean, he worships Yo-Yo, and that's his God, and he does the holidays for that God.
And he's not interested in converting anybody to that.
And that's good from Melville's point of view.
But he's also not interested in anybody else's religion or their sense of the sacred and how he might get in tune with that.
And in a way, Quiqueg is like Jews, like Hebrews, who don't, Jews now, who don't want to are not interested in converting anybody to their religion.
It's their particular relation to God and their particular tradition.
And Melville likes that, but it's still too confining for him.
Here's the discussion of it on 84.
He was talking to Quiqueg about his Ramadan, and he was fasting so much, and he was telling him he didn't have to do that.
And then he says, I don't think that my remarks about religion made much impression on Queque, because in the first place, he somehow seemed dull of hearing on that important subject, unless considered from his own point of view.
That is, he's not interested in other religions.
And in the second place, he did not more than one-third understand me, couch my ideas as simply as I would.
And finally, he no longer thought he no doubt thought he knew a good deal more about the true religion than I did.
I don't understand that exactly about the true religion.
I mean, it's true that it's the right religion for Queque, but he does have an openness to other religions.
Not that he wants to change his religion for them, but even unlike, I guess, the Jews, Cuiqueg, is ready to learn from other religions.
I'll read you that in a minute.
But he does stick to his religion.
He understands that's the true religion.
He looked at me with a sort of, but not of true religion, you know, to go out and proselytize.
That's the important thing.
Not of true religion because it's true, everybody ought to believe it.
It's true for him and his people.
He looked at me with a sort of condescending concern and compassion, as though he thought it a great pity that such a sensible young man should be so hopelessly lost to evangelical pagan piety, which is a funny mouthful of words here.
But evangelical, not in the sense of going out and converting.
So I don't know why that evangelical.
What does evangelical mean, David?
Ah, you think so?
Let's try that.
That's good, because I never understood this sentence.
Let's try it that way.
A sensible young man should be hopelessly lost.
I see, not lost because he has fallen into evangelical pagan from his point of view.
Ishmael, you like that.
You seem sure about that.
I see, well, I hope that's right, that that better be right.
But I never thought of it that way.
So he's lost to it.
I see it too as a kind of pun.
I read this as he doesn't get it.
But then that would mean he doesn't get Quequeg's religion.
And Kwequeg wouldn't refer to his religion as evangelical pagan piety.
So he must be lost to it in the sense that he's fallen into it.
That's the sense of loss.
I mean, see, there are two ways of being lost to something: being oblivious of it and being taken in by it.
And the question is, what's Quequeg thinking?
He's thinking that Ishmael has been taken in by what, from Quequeg's point of view, is evangelical pagan piety.
That's your view.
I like that.
You're Protestant.
Does that mean that it's out to convert people?
Is that a necessary part of evangelism?
That's what I thought.
If you don't think it was the how about 1850 when this I'm not convinced, by the way, you're reading.
The more I think about it, the more I think that the idea that Quequeg understands enough to understand.
Wait, I'm stumped.
Let's have.
Yes, somebody has a helpful suggestion?
He's very thinking Ishmael is conversion.
Not why you're hoping that he's not meeting with apostles, but is that it?
That a sensible young man, that is an Ishmael, should be lost to evangelical pagan piety.
Let me just think.
What is evangelical?
Quiqueg is thinking it.
So it doesn't mean, according to David, that he's deaf to Quequeg's religion.
That would be the wrong way to read it.
That's what Quequeg is saying.
He's calling Ishmael a pagan.
That's about what I've read about pages.
Okay, I'm going to try it once more.
I want it to come out that way.
It just feels, doesn't work very well for me.
He looked at me with a sort of condescending concern and compassion as though he thought it a great pity that a sensible young man should be so hopelessly lost to evangelical pagan piety.
So it had been so taken in by Christianity, is how you read it, which is evangelical pagan piety.
So, well, everybody should come and tell me in office hours what you think.
Taken, I mean, I'm writing down David's version, taken in by Christianity, i.e., evangelical pagan piety.
Okay, I don't know.
But I, I mean, if that isn't, if that isn't the right reading, I don't know what is.
That's because then the only alternative would be that Kleeque refers to himself as, well, there's a third possibility, which is how I've always read it.
Kleequeg feet Ishmael has lost to, no, I don't know.
I stop.
I think I like your way.
I'm going to stick to your way until I, if I can.
I haven't got out.
I mean, that's the best way to read it.
Okay.
Unless anybody else has another opinion, I'm going to go on.
So it looks like Kleeque doesn't buy it.
That's the important thing.
And that, remember, I said it's interesting that he's open to other religions.
Openness to the sacred.
I mean, I just give you all the guidelines I can in this very, very deep and difficult book.
Ishmael is just totally open to every possible form of religion, every possible form of the sacred, unless it's closed, as Presbyterian is, and philosophy is, according to him.
But he's for total openness.
And it goes with his, and keep your eyes open for this, total moodiness.
He's capable of getting in tune with all sorts of religions, and he's certainly capable of getting in all sorts of moods, totally contradictory moods, and he knows it, and he's proud of it.
And that's so that, and so Queque had better not be limited to totally ignoring all other religions because he thinks his is the right one for him and his people.
And he doesn't.
He isn't, because on 84 you find out that, and I think it's 84, that Kweekweg has tried to get something out of Christianity.
Now, that's what I was reading, is on 84, so I've got to go on.
Where is it?
55.
55, which is the end of chapter 12.
No, 54, near the end of chapter 12.
At bottom, so Kwequeg told me, he was actuated by a profound desire to learn among the Christians the arts whereby to make his people happier than they were, and more than that, better than they were.
But alas, the practices of whalemen soon convinced him that even Christians could be both miserable and wicked, infinitely more so than all his father's heathens.
And so he tries to cross-appropriate, to use that term.
Remember from the Odyssey where Hermes takes the drugs from Circe and gives them to Odysseus to use against her.
So he's trying to pick up something interesting from the practices of Christianity that he can use in his tradition and in his religion, but he can't find anything because it's Christianity.
But he's open to other possible religions.
That makes him not an evangelical person, where the evangelical person, as I'm understanding it, and I don't know, we don't know when it became that way, but it means now that you believe there's one true religion, and for everybody's own good, you're going to convert them to that one.
And Kuique certainly doesn't have that view.
Okay, so Quiqued's interesting, and he's the nearest one to Ishmael's own kind of relation to religion.
Let me go through some of the other, I mean, the alternatives that we've talked about to sort of sum them up.
I say in my notes, but I wonder now after what I've been saying and what I've been hearing, that whether this is right.
I say here, I think Quiqued represents a kind of pagan, non-onto-theological kind of monotheism, sort of like Aeschylus, where there are these gods, these various forces.
But I don't even, I don't see any evidence for that.
Scratch that.
I think that there's, I mean, why in Edism is if he sees that there are two religious forces and sees that they are both important and have to be taken account of, and all the things that Aeschylus does.
No, I think he's not doing that.
I think he's just, as I say, just open to other religions, but not open to sharing them, just open to seeing if he can learn anything from them.
He wants the religion that's right for him and his people, and he'll leave another religion right for other people and their traditions.
And he thinks that's Ishmael thinks that's good, but not his way.
I wrote here: Kwequeg believes in idols, but they are really gods for him.
But he doesn't go out and seek converts.
It isn't gods for everybody.
And that Ishmael is ready to worship Kwequeg's God isn't Ishmael's idea.
Remember, it's Kwequeg's idea.
Ishmael joins him, volunteers to join him.
Yeah.
Wait a second.
Boy, when the microphone is on, it's great to call.
Go ahead.
Believe it or not, I can't hear you from back here.
I'll come and hear you up here.
Go ahead.
Do you still, do you believe that Kwequeg still wants to learn from other religions?
Or do you think that he's kind of given up athletic experience with Christianity?
Right.
You know, a good question.
Do I think that Kwequeg wants to learn from other religions, or do you think he's given up?
Well, I think he's given up on Christianity.
But I don't think that means that he would give up on the weird religion that worships the whale skeleton that later comes in.
He doesn't go there.
I mean, so we don't see Quequeg visiting any other religions, but I don't see any evidence that he's given up hopes of that somewhere he could learn something that could help his people.
But he certainly thinks that from a kind of religion that claims to be the truth for everybody, he doesn't think he's going to learn anything from that religion.
You don't see much.
Remember, I said one of the odd features of the book is Queque plays such a big role before they get on the boat.
All of this is before they've gotten on the Pequot.
Once they set out in search of the whale, there's only a few scenes, crucial ones, but very few where Quequeg ever shows up again.
And that's odd, but that's, I think, sort of psychologically interesting, but I don't think it's got any important philosophical significance.
Okay, now I want to go back to something else and rather different.
This question of attitudes toward religion, just to remember, whether they are like Baltington, like Maple, like Queque, or like Christians, that's an interesting issue, and it runs through the whole book.
But there's a more interesting issue for sure, and that is the whale and the sea in their boundlessness.
That special non-representableness, which Melville holds is the sort of deeper truth about reality.
You can only see it in the dark.
But if you see it, I haven't proved this yet in the book, but you'll see as we go.
I mean, if you have a sense of that, then you're open to all moods and the sacred.
It's losing track of the ocean, of the non-representable and the bottomless and so.
It narrows your openness to reality.
But the whale, now, so we got the boundless sea.
And remember, and all of this, you look puzzled, and you rightly look puzzled.
I'm giving you sort of the same experience you'd have if you read the book.
You don't know why.
For instance, when I was reviewing what we said last time, I knew I forgot something important, namely the picture of the whale.
So we're going back to the picture of the whale, which you couldn't figure out what it was.
It was all dark and all mysterious, and it solicited all kinds of interpretations, and it was enough to make a nerve, drive a nervous man crazy.
That is, if you really wanted clarity and ambiguity, this picture would not be one you'd want to be having in your living room.
And in the end, Melville never says that it's a picture of a whale.
He just says that's finally his theory.
That's the theory that worked best.
He'll always tell you his views as interpretations, because he thinks all you've ever got are interpretations.
That's exactly the thesis that Nietzsche.
But Melville already has it.
But anyway, his interpretation of the picture was that it was a picture of the whale in its non-picturableness.
That's what he tells you when he tells you this fascinating story.
And now I'm going to follow that up.
But I want to remind you from last time on page Roman numeral 35, right at the beginning, the extracts, of the connection between the whale as unrepresentable and the sea as unrepresentable.
We haven't argued the whale is unrepresentable at all.
All we've argued so far is the sea.
So here, but we've got this verse to go on.
Oh, the rare old whale amid storm and gale in his ocean home will be a giant in might where might is right and king of the boundless sea.
So now the question is: is he, the whale, it, also unrepresentable and open to lots of interpretations, none of which ever seem settled and which don't add up to any one.
Well, that's what I'm going to talk about for a while.
And I'm going to jump all over the book because I just have to do it.
It doesn't affect where you are when you're reading it and the plot.
So we go on.
The whale, it turns out, can't be pictured or described at all.
So the whale is the sort of paradigm, the representation, the, I would say, personification if it was a person, the mammothation of the unbounded.
So let's look at that.
On 297, way back in chapter 68, about five, six paragraphs in, towards the bottom of 297, he says, in life, the visible surface of the sperm whale, it's only the sperm whale all the time when he says the whale.
The sperm whale is not the least among the many marvels he presents.
Almost invariably, it is all over, obliquely crossed and recrossed with numberless straight marks in thick arrays, something like those in the finest Italian line engravings.
Then, skipping a little, these are hieroglyphical.
That is, if you call those mysterious ciphers on the walls of pyramids hieroglyphics, then that is the proper word to use in the present connection.
By my retentive memory of the hieroglyphics upon one sperm whale in particular, I was much struck with a plate representing the old Indian characters chiseled on the famous hieroglyphic palisades on the banks of the upper Mississippi.
Like those mystic rocks, too, the mystic marked whale remains undecipherable.
That's going to be the theme.
It's going to almost be boring if it weren't that he has endless interesting, sort of crazy varieties of the indecipherable.
So we go from that indecipherable to the tail of the whale.
Believe it or not, the tail of the whale isn't even guess how that could be.
On page 366, the end of chapter 86, you hear: The more I consider this mighty tale, the more I do deplore my inability to express it.
At times, there are gestures in it, which, though they would well grace the hand of man, remain wholly inexplicable.
Nor are there wanting other motions of the whale in his general body, full of strangeness and unaccountable to his most experienced assailant.
Direct him now, oh, sorry, dissect him now as I may.
I may but go skin deep.
I know him not and never will.
But if I know not even the tail of this whale, how understand his head?
Much more, how comprehend his face, when face he has none.
And now we need a little bit of background before I read the rest of this.
Melville is about to make a funny move with a famous part of Exodus 33 of the Hebrew Bible, where I quote from the Bible now: Moses said, I pray thee, show me thy glory.
But God said, Thou cannot see my face, for man shall not see me and live.
And the Lord said, Behold, I will cover you with my hand until I have passed by.
And then I will take away my hand, and you will see my back, that my face shall not be seen.
And now he says, Melville, that the whale seems to have no face.
And he seems to say, Thou shalt see my back parts, my tail, he seems to say, that my face shall not be seen.
And Melville goes on, but I cannot completely make out his back parts.
And hint what he will about his face, I say again, he has no face.
So there you get the same story again.
And on 258, something else, some other version.
What is that?
Nothing is on 258.
No, that's because I'm on 350.
Here we are.
Okay, another, what are we getting?
We're getting, remember, that there's a dimension of reality which is in this book represented by or symbolized, neither of those are good words, which you don't want to say represented because it's unrepresentable.
You don't want to say symbolized.
Melville doesn't like symbols for reasons I'll talk about sometime.
There are aspects of reality which in this book, reality shows forth in the sea, in the ocean, and in the whale.
And he's talking about that aspect, namely the deepest truth about reality, that it can't be symbolized, described, understood, deciphered, and represented.
I'm just telling you so we don't get lost.
On 258, chapter 56, that is, he says, the living whale in his full majesty and significance is only to be seen at sea and in unfathomable waters and floats the vast bulk of him out of sight.
This is 258, about a third of the way down.
Like a launched line of battleship.
And out of that element, it is this thing.
And out of that element, we're talking about the whale.
It is a thing eternally impossible for mortal man to host him bodily into the air so as to preserve all his mighty swells and undulations.
That is, if he's in the water, you can't see him very clearly.
And if you hoist it out of the water, it just goes sort of droopy and globby and doesn't give you the shape the whale has when all those tons of whale meat are organized and floating around.
So that's another one of those.
So the sort of joke is, in a way, or a joke, is when you go back to the painting and the spouter in, and you say the painting is a mysterious blur, and then you say, well, my theory is it's a sperm whale, as if somehow now you've explained anything.
But when you study the sperm whale, it turns out the sperm whale is intrinsically a kind of blur.
There's no way to get clear about how it looks, how it looks when it comes out of the water, how it looks when you look at its face, and so because it hasn't any.
So Melville comes to the conclusion, and this is on top of 259.
For all these reasons, then, any way you may look at it, you must needs conclude that the great Leviathan is that one creature in the world which must remain unpainted to the last.
So the painting didn't succeed.
The one portrait, true, one portrait may hit the mark much nearer than another, but none can hit it with any very considerable degree of exactness.
So there is no earthly way of finding out precisely what the whale really looks like.
That's crucial for him.
I never noticed that it's unpainted.
That sort of nicely contradicts the non-painting of the non-understandable whale from the beginning.
Okay.
And another way to put it is: there's no way the whale actually looks.
He is, quote, as indefinite.
So he is as indefinite as God.
We give her that phrase back from Balkington might be one way of summing it.
Of course, not that there is any God.
God is the indefinite.
Yeah.
Huh?
It's a book that's the classifying whale classification.
Gee, that's a good one.
I don't see it yet.
On page 125, second paragraph.
Yeah?
It said to cla aha.
Yes, to classify of the conditions of chaos.
Okay, that's good.
Yes, I have to add that to my list.
Page 125, whale as chaos.
And another thing that comes out of the satology is that, of course, science can't understand and explain the whale either.
And Moby Dick is and Ishmael is clear about that.
In fact, I thought it was in what I was going to read.
And I haven't read it.
I wonder what happened to it.
Just a second.
He's sure that science can really capture it because he thinks science really can't capture anything in its completeness, but particularly not the whale.
Wonder where he is.
Might be back in those opening extracts.
Let's see, does he tell us anything about them?
Not really.
They're just promiscuously gathered things.
Well, keep your eye open as you read it, and I will too.
I know he thinks that science can't, and of course, if we can't grasp the whale and it doesn't have a face and you can't get it out of the water and you can't understand its tail and all that, science isn't going to be able to fit it neatly into any categories according to him.
So I want to see if anybody finds it, let me know.
I think I must have just skipped it when I was writing these notes.
Okay.
So, and because it's indefinite, and this is very important, the whale keeps open the possibility, in fact, it's really the necessity of endless interpretation.
If you could get the ultimate reality nailed down, then that would be the end of interpretation.
But if reality in the ocean, in the whale, which is the personification of the ocean, the paradigm of the ocean, can't be described, then that keeps interpretation on.
It makes interpretation something that's going to have to happen all the time, and it's all that can happen.
There's a chapter about interpretation where Melville says it in so many words that everyone has their own perspective on reality.
It's their interpretation.
And all there are is interpretations.
But he hasn't said it yet.
But I'm sure you'll recognize it when you get there.
Okay.
All attempts to, even scientific drawings are all wrong, I write here, but I don't give any page reference.
That must be, that's bizarre.
Let's try 501.
There's a page reference running around loose.
I don't think that's it.
Not at all, not at all.
So I've got a claim that I haven't backed up.
But it's even scientific.
I mean, he says in so many words that scientific drawings are all wrong.
Because whenever you hoist the whale enough far out of the water to be able to draw it, you already have lost its true shape.
Okay.
And Ishmael finds all that sublime, but you can't you can't portray it.
Sublime, remember, means it's beyond any understanding and representation.
Here's another one, but it isn't the one that we're looking for.
438.
How vain and foolish then, thought I, for timid untraveled man to try to comprehend aright this wondrous whale by merely pouring over his dead attenuated skeleton, stretched in this peaceful wood.
No, only in the heart of the quickest perils, only when within the eddying of his angry flukes, only on the profound, unbounded sea, can a fully invested whale be truly livingly found out.
Well, that doesn't surprise us.
It isn't the science quote.
It's just the general quote again.
Insofar as you can get any understanding of the whale at all, that says, you can't do it by objectively standing back and detachedly looking at the whale.
By being totally involved in a sort of life and death struggle with the whale, you come to understand about as much of what this indefinite chaotic power is as you can understand.
Yeah.
What I just read is chapter 103, three paragraphs from the end.
How vain and foolish it begins.
Okay.
Now, I was not wanting to get beyond your reading, but I have to because time is short for talking about Moby Dick, and I have to begin, maybe even finish, talking about something which those of you, those few of you who have the book, may not have read yet, but it is such a murky thing that it won't help, it won't hurt to talk about it before you read it.
And then you can check out what I'm saying when you do read it.
And it fits so perfectly in with what I'm saying.
Because the ocean is the unbounded.
The whale is the king of the sea, the paradigm of the unbounded, and we now, and unrepresentable, I hope I've convinced you of that.
Now, what would be even more unrepresentable and unbounded than the ocean and the sperm whale?
This is an easy question if you just sort of think about the book.
How about a white whale?
A whale that is just blank.
Well, that's the next stage.
Moby Dick isn't just any old sperm whale.
Moby Dick is the paradigm of sperm whale because Moby Dick is white.
And so I don't think he has any markings on his tail and so forth.
He's even more indefinite.
So now we have to start talking about whiteness.
And there is a chapter on whiteness, chapter 42, which most people, as far as I know, have ignored in all their interpretations, Freudian, political, American, ecological, and yet it is the chapter that Melville says is the key to it all.
It's, in a sense, the most important chapter in the book.
On my interpretation, it is, and I can explain why it is and has to be, given the way this whole book is laid out, this very interesting, very, what does he say, wicked understanding of reality that the book is.
It's a wicked understanding of reality because it says that nothing is going to be able to give you any definite answer about the meaning of reality.
It's all interpretations.
And even if you came along and said, aha, but this is how the whale looks, and this is how the ocean is, and this is what reality is, Meldo would say, oh, that's good, that's terrific.
Let's add it to our list of interpretations.
He's got a system in which it's in principle impossible for you to come up with anything but, from his point of view, from his interpretation, another interpretation.
And that's all going on in the Whiteness chapter.
And you'll see, and that's why it turns out to be the, for him, the important chapter.
It's the key chapter of the book.
And he says that he hasn't explained it yet, at this point in the book, and of course he never will.
He begins the chapter, what the white whale was to Ahab has been hinted.
And Ahab, what the white whale is to Ahab is infuriating because Ahab wants clarity and he wants control and he wants an answer and he wants to understand what's going on.
He's the guy driven crazy by the picture, the kind of person driven crazy by the picture.
So, but what at times he was to me as yet remains unsaid.
As I was rereading that today for the who knows how many times, I see how sort of unconsciously, but nonetheless consistently Melville never takes a stand on anything.
When he says about the picture that it's his theory that it's a whale back in the end, that's what he should say.
And here he says, what at times he was for me remains unsaid.
That is, this is one of the ways.
This is like a mood.
When I'm in a certain mood, in a certain attunement, this is what the whale is for me.
That the whale means something specific to Melville, has one interpretation, and he's got it.
That's just what he's alien.
So even his story about the whale as indefinite as God and as totally undecipherable and all that is a mood, is an interpretation.
But now we're going to get what at times, and it turns out the only time that he tells you about, and then really the most important time, I'm sure, what the whale is to him.
And now, how's he going to do it?
Well, he's got to talk about whiteness.
There was another thought or nameless horror concerning him, the whale, which at times in its intensity completely overpowered all the rest.
And yet so mystical and well-nigh inethable was it that I almost despair of putting it into comprehensible form.
This is 181.
It's the beginning of chapter 42, The Whiteness of the Whale.
He says, but how can I hope to explain myself here?
And now the crucial thing, and yet, in some dim, random way, explain myself, I must, else all these chapters might be naught.
I mean, there's something, I've got to get you to understand, he's saying, what the whiteness of the whale means, even though I can hardly understand it myself.
Because if you can't understand what the whiteness of the whale means, you can't understand the book.
You can't understand Moby Dick, and so you can't understand the book.
Now, in a certain way, you can understand them, but just the kind of non-understanding that the whiteness is is what's important.
And so he starts to worry about what is whiteness.
And he does a brilliant sort of essay on whiteness for the rest of the chapter.
He starts out saying that whiteness is a kind of horrible thing.
And he says on 182, which is the middle of the page, same chapter all the time.
In the innermost idea of this hue, that is whiteness, which strikes, well, now I better go back a little.
Well, he's giving you a whole list of associations with white.
The white bull, the white dog, the priest's robes, the vision of St.
John had a white robe, and so forth and so forth.
And there's an association with white with what is sweet, honorable, and sublime.
He doesn't believe that.
He said, well, maybe sublime.
He says, yet there lurks an elusive something in the innermost idea of this hue, which strikes more a panic to the soul than that redness which affrights in blood.
So rather than any color and anything frightening, there's something worse.
White is panic making.
He can go into something very important there.
He wants to make it, it's worse than frighten.
Frightening is something threatening you in some particular way that you're going to hurt you or make you lose something or make you hurt somebody you care about.
All that is frightening.
Panic is this sort of total loss of everything, but not as specific, but just sort of total panic is sort of fear, is not even fear of everything.
It's something stronger than that.
It's, I just can't say anything more.
It's just panic.
And he tries to pin it down.
So he's talking about maybe, he tries to go first by pinning it down maybe to the ultimate fear.
Maybe the panic is really the ultimate fear, namely the fear of death.
Because after all, he says on 185, death rides a white horse.
Yea, while these terrors seize us, let us add that even the king of terrors, when personified, rides on a pallid horse.
But he's still in the fear business.
He really hasn't got it yet.
This is all threats to human being and human life.
And fear is not what he's after.
There is what he calls a nameless dread, which comes out of this whiteness.
Dread is like the panic, maybe, or even more weird.
So he goes on and talks about the getting us beyond the fearful on the middle of 185.
Can we then, by the citation of some of those instances wherein this thing of whiteness, though for the time either wholly or in part stripped of all direct associations, calculated to impart to it aught fearful, but nevertheless is found to exert over us the same sorcery, however modified, so no matter how you try to get the fearfulness out of it, it still got it.
Can we thus hope to light upon some chance clue to conduct us to the hidden cause we seek?
So is there something about the whiteness that goes beyond any kind of fear?
And then he thinks he finally got it on page 188.
Remember, it's not some particular threat coming at you in some particular direction.
It's not even the super threat of death.
It's something more than that.
It's something, let's call it dread, because it doesn't seem to be fear.
And now he tells you 188 what it is.
It's pretty strange, two-thirds of the way down.
And he does it in terms of questions.
He doesn't give you the answer, not milk.
Is it that by its indefiniteness, it shadows forth the heartless voids and immensities of the universe and stabs us from behind with the thought of annihilation when beholding the white depths of the Milky Way?
That's getting close.
That's still not it.
But its indefiniteness is now in there, which is important.
The whiteness is not any particular color.
And the whole sort of frightfulness of the universe is in there.
Pascal said he was the first to get the news that the universe was infinite.
I mean, the first generation of people.
And he said it terrified him.
But now that's not it yet.
Or is it that, as an essence, whiteness is not so much a color as the visible absence of color and at the same time the concrete of all colors?
Is it for these reasons that there is such a dumb blankness full of meaning in a wide landscape of snows, a colorless, all-color of atheism from which we shrink?
That's the crucial sentence.
It's pretty, pretty obscure.
You can go back and look at it.
It's sort of almost bottom of 88.
I'll read it again.
But let me just tell you, sort of, it's important that whiteness isn't any color.
It's an absence of all color.
But it's also what you get if you put all the colors together.
He's not thinking of putting them all in a painting where you would get black.
But if you put all the colors together in a shining with a projector on the wall in white, if you add all the colors, you get white.
That's what you get in the rainbow.
That's when you take the rainbow apart as a light beam.
You get all the colors.
Newton did that.
So whiteness is, from Melville's point of view, the absence of all colors that you get by adding up all colors.
That makes it a dumb blankness.
That's the whiteness.
Full of meaning because it's got all the colors in it.
It's the colorless, all color of atheism.
That is a mouthful.
And I can tell you maybe by the end of the hour what this is about.
This is an absolutely amazingly brilliant kind of metaphor for the understanding of meaning that Melville's got.
But I'm going to get there slowly.
There's a little more to spell out yet.
And when we consider that other theory of the natural philosophers, that all other earthly use, every stately and lovely emblossomy, the sweet tinges of sunset skies and woods, yea, and the gilded velvets of butterflies and the cheeks of young girls, all these are but subtle deceits, not actually inherent in substances, but only laid on from outside, so as all deified nature absolutely paints like a harlot, whose allurements cover nothing but the charnel house within.
Boy, is that a mouthful.
But that's a long, complicated way of saying, I think, that you've got to remember that the natural world, and he's just giving you sort of his contemporary science, which we still believe, it doesn't have any color.
And it's just, it isn't even really white, it's just colorless.
And then if color equals meaning, as it does, sort of always, the universe is meaningless.
And all the colors that we see are kind of an illusion of this meaningless radiation on this meaningless blob of matter in our skull and gives us this idea that nature is full of beautiful colors, that really that's our interaction with nature.
Nature hasn't got any color.
And so it's covering up the blankness of reality.
But that's not what's getting him.
It gets closer to what's getting him at the end of the very end of the chapter, which we're getting close to.
He already introduces it here.
He talks about, where does he talk about for a minute about the landscape of snow?
Yeah, the whiteness of snow is important for this.
Condering all this, the palsy universe, P-A-L-S-I-U-V, does that?
Like shaking?
No.
It doesn't mean pale.
I thought it was too, but there you'd think it must mean pale in some way.
I wonder if that's if there are two meanings or something.
The palsy universe would be sort of a universe with Parkinson.
That doesn't seem very normal or sensible.
I wonder what that is.
Well, there's so much hitting you at once when you read this that I have to look it up.
Now I have to write it down about all the new problems.
Look.
I don't know.
Okay, let's anyway.
The something universe lies before us a leper.
A leper being pale, too, for him.
And the willful travelers in Lapland who refuse to wear colored glasses and coloring glass refuse to wear colored and coloring glasses upon their eyes, that is, don't have sunglasses.
So the wretched infidel gazes himself blind at the monumental white shroud that wraps all the prospect around him.
That means the whiteness of the whale is like the whiteness of snow.
And if you are a non-believer, that's an infidel.
And if you look into it without any protection by sunglasses, which are really interpretations that block out most of the color and only leaves a little of it, you will be blinded by it.
And there is a character in the book, the very character who understands that everything is an interpretation.
When he understands that, goes blind.
Well, that's a long story.
Keep your eye on Pip.
Pip is a character who sees more than anybody else in the book, I guess.
And if true, anybody, yeah, I guess even more than Melville, maybe, according to the way this more than Ishmael, that is.
Anyway, so that he gazes himself blind at the monumental white shroud that wraps all the prospect around him.
Of all these things, this is the ending sentence.
The albino whale was the symbol.
Wonder ye then at the fiery hunt.
Oh, you won't understand that.
That's Ahab not being able to stand the whiteness coming in.
But I take it that the glasses cover up the whiteness with a single interpretation.
And why is that wrong?
Well, we're back to that again.
It's wrong because it limits you of being open to all the other interpretations.
You shouldn't, the right way to look at the whiteness is not by wearing one tinted dark glasses.
So what is the right way to look at the whiteness?
If you really understand the structure of the book, you'll understand what the answer that has to be.
But I'm sure you don't, and it took me years to understand it.
And I sometimes wonder whether even Melville understands it.
That in the sense that it's so sort of woven through the book in a funny, marginal-ish way that I have no idea how important it is to him.
But where are we?
So we lay on these interpretations.
If you lay on only one interpretation, you leave out all the others.
That's the dark glasses.
If you add up a lot of interpretations, each one of which, if some observer adds up a lot of interpretations of reality, each one of which takes itself to be the right answer, you also get whiteness, and they all cancel each other out.
What in the world else can you do?
Well, I'm going to jump ahead, but I don't want to, but I don't want to run out of time either, so let me skim to where the bottom line is here.
So, you don't want to, what, how do you get meaning out of a dumb blankness full of meaning?
Well, the answer is, in a way, Newton did it.
That is, what you have to do is turn the whiteness into a rainbow.
To turn the whiteness into a rainbow is to get a whole spectrum of interpretations, to be able to see it from the whiteness like from wearing lots of different glasses.
It's to be able to be open to color meanings.
And when I came up with this, I went to see how there's a dumb blankness full of meanings.
You can get in sync with different meanings with each different interpretation.
And if you try to add them up as answers, let's see, without trying to tell you, instead of using one-color glasses, if you could look at the whiteness with a whole variety of interpretations, you would get a rainbow of colors.
And that's polytheism.
His metaphor for polytheism is a whole bunch of different perspectives, a whole bunch of different moods, a whole bunch of different interpretations, a whole bunch of different gods.
If you all try to add it up, it gives you this terrifying dumb blankness.
But if you live in the openness to all the colors, then you live in the rainbow.
Now, I came up with this after years of reading this, and I thought, well, this is a crazy idea, but does he ever say it?
And the answer is, yes, he does finally say it.
Way at the end of the book, on 541.
He tells you what the story about the whale and the rainbow.
Wow, 541?
No, 362, maybe.
Let's hope.
I don't want to lose my punchline.
There we are.
This is the answer.
Now, on the very last paragraph of 85, he's going to put the whiteness together with the rainbow and the whale all together.
And now, and how nobly it raises our conceit of the mighty, misty monster, that's Moby Dick, to behold him solemnly sailing through a calm tropical sea, his vast mile ahead overhung by a canopy of vapor, engendered by his incommunicable contemplations, and that vapor, as you will sometimes see it, glorified by a rainbow, as if heaven had put his seal upon his thoughts.
Now, you think, well, boy, that is just a passing thing, big deal.
But he goes on, for do you see, rainbows do not visit the clear air.
They only radiate the vapor.
And so, through all the thick mists of the dim doubts in my mind, now we're going to turn it into polytheism of sorts and moodism.
Through the dim doubts in my mind, divine intuitions now and then shoot, enkindling my fog with a heavenly ray.
And for this, I thank God, for all have doubts, many deny.
The doubts are denials, few among them have intuitions.
Doubts of all things earthly and intuitions of some things heavenly.
This combination makes neither a believer, that's onto theology, that's Christianity, nor an infidel, that's atheist, but makes a man who regards them both with equal eye, that is, who rejects them both, and has polytheism, has an openness to a whole range of interpretations, which, and you've got to keep repeating this, you can't add them up and say, well, if there are a lot of different interpretations, let's unify them into one unified interpretation.
Because if you add up all the colors, what do you get?
Whiteness, blankness.
They cancel each other out.
The only way to preserve them is to preserve them as if they were moods or intuitions or interpretations.
And then you can enjoy them, and then the whiteness doesn't upset you anymore.
Then the whiteness seems exactly the, it's the only kind of meaningfulness you've got, and it's the only kind of meaningfulness you need.
Now, I don't expect you to believe on the basis of one paragraph, but there are two whole chapters which spell out this intuition.
And I'll tell you what they are.
We can't get to them for a while.
There's one called the Dago, which is that's the chapter about interpretation.
They're the chapter, something in the Archides.
I forget the chapel in the Archides, maybe.
That's the amazing one.
Because there he takes the whole story he's told you about colors and how they add up to a dumb blankness if you put them all together, but how they spread into a rainbow if you look at them spread out.
He does it with sound.
He tells you the same story that he told you with the whale swimming in the water.
The chapel in the Archides is the people who worship the skeleton of the whale.
And in describing what happens when you worship the skeleton of the whale, he tells you the whole structure again acoustically.
So there is this deep structure.
When I say I don't know whether he knows it or not, it's the casualness that these things come in.
But I can't make any, I couldn't make any sense of the whiteness until I could put it together with rainbows.
Now, this is just my interpretation, I should say, being reading this book.
You should feel free to come up with an entirely different interpretation of what this book is really about.
Melville would be perfectly happy if everybody in the class had a different interpretation of what the book was about.
Anyway, that's enough for today.
Okay.