So we're ready to go back to the Taskylus.
And all of you have, I hope, by now, reading it hard and carefully and becoming authorities on it.
So here we go.
Remember where we were last time.
I said, and there were three solutions that Athena gives to the problem that the culture is hopelessly split and self-destructive and will destroy anybody else who gets caught in it, like Orestes.
And we've had one of the three solutions: namely, she establishes a court system to decide whether Orestes is or is not guilty.
And the court, in this bizarre way, because it, well, just to remind you, because it's very important, the jurors are split 50-50, which just shows how the culture is split.
And then Athena gives a completely crazy casting the deciding vote in favor of Apollo and the new gods and acquitting Orestes because she says, well, she doesn't have a mother and she's one of the new gods, so she's on the side of the man side of things, which doesn't seem very satisfying.
But it looks again like you get one of these reversals.
It looks like there's a happy ending, it seems, for a moment anyway.
After all, Orestes wins.
He deserves to win.
He deserves to be acquitted.
He shouldn't feel guilty.
And nobody should accuse him for having killed his mother.
So they seem to have accomplished something.
But, and that's obvious, it hasn't helped the split between the emotions and reason a bit.
Because the jury is just as split as ever.
And it's even worse than that, because it makes the Furies even madder than they were before.
They were already upset for being, remember, repressed under the new gods and not given any place, and really literally repressed, pushed under the ground, and they are not at all happy with that.
And this sort of arbitrary sort of decision, based mostly on the fact that Athena knows where the thunderbolts are kept and has the power to enforce it, is not going to make them happy.
So, what they say on 163 at the top, the chorus speech, is, and it's just straight about repression: gods of the younger generation, you have ridden down.
I mean, that's the repression.
You have pushed under, you have put down the laws of the elder time, torn them out of my hands.
I disinherited, suffering, heavy with anger, let loose upon the land the vindictive poison dripping deadly out of the heart upon the ground.
Well, that's pretty bad.
Certainly, it turns out that the court system made things worse instead of better, the way it operated in this hopelessly messed up culture.
They go on in the middle of the page: I am mocked by these people, I have borne what cannot be borne, great sorrow and dishonor upon the sad daughters of the night.
And so now we're ready, then Athena has to come up with a second solution, which is a lot more interesting and important to the people of Athens.
So she promises, she understands that the Furies' real problem is that they're dishonored, they're not respected, they have no acceptable place, they are denied their role.
She understands all that, and she s and gives them a new job at the bottom of 163.
This is Athena talking: in complete honesty, I promise you a place of your own, deep under the ground that is yours by right, where you shall sit on shining chairs.
They're not going to be in the gloom anymore.
Beside the hearth, which is the light that they're going to have, they're going to have the kind of light that you get from the fireplace, to accept devotions offered by your citizens.
Well, that's good.
But what happens after that is sort of funny, if you consider sort of craziness and misery to be funny.
The chorus, did you notice this when you read it?
That you think maybe there's some kind of misprint.
The chorus literally keeps repeating itself, the furies.
They just go back to saying exactly what they said on page 163, gods of the younger generation, you have written down.
Guess what?
She makes her speech, she shows that she cares.
She offers them a new job.
What do they say?
Gods of the younger generation, you have written down the laws of elder time, torn them out of my hands, I disinherited, and so forth.
They just go ranting on, repeating themselves.
And that's because they're so upset, being very emotional, that they can't even hear her.
And when you're really angry and somebody else is trying to either apologize or explain or anything, you're just too upset even to hear them.
That's exactly what Aeschylus is putting on the stage in a very funny way.
So there they go.
They rant on the same speech exactly.
And she goes on trying to explain to them that it's not true what they're saying, that they're dishonored.
She says, no, not dishonored.
This is on the middle of 164.
You are goddesses.
Do not, in too much anger, make this place of mortal men uninhabitable.
Then she threatens them with the thunderbolts, but doesn't really come do anything about it.
She promises them, though, at the end of that little speech, you shall win first fruits and offering for children and the marriage right for always.
She's going to switch over the marriage from the new gods and making a sort of an oath to a marriage really grounded in emotions and instinct and sensuous experience.
She's going to hand the marriage over to the furies.
And what do they say?
Well, they say the same thing, what they just said before, that they could, a little variation, that they could treat me so, I, the mind of the past, to be driven underground.
I mean, there's straight out repression, driven underground, outcast, like dirt.
And they get very upset and they talk about at the top of 165, they have wiped me out and the hard hands of the gods and their treacheries have taken my old rights away.
So they really got there.
They've been dishonored.
They've been disenfranchised.
They've been mistreated.
And Athena, what does she do?
She just keeps telling them her story in a total dialogue of non-listening.
So she, well, she's listening.
They're not listening because every time they say something, she answers it.
She says, I will bear your angers.
You are elder-born than I.
And in that, you are wiser, far than I.
I mean, she, unlike Apollo, who thinks that they're just sort of hopeless idiots because they're primitive and have these sort of basic views of the world, that they're stupid.
And she sees, no, no, the emotional side of the world has something really important going for it and tells them so.
And they are going to get at the end of her speech, she says, don't turn your battle.
Well, I don't want to read that yet, I think.
Just a second.
I got to see where I am.
So I have to sort of reorder things.
They rant about being repressed.
That's where I am.
And she shows her respect.
That's what I just read, saying, you're smarter than I am.
And she says they shouldn't really be carrying on fights between families in the city.
They should fight foreign foes.
She says that at the end of her speech: Don't turn your fury inward on yourselves, on themselves.
Let our wars range outward, hard against the man who has fallen horribly in love with high renown.
That is, another translation: one who tries to satisfy his lust for fame.
There's real pride, and they're against pride.
She is too.
And one who has fallen horribly in love with high renown, and no true fighter fights at home, she wants to say.
And then she's still showing her patience.
And do they make another rant, or is this part of the same speech by her?
I forget.
No, they make another rant that they could treat me so, the mind of the past, cast out like dirt.
It's amazing how they can just say the same, not literally the same words this time, but it's the same idea.
And she says, quite correctly, I will not weary of telling you all the good things I offer.
I mean, she's just saying, I'm going to just persist.
She knows what everybody knows, that when you're in an outrage of anger, if you give somebody time, they can't help it.
They calm down.
That's this whole story about how the emotions get tired and go to sleep.
So she's waiting and telling them, and sooner or later, she thinks they'll stop being in such a fit and outrage and rant and listen.
And that's what happens.
It's almost funny.
So she says, I'll not weary of telling you the good things.
And she says, if you hold persuasion has her sacred place of worship and the sweet beguilement of my voice, she's saying, I don't just make speeches like Apollo.
I make, I talk in a sweet way, and I try to take into account the concerns of the people I'm talking to.
She's got something behind the different than just ranting on the one extreme, which is what the Furies are doing, and making sort of abstract pronouncements, which is what Apollo does.
She is always persuasive.
That's a third thing.
That takes account of the current situation and is sensitive, attuned to it.
Athena hasn't changed all that much from Athena of the Odyssey.
So, and what happens then?
This is the funny part.
All of a sudden, they get it.
They've gotten sufficiently cooled off.
She says the same thing she's been saying, and they say, on the middle of 166, Lady Athena, what is this place you say is mine?
Boom!
The coin has dropped.
They see now that she's telling them something important, and they're ready to listen to it.
And she says, no household shall be prosperous without your will.
And they say, you will really let me be so strong.
And she says, we.
She puts them, she gets them together on her side.
She's building a consensus.
We shall straighten the lives of all who worship us.
Athena says that.
That's the big switch over.
They're now on the same team.
And then they say this interesting thing.
You guarantee such honor for the rest of time.
And what she says is fascinating.
I have no need to promise what I cannot do.
So what does that mean?
I think, did I talk about that already?
It sounds familiar.
Okay, well, they, of course, want to have whatever this solution is count forever.
But Athena, you know, I think, knows that it's a cultural solution.
And as a cultural solution, it's vulnerable.
The culture can go back into this kind of problem, or it could go all super, super rational.
Nietzsche says that in the next generation with Socrates and Plato, the Greeks become mad with rationality.
That would be just to go over on the side of Apollo.
She knows that it's a solution that requires that they continually preserve it.
It isn't something built into the nature of things.
It's a cultural achievement.
And so she says, I've no need to promise what I can't do.
That is, she can't promise, and she knows it's, she probably knows, that she can't promise that this cultural achievement is going to last forever.
In fact, the cultural achievement really can't last forever.
Heidegger says that all these works of art and the cultures that they focus die eventually.
People will stop believing in them for various reasons.
So she doesn't promise them.
But anyway, they don't insist.
They say, I think you have your way with me.
My hate is going.
And why is she able to get rid of their anger and their hatred and their bitterness and their harshness and all that so seemingly so easily?
I'm answering this because I was asked by somebody, I don't remember who, sort of to explain this sort of thing that it looks too easy for Athena just to flip the furies over out of their harshness into becoming what will be later called the kindly ones.
But I've tried to prepare you for that.
Because if what's making them harsh and angry and full of hate and bitterness and so forth is that they've been repressed, that they are dishonored, that they haven't been given any lawful place, they don't have any job, they don't have any respect, then all Athena has to do is give them all that.
And they stop being crazy and nasty and ranting, and they do that.
They stop that.
She gives a little speech here on 167, which reconciles the two kinds of gods as a kind of way of stating that there's now a kind of us and a kind of agreement.
Something that has no traffic with evil success, let it come out of the ground, out of the sea is water, from the high air.
I don't know about the sea is water, but something in the ground and in the high air gets together.
And in gentle gales, it washes over the country in full sunlight.
That's the light part.
And somewhere there ought to be the dark part.
Yes, and the seed and stream of the soils yield, that's the ground part.
There's the sky and the ground, the light, and implicitly the dark, all in here, and so forth.
Then be strong and never fail our people as time goes and make the human scene be kept alive.
And then she says at the end of that speech, which is something very interesting: all such is yours for granting.
All such is yours for granting.
That's this new fertile, positive world that they can create.
In the speech and show and pride of battle, I myself shall not endure the city's eclipse in the estimation of mankind.
Now I want to say something about that, but I'm not sure I want to say it yet.
Let me see.
He promises, and I'm going to come back to this later when I talk about the understanding of being, that already what's being said implicitly in this by Aeschylus.
I don't even know whether he's conscious of it because the understanding of being is so pervasive.
But what she's saying is, and he's showing, is that if you can bring out the best in anybody or anything, if you cultivate it, if you are friendly to it, if you let it develop in its own way, then it will be positive and happy, and all kinds of good things will happen.
All bad things happen when you try to force something on people or anything, and don't let it just come forth at its own way.
And she's let the Furies come forth and do their own thing, and so they're happy.
I'll come back to that because I can't do two things at once, and that's got to do with their new understanding of being.
So the Furies ask for a guarantee.
I just read that.
Athena doesn't promise it.
It lasts about 100 years from 432, not even 100 years, about 80 years.
From 432 to 404, they have this golden age of Athens.
Then they start making mistakes and they start dividing up into factions.
Yeah.
It's still hard.
Well, I'm glad you put your hand up.
I wonder what I can do.
John, Dave, let's see how far we can move this nearer.
But it doesn't help.
I looked in there.
It was all set at maximum.
Okay, let's see.
Okay, that's one thing I can do.
And I can just talk louder.
This one is on.
I don't know about this one.
This is on.
Put this back.
Is this on?
But it's not supposed to be.
That's the one for the podcast.
Okay.
Okay, okay, let's see now.
And let's look over here.
But I think that the this projection power microphone, microphone volume.
I'll try it.
Where's the key at this point?
Do I have it?
I think I have it.
Yeah.
I've looked before.
I think the microphone volume.
Oh, I remember.
We can try to do the microphone volume, but we may get feedback.
In which case, we may have to move the table back.
Let's struggle with it.
Okay.
Microphone.
This is full up.
Wireless we don't want to mess with.
Because that's the one that's the yeah.
Okay, let's try it.
Put it up.
And does it make any difference?
Yeah, it is.
Oh, okay.
Hey, I think we did it.
Thanks.
Yeah, and it isn't feeding back either.
How's that?
Terrific.
Okay, let's remember that.
We've got a million things to do every time when we come in.
Just add it to the list.
Uh-oh.
Is that echoing too much now?
No?
Okay, that's good.
Where were we?
Athena can't promise.
It only lasts something like 70 years before the Athens is destroyed in kind of internal troubles.
But it lasts then.
And then comes the interesting thing.
And I do want to say this next, that it's that she says that they will not be eclipsed in the estimation of mankind.
Notice, she doesn't say that they will last forever.
She says they will be admired forever.
So I'm going to read you something from this important book written at the same time as the Orestea, and or a little later, a generation later, maybe, the Peloponnesian Wars by Thucydides.
You may have heard the name.
I hadn't when I was your age, but things from how many have heard of Thucydides?
Aye, progress, yes.
Or you have better schools now.
So then there's the Peloponnesian Wars, war, singular, seems, and that's by Thucydides.
He only seems to have one name.
I'm trying to write big, but I can't write so that the board is clear enough to read anything on it.
Okay, Thucydides is telling about Athens as it is at the time that Aeschylus is writing, which is, you know, Aeschylus is projecting back into the past how Athens became this place which will always, which will never be eclipsed in the estimation of mankind.
I'll just read you one thing, one thing from Pericles here.
I'll read you something else in a little while.
So Pericles is the president, or whatever he's called, the leader, and he's giving his great funeral address and what it was, why Athens is worth dying for.
The Gettysburg Address is modeled on this, they say.
Lincoln knew the famous funeral oration of Pericles when he gave his Gettysburg funeral oration.
He says, The admiration of the present and succeeding ages will be ours, since we have not left our power without witness, but have shown it by mighty proofs.
And far from needing a Homer, for our panegyrist or others of his craft, whose verses might charm for the moment only, for the impression that they gave to melt in the touch, which moment only for the impression which they gave to melt at the touch of fact.
See, he thinks Homer's just legend, whereas they really achieved this.
We have forced every sea and land to be the highway of our daring, and everywhere, whether for evil or for good, we've left imperishable monuments behind us.
I'm going to read you a little more later, but just that's already saying, well, no, I really have to read the rest, though I wasn't planning to.
Why shouldn't I?
Because I haven't really told you that the sense in which it no, no, that's enough.
There is another place, but I won't try to find it, where Pericles says: even if all the monuments that we've made, even if our civilization, our culture, is destroyed, the monuments that we leave behind will make a bigger impression than any monuments even now existing or ever to exist in any other culture.
I'm not quite paraphrasing it right, but roughly, if you dig up the ruins of Athens, he says, it'll be greater and more impressive than any ruins ever.
And the funny thing is, the amazing thing is, that's right.
We are still reading the Aeschylus from that period.
People are still going to see the Acropolis and the Parthenon.
And history begins with Thucydides, and everybody pays tribute to that.
And science begins with math.
They did everything.
And even when they were destroyed, everything they did lives after them, and everything they did we still admire.
And Athena says that's right.
They'll never be eclipsed in the estimation of mankind.
And that seems true.
So we can go on then.
And 160.
So the furies become happy.
They become the source of fertility instead of destruction.
On 168, they're making a kind of fertility speech.
Fox, flocks fatten, earth be kind to them with double fold of fruit in time appropriated for us for its yielding.
Secret child of earth, her hidden wealth bestow, blessing and surprise of gods.
Well, all that is, in effect, if you mix the earth and the sun in the right way, the dark and the light in the right way, you get fertile crops and happy flocks, and they're going to support that.
So Athena's very pleased.
This time it really worked.
I mean, it's not a reversal.
It looks like a real success, and it is a real success.
She's very pleased on the middle of 169.
She says, I admire the eyes of persuasion who guided the speech of my mouth toward these when they were reluctant and wild.
Zeus, who guides men's speech and counsels, was too strong, and my ambition for good wins out in the whole issue.
And the chorus agrees.
They make a happy speech in which they say, in effect, everything is going to be all right.
I'll read that one later, I think.
And let me see my notes.
Yeah, no, I'm not quite ready for that.
The next thing to say is just to sum up what happened with that when the hate and all that is gone, because they got a position, they are transformed into a new kind of being.
They are as transformed as people could get who had been repressed and treated badly and then all of a sudden were treated goodly.
Well, they have become the kindly ones.
That's what humanities means.
They're no longer the Furies.
They're no longer the Irenes, which is another name for the Furies.
They are the humanities.
And I'm going to just read this, Beatrice, and then I'll let you talk.
On 171, we hear the chorus saying, Maidens, wives, elderly women in procession, in the investiture of purple-stained robes, dignify them and let the torchlight go before, so that that kindly company, that's the only reference it makes to the fact that they've become humanities.
So you just got to notice it.
That kindly company, now the humanities, of these within our ground may shine in the future, the strong men to come.
And notice again, and I just noticed as I read it, that there's again always reconciling.
I was thinking too bad.
Maidens, wives, elder women, that's all very well, but it looks like it's gone all over on the side of women.
And what you want is both the old gods and the women and the new gods and the men.
Just before the end of the paragraph, Aeschylus must realize this too, and he says, may shine forth in the future of young men to come.
So the men and women are all together in there.
I think that's always going to be the way it is.
Now, Beatrice, I'm ready to.
They say this is my faird civil war pattern on Maslow and Shamat Thunder in our studio.
It's just we need to go to war because we think we're very specific.
It's not really what the theories were after.
About.
That's right.
Civil war, it really should be sort of family war.
Let's look at the let's look.
The civil war doesn't seem the right way to describe it.
I agree with you.
So let's look at 980.
Remember, I told you this, I put this a copy of this book, which is the most literal translation, on reserve in the Philosophy Library, and a copy of Latimer, which is the most literal of the poetic translations, also.
So when you're writing your paper, if you see things you don't like, the first thing you can do is look and see if it's wrong.
And if you're doing well, you'll find lots of places where you can change the translation to make it work.
So let's see about Civil War on 980.
May faction insatiate of ill never raise her loud voice within the city.
Well, there you fix it.
You're absolutely right.
Faction is between families, or could be.
Civil war isn't in the Greek.
Of course, faction is what it was.
This family against that family, this clan against that clan.
And that's not supposed to happen anymore.
That's not going to be in the city.
And they're all going to get along and love each other.
And then the end of there, I'll mention it already.
There's this interesting place for the emotions of hate, which is probably going to be part of their problem.
Certainly, I never thought of putting it this way.
It's not quite solved.
They haven't really turned all the emotions into positive emotions by giving them this expressive, cultivated honor.
There's still hate, but the hate isn't going to divide the city into factions anymore.
The hate is now turned against the bad guys, whoever they are.
Let love be their common will.
That's how they are in the city.
And let them hate with a single heart.
Who are they going to hate?
Well, I go back in this place that I said I wasn't ready to read it yet, where it looks like it's people who they think are enemies, bad countries.
Where we find it.
On page 165, I was reading, don't turn your battle fury inward on yourself.
That's, again, the factionalism in the city.
Let our wars range outward, hard against the man who has fallen horribly in love with high renown.
Now, that is go against the dictators and tyrants and other bad countries.
They've got this thing that we've got.
There's the empire of evil.
Although we're on the empire of evil, you can still hate them and attack them.
But inside the country, you should be unified.
And that's as near as they come to getting it.
And unfortunately, when they fall apart, the reason they fall apart is they get involved in all these wars.
That's exactly the thing that Athena didn't fix.
She was satisfied to let the hate range outward, and they go around attacking all sorts of other countries and trying to put them in their empire, very much like Iraq.
They just see a country that's got lots of riches that they want, and they just go after it, and they usually capture it, but eventually they get so spread out in the war that they start losing, and then they start fighting with each other, and then the whole thing falls apart.
That's the story in Thucydides, if we had time.
So, anyway, Beatrice is right, translation is wrong, but nothing serious because we can easily fix it.
It's just no factionalism in the city.
But the question is: how is that going to happen?
I haven't really told you the solution fully yet.
What does it mean?
Why are they the kindly ones?
How come they became so kindly all of a sudden?
What happened to hate and moral outrage?
Well, that's what I'm just saying.
They didn't really get rid of the hate and the outrage.
They just got rid of the Klan fighting and the vengeance fighting, the sort of mafia structure of the culture, but their hate is still there against all these other cultures and other countries they consider evil.
But there is some more positive thing happening, which is really what I call the second solution.
That why are they all united in love in that passage I read?
Love be their common will at the bottom of 69.
What sort of love is it?
And why is it that it unites everybody?
Well, that's the great coup.
What happens is she's created a new emotion of patriotism.
That they love Athens.
That's what they end up loving.
And they are the new emotion which leads to unity and not contradiction, which puts the, is an emotion which puts the community first, that is the city-state, and that is Athens, above any of the local interests or any of the family interests or any of the clan or private interests, not in an abstract way like Apollo does, but by filling them all with the same love, namely, of Athens.
It's sort of like this famous quote you hear from Kennedy, John F.
Kay, every once in a while: ask not what your country can do for you, but what you can do for your country.
That is, the most important thing is to love Athens.
Well, it isn't all that clear in here, but it's very clear in Thucydides.
And this is what I kept saying.
I will read it.
No, I won't read it because I wanted to resist reading it until you get it until it's right on.
This is exactly the love that's going to get rid of all factionalism.
On page 112 of my copy, anyway, it says, Pericles says, you must realize the power of Athens and feed your eyes upon her day to day till love of her fills your hearts, and then with all her greatness, and then when all her greatness shall break upon you, you must reflect that it was by courage and sense of duty and a feeling of honor in action that men weren't able to win all this.
That's partly the funeral oration part, that you admire the soldiers who gave their life for it.
That's not what I'm going to emphasize.
The main thing to emphasize is you see how great Athens is.
You're totally overwhelmed by admiration.
You know, they've invented democracy.
They've invented uh a whole uh new moral order.
They've invented the the the jury system, and they've and they are now supposed to be, and they are, filled with their the the the the love of Athens fills their hearts.
That's the second solution.
Uh that's that's what really unifies the culture, is that there is if it wasn't that there was something so great that they could all just be blown away with loving it and ready to do anything for it, there wouldn't have been this kind of unity and wouldn't trump all families, all clans, all special interest groups, all private craziness.
But there is, namely Athens.
And that's all in here, and it's expressed in the procession that you hear about on 171.
I've read the beginning of it already.
All the women and even the men are, particularly right now as we're hearing about the women, they're going to their special place in the bottom.
I have to read you this.
The procession has two parts.
There's the procession where all the women lead the furies to their new home, where they'll be respected and fertile and do good.
And then there's another procession of it, another part of the procession I don't want to talk about quite yet.
But let's read this part.
They're going to there, in the middle of the page, they're going to the primal dark of earthly hollows, held in high veneration, with right back with this fill, bless them, all people with silence.
These are the women marching down to their new place.
Gracious, well, who's talking here?
Athena?
I hope.
Yeah, I can't see.
My book is panting shape.
Yeah, well, no, or is it the chorus?
Well, who what's talking here?
Athena.
Okay, good.
Be gracious be, I'm at the very end of the play now.
Wi gracious be, wish what the land wishes.
Follow grave goddesses, calling them goddesses, of course, rushed in the flame-sprung torchlight, yea on your journey, singing all, follow our footsteps.
There shall be peace forever between these people, Pallas, remember that's Athena, and their guests, that's the humanities.
Peace forever.
Athena's getting a bit carried away there.
I can't do much about that.
What?
Oh, I'm glad to.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, better, better.
Yes, Athena.
Thanks.
I thought I didn't see that in the middle of the page.
Okay, so the chorus, of course, thinks it's forever.
They're inside it, and they don't understand it as a cultural achievement.
They understand it as a recognition of their ancient and always rights, just as Apollo thinks that he's always new and right.
And so they think it's forever, this new reconciliation, between Pallas, which is Athena who stands in for the new gods, and their guests, that's the humanities.
Who's the all-seeing?
Remember, he's behind everything, met with destiny to confirm it, singing all follow the footsteps.
Now, that's very, very interesting, that last line.
Who's the all that's following the footsteps?
Well, there is the priestesses, the priestesses of Athena get mentioned, and there's the humanities who are in there, and there's, I guess those are the main ones.
And it isn't clear yet who the other, who the all is.
And I tell you, there are long detours required to understand that.
And that's what I'm calling the third solution.
The third solution is the important one for this course, for Heidegger and me anyway, and probably for everybody.
The third solution is to turn the whole thing into a work of art.
And that's even more than just getting them all to agree how great Athens is.
What would you have to do besides that?
You'd have to show them how great Athens is and get them to all see, that they all see that this is a great, that Athens is so great that it can solve the problems of the culture and make it into a kind of fruitful culture.
And that's, I have to explain that now more.
And it's so tricky that I have to read it because I lose track, as you'll see, when I try to say it.
Because it's so what I'm calling self-referential.
The play is making itself into a work of art, and it knows it's making itself into a work of art, and they know it's making itself aware.
What is it to be a work of art, remember, is to hold up to the people and shine and glamorize and let them all see what it is that they all believe in, what it is that they all stand for.
And that creates a whole understanding as it's happening.
The work of art articulates the understanding of being and makes it work.
So now let me read it in as many ways.
Yeah, good, say something.
Yes, that's a heat.
Exactly.
Good.
Yes, I was setting it up.
He's articulating a story that will show them how they got to be so great and why they're so great.
And the crazy thing is, I want to say over and over again: and what made them so great?
Their realization that they were so great.
That's the peculiar part of it.
Their pride and patriotism solves all these problems, and they are proud and patriotic because they solved all these problems.
It's very, very peculiarly circular.
So you see why I want to read it, because I have trouble saying it.
So I said it pretty well just then.
So let me try again.
So this is the third solution.
We set up the courts, we transformed the Furies into humanities, and now produced a new emotion of pride in the glory of Athens.
And this is as far as the critics have seen, I think.
Now comes this funny move that Heidegger would see.
He doesn't write about this play, but he writes about works of art in general and articulating.
So what would he say?
Well, the emotions of vengeance and civil war have been turned into the emotions of loyalty and patriotism and love of Athens.
I wasn't into the love part last time when I wrote these notes.
I want to write it in.
Yeah, no pen.
Okay, I still remember.
So where are we?
Okay, why?
So what are the Athenians to be proud of?
Just this, that they've turned the primitive and tribal emotions into patriotic emotions of love of the whole city.
So, the feeling is self-referential.
Their patriotism is what makes them proud, and their pride is what makes them their patriotism.
They're proud of their city because it produced the new emotion of patriotic pride.
That's so weird that I have to keep saying it.
If we ask how this pride was achieved, it was done by holding up to the people what they had done that they should be proud of.
And what was that?
Well, to become the, to all agree to love the city.
And how did that happen?
Well, something like this play does the job of producing the pride by showing them what the city stands for, that they should be proud of.
That's what the play is about.
So, the play is not really, in fact, about this pride and this patriotism and this love, it's producing.
And that's a work of art working.
It's turned them into unified Athenian Athens lovers who put the love of Athens above everything, as Pericles says.
He's a work of art, too, from a Heideggerian point of view.
The funeral oration does the same job.
They're good at this.
They understood how to hold up to themselves what's great about themselves and make them that much greater as they do it.
So, let me see if I can say again.
So, they should be proud of integrating and cultivating the primitive emotions that they've turned into humanities, and they should be proud of the love of Athens.
And this produces the Athenians as Athenians.
That is, they become this special kind of people who put the unity of their city above everything.
I mean, they're not like an empire like Persia, which isn't run by love, but by some tyrannical leader.
And they're certainly not anymore like a lot of families all fighting with each other.
They've got a special thing, love of that polis, in which they all vote, in which they all take a part, take part.
And so, who's in the sacred procession at the end, at the bottom of the very last line of the play?
Well, for one thing, you've got to be very careful.
It says, exit everybody in procession.
Well, who's everybody?
And why should we believe what's in italics anyway, since the italics were telling us the 12 jurors that was just stuck in there by the translator?
Is it really everybody?
And who are they?
Okay, let's see now.
I'm reading, I'm repeating myself a lot.
So the words of the play are actually making it happen that they all feel this love and devotion to Athens.
It doesn't talk about it, it actually produces it.
And then they're feeling these emotions and what?
And, oh, yeah, and the work of art is supposed to shine.
That's a funny word for it.
Remember, I said it looks so glamorized that everybody sees everything in the light of it.
Well, this play is like that.
Remember that this play is the only play to be chosen to be presented every year, whereas all the other plays, even Oedipus Rex, Pretty Good Play, gets presented only during, it gets presented over and over, but only during the one year that it wins the equivalent of the Oscar for that year, and then it's gone.
But no reruns.
But this gets endless reruns every year.
This runs, and naturally, because it shines.
I'll see how I put that.
It's the ultimate artwork, I think, in that it does its job, it holds up to the people what they believe in and produces what they believe in.
It's such a self-conscious work of art.
It wants to say, it holds up to the audience what it is that they share and lets them know they share it.
That's what it is to be a shining thing.
So that's why we can hear about their seeing everything in its light on page 171.
Where's the light?
Oh, yeah, there we are, right with the kindly company, the humanities, at the end of the top speech.
So the kindly company who leads within our ground may shine in the future of strong men to come.
I have to push a little to get that, but there's some shining going on, and I really think it's the shining of the whole play is itself producing this.
Think how proud you would be.
I hope you can understand what I'm saying.
Suppose you were in the audience, and you were seeing the story of how your culture became totally happy, unified by patriotism, solved all its problems of conflict, became a kind of model for all times for human beings, and you're in it.
You're of it.
And you can't help but be filled with admiration and wonder and awe and love and thankful that you're part of this.
But that's not even the last straw.
Aeschylus is so incredible.
Then, how would you show these people that they were part of it?
Well, the answer is they're part of the procession.
It isn't just the women, it's the audience that marches out.
And the procession marches out and goes through the whole city.
It says it more fully in this team, which I trust, so I'm going to read it.
It says, because I wondered about it.
I'll show you a line in the play that makes it true.
But I'll read you what they say, what it says about it.
The chorus is now to be solemnly conducted to the cavern beneath the hills and so forth, with whom the poet here identifies the Irene's, who were the angry ones, the avenging spirits, and so forth.
The procession is formed by Athena at its head.
The chorus of torchbearers follows.
The women who guard the palladium, that's Athena's temple, I think.
Is it?
I don't know what it is.
Anyway, whatever it is, and various others.
In the rear comes the whole Austin in public.
And now you still wonder, what right do they have to write that footnote?
And now I found it, and now I've lost it again.
I can't be.
Right around here somewhere, you hear that they all march.
That's funny.
I have lost my one line that defends that.
Help me find it.
Well, that's what the very last line I read: singing all follow our footsteps, the very last line.
That's the idea.
I mean, even then, it seems to me you have to read something in, but I have to trust this.
When it says, oh, it doesn't mean all those who are on stage, all the actors and actresses follow.
It means everybody follows, because Aeschylus knows and they know that the play is producing right then them as these patriotic Athenians.
And they know it too.
And so it's a play which is a god because it creates those people as the people they are.
It's a kind of creator god.
It's not the kind that produces the world from on high.
It's the shining of the temple itself that produces these people as Athenian people, which is a special kind of people.
Well, that's it.
That's what I want to say about this play.
That's why they kept saying this is the work of art, so to speak, the mother of all works of art.
It does everything a work of art is supposed to do, and it knows it does it, and it shows it does it.
What more could anybody want?
So, anybody have anything to say about that?
Yeah.
That's right.
Yes, very good.
Exactly.
The second solution, number two, which is supposedly, which is Athena giving them respect, supposedly happened somewhere in the mythical past.
But it leads to this actual present in which these real Athenians now have this solution that Athena and the Furies worked out, and that's it.
That's right.
And Athena's in the play.
The play is a work of art because it expresses the love and patriotism of the current Athenians.
It produces the love and patriotism as the sort of essentral feature of these Athenians.
And that's that's and inside the play, you get a story about how hard it was to do that, what they're the only culture that ever succeeded, how it may last for a long time.
Let's hope so.
It didn't, but they didn't quite get their hate under control.
But it's they see it as something so admirable that they can devote their life to love of it.
Yeah.
Has what younteresting.
Yes, I don't know.
That's very interesting.
I've wondered about that once, but then I sort of put it aside and I never thought about it again.
I'll repeat his question.
And now that this is the work of art that holds up to the people what they stand for, namely love of Athens and what human beings really are, our citizens, our voters in a democracy.
What about Homeric work of art?
Does it stop being a work of art?
I think it does.
I think it's a, for them already, of course, for us it's a dead work.
Let me just think out loud.
Is it a dead work for them?
I think it's a dead work for them, exactly like for lots and lots of people and maybe more and more, the Bible could become a dead work.
Then people still quote it all the time and look back at it to see what, I don't know, religious devotion could be like.
But it's because it's true, I've read that the Odyssey is still what everybody reads and is proud of and thinks that it shows what it is to be a Greek and a father and a mother and a warrior and a good son and a good swineherd.
I think they believe, I mean, my hunch is they believe all that, but they don't deeply feel it anymore.
They don't live in it the way a goldfish lives in water.
It's an understanding of being which they, the current people who have a different understanding of being, love and respect, but it doesn't work.
You've led me now to say what I was going to say somewhere.
I want to give you the history of being, two stages of it, so you can keep your eye open for Virgil, who is a third stage.
We've really got the Homer stage, which is, and the more I say it, the more I realize I agree with myself.
That is, I don't think that they live in it anymore.
Athens is too civilized to have Fusis.
I talked about that.
Fusis means welling up.
Or as I like to say from copying a friend of mine, a famous philosopher, Dick Rorty Wunthinov, welling up is Heidegger's word for it.
Frisis is Heidegger's claim that that word names a certain understanding of being.
And what sort of understanding of being?
Well, one in which, let me get my notes so I can do this justice.
So it means nature.
And our word physics comes from this word pieces.
But nature meant something very different to them than it does to us.
Nature meant this business of welling up.
And what wells up?
And the Iliad is the sort of poem that focuses this thesis more than the Odyssey does.
I mean, what wells up in the Iliad?
Well, heroes well up.
Anger and and overwhelming moods.
The gods show up.
Wild animals get talked about.
Brilliant ideas presumably show up, though I can't think of any, we don't really told when when Odysseus or how he gets his brilliant idea to make the horse.
But storms certainly well up a lot.
Poseidon is a big feature in the throes business.
And you get the feeling that whenever they're out at sea, that's when I think I mentioned this already when I mentioned the passaway.
I mean, you get this feeling of suddenly there's this totally overwhelming, powerful storm.
So nature is generally overwhelmingly powerful.
And all sorts of different things can well up, and none of them are the only one.
And so that's now the new one is Poasis.
That's what I'm claiming is going on in the background that Aeschylus doesn't really know because he's right in it.
P-O-E Poasis.
Is that right?
Which means cultivation.
Yes, something's wrong.
We're.
Oh, I, here's an eye.
Okay.
Poasis.
And so cultivation.
It's as if your understanding of being went to being a hunter-gatherer, where animals rush up and you shoot them and so forth.
And not that the people in Homer's time were hunter-gatherers, but their understanding of being was the same as if they were still hunter-gatherers.
They still had this sense of nature welling up.
And what they didn't have, though they were already cultivating things, they didn't.
And the idea was, and when I say this is their understanding of being, I mean those things are most important and most revealing about what things are that whoosh up in the Iliad.
And afterward, now that you get to Aeschylus, it's 500 years later.
And the most important thing you can do is cultivate things, bring out the best in them.
And that you's why I was setting it up.
You bring out the best in the Furies, and the Furies become good.
If you repress them, they become bad.
It's as if Aeschylus thinks that there are two kinds of ways of organizing the world.
What I'm going to call a repressive order, and that's the order that they had before.
I don't think it's Homeric.
I don't think it's Athenian either.
I don't know any word for it.
But there is then an expressive order.
That's what the Athenians have.
That's this understanding of being a poesis.
And all of this I'm saying to answer his question.
Well, I'll have to say more, because I haven't explained enough poesis.
That means for Heidegger, letting come forth.
I said cultivation.
That's my word.
Heidegger is fancier talk.
Letting come forth.
Now, you need examples, or you won't believe it.
I mean, that is, what do you bring forth?
Well, plants, children, the craftsmen bring forth.
Heidegger has a lot to say how the carpenter brings the grain out of the wood and the sculptor brings the sculpting out of the stone.
That's how a Greek sculptor of this period described it.
He was letting the sculptor come out of the stone.
And Michelangelo, I think, said the same thing.
That's a poesis way of thinking about it.
So, and now, let's see.
So, when the furies are repressed and they try to impose order on them, it doesn't work.
But when the furies are officiated and brought out, then they for married love, legal cities, loyalty, patriotism, everything that's good.
So then things don't just well up.
You've got to sort of make a culture that brings out the best in things.
That's what Aeschylus is doing, and saying that Athena is doing.
And I don't think Aeschylus thinks about it this way, because I think he's inside of it.
But now back to his good question.
Who asked it?
You.
Oh, yeah.
So I think you couldn't be really in two understandings of being at once.
I think they don't understand storms and sort of plants just popping up.
Everything that's important needs to be cultivated and brought out.
And the Odyssey is a wonderful, dead piece of art for them, like medieval cathedrals are for us.
So now, yeah.
But it's not what the Tested View.
It's what.
Yes.
That's right.
It's not you imposing an order on things.
It's you letting the order that's in the things.
You get to let the cabinet come out of the wood.
All you do is select the wood, and as a carpenter, the wood will sort of lead you, if you're a good carpenter, to bring out the cabinet that's in it.
We now call people like that or still around in Berkeley Zen carpenters.
But it's a kind of craftsmanship.
And whether you let it come forth or bring it forth seem to be two stages of this.
I mean, you can just sort of clear the way for things to express themselves fully, or you can, and that's what I think, is cultivating and nurturing.
I think that they really need, are the furies just let come forth, or are they cultivated and nurtured by Athena?
I would say they were cultivated and nurtured.
I mean, that's how she has to let them rant on and then gradually persuade them and then give them more and more sense of their own importance and they flourish.
The main thing is, when you do that, then everything flourishes.
That reminds me of something interesting.
That I don't know if I can just find it, but Pericles has written.
Let's try this.
We do not feel angry with our neighbor for doing what he likes, or even to indulge in those injurious looks, which cannot fail to be offensive.
But all this ease in our private relations doesn't make us lawless citizens.
No, there's some place where he says everybody can do what they please, in effect.
Let's try this.
We are the schools of all of Hellas, and I doubt if the world can produce a man who, where he has only himself to depend on, is equal to our versatility.
No, I can't find it.
It amounts to saying that everybody can do whatever he pleases in Athens, and it all works out for the best.
That's the hope of this kind of expressive order.
Athens is set up to let everybody flourish in their own way.
That's what Pericles says.
That's what Aeschylus thinks.
Yeah, did I see a hand over here?
Do you want to talk for 15 minutes?
Okay.
So that's one question.
And you said that this is the mother of all works of art because it goes out of its own time and self-referential and waiting for the West.
I think she's right.
And in a way, the Odyssey is also self-referential.
I thought you were going to say something different, but it doesn't go against it.
And Homer puts himself into it.
The harper is there singing the thing that he's doing, which produces their sense of the marvelous, shining character of their Fusis hero culture.
I think that's right.
That's good.
Maybe every work of art is self-referential.
I don't know.
It'd be interesting if the cathedrals put into the stained glass windows the pictures of the workers making the windows and so forth.
I don't know whether that's important or not that they do that.
But I think we should, I don't want to stop the conversation.
I just don't have more to say about it yet.
I think you will sort of get more and more as we get.
No, okay, let's go on.
Yeah.
And Odyssey, there's no one thing.
That's part of the pluralism of the Odyssey.
There are kings who do their king thing and swinehards who do their thing.
There isn't any city.
There are all these little kingdoms on various islands.
Argos has got its island, and I think the who do they go visit by boat at the very beginning?
Menelaus is on his island.
So there's no unified city.
There's certainly no democracy.
No notion of patriotism, what it could be to be patriotism when there are all these different kings on all these different islands.
But that's just typical of what with a multiple number of little kingdoms.
Cities is something invented later.
Yeah, a multipleness of kingdoms and a multipleness of lifestyles.
Right.
And all of them, in some sense or other, welling up, not being nourished or cultivated, but somehow just popping up when they do.
It's hard to explain how a kingdom does that.
But yeah.
Between Homer and the Oristea.
It seems that in Homer, the Odyssey itself, there is the difference made between civilization and nature because it makes you that the lifelong civilized.
So there is a big difference in the Odyssey between what Beatrice is saying, the really whooshing up most nature person, Poseidon and the storms, but the heroes whoosh up and the gods whoosh up too.
And I think, what else did you say?
Have I?
Oh, yeah, nature.
You and culture.
Yeah, now what is happening in a culture of which is a truce culture?
Well, I don't think so.
Let's take the culture.
Civilization is more, I think, already sort of unified and socialized.
But there are practices, and they all do speak Greek.
There is some, and they have the same bunch of gods.
And they have the same sensibility, I think, that they're not in the nurturing and cultivating business.
But take the way Aphrodite sort of whooshes up and runs off with Helen.
Moods whoosh up.
And moods, yeah, that's the missing link.
If moods are so important, as I claim they are in the Odyssey, and moods just take you over, you can't bring them on and you can't turn them off and you can't cultivate them either.
I don't think you just get carried away, then you can see how the understanding of being and the importance of moods fit together.
That's helpful.
Did you want to say something?
I thought I saw a handbag.
No?
Yo, good.
Go ahead.
Wait, I can't.
There's echo you put in the room.
I can see why you can't tell me.
I can't hear you either.
And you are saying what I do on the honest moods.
Ah, good, good.
I don't know.
You asked a little question.
I have to think about it.
What about moods?
Moods, to begin with, there are good moods and bad moods, repressed moods, like the periods and hate and all that, and good moods.
And the good moods are the ones that get cultivated in the course of the book.
And the bad moods get turned into good moods as far as possible by being cultivated.
And that's what you expect.
So it isn't that moods cease to be important.
It's that that's interesting.
I'm out on a limb.
I don't know whether I'll believe this tomorrow, but it looks like how the culture treats moods is going to be an expression of their understanding of being.
So the Homer ones just accept the fact that whoosh, there's Aphrodite and off goes Helen.
Or that whoosh, there's Achilles.
He finally decides to fight in the elevator and he rushes out and kills hundreds of people in an afternoon.
It isn't as if there's a thought that if you don't nourish moods, they'll become bad.
And if you do nourish moods, they'll become good.
That's just not a thought of the Odyssey.
Moods don't get transformed.
They're just bad ones, and they're good ones, and you just get grabbed by the ones that come along.
But the attitude towards moods is, or emotions we're now calling them, which are related to the moods of hate, of vengeance, of patriotism, and so forth, is that they, that they well up isn't interesting to them.
It's that, if you repress them, they become bad, and if you nourish them, they become good.
Yeah.
Ah, no, good question.
No.
I mean, the polyness is gone in the Oristea.
It's a big step toward monotheism.
The first step is a bad step.
Remember, I said it was sort of multiple, double, dual monotheism.
I never used those terms, but I mean, each of the two forces, the Apollo forces, the new gods' forces, and the old gods, Fury's forces, each say they're the whole answer.
Nobody goes around in the Odyssey or Iliad saying, our way of understanding things, I'm the only God that really counts, or the only kind of God that really counts.
So in that sense, it's turning toward more mono.
But then it gets really mono, if you think about it this way, when the final emotion is patriotism for Athens, and the final sort of one good thing that everything else serves, so to speak.
However you, whatever you do, it ought to be an expression of your love of Athens, is making a much more mono-story.
There is the right mood, namely patriotism, and all the other moods have got to get in step with it.
Namely, the furies have to become kindly ones, and Apollo just gets knocked off the scene.
We don't hear anything about Apollo.
But okay, so that's a good question.
So you handle the moods differently when you're getting past those.
Yeah.
Ah.
Good, good.
That's how it looks to us, because our understanding is the being is control, and everything ought to be controlled.
And so that's what subjects in talk like Descartes ought to be able to control objects.
Science ought to get the whole of nature under control.
That's not how it seems to them.
Say what you just said again, because that's right.
Yes, that's right.
That's part of the feel of whooshing up.
And that is just what it is to be a still primitive culture.
They don't understand these forces.
They don't have an idea that if they had a better science, they could predict and control all of this.
This is what nature is like, I take it, when you don't have any science, things are just whooshing up surprisingly, and sometimes you manage to cope with them, and sometimes they draw you in and destroy you, Heidegger says.
That's part of what the overwhelming, did I write overwhelming up there?
Welling up.
No, one of the versions of welling up is they can just be overwhelming.
And there's nothing to do about it.
That's one of the questions anything.
It wouldn't help to be smarter.
It isn't your fault.
It's just the way nature is.
Sometimes it helps, and sometimes it destroys you, and it's out of your control.
That's how the world must have looked to the Homeric Greeks.
But they weren't scared of it.
I mean, Heidegger thinks in reading the texts, you feel it in Homer.
It filled them with joy and wonder that it was full of surprises and out of control.
They were just sort of thought it was wonderful, the delightful.
That's too minimum, wonderful.
Thalmazoin, what's the Greek word for that?
Yeah, that's the Greek word for wonder.
Wonder was their basic way of experiencing the fusis going on.
And that's very different than trying to cultivate it and domesticate it, like the Athenians were doing, according to Aeschylus.
And it's very different from what the Romans were doing.
Now, I just got to where I want to do.
Beatrice is going to talk next time about Virgil.
But ask yourself this question.
I'm certainly not going to tell you now, not only because there isn't time, but because I think you should keep your eyes open.
There's a whole new understanding of being in Virgil.
The Romans have.
It isn't fusis, and it isn't Poesis.
It's something else.
It's something closer to us than either of those.
And keep your eyes open for it.
I'll give you a hint.
Since Virgil, of course, doesn't understand it, because you never understand the one you're in.
You're too much in it.
Heidegger talks about the necessary blindness of people making a work of art.
They can't look at the deed.
They don't see.
Homer doesn't see that he's doing his facesis thing in the Iliad.
And uh Aeschylus doesn't see that he's got a Poesis order.
Anyway, so look w uh, where would you look?
Well, in in the Iliad, in the Aeneid anyway, look at the metaphors.
There's certain or similes it's called that like something, something, something, something, something.
When Virgil starts that, keep your eyes open.
There are some very interesting similes that ex that express exactly their understanding of being.
Okay.