Okay, I'm going to review because this is so dense and so many interesting ideas come at you all at once that I will talk about for the first 20 minutes or so, I think, the kinds of things we talked about last time, but that was a long time ago, and I can say them differently.
But the overall, and it's still all around this issue of what is a tragedy and whether Lattimore has got it right or not when he describes what a tragedy is.
I wouldn't, I mean, I probably would enjoy beating up on Lattimore anyway, because I get annoyed at people who don't see what's in front of them that are sort of trapped in 2,000 years of scholarly tradition.
But more important, it wouldn't really be worth going over twice if it weren't that what's at stake between my way of reading it and the whole tradition and Latimer, is whether it's going to be a psychological tragedy, like, as Lattimore says, starts with Sophocles, but he reads it back, he reads it back into Eschelus.
That's, I don't know why, but is it going to be a pair of a tragedy of character about something wrong with a particular person who has got a flaw and it's always some version of pride or vanity that is their flaw and they will suffer for that and they will learn from their suffering.
That whole picture that they get from Aristotle seeing and reviewing Oedipus is what you see in Latimer, and it's the psychological.
But it just so happens that Aespelus is a lot more different, and for that reason, also, I think, a lot more deep, for both those reasons, a lot more interesting than the tragedies of character, which means a Sophocles to Shakespeare.
But it's hard to get a focus on that because it's alien, just like the strangeness of Homer.
And the humanists, the great books people are always trying to cover up or don't see what's alien because they want to see everything as culminating in the way we see things.
So they can only see things as getting it right insofar as it's what we think, or getting it wrong if it's not what we think.
So let's go back.
But what's really happening, according to the way I read it, and you've got to make up your own minds.
You certainly shouldn't believe me.
I mean, a brilliant paper would be one that showed that I was completely wrong and that Latimer had it right all along.
I'd be amazed.
I would learn a lot.
Anyway, as I see it, Clytemnestra is trying to get the chorus, which are the citizens, on her side, so that when she kills Agamemnon, instead of coming after her and Aegisthus, as tyrants and enemies of people, they will look on them as heroes because it was Agamemnon who was a brutal, selfish, vain, prideful guy, and they're the heroes because they got rid of him.
So the question is, and Latimer sort of buys what Clytemnestra is saying, and that is that Agamemnon, quoting Vladimer, is a swollen vanity, and he talks about his fatal pride.
So that you've got to look and see.
And I said last time, if you look and see, you see, I'm not going to go over the details, that Agamemnon is the sweetest, most modest, most trusting, good guy you could imagine.
He doesn't want to walk on the fancy family tapestry, but he doesn't want to cross the will of Clytemnestra either.
He's kind of a little bit of a too submissive husband.
She wins that battle, which costs him a lot, his life, in effect, as to who's going to walk on the carpet.
He's too trusting that instead of coming home like Odysseus and sort of sniffing out what's going on, asking at least somebody, maybe the watchman or the swineherd, what's up here, so he could at least know that Clytemnestra has married Aegisthus.
And it's not going to be simple for him to just walk in.
He's so trusting, he just says, hello, dear, I'm home, and gets ready to walk into the palace.
And then they kill him.
And the interesting thing is that they say of him that he is the nicest guy.
I've lost that quote again.
That's amazing.
No, 82, I think.
I was looking for it last time.
I couldn't find it.
But I did find it.
It's important.
I found the quote where it says that he's a hero, but that's not as good a quote as the one on 82.
I'd have to jump ahead, but I'm going to read it now.
They're saying this after they find out that she's killed him.
But that's the same day.
It isn't as if, as Latimer tries to think, well, now that he's been dead a long time, they like him, even though they saw that he was a swollen vanity.
They just say on this important line, on 82, it would be about 1,452.
So the chorus says, I'll start a little earlier, oh, that can speed without pain, and this slow bed of sickness, death could come to us now, death that forever carries sleeping without ending.
And why are they so upset that they want to die?
They say, now that our Lord is down, our shield, kindest of men.
That's Agamemnon.
It certainly doesn't seem that he is a brutal monster.
There is something weird that happens when he kills a Phijania.
I'll come back to that later.
And Dave was mentioning it.
And that's the one moment when he does not seem to be asleep guy.
And remember that he couldn't have done anything that was the right thing to do.
Because if he did kill Ophiginia, that's pretty awful.
And Clytemnestra will never forgive him.
And if he doesn't kill Clytemnestra, they're stuck on all this, and they'll either starve or go home.
And his soldiers will never forgive him.
And he'll have failed in his job as king and failed in his oath to his brother Menelaus.
So we know that he's stuck.
So there is nothing I said last time anywhere that suggests the pride-following vanity story.
And then a student comes up to me and finds a line that looks like it refutes, oh, I was bothered to say yesterday and now, which is terrific that somebody should find such a line.
And you'll see in a minute, sometimes when you find these seemingly contradictions to what your interpretation, if you follow them up in another translation, you can find out that they really support it.
Well, anyway, let's look at the line and see what happens on page 95.
So this time the chorus is saying, having talked a lot about pride at the bottom of 94, and it all seems to be the pride to begin with, anyway, of the blood in the house going way back to the horrible scenes between Thaestes and Atreus.
But anyway, at about line 80, it says, and yet under veils I weep the vanities that have killed my Lord, and so forth.
Well, that sounds like, at least first reading, that my Lord is certainly Agamemnon.
And the vanities that kill Agamemnon must have been his vanities, whose else?
And there you got it, you might think.
The tragic form that the humanists expect.
There's a guy whose pride or vanity made him do things, according to Clytemnestra, kill his daughter and a lot of other young men in a, which he thinks is a stupid war.
Anyway, there's stuff that made him do things that resulted in his death.
And I think, wow, then, and it sounds psychological.
It sounds like there's something wrong with him, his pride.
It's not something wrong, keep in the background.
Is there something wrong with a person or is there something wrong with the culture?
I said that last time, and I'll come back to that.
Here it looks like there's something wrong with him.
So you've got to look up the translations.
And the two that I found, and the most, one was, I weep the vain fortune of my master.
There's nothing there about vanity.
I mean, vain fortune means unfortunate.
All this in vain, you say, which doesn't mean that anybody's got any vanity involved in it.
Or the best translation, the literal translation in the Harvard version, which is Greek and literal translation side by side, says, I weep the foul undoing of my Lord.
So what is it?
It's Lattimore cheating.
He's switching around the translation.
I don't know whether he's lying or whether he just is so deep in his vanity story he can't see the Greek.
But apparently, I've checked it out now with somebody who reads Greek too.
There isn't any talk of the vanities that killed Agamemnon.
There's the talk of what a bad thing it was that Agamemnon got killed.
The foul undoing.
That's Clytemnestra, the foul undoing of Agamemnon.
So you never know.
Sometimes you win and sometimes you lose.
I won.
Lattimore is dead wrong, and he's fighting to cover it up.
And if you're reading carefully and reading only his translation, he'll fool you into thinking that he got it right.
So, but Agamemnon has gone out of his way to show, I mean, I think this ought to be convincing.
It convinces me.
Agamemnon has gone out of his way to show, sorry, what am I saying?
Aeschylus has gone out of his way to show that Agamemnon is a good man, a good king, a good warrior.
The only thing that there is some question about is whether he's a good father, and we will come back to that.
But he has to show, why does he want to do that?
Well, he wants to show that Agamemnon was a model king.
And I got it wrong here.
Okay, my notes are all mixed up.
But what Aeschylus wants to show, he was a model king, and that from the point of view of the sky gods, he did everything right.
And that he was a bad father in the sense of the furies, that is on the side of the emotions.
He did everything wrong.
I mean, it's a terrible thing, it looks like, to kill your daughter.
And so, but the real problem can't be that he had a tragic flaw.
His problem was that the culture had two conflicting frames of justice, and that he was caught between them.
He couldn't do the right thing where the daughter was concerned.
There was no one right.
And so the choices that he had were restricted by the cultural background.
That's the ontological part.
He's not a free, he's a free person.
Psychologically, he can make either of those choices.
There's nothing that forces him to kill Figinia.
He could equally not, he could refuse to do it and fail as a king.
He has a choice.
But what a choice.
I mean, very narrow, very restricted, and all bad.
But it's not a question of psychological freedom.
It's the culture that's put him in a situation in which, even though he can choose freely, he can't choose well, or he can't choose to do something good.
And that's the ontological problem that Aeschylus is interested in.
Now, the background, the culture can constrain the choices of the people in it.
Remember, every time I say this, I feel it's very important to keep repeating, what's the phenomenon?
Is this some spooky thing that Aeschylus is onto or that they were involved in 500 BC?
And we don't have that ontological kind of tragic problem anymore.
And I'm going to say, no, you see it with women still, that the culture constrains their free choices and makes in some cultures all the choices bad.
You see it with, you saw it when the Native Americans were before Martin Luther King came and somewhat straightened things out.
You see it in many cultures for gays, less now.
But in all those cases, you see, it's not psychological.
There's not something wrong with the particular people who are women or gay or black.
There's something wrong with the culture that makes it all a tragic situation to be black or woman and so forth.
And that's not because their character, their pride, their choice, or anything else.
It's not about them, people.
It's about the practices, the background, the culture, the values, however you want to describe it.
And so that's what we've got.
And that's what Latmore doesn't see.
Let's see where we are.
So back to this again.
So how does the culture constrain what's going on?
Well, and again, try to think of the phenomena, not just the strange words.
So whatever Agamemnon does in that culture, it's going to be a disaster.
Well, why?
Because though he's free to kill the daughter or not, but if he kills, let's see, what happens?
I jumped over something, but let me say it.
If he kills Ophiginia, then Plyton Nesper is going to be furious.
This is a statement about the culture, but it's just also a statement about emotions.
And he's not going to be able to live with her.
She's going to hate him, even if she doesn't literally kill him in the bathtub.
Their life together is over.
And if he doesn't, then he's going to be sort of detested and looked down with contempt by the citizens and by the soldiers and by his brother and by the Trojans and everybody else.
The emotions in both cases are hopeless.
He's going to end up hated and/or despised.
A great choice.
So I just want to say again: the culture's style, the culture's interpretation, the culture's understanding of what it is to be a human being, sort of the, and finally in Heidegger jargon, the culture's understanding of being, is what sets up the tragic situation.
Given the conflict between, and I'll put it one more way, emotions and reason in the culture, which is all very emotional, but also brand new and very enthusiastically rational, given that the result of what anybody does is going to end up suffering.
So back to Lattimore again, one last round of Lattimore.
It isn't, as Lattimore claims, a domestic tragedy.
He's sort of shooting all over the place, not having a clear target.
He's sort of going off with the shotgun to try to find out what the problem is.
So he shows, claims that it's a domestic tragedy, a war tragedy.
This is all on page 10 and 11.
A political tragedy, and a psychological tragedy.
That's the love-hate story he gets to play around in.
And there is something of all that.
He's not hallucinating quite.
But the culture has all these problems in it.
But they're all, those things, the domestic problems, the political problems, the psychological problems, are all symptoms of something deeper.
They're, again, the culture's problems.
And the only way to get out of it would be to change the whole understanding of being.
But the question would be: how would you do that?
And all we know is there's got a lot of, you have to get a lot of suffering going because it's only through suffering that you the good wins out in the end, as the chorus and everybody else says every once in a while.
And by the end of the play, you don't have to trust me or Aeschylus or the chorus.
You have to see the suffering and who suffers and how they suffer and why and why that might bring about a change of world, change of culture.
But that's getting to the third play.
By the way, I forgot to say at the beginning: for next time, read the humanities.
Don't let me spoil the plot next time.
You, as the Greeks, should be on the edge of your seat wondering how in the world they're going to get out of this mess or whether they ever could get out of this mess.
And in fact, maybe they can't get out of this mess.
Cassandra, this is a little aside, but I think it's interesting, thinks that nothing could ever change the understanding of being.
Prophets are not people who predict things, prophets in Homer and prophets in Aeschylus.
But prophets are people who understand deeply what's going on and the understanding of being in the culture, what the culture really is committed to.
And if the culture is committed to some very bad understanding of being, like, say, in South Africa or apartheid or in India, the untouchables or something, then prophets will be in touch with how much trouble and suffering that's going to cause.
So on 72, Cassandra, who's a prophetess, she's been named that by Apollo, and there's a whole side story in here that she refuses to sleep at Apollo.
Is that why she gets cursed with her?
Beatrice, you probably remember, don't you?
What happens between Cassandra and Apollo?
Oh, good, good.
Oh, that.
Oh, I was worrying about the sort of gossip in the background about why did he make her a prophet so nobody would believe.
Did he sleep with her or she refused, I believe?
I think what happened?
She had a child?
Oh, she refused to have a child with Apollo.
I see.
Okay, anyway, it doesn't matter.
When I say it doesn't matter, I mean if Aeschylus decides not to talk about it, that's because Aeschylus thinks it doesn't illuminate the tragic structure he's interested in.
But he does show us a Cassandra who is a perfect example of a prophet in that she understands deeply what's going on.
She understands it so deeply, and that's sort of interesting, that she sees that nobody could fix it, that it's not a psychological problem.
This seems to contradict what I just said, that enough suffering can fix it.
She doesn't see that.
So you have to see who's right, me or Cassandra this time.
But the middle of 72, she says, there is a choir that sings as one that shall not again leave this house, ever.
That's what I think is interesting.
If you think that the trouble of the Furies and the whole revenge culture, which is one way to put the problem, or the whole emotion reason conflict, is in the very structure of the understanding of being of the culture, then you think that they're going to be stuck with it forever.
And that's what she feels, being a prophet.
They'll never leave the house.
The song breaks the song thereof breaks harsh with menace and drugged to a double fury on the wine of men's bloodshed, there lurks forever.
See, she's really, he's on this sort of special dimension.
You couldn't say that sort of thing about any just normal events.
Normal events, you can predict them, and they might happen, and they might not happen, but the forever level, that's got to do with the very structure of life in that culture.
So she says there lurks forever here a drunken route of ingrown, vengeful spirits never to be cast forth.
She's very clear about that.
Hanging above the hall, they chant their song of hate, the old sin, and taking up the strain in turn spit curses on the man that spoiled his brother's bed.
That's Atreus seducing the wife of Diestes.
Now, what's interesting, and I don't even really, you don't have to know this, and you may not even understand it, but I think it's fascinating.
If the prophetess, or prophet, let's just say, is on to the understanding of being in the culture, then naturally they're going to be right about the most basic things.
And they're going to be able to predict that they're going to stay that way forever.
And they're not in the business of predicting particular events like who's going to win the Trojan War or not, and so forth.
But, and this is the funny part, if they're interested, if prophetesses apparently can't understand that the understanding of being could change.
That's what she doesn't see.
She, because it might be possible somehow, though we don't have any clue yet how, to change the culture if there's enough suffering and you suffer in the right way.
And all the examples I gave you of the fate of women, gays and blacks and so forth, suggest that even the most awful cultures might well change.
But anyway, she only prophesies by predicting something so deep that it looks to her like it can't change.
And if it can, it's some news that Aeschylus is going to give us that she doesn't have.
And that's all I want to say about that right now.
But I think it's really fascinating what prof what prophets can and can do on this kind of Heideggerian ontological picture.
Okay, now we're still here and on what happened with something that bothers me.
I'm sorry to tell you, but there's an argument I want to make about Clytemnestra one more, and then I'll know where I am.
Somehow, I skipped it.
Just a second.
Ah, yes, I've got to way back at the beginning.
Evidence against the pride-vanity view is piling up after the murder because Clytemnestras went all this trouble to try to set up the Agamemnon and get the chorus on her side.
And the interesting, and she told about how bad he was and how he stepped on the carpet and so forth.
And the interesting question you have to ask yourself is: did she convince the chorus?
And the interesting thing is, it's hard to see things that aren't there.
But that is, you've got to be sensitive to what doesn't happen sometimes.
What doesn't happen is that the chorus makes any reference to all of her arguments against Agamemnon.
They say, remember, now we're on 82 again, our Lord is down, our shield, kindest of men.
So it didn't work.
Agamemnon only convinced Latimer.
Clytemnestra.
She did and didn't convince the chorus, and we weren't supposed to be convinced.
It turns out that it's just a false case she's made against Agamemnon, and then, therefore, she hasn't succeeded in justifying the murder.
And on 85, that's where the talks about him as they call him the great man.
I mentioned that quote last time.
So that's it.
I just skipped a little thing that I wanted to go back and get.
Now I'm ready to go on.
But before I do, yes.
Well, I don't know.
Ah, good question.
Well, how does she predict?
Where is it?
Let's look at it.
Oh, yeah, okay, yes.
I worried about that.
Let me go back and read it and see what I thought.
About a third of the way down.
We too must die, she and Clytemnestra, Cassandra and Clytemnestra.
Yet die not vengeless by the gods, for there shall come one to avenge us also, born to slay his mother and to wreck death for his father's blood.
That means he's going to kill Clytemnestra for having killed Agamemnon.
Outlaw and wanderer, driven far from his land, he will come back to cope these stones of inward hate.
For this is a strong oath sworn by the high gods, and he shall cast men headlong for his father fell.
Now, when I read that, we have to talk about it, I say, that's right.
That follows from the deep understanding in the culture that the Furies are going to send Orestes back to kill Clytemnestra, and moreover, he's going to do it.
But is that going to get them out of the curse?
No, it's not going to get them out of the curse.
As you will see at the end of the libation bearers, I would have to jump ahead.
She fails, she doesn't predict, unless there are other lines that I'm missing, she doesn't predict that when Orestes comes back and revenges his father, that that's going to stop the curse on the house of Acreus.
No, that's just one more stage.
Then somebody's going to kill Orestes for doing that.
I don't know who, when I think about it, I can only think Orestes is going to have to kill himself.
But in fact, it gets a more peculiar twist in the third play.
But we're not there yet.
But anyway, I stick to my story.
She gets it wrong.
And she gets it wrong in a deep, interesting, necessary way.
The prophet's got to get it wrong.
Okay, I'm back to this.
So I've got an aside to remind you.
I'm still reviewing, but now a transition to the libation bearers.
We really haven't got there yet.
Remember now, and I said it, but it's hard to keep track, that there seems to be one big bunch of furies, and they get assigned to certain people.
And I just want to say, and then you get Clytemnestra's Furies on one side of things, and Agamemnon's Furies on another side of things, and so on, and so forth.
And you wonder, well, which side of things are the Furies on?
Well, the Furies aren't on any particular side.
They are against anybody who killed any relatives.
They are against anybody who killed anybody, any bloodshed, because they then stir up the relatives of the person who was killed to go back and revenge.
They're just the revenge emotions, period.
But it's important to know that they aren't any sort of particular people's emotions until they get assigned to particular people.
And that sounds like a crazy thing to say, but I'll explain it.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
I like that.
Yeah.
Okay, well, a good question.
How do they, how come the furies dispute among themselves?
Well, that's because it's very important.
Emotions lead to contradictions.
It's like you take a cab and I take a cab.
Now you've got your cab and I've got my cab, and they crash into each other and start to fight with the cab drivers or something with each other.
The furies that get assigned to Figinia crash into the furies that get assigned to who?
Well, let's see, Ephigenia's blood.
It's a very bad case with the furies.
Her furies really get represented by Clytemnestra.
She says she represents her furies.
But anyway, so Ephigenia's furies, by way of Clytemnestra, are attacking Agamemnon.
Now, listen to this.
This is where your question comes in.
But Orestes' furies are telling him that he has to attack Clytemnestra's furies because Clytemnestra with her furies has killed Orestes' father.
So now Orestes sort of jumps in his cabin, gets his furies out of the pool of furies.
What does that mean?
He gets all emotional and vengeful against Clytemnestra.
And when you put that in fury language, that means that his furies now are leading him to attack Clytemnestra and her furies.
And that's just the way the emotions work.
That's why the culture is in a complete mess.
Yeah.
What's that?
I couldn't hear you.
Apollo.
Wow.
Well, that is a super question.
That question almost made me give up teaching this book.
And it leads to the absolute heart of what's going on in the libation bearers.
I don't know whether to try.
I think I can't even try to answer it yet.
But we're coming there soon.
But you're thinking of the first speech where Apollo sort of sticks the furies onto tells Orestes that the furies require that he kill Clytemnestra.
Now, what's Apollo doing in that?
Put it aside.
It's really wonderful and mysterious, and the whole way the libation bearers works, it took me, I don't know, 10 or 20 years to some TA named John Holbo, we have to put something in his honor, found out what's going on there.
I'll tell you in a minute.
Let's just do the general thing first.
People in the play, listen, emotions are always someone's emotions.
That's what I'm saying to him.
But, and now I just want to again save you from Latimer.
At least that's my version.
Because I say you could save him if you can.
Latimer thinks emotions are private people's sort of kinky emotions, like Freudian emotions.
That is, emotions of individual love and hate, and you hate your sibling maybe, or somehow you hate your father, or I don't know why, all kinds of individual stuff that you have to go to a therapist and get your psyche, that psychology straightened out.
But the emotions in this play are individuals' emotions, all right.
Critomestra has her furies and Agamemnon's, but they are, in a sense, public emotions, since they're the emotions that anybody would feel in that situation.
That's so different than modern subjective emotions.
I mean, somebody has some kind of trauma in psychology, and you have your way of acting to it, and that gives you your special kinky personality, and I have a different way of acting to mine, different trauma.
It's not like that at all.
Everybody reacts with the same way.
And the issue of love and hate, which is a modern psychological sort of issue, only comes up minimally in the relation between Orestes and his mother.
His mother, I mean, Clydemnestra tries to play on his love, and the furies try to tell him to hate, but it's not an individual sort of family psychological story.
He has a reason to hate her that anybody would hate their mother if they did.
They know she killed his father.
And she has a reason to hate Agamemnon that anybody would have if of their husband, if the husband killed their child.
So it's a very peculiar kind of emotion.
It's somebody's particular emotion, somebody's particular love or hate, but it's always the same sort of love or hate that in that culture, in that situation, anybody would have.
See, that's what some modern therapist wouldn't say.
Everybody's very unique in their form of neurosis once you get into the private subjective side of things.
Okay, I just had to say that.
Now, and so people are just, again, people do have their own emotions.
So my hatred, my love, and so forth.
And I can contrast with Apollo.
Nobody says my Apollo or my daughter's Apollo, the way they say my daughter's furies, Kaiden has to say.
And that's because, remember, Apollo is universal reason.
He's totally detached from the situation.
It isn't as if Apollo stands for some sort of emotion that everybody in the culture has and understands.
He stands for not getting involved in having emotions, which in this new culture, everybody is beginning to find very interesting and will eventually lead to theory and science and being a detached observant and disinterested and so forth, which our culture has and perhaps no other culture does.
But so already you can see there's a big opposition.
Yeah.
Wait, wait, let's find it.
Well, let me look.
I want to know whether we should wait or not.
Okay.
Where?
Okay, 985.
Good, good, yes, my father who sees all the sun, sees all, comma, the sun.
Yeah, it is too far.
Let's wait.
That's what you wanted to point out.
That's right.
Apollo, like the sun, sees everything from nowhere, so to speak, and has no perspective, no involvement, and not, and unlike emotions, which are always somebody's and from some perspective, even though they are always public, too.
Apollo isn't even emotional at all.
Okay, now I'm ready for the libation bearers.
We got just time to do it.
But the crucial question, as the audience sort of goes into the libation bearers, well, I think, I'm sorry, there's one more move that Aeschylus makes before that that I want to say.
On page 86, you get the end of the Agamemnon.
The chorus sees that this looks like this is going to go on forever, anger for anger.
Whoever watch shall pay.
That's the law, and so forth.
But Clytemnestra, this is just, in Aeschylus, you get constant reversals of what looks like is going to happen next doesn't happen next.
Right now, the reversal is Clytemnestra, happily, and sort of self-interestedly, thinks that now, thank goodness, the curse is over.
There are not going to be any more killings now that she's killed Agamemnon.
For one thing, there's nobody left in the house of Atreus that Agistas, but she doesn't think about that.
Just read it.
So you see truth in the future at last, that I wish to seal my oath with the spirit in the house.
Those are the furies.
I will endure all things as they stand now, hard though it be.
Hereafter, let him, that should be it, remember the prepositions are funny, let it or her, it's the furies, let, let's say it, go forth to make bleed with death and guilt the house of others.
That is, we're done with this problem.
If there's going to be murders and revenges, they're not going to be in the Atreus household anymore.
And that's it.
It looks like she declares that it's over.
I thought maybe there was one more place that she declared it's over.
No, that's it.
It's clearly not over.
And they're hoping at the end that Orestes will come and fix it.
Okay, now we're ready for the libation bearers.
So the question, and I've got to say it this, I'm going to say this over and over because it's so hard to read the libation bearers.
For years, I couldn't make any sense of it at all.
Because the chorus goes from reasonableness to raving of furious upsetness back to reasonableness.
Apollo, as he says, and rightly goes around and gets the furies on his side.
It looks incomprehensible.
But I can't even tell you quite yet what's going on, but we're getting close.
So, and the audience should be on the edge of their seats, even though they've seen it every year for years because it won the ultimate Oscar for its year and gets performed every year.
They still are on the edge of their seats because there's such an interesting, deep thing going to happen.
So, here's the question you're going to have in mind: In what way is Orestes going to commit this murder?
Killing, killing, you have to say, something neutral.
They all know that Orestes is going to come back and kill Clytemnestra because that's required.
And that's now listen, that's important.
Required both by the Furies, because she killed his father and therefore a blood relative, and required by Apollo, because she killed a king and just killed a human being.
It's just against moral reason to let her go.
She would be sentenced by any court, and she would be killed in any revenge killing.
So they know that they know that Orestes is going to come back and kill her.
And maybe I should read that, just so you know that.
They're asking, saying that he's going to come.
Maybe I can't find it.
Oh, yeah, here it is.
Yeah, at the bottom is 88.
Horace says, But why, why then, you coward, could you not have slain your man yourself?
Who's oh, Aegisthus.
They're upset that Aegis didn't kill Agamemnon instead of making his wife do it.
Agamemnon's wife, but why must it be his wife who killed, to curse the country and the gods within the ground?
That is, by the way, mistranslated.
That sounds like the Furies.
It's really neutral.
To curse the gods of the land.
So everybody's upset.
the high gods and the low gods.
And then the one I wanted to read, oh, can Orestes live?
Be somewhere in sunlight still.
Shall faithful and gracious ever bring him back again to strengthen in strength of hand to overwhelm these murderers?
Okay, that's why I wanted to read that because now we're ready.
And the question is, when he comes back and when he kills Clytemnestra, which they are confident he will do, does he do it in the name of the Furies, in which case the culture of revenge goes on and on?
Or does he do it in the name of Apollo, which it looks to them, and in a way rightly, would stop the culture of revenge?
So everything depends on in the name of which of these forces, the traditional old blood revenge forces, the Furies, or the new rational, legal law justice forces, is he going to do it?
And we're going to be on the edge of our seats for a long time to find out.
Will he do it as the heir to the throne?
I'm going to read this, killing a usurper, an accomplice who murdered the king, so that the impartial, so that impartial justice is done in the light of Apollo?
Or will he kill as a son, killing the murderer of his father, so that vengeance is done in the name of his father's furies?
Is this going to be an impersonal or a personal killing?
Is he going to kill the father or the king?
Is he going to act in the name of the Furies or Apollo?
That's the first question you've got to ask.
The second question you've got to ask is, and will it work?
Does he do something that can end the furies and save the culture?
And last time I taught this, some student was very upset and annoyed, and rightly.
How could some individual save and transform the whole culture?
Isn't that psychological?
Isn't that unplausible?
Well, maybe.
You've got to keep your eyes open.
Does he or doesn't he manage to save the whole culture?
All that's up for grabs at this point.
So now we can understand where Orestes is coming from.
I'm skipping something earlier just as I don't want to read all of them.
So the question is: is Orestes doing it in wrath or in reason?
At the bottom of, at the top of 97, he says, the chorus, Electra says, to come to judge them, that's the law, or to give them punishment.
I take it that's vengeance.
And the chorus is simply one to kill them for the life they took.
The chorus says, don't take sides, stay ambiguous, don't do it in the name of Apollo or the Furies.
That's not going to work.
And then what happens?
Well, you'll see.
So, one more way to put it: Orestes has too many motives.
That is, he's got so many reasons for doing it that it's going to be hard to tell what his reasons are.
It isn't exactly like reasons.
That sounds too rational.
And it isn't exactly like desire.
That sounds too psychological.
There's something like that again, these public motives that he has.
And the public motives are that he's got, he can do it as a son, he can do it as a subject of the king.
And so, but this is the bottom of 103, the very bottom.
He says, Here, numerous desires converge to drive me on.
I would say something like motives, but it doesn't matter much.
The gods' urgency, that's Apollo.
My father's passion, that's the furies.
And these, the loss of my estates, wear heavily on me.
Well, the loss of his estates gets dumped.
I mean, that is not interesting.
That was interesting to Homer, and that was a big problem for Telemeters.
But it's not a problem for Orestes.
He's got a life and death problem.
Never mind his estates.
He's got to be able somehow to manage to kill Clytemnestra without getting killed himself, getting to get out of the contradictions.
So now we have to see: can he do that?
Now comes your question.
What, as I say, kept me from wanting to teach this and sort of stopped me for a long time on having the interpretation I've been giving you is what Orestes says when he comes in at the top of 103.
He's just coming.
He says something.
He appeals.
He asks Zeus to be on his side.
But whenever you get Zeus on your side, it doesn't mean anything because he's behind everything.
So you've got to keep track always not of whether it's Zeus, but whether it's the Furies or Apollo.
But now, you ought to be able to tell whether it's the Furies or Apollo.
And here's the puzzling thing.
The big strength of Apollo's oracle will not forsake me.
When the oracle speaks, of course, the oracle speaks for Apollo.
So don't let that bother you.
For he, I would have thought the oracle was a woman.
I wonder if this is gender verb again.
The oracle of Apollo at Delphi is a woman, right?
I wonder if, anyway, let's not worry about that.
For he charged me to win through with divine, with divination and so forth, and speech articulate.
And never mind all that fancy talk.
Skip down about 10 lines.
He said, and that's oracle Apollo, that else I must pay penalty with my own life and suffer much sad punishment.
Spoke of the angers that come out of the ground, the furies.
And what's Apollo doing talking about them?
For those beneath who turn against men, spoke of sickness, ulcers that ride upon the flesh and cling, and with wild teeth eat away the natural tissue.
That's one of the things the furies can do to you.
I think that's interesting, sort of psychosomatic talk.
It just occurs to me.
This says that if you have bad enough emotions, it'll actually show up in your body, and you'll have ulcers, and you'll have, I don't know, every bad thing will happen to you.
They'll eat away the tissue, you'll become leprous.
He spoke of other ways again from which the Avengers, who are the avengers?
No, come on.
I won't talk unless you're listening.
Who are the Avengers?
Who believes in vengeance?
The Furies.
Apollo is only talking about Furies.
The Avengers might attack, brought to fulfillment from my father's blood, to the dark arrow of the dead men underground, from those within my blood who fell and turned to call upon me madness and empty terror in the night.
Okay, all of that is Apollo telling Orestes that he'd better go kill Clytemnestra because otherwise Clytemnestra's furies will get him.
And why is Apollo doing it?
And why?
It's the same question.
As you read the chorus speeches, you'll see, I'll give you examples, the chorus alternates back and forth between getting all furious and excited and revengeful and telling Orestes to run in there and stab his mother, cut her throat, she's a monster, talk.
And then they switch over as if they don't know what they're talking about and say, now be cool.
We wanted all this to be done in the most detached and fair way that you could possibly do it.
I thought I would find you a quote like that, but we'll get there eventually.
And how is this possible?
How is it?
Why is it true that Apollo has to bring in the Furies and that the chorus has to switch back and forth?
Well, the secret is that Orestes, besides Aeschylus, has a principle which is very, very original and sort of enlightenment interesting.
He thinks that all motivation, that the only reason anybody ever does things is from emotional reason, a not unreasonable idea.
And that if you were a completely disinterested, rational, detached observer like Apollo, you'd never have any reason for doing anything.
And this was an interesting problem for the Enlightenment.
It helps to know that.
The Enlightenment was all for rationality, but there was sort of the bad boy of the Enlightenment, one very smart philosopher who didn't believe it.
And that was David Hume.
And David Hume wrote a book, treated on human nature.
You don't have to know this, but it's so perfect for what we're talking about.
David Hume says that reason is the slave of the passions.
What he means by that is exactly what's happening in the play: that is, you can't do anything except on the basis of your emotions.
And reason will go along with whatever your emotions tell you.
Your reason will rationalize it, and then you'll be able to do it.
And this so much upset Kant, who you've been hearing about as the main Enlightenment guy, he read Hume, and he thought that was terrible.
I mean, rationality is supposed to be the guiding thing.
So Kant made up a rational emotion.
In German ochtum, which you've heard the word, it means respect in this.
He thought, he said, people are attracted to do the ethical thing and moved to do the ethical thing just because it's the rational, ethical thing.
And any other kind of emotion would just get in the way.
And what Aeschylus would say about that is rubbish.
There is only the only kind of emotion, there is no such thing as the rational emotions, Aeschylus thinks.
There's only the kind of emotions that the furies are representing, the kind of emotion that goes with outrage and revenge and so forth.
You don't hear in this play about other kinds of emotions, not Kantian octum for the respect, that gets translated respect for the moral law.
You don't hear about, as you will, when by reading the Aeneid in a week, Aeschylus, Aeneid talking constantly about his duty.
You don't feel that people there do things for duty, not for just simple reasons and not for emotions either.
You don't find anybody in this book talking about doing things out of Christian love, where your sort of God's love goes through you to other people and so forth.
There's only one kind of emotion, and that's something like outrage and other such extreme emotions drive people to do things.
Now you can understand two things.
Why Apollo calls on, tells Orestes not do it out of duty for me, do it out of respect for the moral law.
There are no such talk.
He says, if you don't do it, the Furies will get you, because that's the only way to motivate somebody.
But now you also see why the Course talks nonsense all the time in a deep, deep way.
I hope you see it already.
The Furies want to motivate Orestes to kill Clytemnestra with total Apollonian detachment, fairness, legality, and so forth.
But that's a kind of contradiction.
They can't, on this Aeschylus picture that reason is the slave of the passions and so forth, get Orestes to do it for anything but moral outrage.
But if they ask, if they get Orestes to do it for more outrage, then what happens?
The curse continues, and everything is completely messed up.
So what happens is the chorus, you read it carefully, and you'll see, and I read it carefully and for a long time now I couldn't see it.
But once John Holbo said it, I see it, and I'll show you.
But the chorus constantly wants to get Orestes more and more and more and more upset, telling him how what a nice father he has, what a monster mother he has, what a duty, not duty's the wrong word, how the furies require that he kill Clymnestra till he gets foaming at the mouth furious to do it.
And then they switch and they become cool and rational.
And they tell him in effect, but don't do it when you're upset.
Do it when you're calm.
I have to find one of these quotes.
Where is it?
In the libation bearers, early on.
Well, I know that if I just follow what I've written, I will get there eventually.
So I better just wait till I get there.
Okay.
They want him to do it, and the word is in the translation, temperately.
Don't do it in an emotional fit.
But then if you get all temperate, you won't do it at all.
So the mystery is in the play.
How in the world, and this is what you should be looking for as you read it or reread it, how can they ever solve this problem of getting Orestes to get all enough, enough emotional to kill his mother?
I mean, that isn't just any old emotional.
That isn't as emotional as you have to get to, I don't know, steal something or hit somebody.
He's supposed to stare his mother in the face and slit her throat.
I mean, that's very, very, very hard to do.
They have to get him so emotionally upset about the death of his father that he's capable of doing it.
And they have to get him cool enough that he can do it not in the name of his father, but in the name of law and justice and kingship.
And you'd think that would be impossible.
And Aeschylus pulls off a sort of trick to show how it happens.
And the trick is kind of interesting.
You watch and see how it's done.
But it's a cliffhanger till the last moment whether he can look and sold.
But now we have to follow it in detail.
Yeah.
No, I'm just, I'm sorry, I couldn't hear you.
No, no, wait.
He's asking something that I don't understand why you would ask it yet, but let me repeat it.
Don't the Furies want him to use, do kill Clytemnestra in the name of Apollo?
Why would they want that?
But you don't understand.
I see.
Yes, he's right, of course.
If they do it in the name of the Furies, if he does it, it's going to go on with the cycle of revenge.
But that's the Furies' business.
They love the cycle of revenge.
They just thrive on it.
They're bloody, and they're bloody, they're blood drinkers, and the more revenge killings, the better.
So they want him to do it in the name of Agamemnon.
There's no contradiction there.
And Apollo, it's only Apollo.
And he's in this funny position.
I'll just repeat it.
It's Apollo's problem, too.
He wants him to do it in free, temperate, rational, legal way.
But he has nothing at his disposal to make them, to give him the emotional outrage or the emotional push to do it, because all emotional pushes come from the furies.
That's the problem.
So now let's the only way that you can see how this works is to follow it through now, and that's what we're going to do.
So let me see now.
I keep getting ahead of myself.
Okay, so Apollo's told him that.
There we are.
Then I talked about the enlightenment.
I had this phrase here, which is interesting.
He has to work himself up to do it.
And that working himself up to do it, that can only be done by the emotions.
And that's the trick.
But if he works himself up to do it and does it by the emotions, of course, then the whole thing is a disaster because they, just as Cassandra would predict, they stay inside the cycles of revenge.
So I don't know exactly who's going to revenge whom after that because we don't have to worry about that.
So Apollo uses the furies and so forth.
So the chorus speeches are very confused, but it's a necessary confusion.
It's a confusion which is part of the whole tragic situation.
And they start out calm, and they get more and more emotionally worked up.
But then, just when the deed is close at hand, when they finally have worked up Orestes to such a state that he's ready to rush in and cut his mother's throat, then they try to get control of themselves and him so that everything will become rational.
And so let's see now.
The best plan I've written here, if you could do it, would be for Orestes to be motivated by the furies, worked up until the last moment, when he suddenly becomes cool and does the deed in the name of Apollo.
And damn, but how could that happen?
Well, how many have read it already?
How many know how that happens?
What happens?
Okay, go ahead.
I don't need to know.
I don't want you to tell me what happens.
Anyway, we get ahead of the story.
Go ahead.
Yeah?
Okay, we're going to get there.
I'll say it now, but it's more fun in context.
He means that you brought her on yourself.
I didn't care.
I'm only, the translation is bad.
He says, no, where is it?
126?
The middle.
Yeah, I see.
Yes.
Okay, yes.
You, I'm not killing you.
I'm only a channel for killing you in the sense that you've done a deed that requires killing, and I'm the one that was required to do it.
So, but it's really you that's forcing me to kill you.
This is a very peculiar argument.
We'll get there.
Do you want to say more about it?
Who's the one in my show that's Barnes Martyr?
Why don't you just see it, you mean?
Oh, that's interesting.
He wants to know why you well, you never see on stage in Greek tragedy the bloody scenes.
It's not like America, current American movies.
Whenever there's a bloody killing, it it's just the tradition, and it shows their sensibility that they're they'd be too upset to see the real, to do it the way Shakespeare did with bags of blood spurting out over the audience, so that the front row of the people were covered with blood when somebody got killed.
That did not appeal to the Greeks.
So it's always, they remember already we've seen it when they killed Agamemnon.
They took him into the palace, and then there were a moan from the palace, and then she comes out and says we just kill him.
So the same is going to happen with Clytemnestra.
When they finally get ready to kill her, Adagisthus, they do it offstage.
And that's just the way they do it.
I think that's terrific.
But we'd be bored.
Yeah, does somebody over there have a hand up?
Okay, let me get further with this.
We will see, because these things will fit into place that you're asking about.
Okay, so let's see now.
So the chorus just starts out hysterical, practically, and stays that way most of the time.
On 104, for instance, they are in their typical mood.
He says, Almighty destinies, let these things be done in the turning of justice.
By the way, justice, of course, well, I don't know what the Furies are saying.
Oh, these aren't the Furies.
Aha, that's what.
What am I saying here?
The Chorus, by the word of hatred.
Oh, yeah, but you see, they understand justice in a fury way.
Remember, the justice and vengeance and right are all defined in context because nobody has, I guess, Aspos doesn't have a vocabulary for saying the difference between justice and somebody getting their just deserts by vengeance, and somebody getting their justice by a court.
So he says, anyway, but you can see that this fury talk because he says, it says, for the word of hatred spoken, let hate be a word fulfilled.
The spirit of right, so right and justice, both of them now have been taken over by the furies.
And spirit is a clue.
The spirit of right cries out aloud and extracts atonement due, blood stroke for the stroke of blood.
So there's no question, but what they mean by justice and right is revenge, shall be paid.
Who acts shall endure?
So speaks the voice of age-old wisdom.
Oh, boy, is that a fury speech?
And they're in a fury mood from the start.
107, I just want to sort of follow it through.
The chorus, the top chorus speech, he says, it says, that it is but law that when the red drops have been spilled upon the ground, they cry aloud for fresh blood.
Well, that can't be Apollo, for sure.
For the death act calls out on fury to bring out of those who were slain, to bring out of those who were slain before new ruin on ruin accomplished.
Yes, that's and they understand that.
And Orestes gets worked up and joins them as he starts talking that language.
Hear me, you lordships of the world below, the furies.
Behold, an assembled power, curses come from the dead, more furies.
Behold, the last of the sons of Acreus, foundering, lost, without future, cast from house to house.
Oh, God, where shall we turn?
So Orestes is, they've got Orestes all upset.
And now, and I'm not going to go through the details because I want to be sure to get to something interesting.
So then Clytemnestra comes on and confronts them.
They confront each other.
And he becomes suddenly, totally rational.
They go back and forth a lot, but I won't do it.
Let's go on to 113.
And now, he's confronting Clytemnestra.
And the interesting thing is, when he finally gets to confronting her, then the furies...
Oh, sorry, then the chorus puts on the brakes, and he puts on the brakes, and everybody tries to become rational.
I'm still looking for this passage I've learned where they say, let everything be done in a temperate way.
I wonder.
I'm going to look one more time.
Wow, 121.
Is that way back there?
Sometimes I'm looking in the wrong places.
Yes, grant that those who struggles, temperate things done in the house, and so forth.
That's right.
Stand above those who hate.
That's the hope.
And I just want to keep that in mind.
And that's what makes him suddenly become rational.
And there's a quote from a person you probably never heard of, a writer named G.K.
Chesterton, who says, the madman is not the man who has lost his reason.
The madman is the man who's lost everything except his reason.
And at this point, he becomes crazy from rationality.
And this is so, it's really funny if you've got that kind of sense of humor.
He's going to kill his mother with syllogisms and counterexamples, as if she were killed by taking sort of an elementary logic course.
You've got to see it to believe it.
Orestes becomes this absurdly logical person confronting his mother.
And he says, she tells he has this dream about the snake that bit her breast, and instead of milk, there was blood.
And he says, as if he was writing a paper in logic at the top of 113, if this snake came out of the place whence I came, if she wrapped it in robes as she wrapped me, and if, and these are all a big bunch of if-thens, and if its jaws gaped right around the breast that suckled me, and if it stained the intimate milk with an outburst of blood, so that for fright and pain she cried aloud, it follows then.
I mean, there it is, just a kind of logical argument that she nursed this hideous thing of prophecy, she must be cruelly murdered.
I turn snake to kill her.
That's what the dream portends.
And then there starts to be a kind of debate after that, which is logical and funny all the time, as if Orestes turns into a star debater.
So it looks like Apollo has won.
So Orestes says in the next speech, three lines down: as they by treachery killed a man of high degree, but not, he doesn't say his father, a man of high degree, the king.
But that's important.
Killed a man of high degree by treachery tangled in the selfsame net, they too shall die in the way that Luxius, remember that's Apollo, has ordained my Lord Apollo, whose word was never false before.
So it looks like somehow, mysteriously enough, he's going to be able to do it in the name of Apollo, but he hasn't actually split her throat yet.
And it's not obvious that he's going to be able to do it.
And he gets emotional when he gets near Aegisthus, because Aegisthus is the part of the blood curse.
So on 114, he gets pulled back into being emotional again.
And back and forth it goes.
And here he says, who's talking?
No, Orestes.
I thought it was the choruses.
It was so emotional.
Before he, that is Orestes, can say, where does the stranger come from?
This is the top of 114.
I shall plunge my sword with lightning speed and drop him dead.
Our fury, who never starved for blood, shall drink for the third time, and so forth.
There he's all inside the revenge story.
That Augustus, you know, is the son of Atreus.
And I'm not going to keep this sound straight.
Theestes.
And so it's just a question of house of Atreus' blood, and he goes into a fury state, but he gets out of it again.
If the question is, how are he going to kill his mother?
And he gets out of it again on 114.
At the end of that speech, he says, and now I call upon the God who stands close to look on and guide the actions of my sword.
That's Apollo.
So having killed Aegisthus in the name of the Furies, he's now going to kill Clytemnestra, which is the important one as far as his furies are concerned, in the name of Apollo.
So it seems.
And I, now, it all seems raving craziness for a while, but as long as you keep your eye on what's going on, you'll see that it's all a question of how he's under, remember, for the sake of what?
How is he going to kill his mother without getting all emotionally upset to do it?
And we've got to see what happens.
So the chorus who's getting nervous about this, because they don't want him to do it in the name of the furies, kill Clytemnestra, that means the curse goes on and the country's in a mess.
So the chorus says at the bottom of 120, now do I supplication, Zeus, father of the Olympian gods.
Aha, this is what I was looking for.
Just what you said.
Grant that those who struggle hard to see temperate things done in the house win their aim in full.
And going on, Zeus, make him who is now in the house stand above those who hate.
So all of a sudden, they're switching over to Apollo and the Zeus side of Apollo, or the Apollo side of Zeus.
Then hatred is bad.
Temperance is just what he needs.
The question is, can he kill his mother?
Can you slit your mother's throat with temperance?
And that's tricky.
Yeah.
And that's 121.
The top of 121.
So now it's, I still want to go further here.
So he just gets, he can kill Augustus.
There's no problem.
And he says that he does it on 128.
Where am I?
About killing Augustus, he says, and on the two-thirds down on 128, so shall my father, but not my father.
He's not going to do it in terms of bring in Agamemnon, but that great father who sees all the sun.
Look on my mother's sacrilegious handiwork and be witness for me in my day of trial, how it was all right that I achieved this death, my mother's.
As for Augustus' death, I take no account.
He was a seducer and he got his punishment and it was legal, no more than law.
So now we're back to the confrontation with the mother, which is the fun part.
And so he confronts his mother, and things get tough.
And now comes the crucial question, but it's not done yet.
Aeschylus has many cliffhangers.
But he turned.
But now this is all the further we're going to get today.
But now comes another funny thing.
Remember, I said there has to be a trick.
Aeschylus needs a trick.
Because the question is: how, at the last minute, having worked himself up to kill his mother by calling on the Furies, is he going to be able to just stop and do it in the name of Apollo with no additional motives?
Now comes a funny question.
You may have wondered, who is this guy, Pallades, who's been following him around for the whole play?
You've got to pay an actor to stand there for a whole play and not say anything.
Well, he's got one line.
And he's got an important position in the play.
Because now, at the very moment when he has to decide what to do with his mother, Orestes hesitates.
He's got the full force of the Furies motivating him, and he's got the full sort of logical power of Apollo telling him, don't do it for the Furies, do it for me.
And he turns to Pallades, who's been there all along, and asks him what to do.
Now, do you see why the cards are stacked if he asks Pylades what to do?
What's Pilates bound to say?
What's his relation to this whole thing?
None.
He's a total spectator.
He's got nothing to do with the problems in the house of Acreus of the blood of who killed who and what bad things Clytemnestri did.
So when he asks Pylades, he gets one sentence, crucial answer.
And where is it?
Tell me where it is.
125.
Philadelphia says, what if, okay, he just says exactly what he has to say to make him do it for the right reasons.
What then becomes of the oracles declared by Alexius, that is Apollo?
What if sworn oaths?
Remember, that's their job, oaths.
Count all men hateful to you rather than the gods.
And Orestes says, completely rational.
I judge that you win.
Your advice is good.
And now he's become totally, insanely rational for the rest of the play, almost the rest of the play.
So first he says, I'm just going to read you this quick, come over, and you can read it on your own.
Come over here.
My purpose is to kill you over his body.
So that's what he says to his mother.
And then they have a debate.
She says, I raised you when you were little.
May I grow old with you.
And he says, you killed my father.
You want to make your home with me?
I don't want to live with you.
And she says, well, destiny has something to do with it, my child.
And he, very cleverly, good debater, says, well, then destiny is so rotted that I'm going to kill you.
No problem.
Then she says, a mother's curse.
Are you not afraid?
And then it comes really interesting.
He says, no, you bore me and threw me away to a hard life.
She sent him away to strangers when he was 11, so that she could have the whole place to her and Augustus.
It's like she sent him away to prep school to get him out of the house.
He says, no, you bore me and threw me out to a hard life.
That is, you're my biological mother, but you're not my psychological, that is, emotional mother.
And she says, I sent you to a friend's house.
It's like I sent you to a good prep school.
That does not make him at all happy.
And then it gets really rational in the middle of the next page.
She says, I think, child, you mean to kill your mother.
It's just becoming crazy.
And he says, it will be you who kill yourself, not I.
That is, you brought it on yourself.
Then she says, it's all perfectly logical.
Take care of your mother's curse like dogs will drag you down.
And he says, How shall I escape my father's curse if I fail here?
And then he says at the bottom, I just want to get the translation right, and we can stop.
He's ready to kill her, and he says, You killed, and it was wrong, now suffer wrong.
He can't mean that.
It says in another translation, you did a terrible thing, now a terrible thing is going to happen to you.
And he drags her off stage and he slits her throat.
Now, we'll stop there.
The question is: has Aeschylus called it off?
The audience is on the edge of their seats.
Did he succeed in doing just what we thought he couldn't do without being motivated by any fury forces, manage in the name of temperate justice, kill his mother?
It looks like it, but we'll see.
Okay.