Okay, now I start by quoting page 526 then, where he's where they're talking about that.
The bottom of 526, we're in the middle of the first chase.
And chapter 133, for those who don't have this one, in the middle, roughly the middle of the chapter, a paragraph that I'm going to read.
Now, by reason of this untimely spinning around, the boat upon its axis, its bow by anticipation, was made to face the whale's head while yet underwater.
But as if perceiving this stratagem, Moby Dick, with that malicious intelligence ascribed to him, silently transplanted himself, as it were, in an instant, shooting his pleated head lengthwise beneath the boat.
And he knocks over the boat and splits it all up through and through and so forth.
And then, let's just read on.
Through and through, through every plank and every rib, it thrilled for an instant the whale lying and so forth and so forth, and slowly and feelingly taking its bows full within his mouth so that the long, narrow, scrolled lower jaw curled high up into the open air as one of the teeth caught in a rock lock.
The bluish pearl white of the inside of the jaw was within six inches of Ahab's head.
So it looks like Ahab's going to get a front eyeball to eyeball or head to head.
Somebody after class was worried about the fact that the eyes on the whale are on the side, but he seems to be able, the whale, to keep somebody in view simply by getting beside them.
The whale can see things on the side.
You can only get one eyeball at a time confrontation, but that doesn't seem to be a problem.
The bluish so-and-so, in this attitude, the white whale now shook the slight cedar as a mildly cruel cat her a mouse.
With unastonished eyes, Fadala gazed and crossed his arm, but the tiger-yellow crew were tumbling over each other's heads to gain the utmost stern.
And it's all this is all this crucial part.
I'll just read it all.
And now, while both elastic gun walls were springing in and out as the whale dallied with the doomed craft in his devilish way, so it looks like he's the this is the malicious intelligence whale, you see.
And from his body being submerged beneath the boat, he could not be darted at from the bows, for they were almost inside him, as it were, and so forth.
Then it was that monomaniac Ahab, I mean, we've heard him called monomaniac by me lots of times.
I don't remember how often or whether already, but he is, of course, monomaniac.
Furious with this tantalizing vicinity of his foe, which placed him all alive and helpless in the very jaws he hated, frenzied with all this, he seized the long bow with his naked hand, long bone, that is, the jaw, with his naked hands, and wily strove to wrench it, to wrench it from its grip, that is, to get the whale to let loose of his boat.
And now he thus vainly, as now he thus vainly strove, the jaw slipped from him, and then everything collapsed and so forth, and things broke into pieces and fell apart.
And Ahab saw what the whale was up to, the next paragraph.
Ahab, first to perceive the whale's intent, loosened his hold for the time.
At that moment, he pushed the boat out of the bite.
But instead, he only slipped further into the whale's mouth, but skipping now to the top of 528, but soon resuming his horizontal attitude, Moby Dick swam softly round and round the wrecked crew, sideways turning the water in his vengeful wake.
So this interpretation has him malicious and angry and toying with them intelligently, as if lashing himself up for still another and more deadly assault.
And round and round, then he swam round and round Ahab, who became the center of things at the next, at the end of that paragraph.
With straining eyes, the men, that is, they, remained on the outer edge of the direful zone whose center had now become the old man's head.
And that's, and then after that, the whale just swam off.
Let's read a little more.
But struggling out again, he shouted, Sail on the whale, drive him off.
The Pequads, so they got the big ship involved.
The Pequad's prows were pointed, and breaking up the charmed circle, she effectively parted the white whale from his victim.
As he sullenly swam off, the boats flew to the rescue.
Okay, there he is, vengeful, sullen, malicious, and so forth, and devilish.
I'm just catching all the things.
And out to get Ahab.
Finally, that they save Ahab by separating the Mobidig from Ahab.
And he swims off sullenly, presumably because his malicious intentions have been frustrated.
And he's annoyed.
All very kind of personified, evil, just what Ahab thought he was.
And in a way, Ahab should be happy about it.
It looks like he's very much concerned about Ahab.
But the second day, we go from malicious intelligence to just awkward intelligence.
And that starts on 536.
By the way, if anybody wants to add anything or say anything, just do it.
There's time to cover the three, and I don't know if I've got all the point or the details of each chase as we do it.
But until you say anything, I will go on.
I'm now on chapter 134, the chase, second day.
And so into that chapter a ways, about halfway, a little more than halfway, I'm going to start reading in the middle of a paragraph that begins while the two crews were yet circling in the waters, reaching out for the oars and so forth.
Well, I guess I should say, where does it happen that Moby Dick must have got rid of their boat again?
They've lowered away for the boat on the previous page.
Though Moby did, so as if to strike the middle of 535, as if to strike a quick terror into them, by this time being the first assailant himself, Moby Dick had turned and was now coming for the three crews.
Ahab's boat was central, and cheering his men, he told them he would take the whale head and head, that is, pull straight up to his forehead, and a not uncommon thing, and so forth and so forth.
But ere that close limit was gained, I'm on 535 below the middle.
And while yet all three boats were plain as the ship's three masts to his eye, the white whale, churning himself into furious speed, almost in an instant, as it were, rushing among the boats with open jaws and lashing tail, offered appalling battle on every side, and heedless of the irons darted at him from every boat, seemed intent on annihilating each separate plank of which those boats were made.
But skillfully maneuvered, instantly wheeling like trained charges in the field, the boats for a while eluded him.
But then finally, we can skip a little, he just starts thrashing around and trashing every boat.
And where shall I start again?
On 536, at the middle of the middle of the bottom paragraph.
Ahab's yet unstricken boat seemed drawn up toward heaven by invisible wires.
He comes at the boat from the bottom.
As arrow-like, shooting perpendicularly from the sea, the white whale dashed his broad forehead against its bottom and sent it turning over and over into the air till it fell again, gun whale downward, and Ahab and his men struggled out from under it like seals from a sea cave.
Now, now becomes the sort of indifference of Moby Dick.
The first unuprising moment of the whale, modifying its direction as it struck the surface, launched him along a little distance from the center of the destruction.
And so he now lay for a moment slowly feeling with his flukes.
I'm at the top of 537 from side to side.
And whenever a stray oar, bit, of plank, or the least crumb or chip of the boats touched his skin, his tail swiftly drew back and came sideways, smiting the sea.
As soon as if satisfied with his work for the time was done, he pushed his pleated forehead through the ocean and trailing after him the intertangled lines, continued his leeward way at a traveler's methodic pace.
Now, so instead of focusing his attention on Ahab this time, Moby destroys all the boats and destroys Ahab's boat last, and then just goes off and doesn't seem to be interested in Ahab.
He seems to be just awkwardly, without knowing what he's hitting, threshing around with his tail.
It doesn't seem that he's meant to do what he did.
Sort of random violence this time.
And after having enough random violence, he just goes away.
Only one important plot thing has happened.
The Farsi is found to be missing.
And the Farsi in the prophecy is going to, it goes, will die ahead of Ahab.
And now the fact that he's missing is very upsetting and important.
He seems to have been dragged under by Moby Dick, pulling Ahab's line.
This confirms the Farsi's prophecy that he would go before Ahab to his death.
So much for the second round.
Now, the third round is of that he's not only sort of awkward, so there was malicious intelligence, then there was this kind of awkward intelligence.
I mean, he seemed to know what he was doing, but it doesn't seem like he's very focused on Ahab or focused on the Pequad when he's doing it.
But he seems to be intelligent because he's satisfied with his work for the time.
That sounds like, well, he wanted to destroy all the boats that he did, and that was that.
So that's what I'm calling awkward intelligence.
But that's not as indifferent as the third one, where he does, and the third one is really the punchline.
I mean, if you're trying to figure out, well, is Ahab going to get a confrontation with him, or is Ahab going to discover that he's indifferent or discover that he's malevolent?
How is Melville going to end this chase thing?
Well, I don't know how many did get there.
How many have got to it?
Not so many.
Okay, well, I have to read the last one now.
The third day is peculiar.
Ahab's now aware that he's doomed because the prediction says that once the Farsi dies, he's going to die afterwards.
But he's still trying to get a personal confrontation because he hasn't had that yet, although he seems always sort of almost to have it.
On page 542, now of chapter 135, the third day of the chase, he says near the beginning, how near?
Two pages in, the paragraph, forehead to forehead I meet thee this third time, Moby Dick, Ahab says.
So now it looks like he's really going to get a confrontation.
And lots of stuff happens.
Then in 548, the whale sort of attacks Ahab's boat.
I'll start at the top of 548.
And when Ahab cried out to the steerman to take new turns with the line and hold it so and commanded the crew to turn around on their seats and tow the boat up to the mark, the moment the treacherous line felt that double strain and tug, it snapped in the empty air.
What breaks in me some sinew cracks, tis hole again, oars, oars, and so forth, burst on.
But then the middle of the next paragraph, what about Moby Dick?
Well, seemingly seeing in it the source of his persecution, bethinking it may be a larger and nobler foe, of a sudden he bore down upon its advancing prow.
The whale turns toward the Pequad now, smiting his jaws amid fiery showers of foam.
Oh, I'm sorry, I knew I missed the crucial line.
That's 547.
He hasn't got to the Pequad yet.
He's getting first, he turns on Ahab.
The paragraph that begins, at length the craft was cast to one side and so forth.
And then Ahab finally throws the harpoon at Moby Dick.
This is the crucial line for that.
He darted his fierce iron and his far fiercer curse into the hated whale.
And then what happens?
All sorts of things happen and people get thrown around.
But I can't find the crucial.
Oh, it hasn't happened yet.
That's why I can't find it.
So on page 550, Ahab gets another chance.
The paragraph that begins, I turn my body from the sun.
He says, Toward thee I roll, though all-destroying but unconquering whale.
To the last I grapple with thee, from hell's heart I stab at thee.
For hate's sake, I spit my last breath at thee.
And then what's going to happen?
I mean, now it's finally got to either, he's either got to confront Moby Dick in an indifferent way or a head-on way and so forth, but none of that happens.
He throws the harpoon.
He says, thus I give up the spear.
Then what happens?
The harpoon was darted.
The stricken whale flew forward.
With igniting velocity, the line ran through the groove, ran foul.
Ahab stooped to clear it.
He did clear it.
But the flying turn caught him around the neck.
And voicelessly, as Turkish mutes bolstering their victim, he was shot out of the boat ere the crew knew he was gone.
And not only did the crew not know he was gone, he didn't know he was gone.
What happens was he gets killed, strangled by Moby Dick without him knowing what happened and without Moby Dick knowing what happened.
It's just a sudden accident that he gets caught in the line and with the rope around his neck gets dragged out of the boat.
It's interesting that Melville has all this in mind.
You notice how much this sounds like the blade of grass as the Turks, Turkish mutes bolstering their victim.
I mean, I guess, I mean, that doesn't help clear it up.
But I mean, it turns out, all I can say is, as indifferent as a mower cuts down a blade of grass, so it looks like Moby Dick kills Ahab, but without any recognition of Ahab as an enemy or without even or indifference, he doesn't even sort of turn around and slim away from Ahab.
He doesn't even know he killed Ahab.
Ahab doesn't know he was killed.
It couldn't be a more meaningless seeming death.
That's the crucial thing for this, I think.
And that's, let's stop with that until I say a little more about it.
So I'm going to go back to the fact that Moby Dick was on his way toward the Pequad, whom he thought when he strangled and dragged along Ahab without even paying any attention to Ahab.
We have to come back to that in a minute.
But first, let's see now.
So this is this: so you're listening, and you hear Ahab say this is his last time to kill Moby Dick head-on, and it turns out Moby Dick kills him in a kind of simple animal panic without knowing that he's done it.
So it looks like indifference is the last version about the universe.
But I think it's important that it's sort of accidentally the last version.
It isn't the truth about the universe.
It's just another perspective.
I mean, among the malicious behavior, the swinging around Ahab behavior, and then there is the killing Ahab without any purpose.
I don't think you're supposed to think that, okay, now we understand there's one right interpretation of the universe as embodied in Moby Dick.
It's indifferent.
That's sort of Camus metaphysics.
And just to take it, I mean, that's, in the plague, Camus, how many read The Plague?
I mean, Camus tells you, and they realize, that the universe is indifferent, period.
That's the right perspective.
I mean, that's the one that counts.
I mean, the priest tries to give another perspective, and the doctor tries to give another perspective.
But it's clear that Camus thinks he knows the answer about this universe.
Well, that's not the Melville thing.
He's not, I think, supposed to be telling you, finally, we see that that's the right one.
That would be a particular interpretation.
That would be a particular color.
That would be a metaphysical, total understanding.
No, that's just the last one.
And that's all you can say about it.
It just still comes out indifferent, but it comes out indifferent in Melville, not as being the right answer, but it being in a way like whiteness.
It seems to be the canceling out of all the answers, so that there is none, no right answer to the question of how we relate to the universe and it relates to us.
That's how, I mean, I'm not sure about this, and if people want to write paper topics better explaining what's going on or taking or disagreeing with me about what's going on, I'll be happy to see them.
But that's where I'm going to stop about the chase, unless any of you who have read it or have thoughts about it that contradict what I'm saying.
There's in the end, it's a kind of letdown, but that's the point, I think.
I mean, that you keep expecting finally there's an eyeball to eyeball confrontation, and either he gets a chance, a have to throw his harpoon right into the forehead of Moby Dick, or Moby Dick gets a chance to chew off his other leg or something.
You expect some significant encounter.
And the important thing is, I think, that you don't get any one significant encounter.
Yeah.
He would die by him?
Oh, he does fulfill the prophecy, right?
And the farsi goes before.
And we see the Farsi, don't we?
I just suddenly don't remember.
Tied to the Moby Dick by getting caught in the rope.
And Ahab, do we see Ahab again after the rope gets him around the neck?
I don't think so.
But it's and predict and fulfilling the prophecy.
I see why you're saying it.
It's a funny thing about the universe that the Farsi can know what's going to happen.
I have nothing to say about that, I'm afraid.
Generally, as you know, I haven't said anything about these mysterious but Farsi figures that stand around and sort of keep Ahab in his mono mood and in his maniac mono mood.
And they, with their Sfadala, and he's the main one, right?
And he's the one who finally predicts that he will die and then does.
And I'd say just totally mysterious.
What somebody in the class is going to write about the Zoroastrian religion that's sort of in the background about what I don't know if Melville knows anything about Zoroastrian religion.
For all I know, he's just bluffing.
But at least it would be interesting to know what he might have said and even maybe what he does know and understand.
And maybe that casts some light on the prophecy, but I fear not.
So it's a loose end for me.
I mean, anything, I mean, I'm sure that Melville is just having literary kind of fun.
It reminds you of the end of Macbeth, and I think it's supposed to.
I mean, you get a prophecy that Macbeth can only die after if Vernon Woods moves on Duncanay, and he could only be, and no man born of woman will kill him, and then he discovers the Woods is moving, and then he discovers that who kills him?
Whoever it is, Macduff.
Macduff isn't born of woman, he was born of a Caesarean, and so forth.
So this complicated prediction at the end of Macbeth comes true, and I don't think Shakespeare has any interesting views about it.
It's just a literary event, and I don't think Melville has anything interesting about it either.
It's a literary event, sort of copying Shakespeare, whom he likes a lot.
I don't find that very illuminating, what I'm saying, but I wish I could say something more.
But I'm glad you asked.
Sorry, I can't say something that would be helpful.
David, do you want to say something you look like you might?
No, the kind of how the difference remains.
If there is no signal, I don't mind.
I mean.
That's right.
Well, that's what I think.
But what I want to say, and I didn't say it very well, so I'm glad you asked.
I mean, I have it written here as a higher order kind of indifference than this metaphysical kind of claim of just that I'm picking on Camus, but you could pick on lots of people, that it's just plain indifference.
It's the whiteness that you get from summing up all the perspectives which don't fit together.
So, look, he seems to be after Ahab, and he's sullen when he can't get Ahab, and he's vindictive, and he's malicious.
And it isn't as if the final fact that he drags Ahab off in the rope without either one of them knowing what hit them, that doesn't settle it on the level of which interpretation is right, but at a higher order, these interpretations all add up to there being no right interpretation, which is the whiteness, which is the indifference.
Yes, and how he survives is important and interesting.
Let's go to that.
Although, I can't say, I wish I could say more about the indifference, but I keep wanting to say that the crucial thing in Melville is how all the interpretations add up to blankness, which doesn't mean that that's on the same level as the other interpretations and it's the right interpretation.
It just means that there's a whole lot of interpretations, and none of them get it all together right, and none of them are altogether wrong.
They are just all plausible interpretations, and they don't fit together, period.
I'm not doing very well.
But there's somehow basic, I mean, it is, but they don't add up to an answer.
The universe is indifferent.
There wouldn't be any rainbow in that answer.
The answer, the dumb blankness of the whiteness, is that there are lots of, you could say, true interpretations, but there's no one true interpretation.
They don't add up to anything, but that's a different kind of indifference.
It's got more content in it, but that's what the whiteness and the rainbow, that means it's a kind of atheism or of interpretation where you get this answer that the universe doesn't mean any one thing by giving you a lot of different things that it means instead of just saying, look, it's a meaningless universe and it doesn't mean anything.
I think you're supposed to think Moby Dick is malicious, and Moby Dick is a dumb brute, and Moby Dick is out to get Ahab, and Moby Dick doesn't care at all about Ahab.
All of that's right.
And at least that's how I want to read it.
It's a lot more interesting than to say, and more tied up with the rainbow and the whiteness, than to say, well, finally the bottom line is the universe is indifferent.
It's Ahab, but David's point still bothers me.
Ahab doesn't get recognition from the universe.
That's a fact.
And nothing about the spectrum of colors changes that.
What do I want to say about that?
The universe is really indifferent to Ahab?
I don't know yet.
Let me think.
That's right.
Ahab certainly is a monomaniac trying to find the meaning and his place.
And it shows there's no answer to the question of whether the universe is malicious or not malicious, whether there's a God or not a God.
That's a wrong kind of quest.
And there's no answer to the question either, I think, of whether there is any special place for Ahab in the universe, which he wants to settle.
Because that's the wrong kind of quest.
I want it to come out somehow that the answer isn't, well, Ahab, it turns out the universe doesn't care at all about you.
The universe is simply indifferent to you.
It somehow isn't the universe.
I mean, the way the book is set up, that would have to mean Moby Dick doesn't care about you.
Moby Dick is indifferent to you.
But that isn't what happens.
When he gets caught in the rope, it doesn't show that Moby Dick is indifferent to him or out to get him.
That just shows that none of those answers actually describe what happens.
Is that any hope?
I don't know.
I leave it to you all.
If I can do better next time, I will.
I'm pretty sure that this is my right track, but I haven't convinced you, I can see, and I haven't, then it's not your fault, it's my fault.
Go ahead.
Interesting, interesting.
Yes, that's very important.
Pip really saw something metaphysical, I'm almost when you say, but that you have to be careful, I mean, because it shouldn't come out that it's like philosophy or religion or metaphysics and that he, that Pip saw the answer.
But he did see something like an answer.
He saw that the universe was not made according to any kind of plan, that it was all done by a completely indifferent kind of random weaving.
And that turns out to be true.
Showing the randomness.
Right.
And showing that the universe doesn't care.
Yes, but there's something, and I think you're right.
That's important.
I mean, there is something right about, and that's what David's saying too, and maybe others.
But now, if the universe doesn't care, it's somehow a random event, not a particular sort of attitude of the universe.
I mean, it's just sort of whether the universe cares or not is an irrelevant question once you've seen that it's made by random coral insects just spinning things together at random.
The main thing is to see the randomness of it, and it's not even indifference.
That's too intentionalistic.
That's too meaningful, as if the universe had some kind of attitude that the universe is just plain random.
That is the final truth.
It's chaos.
It's indifferent as God.
There are things like that that Melville says, and I think that's okay.
But that is to, I guess, to say why it's a wicked book.
There's not, you can't have the universe is not good with a good God running it.
It's not bad with a bad God running it.
It's not sort of indifferent doing its own thing and not caring about us either.
Even that's too specific.
The universe just is random.
And good.
I think I try to once more.
If you say something like Camus, the universe is indifferent, I can't do it yet.
I feel that that's attributing some more specific state to the universe than just that it's random.
I guess what I want to say is here, I'm trying again.
When the universe is random, that means sometimes it does care.
Sometimes it's lovely and beautiful, and the right mood in the book is to get in sync with the loveliness of nature and the fact that we're all part of it.
And sometimes it's brutal, and then it's like storms.
And so to see that it's random is to see that you can get in sync with it and get in moods about it in all sorts of different ways, and that they don't add up to anything, which is different.
You're looking skeptical.
You think I'm on a hopeless track here trying to say this.
That's right.
That's good.
You're getting, that's what I'm trying to say.
But that's a different thing than sort of as if the indifference of the universe were the one right perspective.
There's a kind of randomness of, which makes all the perspectives right.
And that's the interesting thing that Melville is on to.
I think I'm getting better now.
It's not that all the perspectives are wrong or all the perspectives are just perspectives.
They are all valid ways of seeing the color, the meaning, and so forth of the universe.
But since they're all equally valid ways, they add up.
That's what I want to say again in this meta-way, in this higher way, they do add up to indifference.
But they don't, but that's not to deny that all these other perspectives are true of the universe, as true as you can get, because there is no onto theological truth.
There's no truth about the universe.
There are just perspectives.
And each perspective reveals something important, and you can get in that mood and get in sync with it.
And then I keep repeating: the interestingness thing about it is they don't add up.
You can't get better and better grip on the universe.
They're just all okay perspectives.
On the Nietzsche page that I gave out, give me back one copy of my Nietzsche page.
At the bottom, I put a quote from Nietzsche, which comes very close to Melville, but it's not the same as Melville for the reason I've just been groping to try to tell you.
So this is getting awfully close.
There is only a perspective seeing, I'm at the bottom, only a perspective knowing.
And the more affects, those are the moods, we allow to speak about one thing, the more eyes, different eyes we can use to observe one thing, the more complete will be our concept of this thing, the more complete will our concept of this thing, our objectivity, be.
It's the last one that Melville is more radical.
There isn't a complete, there isn't even approaching complete objectivity or concepts of things.
You can just go on multiplying interpretations indefinitely.
And the reason you can't have a complete one or even converge on is that there are contradictions.
You can have all kinds of contradictory interpretations.
Not, say, of a house.
It's true.
You can know more and more about the house.
You can get more and more complete concept of the house.
You can never get a complete one, but you can do that.
But when it comes to these big philosophical questions, like what the universe is up to or here for, or what we're up to or here for, then you don't get them adding up to a more and more complete, better and better interpretation.
Because, now let's try to go back to the whale.
The malevolence of the whale is there, the stupidity of the whale is there, the awkwardness of the whale is there, the intelligent cleverness of the whale is there.
It's all there.
So they've refused to, when you look at it with all these different perspectives, it doesn't get more complete and coherent.
It just stays ungraspable, unrepresentable, and so forth.
And it's because at the bottom of it all, it's ungraspable, unrepresentable.
And that's even something more strange than random, I think.
Then that means that all these perspectives are true, as I keep saying, as true as you can get.
If there was some right answer about the universe, then it might be that some perspectives would be truer than others.
But remember back to the doubloon.
There isn't anything, but I look, you look, they look, we look.
Each one sees some aspect.
But you don't get, aha, this is, I'm being good about this.
I'm glad I brought back the doubloon.
You don't get a clear picture, finally, of what the balloon is.
What am I trying to say?
The dabloon is, you don't, when you add the Ahab dabloom to the stub dabloom to the Starbuck, Starbucks sees three peaks and he sees the Trinity.
Ahab sees himself.
Glask or stub, I forget which one sees that you can buy 160 cigars with it because it's a piece of gold and so forth.
And which one is right?
Well, the way it's supposed to be set up is they're all right as you can get.
And none of them write in the normal sense of right that you want to say, well, which corresponds to the way the doubloom really is.
So this is a tricky position, but fascinating, I think, that Melville's trying to get explained.
Okay, but I can't explain it anymore anymore.
You're still looking worried.
No, good.
Well, at least when, and are you still looking worried?
No, okay, I just quit while I'm ahead.
Okay, there's still plenty to talk about.
So let's go back to what happens next.
There's still many fascinating things going to happen.
So what happens with Moby Dick and the Pequad?
Well, Moby Dick just seeming, remember, to see that it's the source of all his evil, all the evil.
Where is that now?
Okay, Ahab goes down on 550.
And the ship has already gone down, right?
That's very bad.
Yeah, on page 548, seemingly seeing in it the source of all his persecutions.
And I don't think we're supposed to think seemingly there.
I'm still worrying about this.
Means, well, it isn't so.
It just seems to be so.
That's a use of seemingly.
No, this is again as so as it can get.
I mean, so it, so he sees in it, as far as we can tell, the source of all his persecutions.
And bethinking it, it may be, of course, it's alternative, it's just an interpretation, but there's no right answer, so you've got to believe the interpretation.
Bethinking it, it may be, a larger and nobler foe of a sudden he bore down upon its advancing prows, smiting his jaws amid fiery showers of foam.
And that means that we're now later, the ship is going to go down, and it goes down on page 550, I still think.
Where, though, where exactly does it sink?
It sunk by the bottom of 550.
It's gone.
The ship, great God, where is the ship?
But where did we hear it'll be going down?
Okay, let's try the bottom of 549, diving beneath the settling ship.
The whale ran quivering along its keel and so forth.
Shot to the surface again, far from the bow, and so forth.
No, that's not going to do it.
Don't tell me he never actually describes the ship going down.
No, here it's going to go down.
Yeah, going down is the last full paragraph.
I was just stuck to do.
Okay, so then, and there, so now we're going to hear about that.
But at the last, whelmings, intermixing, poured themselves over the sunken head of the Indian at the mast, leaving a few inches of the so-and-so erect.
Let's skip a little.
There was Tashigo there, about ten lines down at the very end of the thing.
This, and there's a bird, and he's Tashigo is there at the mast, nailing.
It's all very important to get this scramble, what's going on here at the end, because this is another example where something is being said, but not an ordinary sort of thing.
So there's the Indian, I'm at the bottom of 550, at the main mast, and he's up there and he's hammering the flag to the mast.
I don't, does it tell us why?
I don't think so, so let's go on.
Maybe we'll find out.
But a skyhawk that tauntingly had followed the main truck downwards from its natural home among the stars, pecking at the flag and incommoding Tashtigo there.
This bird now chanced to intercept its broad fluttering wing between the hammer and the wood, and simultaneously feeling that ethereal thrill, the submerged savage, that's Tashtigo, who's hammering the flag to the mast, the submerged savage beneath in his death grasp, kept his hammer frozen there.
And so the bird of heaven, with archangelic shrieks and his imperial beak thrust upward, his whole captive form folded in the flag of Ahab, went down with his ship, which, like Satan, wouldn't sink to hell till she had dragged a living part of heaven along with her and helmeted herself with it.
That there's a new one.
We're going to have to spend this today groping around these hard things.
What in the world is going on there?
It must be important.
I mean, the last thing is that this bird goes down with the ship, and Melville stops with that.
I mean, I'll read the rest, but there's nothing more to say.
Now, small fowls flew screaming over the yet yawning gulf, the sullen white surf beat against its steep sides, then all collapsed, and the great shroud of the sea rolled on as it rolled 5,000 years ago.
Now, by the way, somebody told me what the 5,000 is.
Do you know why?
Why?
5,000 years ago.
I thought it was because, according to the Hebrews, the world was created something like 5,000 years ago.
This is the year 5,000 something in the Hebrew calendar.
But somebody told me, and it sounds much more right, that it's the time of the flood was 5,000 years ago if you count back from 1850.
Somebody wants to do it, check it out.
But I bet it's the flood, the last time everything was collapsed under the ocean.
But I don't think that's important.
I think that's just a fact that he throws in at the end.
I think it's important that this bird goes down.
And I don't claim to be sure what it is, but I'll give you an interpretation, and then you can have something to accept or to struggle against.
This is pretty far-fetched and maybe too clever by half.
And if anybody can have a simpler interpretation, I'd be happy to have it.
But how he describes the bird is interesting.
It's the bird of heaven with its archangel shrieks.
That sounds Christian.
Archangels and birds of heaven.
And his imperial beak thrust upwards.
That sounds Roman.
And his whole captive form folded in the flag of Ahab went down with the ship.
So, and it's a piece of nature.
It seems to be dragging a living part of heaven along with her and helmeted itself with it.
It seems to me that what's happening is that everything, something Christian, something Roman, something natural, all goes down with the ship.
In fact, everything goes down with the ship.
All collapsed.
And what's the idea there?
The idea there, I think, if he's got an idea there, and I have a feeling Melville never has exactly got an idea.
He's writing out of this deep feeling he's got.
But whatever his feeling there is, that once you get a monotheistic God, which has got the Hebrew archangel component and the Roman imperial component, and all of nature brought into that component, if that God is dead, if that God collapses, if monotheism fails to work, then it's going to take everything down with it.
And to think of it this way, I mean, of course, Christianity goes down with it, and the Hebrews that have fed into Christianity, and modernity and the idea of the autonomous self-replacing God.
All of this is a kind of variation of one monotheism, which has got a Hebrew component, a Greek component, and a Roman component and a modern component, but they're all onto theology.
There is one supreme being that explains it all.
And everything is made intelligible in terms of that.
Now, it hasn't happened yet, but that combination of Christianity and, as I said last time, technology, which is the modern onto theology, that everything will serve our interests and everything will be brought under control.
All of that gets spread all over the world.
So that already, what's his name?
Quequeg is corrupted.
I mean, you have to ask yourself, and why did Quequeg go down with the boat?
I mean, that's really pretty upsetting.
Queque was the nearest thing we got to a human being who was healed.
He was healed when he was in the coffin thinking he was dying.
He was completely blissful and had calm and obviously no anxiety.
And yet he went down too.
And remember, he says early on that he's been corrupted by his connection with Christianity, that he can't go back and lead his people anymore.
So there's something, even Quequeg has been infected by monotheism.
But something about Quequeg is definitely the saving thing.
And you're going to get to that next in a second.
But Quequeg himself has been corrupted.
Though what sort of Quequekweg stands for is the saving power, I think.
But anyway, everything goes down is all I want to talk about right now.
It all collapses.
And the person who understood that best, Melville is certainly, if he's telling it to us, he's telling it to us in a very cryptic way and a very fast move at the end.
The person who really understood it and spelled it out is Nietzsche.
So now I gave you this Nietzsche paper to read you passages which I wanted you to have so you can look back at them.
Don't look at the first passage yet, the great advantage of polytheism.
That's for tomorrow.
I mean, Tuesday.
Look, and then not the brief habits either.
That's all for later.
The crucial one right now is the meaning of our cheerfulness.
That's a very funny name for the following passage, which seems anything but cheerful.
Okay, the greatest recent event, that God is dead, that the belief in the Christian God has become unbelievable, the event itself, then skipping a lot, that event itself is far too great, too distant, too remote from the multitude's capacity for comprehension, even for the tidings of it to be thought of as having arrived as yet.
Much less, and this is the line that I want to lead up to, much less may one suppose that many people know as yet what this event really means and how much must collapse, very same term, now that this faith has been undermined because it was built upon this faith, propped up by it, growing into it.
For example, our whole European morality.
That's just an example.
Everything, according to this Nietzsche picture, finally gets taken over by onto theology and the history.
That's the history of the West, and then once it is, it collapses.
And now comes the funny, strange part.
That sounds pretty terrible, but after all, it doesn't seem terrible to Melville.
I mean, onto theology has gotten to the point where it's monomania in Ahab, where it's sort of turning all the colors of the rainbow into whiteness.
And so Melville and Ishmael aren't upset by it, and neither is Nietzsche.
Now he goes on.
The consequences, it shouldn't be of ourselves, it should be to ourselves, are quite the opposite of what one might perhaps expect.
They, boy, problems here.
They are not at all sad and gloomy, but rather like a new and scarcely describable kind of light, happiness, relief, exhilaration, encouragement, dawn.
Indeed, we philosophers and free spirits feel when we hear the news that the old God is dead, as if a new dawn shone on us.
Our hearts overflow with gratitude, amazement, premonitions, and expectation, and then this very Melville conclusion of all that: the sea, our sea, lies open again.
Perhaps there has never been such an open sea.
And that's the picture.
Once you're out of onzootheology, all kinds of new wonderful possibilities will come along.
It's interesting that Balkington is too much still in it by standing against it, this heroic nihilism, sort of in the face of the indifference of the universe.
He hasn't got the kind of gratitude, amazement, premonition, expectation.
And in his letter to Hawthorne, I wish I had brought it, I didn't think I was going to mention it.
He says to Hawthorne, Melville does, I'm not unhappy.
I have to go read it again.
I'm not unhappy, but I'm not sort of blissful, I'm content.
There's something very satisfying about the possibilities that are open.
What are the possibilities that are open?
Well, they're the colors of the rainbow.
They're finding the sacred all over that would have been wiped out by this mono-god if it managed to take over all the world, if technology and the Judeo-Christian and Muslim, all those supreme being religions and even not religions like technology, all those mono-activities, if they'd taken all the world, then everything would have gone down.
But not quite everything goes down.
I mean, there is the sacred still in all the various parts of the world where it hasn't been destroyed.
And it turns out that it's good news that people like Ahab, the view that Ahab lives is what goes down and drags a whole lot of stuff with it, but it really opens up new possibilities.
I think that the new possibilities in Nietzsche look pretty different than the new possibilities in Melville.
But I want to save that till next time.
But I want to make sure I cover something else before we get to that.
Let's see if I want to say anything about it while I'm at it.
I really need another quote from Nietzsche.
Nietzsche, I'm going to find it.
I want to find two more quotes.
One of them I haven't told you about.
But this one, I mean, what Nietzsche thinks you should do is disclose new worlds, have new eyes, new ways of thinking about things, new perspectives, that that will be the final satisfaction that you get if you're a free spirit.
I'll give you a quote.
That certainly doesn't seem like Ishmael.
That's too willful.
It's too, it's sort of mono in its own way.
It's as if you can, instead of having one world, you've got a whole series of worlds, but it seems like you've got a series of total worlds, maybe.
I'm thinking out loud, and I shouldn't be.
Let's go back to this.
I'll talk about that next time.
Go back to what's happening here and what is happening here.
Well, there's still more.
The book has an epilogue.
And now we're on page 552, the very, very last page.
Apparently, I read somewhere, Melville wrote this later because people wanted to know: well, how did Ishmael survive to tell this story?
Or who survived?
How do we know all this?
And so he wrote an epilogue saying that Ishmael survived.
And while he was at it, he said lots of interesting things.
So let's do that.
But first, I have to see, I've got my whole section here, Why the Bird?
And while you think about Why the Bird, I have to catch up and see whether I've said what I think.
I'll just read it one more time.
The moral seems to be that mono-something, I mean, why I want to call it onto theology instead of monotheism.
It's any view that you can somehow understand and control the whole of everything.
That has spread to all other cultures and corrupted them.
Everything gets absorbed into it.
And whether it be the monotheism of Dante, where everything has a place in the creation, or the new total view that everything could be ordered by the human will and understood by science, all practices bound up with either of these ways, the Christian, which is the Judeo-Christian, Muslim, theological, or the modern willful scientism, all of those are going to go down.
And they've all will become unbelievable.
And they take everything down with them.
I said all that, and that this is good news to Melville that it all went down.
Good news to Ishmael.
He's not complaining.
Okay, I caught up.
Well, now, the question.
Yeah, David.
That's what I meant when I said, yeah, right, when I assumed that much, I shouldn't.
We should tell everybody.
When I say the imperial beak about the bird, the way Christianity took over the world, the first major step, nothing like that has ever been equaled, is they converted an emperor, Constantine, of the Holy Roman Empire, which was the whole known world to Christianity, in what, about 300?
And that's how the imperial story gets together with the archangel story, and that's all going down.
And I take it, I keep wanting to say, and nature too is going to go down in the form of the bird.
How does nature go down?
Well, the way the whale gets turned into an object and fished out of the ocean.
I mean, it isn't going to really happen that everything sinks like this.
But it's going to sink more and more gradually to talk like Nietzsche.
The whole Supreme Being, anto-techno story is going to seem more and more implausible.
And finally, it's going to seem so implausible that there'll be all this terror of people finding the world unintelligible, having no morality, no to guide them, and so forth.
But on the other side of it will be a world that, in a certain sense, will return to Homer-like world.
That would be the happy, that's the, that is the happy result.
But I'll talk about that more tomorrow.
But it's the result of the Homer world is plurality of gods, plurality of sacred.
Finally, you get out from under the mono.
Remember, the Course is called From Gods to God and Back.
And God just sank.
That's to sum it up in one sentence.
And now we're going to find out, start talking about saving things.
And so the first thing is, how does Ishmael get saved?
Because it's a clue to what is the saving, what is the saving thing that doesn't go down with the archangel Judeo-Christian and doesn't go down with the Roman Catholic Imperial, doesn't go down with nature as what he later calls the disenchanted hill where nature just becomes stuff.
What doesn't go down with it?
Well, Ishmael, who's got the right way of life, namely being open to all the moods, which is the cat bird, the catskill eagle that can fly high up and be very happy and low down and be very sorrowful and always open to more and more and interesting and deeper moods.
That doesn't go down and the coffin doesn't go down.
Why is it important the coffin doesn't go down?
Because what's carved on the coffin is the tradition, the background, the culture, the practices, the understanding of being, all these words I use for that.
That is what it is that makes it possible for people to be people and find meaning and treat things in some particular way as creatures or as welling up or as objects or as resources.
But the most important thing is, the saving thing is that there is a background.
You've got to be grateful for that.
And that's, and it isn't, of course, that it isn't perfect, because it isn't as if Quiqueg's tradition saves him.
I mean, Quique doesn't know Kwequeg's tradition, and it isn't carved in his body.
But you have to make a sort of jump and say, what saves him is the whatever it is that's carved into people's bodies that they can't understand, but that gives their life general orientation and meaning, and that's summed up in what's carved on Kuikwood.
One example is what's carved on Kuique's body, and that is example, is there because it's carved on the coffin.
And that's the sense in which Kuique, in a way, survives and is an example of some saving something.
All things get very puzzling, and you look very puzzled, and I can well understand.
There are two saving somethings.
And I've talked about them variously.
Maybe there are three.
I think there are three saving somethings, probably.
There is the general background understanding of being, which every culture has, and which the unrepresentable, put that in there.
That's the carved on the body, but you can't read it.
The unrepresentable understanding of being is part of the saving background.
The particular sacred something or others that each culture has, and each culture can have sacred something or others because, they remember, that Mobidik and the ocean and the unrepresentable keep you from ever getting sort of this total control that Ahab was trying to get and leave you able to have local sources of meaning.
I'm trying to think whether there are two or three.
I think I go back to two.
I think the sacred and the holy, which is what heals you.
Remember, you've got to have more than these background practices because people have all something wrong with them.
They're cracked about the head, and you need something that saves you.
Queque had it in his tradition, and everybody can have it in their tradition.
Well, except the poor people in the West and all the people they drag down with them.
But the people that they haven't dragged down in all these other cultures that Ishmael visits like to have their temples and they're sacred.
And that's the sacred and the holy.
I don't know whether they're two or three.
I'll tell you why I'm puzzled about this.
And I'm going to come back to it next time.
I mean, remember all the kind of okay things that you get in the squeezing of the hand, the squeezing of the sperm passage.
The home, the bed, the wife, the table, horses, politics.
These are all things that give meaning to people's lives, give them a center, give them a focus, give them an orientation.
Are they all sacred?
Or are they something else that's a supplement to them besides the sacred?
How many things are left when the onto theological world collapses and takes everything that it has taken over down with it?
And what's left that's saving?
Well, the coffin.
And that's one thing.
That's the tradition.
And that everyone has their tradition.
And insofar as that hasn't gone down, that's saving.
It almost all went down, but luckily, at least the coffin didn't go down.
Now, here's the question: Are there two other things that are saving, or only one?
I mean, that means: is there something called the sacred and something called the everyday kind of satisfactions?
Or are the everyday kind of satisfactions the sacred?
The healing?
I think my hunch is that there are two kinds of healing: the special religious kind, which is extraordinary and outside of the everyday, and the everyday kind.
And Melville quote, slash Ishmael, is interested in saving both of them.
No, they're all sacred.
I found a passage that told me it.
Even the everyday is sacred.
And you know how we know?
Let's go back to the squeeze of the hand.
Anything that heals you is sacred.
And the everyday, when you get it right, heals you, as well as special religious ceremonies.
Help me find the squeeze of the hand.
Chapter 42, page 402.
Here's why we think, why we say, okay, here we go.
This is what's left besides the background, besides the ocean and Moby Dick, which is the unrepresentable in the traditions, carved on the bodies.
What else?
This.
This other kind of attainable felicity.
You should place your conceit of attainable felicity.
That is, where do you place your belief as to what is what makes life worth living?
What makes for happiness, contentedness.
And here's a list.
So you get the, see, I did it pretty well.
The wife, the heart, I take that to be friendship.
The bed, that's Aphrodite and erotic.
The table, that's the food, dinners, the saddle.
I don't know why the horse people get singled out, but they do.
The fireside, we talked about that as the focus of the family once upon a time.
The country, that's the best example of that, where it was the Athenians at the end of the Orestea, when the pride in Athens was what gave their life meaning and direction.
Now, why do I think that's sacred?
Well, look what it says next.
I am ready to squeeze case eternally.
In thoughts of the visions of the night, I saw long rows of angels in paradise, each with his hands in a jar of spermaceti.
Well, that sounds like the ordinary, which is just what that list was, of which the squeezing of the sperm was a kind of example of friendship, at least.
And all that ordinary is something that is brought together with the angels.
So it must be a kind of sacred.
Then the everyday must be holy.
That is, it must be healing.
So he's got two proposals, I think.
This has not been so clear to me, not that it's all that clear now, but there seem to be two proposals here in Melville that you, well, one of them is this, I keep saying this Heidegger background thing.
I mean, that's not what that's the you think you've got to appreciate the ocean, the whale, and all the unrepresentable where the book starts and so forth.
But I'm seeing besides that, what is there?
Well, there's looking at the sacred all over the world, which is what Ishmael does when he travels around, or settling down and making some local kind of good thing able to be your meaning-giving healing thing.
I think he's got both of them.
And I think they both come under the sacred.
But there is, I gotta, but some of the sacred is sort of extraordinary, like the whale temple.
And like, I don't remember whether he ever talks about it in here or not.
I had this dim feeling that he does.
Sacred drugs, for instance, which he certainly would have thought was fine, eating the mushroom for the peyote ceremonies of the Native Americans and so forth.
That's a kind of extraordinary experience.
It's not something you do every once in a while.
There's all, religion is full of, in all these places, special things you do only under special conditions on special days.
And then there's these everyday things that you do.
So there's something ordinary, this is how I want to put it.
There's something ordinary and something extraordinary.
And they both have healing power.
And they both will only flourish and heal if you get rid of the onto theological, which is keeping them into sort of second rate.
And thinking that there's this Dante being the extreme, that there's this super Supreme Being which you can leave all that local stuff behind and get a real, immediate, total, mystical confrontation, which is completely fulfilling, completely eternal, and shows the meaning of everything.
That's the danger, because that doesn't really work.
And it levels out what does work, just the way it levels out even Beatrice in the divine comedy.
It levels out politics in the divine comedy, two of the on that list.
Either wife or I guess we'll call her wife, although it's not.
But anyway, so I guess that's the final feeling you get.
I'll just repeat it again, that it's an amazing disaster when Ahab, as the final monomaniac example of a kind of all forms of monotheism, brings down everything, almost everything, and almost everybody.
But it's not really a disaster because there are these two kinds of sacred left.
That's why I can't decide whether to count them as two or one.
There's two forms of sacred left.
The ordinary, meaning not the boring ordinary, not watching television and so forth, but the a fulfilling, a happy, fulfilling kind of ordinary, like having this good meal with your good friends and so forth.
That's fine.
And the extraordinary, that is, where every what every religion has, which, like yo-yo for Kuique, is some special something which has which gives meaning to your life and orients you somehow tells you what is important.
I just realized I didn't say one thing, and I have one minute, but I don't know what to say.
That is moods.
What do I want to say about moods?
Because moods are very important.
I'll come back to it next time, but I'm trying to sum it up in my head right now.
Moods are what attune you to what?
Not the tradition.
That's global, but it's not a mood-like thing.
Not the ocean, not the background.
But moods attune you, I think, to everything else I've been talking about.
Each of those family, meal, horses, politics, you get attuned to them by way of moods.
And the sacred, presumably, in its extraordinary, also with drugs and and and rituals and dancing and whatever its version is, is another something you get attuned to in moods.
So moods are going to turn out to be very important uh in period.
It's it's five.
I will go think more about it and Tuesday I'll try to be even, if I can, try to be more clear.
Okay.