We've done the city of dis, the wall, and then how Virgil didn't know how to get in, and how finally an angel is sent down by Beatrice to bash the door down, and they get into the city of diss.
And now we're ready to have different kinds of punishment.
That's where we're going to begin.
Outside of the wall of the fortress, remember, it's a fortress and not a prison.
And you'll see why, and that's relevant right now in a minute.
Outside the wall, there was wrongly directed desire.
That is, desiring, making your whole world around romantic love like Paul and Francesca, or about food, or which you don't have to read and think about, or about material things.
Those were all misdirected love in the language of St.
Thomas Aquinas.
It's not the language of Virgil.
Virgil doesn't understand that.
We'll get back to that later.
And now we're going to the crimes of turning away from God.
And sorry, no, those are all ways of turning away from God and making some lesser good, like sex and love and food or whatever, your God.
And now we're going to rejecting God's creation.
And in effect, making your own will, your autonomous willpower, your God, the ultimate authority in your life.
The only authority that you pay any attention to is yourself.
Those are the sinners.
They have remembered that they have built the wall of the fortress to exclude God and that inside they have set up their own objects to love, always unnatural.
And I keep coming back because it's the simplest to the homosexuals who instead of engaging in heterosexual love willfully reject that which God made for people and made people for.
Damien, you know, was the natural, as they would say, thing to do, and made up their own unnatural pleasures.
And all of them are like that.
Within the fortress, they've rejected the things that are naturally attractive and go after things that are, they make, they choose to make attractive.
But the important thing, as far as they're being sinners, is concerned, is that they have rejected God's creation.
That is, the natural things and their natural attraction and the natural attraction of God.
And as you go down, this is the final sort of punchline, the sins are ranked by the fact that they reject more and more until at the very bottom, we have to skip all but the one on Odysseus just because we haven't got time, and because the punishments are pretty boring anyway, they're the you did so-and-so, and now we're going to do some funny trick on you that is the sort of opposite of what you were doing.
But we want to look at the very bottom ones because they are the worst.
And what makes them the worst is they are the people who rejected even the claims on them of their country, which particularly Dante feels very, very strong patriotism, and their own intimate, their own children, and brothers and so forth.
They have rejected the most extreme form of claims and asserted their selfish, prideful autonomy, that only, after all, what they care about, what they choose to care about, counts.
Now we're going to just go into detail on one of the cantos, canto 26, on 221.
And our reason is because it's about Ulysses, that is Odysseus, as we called him when we were reading him in Greek.
Now in Latin, he's called Ulysses, and same person, but Dante's got a very different story than Homer to tell about him.
And it tells a lot about the world, the difference between the world of Homer, the multi-worlds of Homer, and the very unified world of the creation.
I mean, I used to say the universe, but the universe is some special modern thing.
The universe is where the nebulae and the electrons and all are all in one system of causal interaction.
And I was worrying for a while, and the Greeks would have called their world the cosmos, which is the sort of lawful order of the planets as they saw it.
And I was trying to figure out for a while: what am I supposed to call the world of Dante?
If it isn't a cosmos, then it isn't a universe.
Well, it was staring me in the face.
It's the creation.
That's what it's called.
If you've got a creator God, what the creator God creates is the creation, and we're all creatures.
So now we're going to go down and just look at the different relation of Odysseus to his world or worlds and why and what's wrong with that from Dante's point of view.
It's the wrong way to relate to the creation.
Okay, so here we go.
According to Dante, Odyssey goes directly from Circe without even going through Hades and without going home and heads directly toward the Mountain of Purgatory.
He doesn't know that's where he's heading.
He just heads out into the Atlantic Ocean to see what's there.
Now, and his punishment is in the circle of the false counselors.
Only we don't know yet what he was falsely counseling.
His punishment exactly is to be a flame.
And now, sort of in a flame, only you can't even see him.
There's just a flame.
And the tongue of the flame is his tongue.
And when the flame tongue waggles, then that's how he talks.
And he's going to tell us his story in a second.
So why is he in the punishment for false counselors?
Well, look on 222.
And before we even get into his punishment, though, I better back up a tiny bit.
On 222, what's important is Dante's reaction to him.
You won't understand yet why it's important till you understand what his false counseling was.
But it's important already to see the third stanza, line 40, roughly, in Canto 26.
And this is Dante talking.
I stood on the bridge.
It's a rock bridge overlooking this place down below where these flames are walking around.
I stood on the bridge and leaned out from the edge so far that, but for a jut of rock I held to, I should have been sent hurtling from the ledge without being pushed.
And seeing me so intent, my guide said, there are souls within those flames.
Each sinner swathes himself in his own torment.
And the important thing to see is that Dante had a special relation to this sin, the way he almost got into the sin of Paula and Francesca, so much so that he was talking to them and then fainted because he felt so identified and empathetic with them.
So he somehow feels identified and empathetic with Odysseus.
That is something Odysseus has done that Dante is also tempted to do.
And now we have to find out what.
Well, there's a mention in line 59 of the ambush of the horse, but that's not false counseling.
So that's just making a trick that the Trojans fell for.
I don't think you get to the false counseling until you get to page 223, line about 85, where he says, not 85, 88, not fondness for my son, nor reverence for my aged father, nor Penelope's claim to the joys of love, could drive out of my mind the lust to experience the far-flung world and the failings and felicities of mankind.
And that's important.
That means what is finally motivating him that keeps him from going home and so forth.
When I read the Odyssey, I always puzzle about why he does go home.
If his main interest is to go where no one has gone before and see what no one has seen before, then it's better that he just keeps traveling around and seeing more of these amazing sights and monsters and civilized people and like the Phaeacians and uncivilized people like the Cyclopses and so forth.
It's really peculiar that he does go home and it needs a lot of explaining, which I can't really do.
Dante, I think, has a better intuition that the character, the Odyssey of many twists and turns, which is the first sentence of the Odyssey.
By the way, I decided the right way to translate that funny poly, what's the polytropic, the word that nobody knows how to translate.
I've decided that it's devious.
That's what he is.
But I'm not sure, I mean, that doesn't capture it either.
There's no one word to capture what the, but it's got to do with the fact that he's able to sort of get people to do things by sort of saying the right things to them.
He's able to change, you know, disguise himself and so forth.
So anyway, according to Dante, quite plausibly, he just sets out to go on to more adventures.
And now I have written in the margin, 254.
Why do I want to see 250?
No, we don't want to see 254.
And so, and now, but where's the false counseling that he's there for?
Not yet.
So, he went on with his men who, and it's now what he says to them.
That's why he's aflame with a tongue.
False counselors say false things and get people to do bad things.
And what does he say to them?
At the top of 224, he says just what he ought to say.
Shipmates, I said, who through 100,000 perils have reached the West, did not deny to the brief remaining watch of our senses stand experience of the world beyond the sun.
I don't know why he puts it that way, but it doesn't matter.
The crucial thing is experience.
More experience.
That's what he really wants.
And then he says, Greeks, you were born to live like, not born to live like brutes, but to press on toward manhood and recognition.
I think, I don't know what manhood is exactly, but I take it sort of being mature, not in the Kantian sense of being autonomous, but growing up to be what human beings are at their best.
We should be what human beings are at their best, and that is to have lots of experiences.
It's a common, it turns, I hadn't thought of putting it this way, it turns Odysseus from James Bond into Captain Kirk.
I was close to saying that.
And now the whole point is having lots of experiences.
And with this brief exhortation, I made my crew so eager for the voyage, I could hardly have held them back from it when I was through.
And that's the false counseling.
The false counseling is to say that the highest thing you can do, human beings can do, is have lots of experiences, see all the good things and the bad things that people can do, and that would be to be a human being at his or her best.
And to put it in our way, he says, let's experience other worlds, other gods.
Let's find new ways of getting in sin.
After all, Zeus, the highest god, is the God of world crossers, so we should keep on crossing over into new worlds.
And that sounds right.
That's more important than staying at home with Penelope.
That is, in a world, in an understanding of what it is to be a human being, where the top god is a god of strangers and guests, sort of settling down at home with your wife and kids and father and mother, it doesn't seem like the highest thing you could do.
And now, why is Dante sort of leaning over and almost falling into the punishment himself?
That's where sort of the medieval world comes to collide with the Homeric world.
Dante sees the attraction of what Odysseus is saying, but he says that it's false counseling.
It's wrong.
And what's wrong?
Well, Dante, what's wrong is, so there are two things.
I don't know which way to start.
Okay, what's wrong with it is that you shouldn't just be out for experiences.
You should only have, there's only one thing that's important, and that is salvation.
And there's only one world, that is God's creation.
There's no way to explore new other worlds because there aren't any other worlds.
Wherever you turn in this creation, there's going to be the same kind of human beings and the same kind of love that is rewarding and the same kind of unnaturalness that is punishable and so forth.
So the idea of going around and experiencing other worlds could only mean just like just like sort of having a lot of fun, getting thrills.
You're not really going to learn anything important, and you're going to be distracted from what is important, understanding better and better what it is that human beings really need, namely God, and how to get in touch with God.
Now, the only missing piece is: why is Dante so dangerously tempted by the keep having experiences of other worlds?
Well, that's because he lives at this very interesting moment between the medieval time, which was a closed world, which was God's world, all organized hierarchically, everyone had their place, and everyone understood how to get from their place to the highest place, and everybody had this opportunity to go and have a direct vision of God if they lived a good life, and so forth.
Dante comes from that world into the Renaissance, which is happening in Italy then, which is the whole rediscovery of the Greeks and presumably, of the fact that there were these other than Christian worlds, and that and Dante is just fascinated by all kinds of other possible experiences, other possible places.
He would have gone on that boat ride out through the Straits of Gibraltar into the Atlantic to see what was there, just like Odysseus.
So it's dangerous for him.
I don't see where we are.
So it makes no sense to seek just new experiences, sensations, curiosities, see all the failures and felicities of mankind, as Odyssey puts it, just for its own sake.
If they don't teach you anything new about what's important, namely salvation, they're just a distraction.
They have no merit.
They don't make for manhood or for human beings at their best.
And you can't get to purgatory and paradise by doing that kind of looking around.
And that's what happens.
The boat is headed for purgatory by accident, in a way.
Odyssey didn't know that there was nothing out there in the southern hemisphere where he was heading, but the purgatory mountain, that they saw the mountain of purgatory.
And then at the bottom of 224, about line 125, they saw this peak that was very tall.
And then there was a storm, and the ship was turned around three times and sank.
And at the fourth, well, three times at the fourth, the bow went down and the sea closed over us, and the light was gone.
Their boat was sunk because they were on the wrong mission.
And Dante doesn't want to fall for that temptation.
But if you read the whole book, you'd see that every time there's some new information about some other country or some scientific experiment or any sort of news about the open world, so to speak, Dante's interested in it.
I mean, he's no polytheist, but he's also definitely thinks that anything that you can understand, even if it isn't directly edifying, that is directly leading you to God, is fascinating, and therefore he's fascinated by Odysseus.
But he shouldn't be.
I mean, he's, because he was in the dark woods, because he was in despair, he's been put on this mission to discover how to lead a good Christian medieval life by Beatrice and God and the Virgin Mary all and cooperating and so forth.
And that's what he should be worrying about.
And he shouldn't be paying any attention to any of the kind of interesting quotes, interesting things about which he's so curious, because they don't matter unless they teach you how to be a better person.
Okay, so that's anybody want to say that's all I have to say about the Odyssey one, but it's kind of a little window into the difference between polytheism and multi-world people like the Homeric Greeks, who had to remember lots of worlds were whooshing up and lots of gods, and the kind of closed world of the medievals where it's all created by one God in one hierarchical order, and it's all the same all over, and it all points toward God.
Couldn't be more different, what God and gods are and what human beings' jobs are than that.
Okay, now, anybody want to say anything about that, or we'll go on to the next events?
Yeah.
Would it not be a good thing to do?
Interesting, interesting.
My first thought is it's fine to admire the whole creation.
Now, this is sort of me talking, and it may turn out to be wrong, but what I was saying earlier, sir, my feel is that there's no point in going anywhere else because the whole creation is all the same.
Whether you stay at home and admire every little thing and love every little thing because God made it, or whether you go off to Bali, you won't see the Bali people worshiping some other God in this perspective.
You'll just see them doing the same things that we do.
So, there isn't, as soon as you get into the Renaissance, you can rephrase it that way.
And I think Shakespeare, for instance, would have understood looking at all the different wonders of creation.
But I don't think in Dante there's any point in looking at anything.
Anything you see is God's creation, and anything you see has a certain amount of fulfillment value, and you should get your love in sync with it, I think.
Beatrice, did you want to say something?
Ah, well, good.
Well, but he's exiled, you mean?
No, he goes on a journey.
I thought the business would be something about what he had.
The journey through hell, and yeah, the journey, the big journey, the book journey.
He goes on a, yes, he goes on a journey, and it's to see a what now between the two of you.
I have to figure out this.
He he sees all of creation, all right, and that's a lot of stuff, all the inferno and all of purgatory, and it's important that he does that.
But it's always with the final edifying direction that he should see it only insofar as it teaches him the right way to get into the relation to this creator, God.
He shouldn't see it as a variety of worlds interesting in their own right.
As soon as you do, you go from being a pilgrim, which is what he's called.
I don't know by whom, but I mean, by Chiardi, and that's all right.
The pilgrim is on a trip and he sees lots of things, but he's got one goal, and they're all supposed to be teaching something such that he will find and appreciate that goal.
Whereas you try to think, you can't think of Odysseus as a pilgrim.
He's not going any one place, and he's not going to find out, he's not going anywhere to find out about his salvation.
He's a what?
I don't know what's the word.
Well, what was Captain Kirk?
Yeah.
Yes, that's what I couldn't be the case for Dante.
Right.
If the journey is an end in itself, but even in every bit of each piece of the journey, which just comes to the same thing, the more worlds you see, the better.
And that's the point in this.
But everything that you see has to point toward finally getting the right relation to God.
That's the point if you're a pilgrim.
It's a subtle difference, but a really, really clear one, I think.
And that's, I mean, and if you don't, that's, you only see it if you see why he's so tempted by and yet trying hard to be utterly different from Odysseus.
And that's so that he has to see all of this as he says.
He has to see all these aspects of creation, but they don't, they always teach him the same thing, so to speak, which, and now I don't know what to say.
I want to say something like, he could have learned at home.
You don't have to go on this trip, you wouldn't think, to become saved.
Why did he have to go?
I'm just trying to figure this out as you guys push me into it.
I can't imagine.
I mean, he's the only one who did this trip in the history of the West.
And so there's something very peculiar, maybe a kind of loophole that there's no fixing.
I can't think of any reason why, however, he was lost in this dark woods, despairing, disoriented, having affairs with other women, Beatrice accuses him of, among other things.
And getting into this political squabbles and turning out to be on the wrong side.
All of that, none of that would seem to motivate having to go to the bottom of hell, to the top of purgatory, in order to get to paradise.
Nobody else seemed to ever had to do that.
I could give a kind of version of it that would be later Kierkegaardian kind of thinking, that you have to go to the very bottom of despair before you can come out on the other side.
But that doesn't seem to be a Dante thing.
It isn't as if he gets more and more despairing as he goes down to the bottom of the inferno.
He's already hit bottom in the dark woods, and then he has to go on this whole trip, and then he gets to see God.
I'm stumped.
If anybody knows an answer to this, let me praise the question clearly.
Why does Dante have to make this extended pilgrimage to end up with a vision of God thousands or tens of thousands or maybe millions of other people have had without making this trip?
I don't know.
You have an idea?
Well, in a way, that's what you have to say: that Dante's doing it so that all of us can learn all the wrong ways of doing things so that we can avoid them and finally end up doing the right way of doing things.
Yeah, he doesn't, I mean, that sort of somewhat conflicts with the dark woods.
Well, not really.
I suppose he's lost, and therefore he, and everybody's sooner or later lost.
And I still don't really understand too well why you have to see all these things which he doesn't have even an inkling of doing.
I mean, he's not interested in collecting material possessions, and he's not a schismatic, and he's not a bad kind of lawyer, and he's not a murderer.
Why he has to see that all these things are wrong and produce bad things, except if, as David says, it's not really Dante who has to see them for himself, but he sees them to report this for everybody, to help everybody.
He certainly doesn't present it that way.
And see, yeah, it's a kind of summing up of all the wrong ways, and finally, at the end, all the right ways when you get to the Paradiso of getting a completely fulfilling life.
And Dante is going to show it to us.
But I think there's a kind of tension between that and the idea that he's personally lost and that it's for him that Beatrice came down to do this and so forth.
I think probably you're supposed to read it both ways.
I mean, but I don't understand really the for him part.
I think David's got a view of the for everybody part because this is going to teach whatever your temptation is, it will show you sort of what an ugly thing that really is and what a terrible life in eternity you're going to have if you go on doing it.
And then it's going to show you how to try to get over your addictions and your willful pride in purgatory, and then it's going to show you all the rewards you're going to get in paradise.
That's for each person, some other, some part of the book or other should show them something edifying.
And that still leaves me a little puzzled about whether Dante himself gets edified by it.
Okay, Beatrice, yeah.
And which is the she-wolf?
I don't remember which animal is which.
Yeah, but one of them, each of them symbolizes something.
I'm just curious which bad thing is he most endangered by.
Really, I hope so.
Because I don't think of Dante as pride, autonomy, and so forth.
I think I think of him as either overwhelmed too much love for Beatrice, which I don't think he could possibly have by his chivalric thing, or he's got these temptations to anger, and he's got those temptations to other women, and I guess that's what's his problem.
But it's clearly much bigger than his problem somehow.
I mean, the book.
I mean, for that, those little problems, people have had them and gotten and gotten over them without having to see the whole moral universe or moral creation.
And I think David's right, but I think there's no easy way to say that this is for everybody.
You've got to figure that out for yourself.
Dante wants to tell it as a story about his life and his relation to Beatrice and so forth.
Okay, I can't do better.
If anybody can put it together in a paper, that would be terrific.
Yeah.
Ah, that's nice.
I wonder what that is in Italian.
You got the inferno in Italian, right, Beatrice?
He wants to know, oh, he does.
Well, and it says in the middle of our life.
Okay, great.
I didn't realize you had it.
Terrific.
So that's good.
That's helpful.
You see what he's saying?
So Dante sort of builds in the generalization that he's not just talking about in the middle of my life I found myself in the dark woods, but sooner or later everybody in their own way goes astray and finds themselves in the dark woods.
And this book has got something in it for everybody who finds themselves in the dark woods, not just Dante.
I think that must be how it's supposed to work.
It still has this peculiar feature that even why it doesn't, why each person in their own way didn't find their own pilgrimage, but why anybody has to go through seeing all of this ugly scene, and I still don't understand.
But if you do say, well, but this is a book for everybody and that's how they took it, then it makes sense because surely somebody who's reading it needs to experience each of these punishments.
I mean, the one that's important for them, Dante's tempted by the anger punishment.
I mean, it's interesting to try to keep track.
Certainly, he faints for Paula and Francesca.
He gets involved, I forget how, in the anger punishment, but you could look.
He gets very nearly into the homosexual punishment because he wants to talk to his old homosexual teacher and he has to go under the falling fire flakes to do it.
And he almost falls into the Odysseus temptation.
And he has to go through, you'll see the fire at the top of the purgatory, which is purging lovers of any kind of misdirection in their love.
So you can see that there, Dante, maybe that's part of it.
Dante sort of includes in the book a kind of distinction, which I was bringing out, but I wasn't really paying attention to it, between the sense in which this is specifically relevant to him.
And you can find out by looking to see which punishments he is close to falling into and has to be warned about.
It's interesting that he sort of sometimes he's telling you in one level about his life, and then he's emphasizing which punishments he really cares are important and edifying for him.
And sometimes he's telling you about human life, our life, and then he gives you all the punishments.
That's helpful a little, yeah?
That's right.
Good, good, good.
Because it's this kind of hierarchical system, you have to understand why this sin, if it's inside the city, or this, what's the opposite, what's other than sin, because sin is always rebellion and rejection of God.
What about these people who love too much?
With this, I just need a word, vice.
How's that?
The virtues and vices talk will do.
We need to understand each vice and why it's wrong and how wrong it is.
And that's the sense in which all of the, and they all relate to each other.
I mean, you have to understand why gluttony is a worse vice than too much romantic passion.
And you have to understand why the people, why the homosexuals are worse than the, or at least the promiscuous ones in hell, are worse off than the lovers and worse off than the happy homosexuals you'll see at the top of the parody of the purgatory who are monogamous and so forth.
And all that is in a big system.
And you're right.
You have to understand any one of them as worser or less than another.
That's what you're thinking.
Okay, well, that's all sort of important and somewhat exhausting.
I guess now I wasn't going to talk about something, which now I have to, but it's not in your reading.
But we come so close.
If I list all the places where Dante gets into trouble, one of them is a place where he is looking at what's going on as if it were entertainment instead of edifying.
He's not learning about how it affects his life, and it's a temptation for him, presumably.
This is on page 254, this is Canto 30, line 120.
There people are sort of yelling at each other and putting each other down like a kind of sitcom, and they're making, they're insulting each other, and I guess are they punching each other?
I'm not sure.
I don't think so.
They're just sort of insulting each other.
And Dante's finding this very exciting and fun, just like watching a sitcom.
And he gets in trouble for it on 254, the bottom half of the page, about line 130.
I was still standing fixed upon those two.
Those are the ones insulting each other.
And when the master said to me, Now keep on looking a little longer and I quarrel with you.
When I heard my master raise his voice to me, I wheeled about with such a start of shame that I grow pale yet at the memory.
See, he's involved again.
He's gone in, he's taken in, he's enjoying this kind of activity instead of realizing that it's a bad thing and trying to see it's what you're supposed to not do it.
And then I think that's enough.
Yeah.
So it's interesting that that's the only other place I know of where he sort of puts himself into the story as an almost sinner.
Okay, now we want to jump ahead to the bottom of hell, because we need to talk about that too before we can get on to purgatory.
And that the bottom of hell is the worst.
Oh, I left out a little something on 255.
My book is still open to it.
What Virgil says when he explains why Dante shouldn't do it, it says to wish to hear such baseness is degrading.
That means something like, well, not all experience is edifying.
Some experiences are just, I don't know, stupefying or brutalizing and so forth.
And Dante had better not be going around collecting those experiences.
Okay, now we're going to go to the bottom of hell.
The bottom of hell are the people who are the most bad, that is the most prideful, that is the most self-suff sufficient or trying to be self-sufficient, and they've excluded themselves in the name of autonomy from ever getting fulfilled by God's love.
And now there's a bit of important psychology here that Dante believes.
And it's going to turn out to be very important later when Virgil explains the whole system of all these punishments.
That is, God has created the world.
This is a very important thing to just say sometime, and right now just as well.
God has created the world with stuff with all sorts of varying degrees of fulfilling power.
Other bodies, good food, material possessions, power, I suppose.
I don't know how to put it.
But everything, you should know.
And you should sort of love, or now love means desire.
It doesn't mean agape love.
It doesn't mean erotic love either.
You should just desire things in proportion to how satisfying they are.
So that is at the top of the list of things that are pretty satisfying, except that if you go into them with 100% the way Paolo and Francesca do, then they get to have their own drawback.
But each thing then is, all of it's created by God's love, and we're cree and each thing is created with a certain amount of fulfilling power.
And we're created, I call that, I think, homing missiles from Augustine-like, that is, and we're created as needing total fulfillment and getting a certain amount of fulfillment out of all these created things, and seeking total fulfillment, none of them can satisfy us except finally a direct vision of God.
That's the picture.
Now, why do you need to know it now?
Well, because of the peculiar character of the people at the bottom of the inferno.
You've all read it, I hope.
How many know what the punishment is for the people at the bottom of the inferno?
The really, really bad people?
One or two.
You only, the rest of you don't know.
Are they in hellfire and brimstone?
Are they cooked for eternity?
No, they're frozen solid in ice.
It's marvelous how different Dante's view of evil is from the Protestant view of evil.
For Dante, they are immobile, frozen in ice, and that's because you need just one phrase to understand it.
If you're open to the attractiveness of things, then you are moved by the light, food, or romantic love again, and so forth.
And now it's a pun on move, the way I'm saying it.
When you're moved by something, you are literally moved.
That is, you don't do anything or act.
People don't do anything or act except insofar as they're moved literally by the attractiveness of the various things in God's creation.
And that means if you reject God's creation and its attractiveness and want to be autonomous, then you get less and less moved the more autonomous you get.
So if you got to be completely autonomous, you'd be completely immobilized.
Nothing would be attractive for you.
And since nothing was attractive for you, since all attractiveness finally comes from God, and you rejected God, then you are just, and you are cold because you aren't emotionally involved, you aren't passionate, you aren't loving, you aren't open to anything.
I mean, even the guy who loves his white BMW convertible isn't cold.
He's got a rather limited object, and he's over, he's obviously over-committed to it.
But to be really, really cold is to have no attractions at all because you're so self-sufficient.
And that is so prideful that you won't accept to give up your willpower for the attractiveness of anything.
That's then, you know, the line better to rule in hell than serve in heaven.
And if you won't give up your willpower for anything, finally you won't be moved by anything.
And that's why you're in the ice.
And that's that, the ice is just the realization of that, that is the sort of dramatization of the fact that these people are cold and not moved by anything.
The more you get to the bottom, the more you find people who have turned against their lords, their bosses, their brothers, their family, their country, and the more we find these sinners who, having refused all attractions, are just like rocks.
Dante kicks one of the heads of the people frozen in ice, and Virgil says that's a good thing.
Don't feel bad about it when he trips over it, because they're just objects.
These really, really bad people.
They're the ultimately unresponsive people, unopened.
They refuse all connections to stay self-sufficient.
And that's it.
I just wanted you to notice, I mean, how different that is than thinking that hell is hot.
I mean, in Milton's Paradise Lost, which I mention every once in a while, and which I think I may have said I had in this course until I discovered that nobody, neither the students nor I could really understand it.
Has anybody read Paradise Lost?
It's very, very hard.
You read it in high school?
Wow, that must be quite a high school.
Did you understand something?
No.
Okay, well, that's what I was afraid of.
Okay, anyway, but this much is clear: that Milton has lost the sense.
Well, let me put it to the first one, he's lost.
For Dante and St.
Thomas, evil is non-being.
And that means sort of the eviler you get, meaning the more self-sufficient you get, the more you reject the attractiveness of the creation, the more you are just impotent.
And so you get to Satan, who's frozen in the ice at the bottom, isn't flying around rallying his troops the way he is in Milton.
He's just, he's all he can do is flap his wings and act as the kind of refrigerator for this lowest part of hell.
He's the one who's cooling the ice.
But the important thing is that in Dante, evil is finally sort of self-destructive and weak.
Whereas Milton really believes in the power of free will and really has Satan full of energy, running around defying God, rallying the truth, setting up a whole other world, other community in hell.
And heat is somehow associated with that.
I mean, I don't even understand the Protestant story.
I mean, why should hell be full of fire and brimstone?
Why not ice?
Why should evil people be hotter than non-evil?
You can understand Dante better, I think.
I mean, I can understand the view that says that evil people are colder.
And the eviler they get, the colder they get.
I can't understand the idea that Satan is full of energy.
And Milton seems to admire that.
Well, I guess I really think is that Milton and the Protestants are sort of already in the modern world where will and energy are thought of as good things and not as rejecting what God has to offer.
So, in any case, I'm going to just.
So, in modernity, we have an active, willful, Protestant Satan, and Milton admires his energy.
And then let's go to the end.
So, we're down at the bottom of hell, 283.
There's one last joke, which Shiardi doesn't get, or else he's too prudish to tell it.
I wonder if you get it or got it.
Or maybe I'm making it up, but I don't think so.
Okay, so there's Satan on 283, the very beginning of Canto 34, like a whirling windmill, there he is, stirring up a bitter wind, and so forth.
And that's and now he's hideous looking and so forth.
And look at this, those three faces.
I just noticed this for the first time: 40.
One was in front, and it was fiery red, and the other ones were what?
White and yellow.
I don't know, it wasn't fiery red in the sense of hot.
I'm sure, although I'm surprised that Dante calls it fiery red.
That seems to me a kind of glitch in the poetry.
But anyway, we get to page 285, line 75.
They finally reach the bottom of the world.
But that's already a sort of pun.
The bottom of the world is Satan's bottom.
And because he's imprisoned in the ice with his upper part sticking up into the inferno and his lower part sticking into that sort of empty space where between the inferno and and the paradiso.
So he's if this, so down here, I don't think I drew it quite far enough down.
So down here, Satan is in here and his head is up here.
That's where he's got the three in his mouth he's chewing Brutus and Cassius.
and Judas.
By the way, just parenthetically, look how committed to politics Dante is.
He's got these three bad people.
You can see why he has three.
It's sort of the opposite of the Trinity.
But of the three, one is the betrayer of Jesus.
You'd think, I mean, that would be pretty serious, super serious.
And then Brutus and Cassius, who killed Julius Caesar and brought about the change of the Roman Empire into an empire.
And Dante has views about that.
And oddly enough, he's put in the mouth of Satan those three, one too political and one religious bad guy.
And then the legs of Satan stick down here into the space that is a sort of crack that Virgil and Dante go to to get to purgatory, which is made out of the dirt that's hollowed out of the inferno and out of this space in here.
But and the bottom of the world is the where the most bad matter is.
And so as you go down, things get more and more just plain matter.
And as you go up and up, they get more and more spiritual until you go way up into the Paradiso, where they're completely spiritual.
So, what happens when they reach the very bottom at the two two eighty five, seventy five?
When we have reached the joint where the great thigh merges with the spelling of the haunch, that's literally the bottom of Venus Lee.
And then Virgil has to turn around.
They've been climbing this way, and now they turn around at Satan's bottom and start climbing up this way along his legs.
And so his master screening turned his head to where his feet had been and began to grip the hair as if he was climbing so that he moved toward the world.
So where do they turn around when they've really reached the bottom?
Well, it's Satan's anus.
It's the asshole of the world, the way Dante sets it up.
There's no question about it.
Chiardi just doesn't tell you that in the footnote, but you can figure it out.
And that makes perfect sense in this picture of creation.
So there they are at the absolute bottom of Satan, and then they climb up here and they get to purgatory.
So now we're going to get to purgatory.
Any comments, though?
We're just leaving the inferno.
It's time anybody who wants to say anything about life in the inferno should say it now.
Usually somebody has some hard question or some objection, and we learn something.
We've already got enough hard questions already about the journey and who's at the pilgrim and who is benefiting from it.
I haven't learned something yet.
I've learned something to worry about, but that's the first stage.
You start to worry about something, and if you're lucky and if Dante is smart enough, there's something deep going on that you can find out.
And the hour journey is the hint.
But anyway, onward now.
We're going to purgatory.
And for all these.
Thanks.
Okay.
So I'm just going to sum up quickly.
From eternal torment, you go to a new kind of torment, which lasts for a long time.
But it's a different kind of torment because it's no longer meant to punish you forever.
But it's the kind of suffering that an addict has to go through to get over their addiction.
Whether the whole purgatory is filled with recovering addicts who repented and have chosen to try to get over their addictions.
So the punishments look like the bad kind of inversions of the inferno.
For instance, the gluttons are the food they desire most is right out of reach.
They get a punishment from tantalus.
But those gluttons are people who are, in effect, dieting, starving themselves in order to get over their desire for food.
And it's true of all of them.
They're bending over, literally bending over backwards, some of them, like the pride people are carrying heavy weights and are all bent over because they were all too high.
They're all being voluntarily suffering the opposite of their particular kind of addiction so as to get over it.
And when they do, then they can go on to paradise.
And it's up to them.
They'll know when they're.
And notice I never said this before, but obviously, what's being fixed are their desires.
This is Christian.
It's not that they're learning to behave like not eating food.
This is important.
How did I never say this before?
It isn't as if they've learned just not to have sex or with the promiscuous or something and so forth.
It's not that they learned to stop being gourmets.
It's, those would be actions.
They've learned to stop desiring promiscuity.
They've learned to stop desiring fancy food, et cetera, et cetera.
They've learned to stop desiring being the best and proud and having people admire them.
And when their desires are sufficiently purified, they'll know it when food doesn't look attractive to them anymore, etc.
And then they'll be able to go on up the mountain of purgatory, stopping at the various places where the particular punishment or particular sin that they've got gets punished.
By the way, Chiardi's got something wrong in a diagram I want to mention to you simply because the moral is I've now checked and it turns out to be absolutely wrong to, I mean, or anyway, these names of the ledges are not Dante's.
He didn't name the ledges and the punishments.
So remember, when way back to my fussing about the opportunists, and I said, those weren't opportunists.
Those were people that were the lukewarm, which is very different than opportunists.
And then I worried, but whose name is Opportunist?
And it's Chiardi's.
And so the moral of this is when you think about your papers, if you come out with the feeling that after reading a certain punishment, that it's really not the way it's described by Chiardi, you are right.
You have a complete right to rename that canto.
And here is a place where he renames, well, I want to rename everything.
And we'll get back to it, but I may forget, so I want to look at it right now.
On page 30, there's no page 30, but if you go back from page 32 to 31, you will get to page 30, is the picture of purgatory.
And the top level, Chiardi calls immoderate love.
Now, I'm going to say this over and over because it's very important.
There is no immoderate love in Dante's version of the creation.
Because total love and devotion is the appropriate relation to God.
So what is the problem?
It's never immoderate love.
It's misdirected love.
I mean, the only thing that you could do wrong is to totally adore, totally worship, totally love anything other than God.
And so we don't want to call the top level immoderate love.
You want to call it misdirected love.
And Dante's clear about that.
I don't know.
Chiardi's got this problem with trying to...
Chardi's a stoic who wandered into translating this book by mistake, I think.
But where are we now?
Okay, so one more thing, and just to give you the overall picture, that everything is different.
So you don't have to, you aren't reading much of the purgatory, so I have to give you some feel for it, anyway.
So instead of this terrible smell, which they had in hell all the time that gets mentioned every once in a while, it's now fragrant and perfumy.
Instead of all the howling bad noises from hell, it's now people singing.
Instead of blaspheming God, it's now prayer.
And in general, instead of darkness, which is the general way it must be in the inferno, mostly only by the fiery walls of the city of Dis, it's the sun shines.
I mean, I don't know how the sun shines.
Well, sure, the sun shines, that's right, because they're out here now.
And so the sun shines in the daytime.
And the sun, it's important to know, is stands in, so to speak, represents, or I don't know quite how to put it, the attraction of God.
The sun is God in the way it's treated.
And so whenever the sun is shining, then you can go toward it, and it's attractive, and it pulls you to get better and better as a person.
And at night, it follows from this that at night, when the sun doesn't shine, you can't do anything.
You can't walk from your ledge to the next ledge if you're purified.
You can't even walk upward getting better at what, getting more over your addiction.
You can't do anything at night.
Because remember now, all movement comes ultimately from God.
Another way to put this is God is the prime mover, because God's attraction is what ultimately moves people.
And if there's no sun, then you're out of the presence of God.
Then there's no prime mover, then you can't move.
And that's exactly what happens.
Dante's very consistent.
So, and Virgil can't understand this because he doesn't understand ever, and you've got to keep remembering that, that God is the completely fulfilling something or other that makes it always, you can never love too much, because God is worshipable, adorable, totally lovable, and so forth.
But when the sun isn't shining, then these people can't improve.
This is on Canto 7, line 14.
Well, 14 is just the name of somebody.
Sordello's talking, and on page 85, line 40, he's explaining, this guy, Sordello, just what I'm telling you.
He says, we're not fixed in one place, he replied, but roaming at will up and around this slope, far as the gate, and I will be your guide.
But the day is fading fast, and in no case may one ascend at night.
We will do well to give some thought to a good resting place.
And then, skipping a verse, getting to 49, what is it you say, my guide asked?
He's puzzled, Virgil.
He doesn't understand this whole picture of something utterly fulfilling that's attracting you and making you able to do whatever you do.
He says, if one sought to climb at night, would others block his way, or would he simply find that he could not?
And that is really, he's asking, why can't people do things on their own willpower?
And he's getting the answer: you can't do anything really on your own willpower.
It's always what you do, a response to, it's always what you do is in terms of your desires, and your desires are always responses to the attractiveness of the creation, and therefore ultimately responses to the attractiveness of God.
And Virgil can't understand any of that.
He says, Sardello says, once the sun sets, that noble fellow replied, you would not cross this line.
And he ran his finger and so forth.
Then skipping to 61, I heard my Lord's voice, that is Virgil, touched with wonder, say, lead me to the place that you spoke of, where we can, in effect, lie down and rest.
So the whole principle of why and how they're climbing this mountain is something Virgil can't understand.
And we're beginning to be prepared for what's going to happen when Virgil's understanding really gives out completely.
Virgil's always sort of got it wrong.
Because if he doesn't understand this basic truth, that there is something in the universe that's absolutely fulfilling and adorable, then everything he's going to think is going to be wrong.
But it gets clearer and clearer that it's wrong until the middle of the purgatory, which we'll talk about next time, or maybe we'll talk about this time, I'm not sure.
Let me think about it.
No, let's do it now, because I'm talking about it.
So let's jump to Canto 16, 16 to 18.
That's where Virgil finally explains everything and blows it completely and gets everything all mixed up.
And we'll start with it now and I'll review it again at the beginning next time.
But it's so, it's all, and I've been sort of preparing you for it.
But on Dante's not much help, because Dante seems very confused at secondhand, so to speak, about what Virgil knows and understands and what Virgil doesn't know and understand.
He was very clear at the wall in hell that what Virgil didn't understand is something called sin or rebellion or whatever that Christians and the Christians understand.
But now we've got him trying to explain everything.
It starts on page.
Oh, there's this whole discussion of free will.
I'm going to skip that for the time being.
And then Dante's whole discussion of the relation of church and state.
I'm skipping that for the time being.
I want to go directly to Canto 17 and then talk about what's going on.
And now you've got to realize that scholars have only, don't try to read secondary sources about this, because they are all completely hopeless.
Because somehow or other they've got the view that you can believe what Virgil says.
And you could see already at the wall that Virgil doesn't understand what it was or why it was important.
And now Virgil's explaining the whole structure of purgatory and of God and of love and everything.
And he's all mixed up.
And if you go to find any help from the critics, you're not, because they're all mixed up.
And I can't fix it, but I can show you what he's trying to say and how it's mixed up.
And also, maybe give you an account of why it's mixed up.
Okay, let's see now.
So here we are in the middle of purgatory, and what you're getting is some kind of mixture of Aristotle and Troubadour Christianity, somehow put together to try to explain everything that's going on.
I mean, what I really think is there's no coherent way to put it together.
It's not Dante's fault that you can't get Troubadour love of your lady together with Aristotle and Stoic views about desire and views about the total blissfulness of contemplating the supreme being.
There are just too many balls in the air to keep track of.
What I sort of reproach Dante for is that he doesn't signal the fact that Virgil is all mixed up until by the time he does, I'll try to show you that he does, but by that time we're all mixed up.
So here's what the best I can do.
So we discover you can't move at night, but after the sun goes down, you discover that different stars come out, starting on 181.
We're now in Canto 17, line 70, roughly.
And then now they discover they can't walk anymore.
Our strength, why do you melt away?
I said several times.
They're in a different place than they were the previous night, I think, but doesn't matter.
It's night again.
And my legs were turning to lead, and they've gotten to a certain style and as a certain level.
And now he asks Virgil, line 82, Dear Father, what impurity is washed in pain here, though our feet must stay, I beg you not to stay your speech.
And he, and now he starts a big speech about how things are.
They happen to be in the circle of sloth, which we'll come back to, but that's not what he's explaining right now.
He says, and he says, now at line 85, that love of good which in life before lay idle in the soul is paid for now.
Here, sloth strains at the once neglected oral.
He's already telling you, sloth is sort of being too lazy, not, again, not passionate about anything, not caring enough about anything.
But that you may more clearly know the way which your entire attention, give your entire attention to my words, and you shall gather good fruit from delay.
We'll use this time we can't walk for Virgil to explain things.
Now comes confusion.
He says, neither creator nor his creatures.
Now, what is he knowing about creator and creatures?
He's supposed to be talking from antiquity.
I've looked it up in the Italian.
That's what it says.
I don't know.
I mean, it looks like, I don't know what it looks like.
It looks like Dante's can't get it, can't keep clear track of what Virgil can know and what he can't know.
And you'll see it happening again in a minute.
He says, neither creature nor creator move as you well know, but in the action of animal or mind-directed love.
Now that's funny, because he didn't know a little while before that you had to be in the sun in order to move.
Now he says it's perfectly obvious as if, well, either he just learned it, which I don't think, or that anybody knows that you don't move except insofar as you love.
Now then it becomes three stanzas of total confusion, I think.
Natural love may never fall to error, the other may strive to good or bad ends by too little or too much fervor.
Now, I don't know, that sounds like a story about misdirected love.
And that's nice, except that's not an Aristotelian Virgil sort of thing.
And then it gets even weirder.
While it desires the eternal good, I don't even know if I should put you through this.
Don't get upset and don't try to understand it, because it doesn't, it's all confused.
The primal good is, or the eternal good is Aristotle's prime mover.
There is a kind of God-like something in Aristotle.
It's just not the God of the Christians, and it's not a God that you love, but it is somehow the mover of everything.
And then you should love secondary goods in reason.
Well, Virgil is talking mostly Christian-like, only sort of mapping it sort of into sort of semi-Aristotle talk.
Oh, dear, I don't know.
I shouldn't have even tried, but I'm going to read you one more paragraph, and then I'm going to say I don't know what to make of it.
But when it turns to evil or shows more or less zeal in it aught for what is good, the creature turns on the Creator.
You realize how all wrong that is for those three stanzas?
That's not Virgil's and Aristotle's view.
That's the Christian view.
I've just been telling you, that you can love some things too much and some things too little, that you desire the primal good, and the creature can turn on the Creator.
But he didn't understand how the creature could turn on the Creator.
That was what was happening at the wall.
So Virgil launches into this seemingly Christian story, and I don't get it.
And then he says, on the top of 182, line 110, and since no being may exist alone and apart from the first being, whatever that is, by their nature, all beings lack the power to hate that one.
Well, now he seems to think that now he's being like Virgil, sort of, because he doesn't understand the wall.
He doesn't understand sin.
He now has flipped over to the view that since God is desirable and fulfilling, no one could hate God.
So now he's missing his story about sin.
I shouldn't have launched into this.
Let me go to the punchline.
Where does he get things wrong?
I've got three minutes.
Go to page 190.
The final important thing for him is that you have the power to control your love.
And that means to, let's go back to the bottom of 189.
The crucial thing is in line 63.
That is, what you just take line 63, that you, because you have reason, you can guard the threshold of consent.
That Virgil thinks that since nothing in the world is really worthy of total love, your job to be a good person is to cut down your love to equal the relative lovableness of things.
But being a Stoic, he thinks that the most important thing you've got is the willpower not to totally love anything.
And that's right.
Here Virgil is being consistent.
I mean, he's being wrong in explaining the divine comedy, but he's consistent with his Stoic view that the highest thing you've got is the power not to go and adore anything, because nothing is worthy of total love and adoration.
That's sort of the sadness of Virgil.
That's why Virgil is in limbo.
Now, one, I got, according to that clock, one minute.
I said at the very end, Dante lets you in on the fact that at that point Virgil has gone wrong.
And how does he let you in on it?
Well, he says he was listening to Virgil, and what did he do listening to Virgil?
He said he found himself falling to sleep, line 87.
So since Virgil had answered my question so clearly, is he being ironic?
I think so.
My mind was rambling, I was rambling drowsy within my mind.
So the first thing is, when somebody gives a good lecture, explaining things clearly, you don't go to sleep.
I don't see anybody asleep here today, at least, happily.
But if you do give a confused and over-the-head of and bad lecture, then people start to go to sleep.
That's the first thing.
Dante hears this whole story, and his response is to fall asleep.
Secondly, it turns out that since they're on the level of sloth, the people who are always being done given the opposite of what they had before, these people who didn't love enough, are being made to be frantically energetic.
So he was awakened.
Now I'm 89, I'm going to stop, in an instant to a pack of people running towards us, a mob, they broke upon the mountain.
And what are they saying in line 103?
Faster, faster to be slow in love is to lose time.
So Virgil is talking on the circle of sloth because he is a case of sloth, because he's slow in love.
Because instead of saying you should soup up your love and direct it toward God, he's saying you should control your love and cut it down to how satisfying the world is.
And there Virgil has gone completely wrong.
At least it gets clear there.
There's a while I don't understand it, but there I think you can see Dante repudiating Virgil's view.
Okay, stop at that.