All I want to talk about is what it is to be a work of art and say that this is our best and in fact only example of a reconfiguring work of art that we've got, and that you can see enough in it to get a sense of what it is like to be a reconfigurer, changing the culture radically, but not quite knowing what you're doing.
And I'm going to go back to talking about that right away.
So the slogan for what it is to be a reconfigurer is that he was in the world and the world came into being through him.
As John says on the first page and all over the place over and over.
But I'm talking about what is, I've been told I should do book and verse instead of page numbers.
So I'm in, how do I do that?
11810.
If you look in the top corners, you get the book and the verse, I guess.
And then if you look at the little numbers, you get the line.
So if you say 1, 18, 10, you find he was in the world that had come into being through him.
And that very peculiar relationship to be able to create the world from within it is what we want to talk about.
And I had one new thought about it.
I think I think about it all the time.
And every once in a while something strikes me, and sometimes it turns out to be illuminating, and sometimes not.
It's very hard to describe.
I knew that.
What the artwork, when it works, or in this case, what Jesus does when he does his reconfiguring.
He's not discovering what was already there.
That would be articulating and renewing.
And he's not creating it.
It's something more like creating it, but creating it suggests that sort of creation ex nihilo, as they say.
That is, it's certainly not creation out of nothing.
There's something already there.
Otherwise, as I keep saying, the reconfigure would just be raving madness.
And Jesus comes close to being raving madness.
And a lot of the priests, high priests, think it is raving madness, but it isn't.
So what is it between discovering and creating?
Well, there's a word for it.
It's revealing.
It's a revelation.
We don't have to make up a word for it.
That's what people said it was.
That what Jesus is bringing is bringing a revelation.
A revelation isn't just discovering something that's already there, and it isn't creating it out of nowhere.
I've been calling it articulation.
I now think the Bible name for reconfiguring is revelation.
And I try to remember to use it that way.
Maybe that'll be illuminating and maybe it won't.
But I'll give it a try.
Where we were last time at the end was talking about the Holy Spirit.
I think I got the Holy Spirit wrong.
So I'm going to try again.
I was in a big hurry at the end, and I said the Holy Spirit is like the way the artwork shines, and it's the fact that in the light of the artwork, the Christian will always know what to do in each particular situation.
And I think that's all true.
The artwork shines, and for reasons I'll explain later, before the end of the lecture today, why the Christian knows what to do in every particular situation and doesn't need the law to tell the Christian.
But that's not what the paraclete, the Holy Spirit, is doing.
That the Holy Spirit is a counselor.
It gets translated that sometimes.
It's not something that happens to the Christian sort of inside.
It's something that happens in the public domain.
The Holy Spirit or the counselor comes after Jesus is gone.
And Jesus says, and we'll go look at that: the paraclete, that is the Holy Spirit, will teach you everything and remind you of all I have said.
Look at, I have to say 1264 to myself, and you can hear it too.
And then when I get there, to those who have a sense of what I should be saying, I'll give you the lines verse and so forth.
So in 164, we're in 1420.
And 1420 from there, we're in line 25.
Jesus says, I have said these things to you while still with you, but the paraclete, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, will teach you everything and remind you of all I have said to you.
Well, boy, is that different than saying, you know, that they will ask, every Christian will see everything in the light of this and act sort of spontaneously.
That's true, all right, but that's not the job the paraclete's doing.
It's going to teach, look at you everything and remind you of all I have said to you.
And remember that things weren't understandable before.
The world did not understand him or it while Jesus was around.
Well, after I said all that, what do you think the Paraclete is?
I mean, if you're trying to map this on the kind of ontology in which you've got reconfigurers, well, I'm convinced now until I get talked out of it, the Paraclete is the articulator.
Remember that I said, I mean, I was right in staring me in the face.
I said last time, every reconfigurer needs an articulator, because the reconfigurer is so confused because everything is so new, and there's no language to say what he's trying to say, or to trying to put in the work of art of whatever sort.
Every reconfiguring work, and I only know this one.
Well, no, I know I said Descartes was another hill, and there are probably more if you think about it.
But anyway, a reconfigurer needs at least one articulator.
Descartes had Kant, but then he had people after Kant too.
And Jesus has a whole bunch of articulators coming after him.
And I think they're all the Holy Spirit.
So the disciples are so dense, not out of stupidity, but just out of the fact that they can't, it's all so new, and there's no framework for Jesus to explain his teachings and practices.
So he better send somebody who can make sense of it all later on when he's gone.
As long as he's around, they can just sort of imitate him and be sort of overwhelmed by his glorification and his miracles, which I had forgotten play such a big role in the Gospel of John.
They don't play any role in what I'm talking about.
Well, I guess a weakness, but again, it's not what I'm trying to talk about.
So Jesus had better send somebody, and he does, and that's, and sends a whole series of people to explain what it's all about.
So there's more about this on 160.
That's 16, 13, 16, and then 13, and then line 13.
However, when the Spirit of truth comes, that's the Holy Spirit again, he will lead you to the complete truth, since he will not be speaking of his own accord, but will say only what he has been told.
That is, the articulator will do not what his own ideas are, but he'll articulate what the reconfigurer was, so to speak, groping for and trying to say, only it was so new he couldn't say it.
That seems, yeah.
Uh-oh.
Which part?
Now, I hear lots of strange noises, but I can't tell what I'm doing.
If I fixed it, I can't tell by feeling.
Okay, now, is that okay?
And now I'm not going in and out, and it's better.
Okay, good.
Thanks.
Whenever you or anybody finds that it's not going well, let me know because we've got these podcast people literally all over the world who are listening.
I just got an email this morning from a truck driver who listens as he drives his big rig across the country and says when he comes to a truck stop and gets time, he's going to send me a paper on the Brothers Karamatsov.
He's listening to Pelosi 7.
So we have to be helpful to these people.
Okay, so here we are.
Now, so the Spirit will lead them to say what the Reconfigure has been trying to say.
And who are these articulators, these counselors, these Holy Spirits that are being sent?
Well, I think they are St.
Paul, who is the first to write his systematic account of what's the most important thing in all this, which for him is love.
It's amazing how little the role of love plays in the Gospel of John.
It gets mentioned, I think, just twice, but it's the most important thing.
And Jesus already says it's the most important thing, but Paul makes a big fuss about this being the most important thing.
Then there's the Gospel of John.
I think that's also sent.
And then people you've vaguely heard about me mentioning maybe St.
Augustine in 300 AD, roughly, has his way of articulating the whole thing by mapping the whole story onto Plato, which turns out not to be very successful for reasons I haven't got time to go into.
And then St.
Thomas Aquinas does his articulating, and that's what Dante draws on.
So next week, I'll say a little bit more about Aristotle and St.
Thomas.
And then Luther comes along as another kind of articulator and another example of Pericleta, I think.
And he, well, Dante makes total sense of this and St.
Thomas.
But they make sense of it one way, as you'll see.
And then Luther comes along and just flips it around.
He's almost a reconfigurer, but not really, because Jesus and the Savior and all that is still central for him.
But Luther makes a big switch on it and renews it.
All that's under the category, under the, I think, of what the Holy Spirit does.
And what's interesting is there could be only one reconfigurer.
That's why Jesus is the incarnation.
He's not an incarnation.
I mean, you can't re, if there were another one, it would be of a different world because every reconfigurer produces a world.
But there can be lots of articulators.
And I don't think one should think of them as little incarnations.
Incarnation is a job for reconfigurers to embody a new truth.
But there is this one incarnation, and then there are all these articulators, and we need a name for them.
So we'll call them the Paraclete.
And that's what I think I should have said.
Now, now comes what I want to talk about today, having fixed, I hope, what I did last time.
And that is, well, how is this reconfiguring done?
We get to see it done right, so to speak, in front of us.
Uh-oh, but we don't get to see it quite as much as I hoped, because I think I left a page.
Come on, but that's all right.
I sort of know it.
No, I've got it.
But I'm not ready to read it yet.
So, how does it get, we're going to see in front of us in slow motion, so to speak, a world being transformed utterly, namely the Hebrew world being transformed into what will later be called the Christian world, and we need to see how it's going to happen.
And there are probably lots of ways of looking at this, but the way I want to look at it, because it's the way I can understand it, is that Jesus says he's the truth and the way, and you can hear this.
The truth is that he's got a whole new description of everything, cosmos and God and people and so forth.
Then, the way, I just decided this morning means it's a way of life.
It's also a path to God, in that sense, the way, but that's not what I want to think about today.
In Dante, there's a different sense in which Jesus is the way, the way to get there.
But I think the main thing is it's the way to live and to be the only way, according to Jesus, to live, to be a human being.
And that's what we have to figure out: what that way is, and how he's going to switch the Hebrew way of being to the Christian way of being.
And so, here we go.
The Hebrew way, as you hear sort of in the background conversation, because since they're all Hebrews, they can sort of take it for granted, is that you live according to the law.
I mentioned that already.
There's the Ten Commandments, but there's also the whole book of the Old Testament devoted to the laws, down to the tiniest laws about what you can and can't do on the Sabbath and what you can and can't eat and so forth.
And the laws sort of totally circumscribe what you can and can't do, and you live by that, then you're righteous.
I talked about that just briefly, but now we have to talk about it much more.
And what Jesus is going to do is get rid, well, get rid isn't the right way to put it, is going to do something to the notion of righteousness so that it turns out to mean something very, very, very different than what it meant before.
And the way to live is going to turn out to mean something very, very different, something totally new on the planet, I think.
I don't think any other culture had it or any other culture ever got it except the way, except our culture, insofar as and as long as we are or were this kind of Christian culture.
And I did give a slogan for what will have to be done by a reconfigurer.
I don't know if any of you remember.
I'm not even sure whether I actually said it.
But the way you reconfigure, well, let me set it up.
How could you reconfigure a culture?
It looks like it's a kind of impossible thing.
Because if you totally change it, you're crazy, and nobody understands a thing you're saying.
And if you use the language that's already there, you're just an articulator of the old.
You're not a beginner of the radically new.
But is there something in between repeating and sharpening up and articulating on the one hand and being raving mad on the other?
Original to the point of craziness.
Yes, there is, and it's very interesting.
Jesus shows us how to do it.
And that is, take something crucial in the practices that you're in at that point and make it marginal.
And take something that's marginal in the practices, barely noticed, and make it central.
That gives you all you want.
It sort of destroys the old understanding or totally relativizes it.
And it makes you intelligible because you've got something from the old practices.
And Jesus does it.
And he does it in something that you don't have a copy of because I didn't think of adding it to the Gospel of John handout.
So I will have to tell you, it's the Gospel of Matthew 5.
And I'm going to read you from it.
The crucial sentence.
I mean, this is all my story.
I don't know whether I didn't find this in any books.
For all I know, everybody says this or nobody says this, but here's how it looks to me.
There's one way to see the flipover.
As I say, not the only way.
Is a sentence in the Sermon on the Mount.
Jesus is giving this speech.
Is it in anything besides Matthew?
I don't think so.
It's in.
I see.
Is this sentence in it always?
He says, you have learned, you were told, do not commit adultery.
But what I tell you is this.
If a man looks on a woman with a lustful eye, he's already committed adultery with her in his heart.
I don't know if that's in all of them, but that's going to flip around.
When you see all the implications of saying that, you will see that if you believe that, you're no longer in the Hebrew culture.
You're in some completely different world.
But I have to spell that out to explain why that's so.
Now, why is that so weird?
Well, if you are obeying the law, then what you do is a public sort of thing.
You don't kill people.
You tell the truth.
You honor the Sabbath.
It's a whole list of things.
You eat what's kosher or not, and you don't eat what's not kosher.
There's a whole list of things that you do, public things, and you don't commit adultery.
Or if you do, you're in big trouble.
Then you do a public thing.
You sleep with somebody's wife or husband.
And so what's interesting is if you obey the law, then it's all a question of options, public actions.
And it's under your control.
I mean, you can commit adultery or not commit adultery.
It's strictly up to you.
Or murder somebody or not murder somebody.
There's a whole list of things that you're supposed to do and you're able to do and able not to do.
And that's how you, and if you do what you're supposed to do, you lead a righteous life.
And if you don't, you lead a life.
I don't know what's probably not called sinner.
What's the opposite of righteous?
Do you know?
Wicked?
But I don't know what the term what I don't know what it is.
But anyway, you do the opposite.
You're unrighteous.
We can at least say that.
Okay, so, but the idea is that you should, it's all right to say don't commit adultery.
That's part of the law.
But suppose you say, don't lust after a woman in your heart.
What weird commandment is that?
It's nothing public.
You can't sort of get three witnesses who say, yes, I saw him.
He was lusting after her in his heart and drag him into court.
There's nobody who can tell, and it doesn't make any difference anyway, because you don't do anything about it.
And suppose you try not to lust after a woman in your heart because you believe Jesus that that's a very bad thing to do.
Well, of course, that makes it only worse.
You will have more fantasies about what you might be doing with this woman.
You can't control your desires.
And Jesus is saying, and this is the crucial thing, what you should do is have pure desires.
And what you are told you can't do, you will be sinful.
Now we have a word for it, if you have the wrong desires, like lustful desires.
So what was, so, and you are defined by your desires.
You're either a pure person who has the right kind, the good desires, or you're an impure person who has bad desires.
And if you have pure good desires, you're a good person.
And if you have these bad, lustful desires, you're a bad person.
And lo and behold, you can't do anything about it.
You can't decide by your free will and your actions whether you're a good person or a bad person.
That is pretty serious.
That was driving Paul crazy that he was going to be sort of defined by his desires, and he had all these desires that he didn't want to have, but he couldn't help having them.
So, and what is and what is he doing?
Well, Jesus is taking the law culture where desire doesn't even have, doesn't seem to have even a marginal, and you can't control it because there's no public example of it, you can't see it happening, and so forth.
And he wants to make it central, take it from being marginal and private and make it definitive of what you're doing and who you are.
And then I got to this point and thought, I've been teaching it this way, I've been teaching it this way for years, when a student came and both gave me a tremendous problem and solved the problem all at once.
Here's the problem I was worrying about, but what about what marginal, if your desires are what you shouldn't have?
And that's a marginal practice to say that there are desires you shouldn't have.
Where is there any evidence of that in the Hebrews that they cared at all about desires?
I mean, it's all about law.
That was my problem.
Because I had this theory, it must, how is he going to be even intelligible?
If you went into Bali, for instance, and said, you know, you committed, you become sinful if you lust after a woman in your heart, it's not likely to be intelligible at all.
How come it was intelligible to the Hebrews?
Well, then a student said to me, thinking he was shooting me down, that really helping me a lot, but the Hebrews do care about desires.
How many know the Ten Commandments?
Anybody?
Do you recognize what there's a commandment about desire tucked in there?
One.
Exactly.
You shall not covet your neighbor's property, his wife, and so forth.
That's coveting is a private desiring thing.
You can't sort of catch somebody coveting and then take them to court about it.
Moreover, if you can't help coveting your neighbor's BMW or whatever the latest version of this is.
Yeah, Barry.
Aha.
Interesting.
How does it fit with Descartes inventing the inner, Barry asks?
Because they had the inner already.
I guess it's another version of taking something marginal and making it central.
For the Hebrews, there was something inner.
For the Christians, what was inner was very important.
For Descartes, everything is inner.
I mean, there's us and there's the external world.
And all of our experience is inner.
We can talk more about that.
But it gets more and more extreme.
But it's inner enough already with coveting.
And it's interesting that it's not an accident, I'm sure, that the Hebrews get more inner in Jesus and it gets more inner in Augustine.
What's puzzling is it doesn't get any more inner in St.
Thomas, but that's because Aristotle got into the act.
Well, we'll have to put, let's put that aside.
Okay, we'll talk about it when we don't have to presuppose things that I would have to explain.
So let me go back to, so here we are.
I got told, look at this commandment about coveting.
At the time, I thought, gee, that's the disaster for my view, because I just said the Hebrews don't understand how you could be responsible and guilty for your desires.
And here they are giving you one of the commandments for which you should be responsible and guilty for your desires.
So my first move was, as you might imagine, look at the translation.
Surely people have mistranslated the Hebrew for years.
Coveting can't be.
Those are sort of wishing you had what the neighbor has.
And I couldn't, I mean, I tried all the various Hebrew translations I knew of people to give me.
No, it really says coveting.
Coveting is really when you're looking on your neighbor's whatever and wishing you had it.
And so, but then I realized, no, but that's, I shouldn't be trying to get rid of it.
It's the answer to my problem.
It's the marginal practice that there is a dim sense that sometimes your desires can be bad and can be important.
They're not very important.
They don't define you.
We've got all kinds of other important jobs to do that are not desires.
Keep the Sabbath, keep the food right, don't kill people, and so forth and so forth.
Let me say one more thing, and then you can.
But what's interesting to me, and maybe you're about to give me a new problem, I love it, if it's true, that there's exactly 10% of the practices in the Ten Commandments anyway, are desire practices, and I suspect 90% are action and law practices.
As I said, you can actually see it happening that you're switching the marginal to the center.
Jesus is, and he's switching, and we haven't seen what he does to the law yet, but it's clear that if it's going to turn out to be important, how if your desires are going to turn out to be what's most important, the law is going to be put in some kind of new position.
But first, I want to hear what you have to say.
Yeah.
Because I'm not sure I heard you, but I think I did.
You mean because it's one of the Ten Commandments, it's already not marginal.
It's important.
Is that what you said?
Okay.
Yeah, I think that's right.
But it's only, I mean, how can I put it?
It's very important, but there are at least nine other equally important, or some of them much more important, I think, for the Sabbath and God honoring God and so forth.
It's 10% of what's important is all right with me.
That's pretty marginal.
I mean, it doesn't, nobody gets, sort of spells out and worries a lot about coveting, as far as I know, where they've got other things to worry about, like the law about the Sabbath, because the law tells you what you can and can't do.
So I'm going to stick to this.
I mean, you can just make it sort of, you know, rough.
I mean, I can't, there's no such way as to say exactly what percent of the practices, coveting practices are, and what percent of the law prohibits desiring things.
And you can look for yourselves, reread the Ten Commandments, think about it.
How much of the Hebrew system holds you responsible for your desires and thinks of you as guilty or not, depending on your desires, and finally defines who you are in terms of whether you have pure or impure desires.
That's what makes the difference between being saved and not saved.
As we'll see in a minute.
Okay, now let's see.
So, what you have to do is purify your desires.
I'm now back, I'm not in the Hebrew anymore.
I'm back in the Christian for a minute.
From Jesus' point of view, you have to purify your desires.
But that's not up to you.
So, what does it mean?
You have to be saved.
That is, somebody has to come in and rescue you, because there you are, full of bad desires, and everybody has them, and the more you resist them, the worse they get.
And only a Savior can save you.
And how would a Savior save you?
Well, you'd have to be in some way transformed.
And the words for it are reborn.
You have to be reborn as a non-sinful, non-bad desiring person.
And only Jesus can do that for you.
If Jesus takes over your body and lives in you, then you no longer will have the sinful desires.
And that's a big change.
You see, the more you spell out this one little thing about don't, you commit adultery if you lust after it in your heart, and you see all the implications of it, a whole different role for Jesus comes in there.
I mean, no rabbi or priest had to come along and save you, transform you, give you the new body, and in order to make you able to be a good and joyful human being.
Anyone want to say anything about this?
Glimmers of doubt or agreement.
Okay, well, I'm going to go on.
So, and when you get transformed, you will have a new commandment.
The new commandment, which is a very important one, 1263, and in fact, replaces all the other commandments, it turns out.
Oh, where's my 1263?
Ah, yeah, 1263.
Okay, that's 14, 19 in the right-hand corner.
It's line 34.
I give you a new commandment.
Love one another.
You must love one another just as I love you.
Now, that's a bigger deal than John makes it out to be.
Paul is the one who sees that that's a very, very big deal.
Because once you love one another, you aren't going to have these bad desires anymore.
You're going to help your neighbor.
But the question will still be: and how do you get to be able to have this kind of love, which I will explain more in a minute.
Well, you can't do it by willpower because you're full of all these bad desires.
So you have to be, we're back to that again, transformed and reborn.
But when you are transformed and reborn, then you've got love.
And gape.
That gets translated charity.
But now charity has come to mean so much like giving to the poor that it's better to go back to calling it love.
And Paul says faith, hope, and love are the main thing, and of those three, love is the most important.
I think he says that, doesn't he?
So love turns out to be everything.
And agape is a kind of love, and it's a different kind of love than what you have when you have the bad desires.
That's eros.
Eros from Plato, we get erotic from that, is desire that comes from lack.
You need something.
And that's how you are when you're lusting after your neighbor's wife or husband and so forth.
And agape is the kind of love you have when you've already been transformed and completely fulfilled so that you don't need anything.
And you've got overflowing love for everybody that you can help in any way that gets sort of summed up in love your neighbor.
And now, how is this related to the law?
Well, in a way, there's so many things I want to say at once.
I think the way to do it is this.
I don't think my notes are in the best right order.
In the Sermon on the Mount, back to that.
Here it is.
He begins, Jesus, by addressing the question of the law.
Because I guess I should try to keep this in clear order.
Now the question ought to be.
Let me try to keep it straight.
How is this going to be, what are we going to do with the law?
It's going to preserve it but marginalize it?
Because that's what you've got to do if you're going to flip around the margin to the center, which we just did.
Desire and a special kind of, not even desire.
It turns out desire is still bad.
Love turns out to be, a certain kind of feeling turns out to be central to everything.
It's the commandment.
But what happens to the other commandments?
What happens to the law?
You can't just throw it away.
You're not going to get the Hebrews to throw away the law.
So you've got to have a way to save the law.
Well, this is what Jesus starts the Sermon on the Mount with.
Do not suppose, it doesn't start.
It's Matthew 5:17.
Do not suppose that I have come to abolish the law.
But I did not come to abolish, but to complete.
I'm going to have to figure out what that means.
I tell you this, so long as heaven and earth endure, not a letter, not a stroke will disappear from the law until all that must happen, has happened, all that must happen has happened.
I don't know what that means.
Maybe it means that everybody has been transformed into loving people.
If any man sets aside even the least of the law's demands and teaches others to do the same, he will have the lowest place in the kingdom of heaven.
So it looks like, at first sight anyway, it's really complicated and interesting.
The law is doing fine.
Jesus hasn't put down the law.
You're supposed to obey it completely.
And it's the most important thing to do to obey it completely.
Yet, and this is when it gets sort of puzzling and interesting, Jesus himself breaks the law.
And that's when the rabbis get very upset at him.
He's not honoring the Sabbath on 1243.
Then I'll tell you what else that is.
1243?
That seems unlikely.
Yeah, yeah.
The very first, the very beginning.
Line 16, the first page.
Indeed, from his fullness, we have all of us received one gift replacing another.
For the law was given through Moses, grace and truth have come through Jesus Christ.
So something has replaced the law, but not gotten rid of the law.
How can you understand that?
Well, for one thing, you don't really have to obey the law anymore in spite of what the Sermon on the Mount says.
And it's all sort of confusing because, as I keep saying, Jesus is very confused about it.
He hasn't got a clear idea of what it is that the law is supposed to do, but he knows something, namely, that you don't have to literally obey the law in order to somehow be in tune with the law, let's say, or, yeah, something like that.
So here's what happens.
We're now on page 1248.
Just to say it quick outright, guys, some of you probably noticed, maybe.
Jesus goes around and does things on the Sabbath that the law says you're not supposed to do on the Sabbath.
So it can't be that when the Sermon on the Mount says you shouldn't, you have to do, not one letter, not a stroke of the law will disappear.
That can't be quite taken literally because he's breaking the law.
And here it is on 437, line 8.
Jesus said, after he heals this man who's been crippled for years, get up, pick up your sleeping mat, and walk around.
The man was cured and walked around.
Now that day happened to be the Sabbath.
So the Jews said to the man who had been cured, it is the Sabbath.
You're not allowed to carry your sleeping mat.
And he replied, that the man who cured me told me, pick up your sleeping mat and walk around.
And then looking at the next page, line 15, the man went back and told the Jews that it was Jesus who had cured him.
It was because he did things like this on the Sabbath that the Jews began to harass Jesus.
His answer to them was, My father still goes on working, and I'm at work too.
But that only made the Jews even more intent on killing him because he was breaking, because not only was he breaking the Sabbath, but he spoke as if God was his father.
But we're sticking to breaking the Sabbath.
Now, how can you understand what's going on there?
And how does the law get marginalized into something much less important than it was, and even in a certain sense, clearly breakable, and yet completely, somehow preserved and even completed and fulfilled?
Well, Jesus doesn't explain it.
As I say, he doesn't understand it.
And John doesn't explain it.
Even he doesn't understand it.
I don't know whether Paul might.
I'm not an expert in reading Paul.
But Augustine understands it.
Augustine says, love and do what you will.
Now, what does that mean?
That means that if you're filled with agape love for all people, and whatever you do will be, so to speak, in that situation, the right thing to do, the good thing to do.
And it'll sometimes, as I said, I think last time, I don't remember why I already said it, it could be tough love.
in which you refuse them what they're asking for.
It could be tender love, in which you give them what they're asking for, or it could be the kind of love that helps them understand what they really need.
But in any given situation, if you don't have any selfish desires and any needy lusts, but you are just sensitive to what the situation requires, you will do the appropriate thing.
And on the Sabbath, if somebody needs to get cured and get up and carry their sleeping mat around, then they'll do that.
And that, this is my version.
Now, maybe not the right or the official version, I don't know.
But that completes the law or fulfills the law because if the law was trying to get people to do what was the right thing to do by giving them all these rules, this fixes it because now you can do the right thing without having to have any rules, provided you have the right desires or the right, you see, if I put desire up here, I need something to call this.
I don't know what to call it, the right feelings or something.
What is love?
It's not a desire.
It's a, I don't know, affect maybe.
Fancy word.
Anyway, just one second.
Let me say, so, so, let me just try to finish this.
So the job the law was trying to do was to get, which was to get people to do what was a good thing to do, has now been completed better because these old rules were just too crude.
Just to say you can't ever help somebody out on the Sabbath if that helping out goes against the kind of things you could do or not do by the rules.
That's much too crude.
If you could get somebody into an emotional state in which they were always open and sensitive to the needs of whatever was going on, you would do what the law was trying to do, that is, enable people, lead people to do good things all the time, and then you would have completed the law.
But you would have, and then I'll let you talk in a second, would have relativized the law.
Because now the whole law turns out to be all turning around this commandment that you should love your neighbors and be filled with agape love.
And the details of the law aren't important anymore at all.
Because they, again, I say, it's the spirit of the law is now what's going to save.
That's a Jesus comment, isn't it?
The spirit saves.
Paul.
Paul says the spirit of the law saves, but not the letter of the law.
And that's just what I'm saying.
I mean, don't worry about the rules as long as you are a saved, reborn, pure, loving person.
Do whatever seems like you need to do.
Love, as Augustine says, love and do what you will.
That's my version of how you can marginalize the law without in any way thinking that you've abrogated it.
Now, I saw a hand.
Where was it?
I don't want to keep you from talking.
Somebody over there.
Yes.
Yes, it certainly is.
In fact, I'm making it up from there.
Let's see if I can say anything that will help.
That's a deep, deep question.
I mean, here's, there is in Aristotle the idea that the phronomus in Greek, that people use the Greek word, but it gets translated the man of practical wisdom, does the appropriate thing at the appropriate time in the appropriate way.
That is, without any rules, this wise person who's had lots of experience just is sensitive to the needs of the situation.
And that's virtue in Aristotle.
Now, you pose me the really tough question, too.
I don't think the phronomus, the man of practical wisdom, and who has virtue, is at all like the Christian saved soul that is filled with agape love.
Now, why is that?
Well, my first hunch is, oh, you all, he'll follow, and then you, and then my, go ahead.
Yes, but I mean, but we need the phenomenology of it.
That is, what's the experience of agape love and the way it you live when you're when you have it that differs from the experience of the phronomus who has virtue and live in when he has you think let's let let Dave try.
Yeah.
I think that the discussion there's been that friendship ah that's that's true.
Let's put that in here.
That doesn't solve my problem altogether.
But it's activity.
That's true.
For Aristotle, when you're doing this practical good thing, it's in the context of doing good things for your friends, doing good things for the polis, doing things that will make you flourish, doing good things for your own happiness.
The idea that you just do good things for no reason except that you've overflowing love and you don't do them just for your friends, and you certainly don't do them just to flourish, and you don't do them for your country.
You do them just out of love, period.
That's the difference.
And the other difference I was going to get at, which is related to that, the man of practical wisdom, the Aristotelian one, has willpower involved.
I mean, he can do it or not do it, do whatever he thinks is the appropriate thing.
And so he and he has, so his character is what, and his strengthening of his will is important.
Whereas the Christian soul is going to give up his will altogether and let Jesus' love flow through him or her.
And it's not the kind of thing that you can resist and say no to or sort of decide to do and then do.
There's a lot more rationality and control, I think, in the Aristotelian man of practical wisdom than there is in the Christian saint.
I mean, this, the pure reborn person is a saint, obviously.
They are when they say things like Jesus lives in me, Jesus acts through me, they are a channel for this agape love.
And Aristotle couldn't have any view like that.
But the idea, but this prepares you for Dante, so I'll say one more thing.
Dante is trying to understand Christianity using Aristotelian categories.
Or that isn't even quite right.
Dante is using Virgil to explain Christianity using Aristotelian categories.
And the interesting question you have to have in mind as you read Dante, I'll show you how to do it next time, is Virgil getting it right, trying to explain the Christian world with Aristotle as his only person to go on, which reminds me of something even more important, to give you the assignment for next time.
So you've got the inferno now.
You want to read for next time.
It's on the syllabus, but I just want to repeat it.
So cantos, that's what they're divided up into now.
Cantos 1 to 11.
Yeah, Beatrice.
That's right.
But in this new way, you don't have to internalize all the rules because you have one rule that we face.
Yes, I think that's right.
But the thronomus starts with rules and ends up with this sort of sensitivity to the particular situation.
Whereas the Christian, the reborn Christian, just both gets rid of the rules, that's the letter of the law, and keeps the spirit of it as understood by Jesus and Paul, namely loving whoever loving your neighbor.
Okay, anybody else?
I better go back to where I am, which is hard to know because I've jumped all over.
So give me a moment.
Well, I wrote here, of course, the disciples don't understand this.
Let's look and see what that means.
1245.
I mean, the more you think about it, the more you see how hard it would be for anybody to understand it.
And the disciples are not in any particular position to get it right.
And if you think of Jesus as somebody who is somehow knows that he's a reconceived, I mean, no, that's not the way to put it.
Jesus, who's got a whole new way of thinking about what human beings essentially are, namely defined by their desires, and what the law really is, namely, not rules, but something more basic, they're going to have trouble articulating this.
So let's see now where I am to check this out.
Okay, 1245.
Actually, wait a minute.
This is not what I'm expecting to see.
What I got here is just to show you something I already said, that I've got to go back and look at it.
That is, down on 3, 6, line 3, they're talking to Jesus, and this is about being reborn.
Well, now let's go down to line 5.
In all truth, I tell you, no one can enter the kingdom of God without being born through water and the Spirit.
What is born of human nature is human.
What is born of the Spirit is Spirit.
All that is just to say you've got to be totally transformed.
You can't just be born once, and then you're just a human being with all your lusts and desires.
You have to be reborn to be able to be pure in the way that Jesus is claiming you have to be pure.
And I don't know why I say that they couldn't understand this.
Now, I don't want to go into that.
So, did I read you already 148, 149, where he's setting aside the law and how he's talking about that?
Okay, well, we've got to look at this.
Okay, there's where he picked up.
Oh, yeah, I've done that.
Good.
And I've done it.
We did that.
That's where you are even better.
Okay, I'm ready to sum up, which I will do.
I'm not keeping anybody from saying anything.
Then let's go look at this.
So, what does this new cultural paradigm, this reconfigurer, Jesus, plus the articulator, John, change from the world of Virgil, the Roman world?
Well, one thing is that instead of being stuck with sluggish bodies, the body is now absolutely central and important.
It's not the lustful body, but the reborn body, but it's still the body.
After all, God became a body.
If there was something wrong with bodies, if they were just sluggish and stupid and got in the way, why in the world would God become a body?
Having a body is absolutely essential to being a human being on this line, in a way that it isn't at all in Virgil.
And you get this coming out on 1245, 3, 6, and then 19.
Jesus says, Destroy this temple, and in three days I will rebuild it.
The Jews replied, It's taken 46 years to build the temple.
Are you going to raise it up again in three days?
But he was speaking of the temple, it was his body.
And when Jesus rose from the dead, his disciples remembered that he had said this.
I just, that's a hint that the body is a temple.
The body is a very, very good thing.
You'll see in Dante, too, that the people who die can't get along at all without bodies.
And Dante has a problem about that, which he solves.
So the first thing is the body has become important.
The word has been made flesh from that.
And it turns out that what happens in the world is important.
You can't get out of the world.
Remember, because Jesus is now incarnated God and shows God and is God, then there is an individual being in the world, in time, who is crucially important.
God isn't some other some, God the Father is something.
You don't ever get to see God the Father on this new version of Jesus' version.
You get to see Jesus, who is an embodied, particular human being in the world, and yet crucially important, able to be worshipped, and is in effect a God.
He's a God, if you think of him in the way that he did in the people writing and the Gospel of John did, somehow God with a capital G.
I mean, I don't, I'm not a Christian believer, so I'm not sure I understand what that is, but that's all right.
He's also a God in the sense that he's a reconfigurer, he reveals a new world, he changes what it is to be a human being, that is, changes, makes it possible for people to be reborn, and all of that is something amazing that an individual human being could do that.
And when a human being can do that, they're no longer just a human being.
They're treated as sacred, they're adored, worshipped, they have all the properties of a God.
And that's happening.
And the present is important because unlike in the Aeneid, when it's either for Aeneids the past, the glory of Troy, or the future glory of Rome that matters, but the present doesn't matter.
This is what in the Bible is called the fullness of time.
When Jesus is there, that is the most important present.
Everything led up to that and everything that's going to happen from now on in the world is going to be determined by that.
That's why we recount the years from zero when Jesus, everything up to zero leads up to the God becoming man, and everything after zero, us, after AD, after God, that's what that AD means.
I'm saying, Doningo, everything after word gets its meaning all from this moment, this special moment when Jesus declared what?
Well, now we have a word for it, the revelation.
He reconfigured everything.
Okay, so the present is very important.
The law has been replaced by adapto, that is the law, the duty of the Romans to obey the law and do their civic duty.
All that's been replaced by love and do what you will.
And, well, I keep saying it, and that's the sense.
Now, I just sort of step back and say what I've said.
There you get to see what reconfiguration looks like, sort of step by step.
I'm sure you could tell the same story about without having to start with lusting after a woman in your heart and adultery.
But you'd come to the same place no matter where you started.
You would be able to tell a story about how marginal practices got to be central for the Christians, and how the practices that were central for the Hebrews became marginal, and therefore you got a whole new world.
Okay, that's how much I want to say about that.
Now, either you all can say something, or I'm going to go on and talk about a kind of transition to Dante so that you have it in mind when you start trying to read it.
But first, I want to make sure we've finished.
I finish what I have to say about this, but I want to make sure that you finished, that you're either helpful or objecting or confused and want me to unconfuse you, or you want to confuse me.
Yeah, Beatrice.
Yes, Jesus.
Good.
Jesus is, as described by John, of course.
We have to take John's word for it in this course.
So Jesus, as described by John, is a work of art working.
He is in his activity and in what he's saying and what he's showing, revealing a whole new understanding of being, and that's that makes him a work of art working.
What is God the Father?
Goodly.
Yeah, let's go through the Trinity again.
By the way, I found one place where John comes close to mentioning the Trinity.
For Christians, it should come as a surprise that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, which are the three aspects of God, hardly ever get mentioned in here, as far as I know, once.
And in the other Gospels, I think not at all.
There's God the Father sometimes.
There's God the Son sometime, that's Jesus.
There's the Holy Spirit sometime.
But the idea that they're all three, and all of them are God, you hear at various points, but that there is one God who has these three aspects put together in one sentence, so to speak.
I only found it on 1250 27.
Oh, wrong.
I'm sorry, that's not what I'm saying.
I may not find it.
I wasn't going to mention it.
But I think it's important to mention.
Although it's not a very exciting sentence when you get right down to it.
It's just that all three characters in it are mentioned.
If I don't find it, no, I didn't find it.
But anyway, I'll tell you.
What I'm taking to be God the Father, who would remember is invisible and is the creator of everything in that it it's thanks to God that anything sh shows up as anything.
People and things all get their shape and so forth.
And that's the background practices.
That's the basic general language and practices of the people.
That's got to be there already.
And then the articulator, Jesus, will take what is invisible background and embody it and glamorize it and make it shine.
By the way, glamorize, I realize too, there's a word for that.
All these words that you sort of I make up in trying to talk about it, I discovered the people who talked about it already had words.
Jesus, as a work of art, isn't glamorized.
He's glorified.
That's the word for it.
And he is, in his shining and in his glory, manifest the invisible background practices so that you never have to get in touch with them anymore.
I mean, they pervade everything.
They're the background of all intelligibility and meaning.
They're why anything is able to show up as anything.
But Jesus has now made it much more clear what the implications of all that is.
And also, not only he's revealed it, but that doesn't mean it was there all along and he just discovered it by telling people how the law is fulfilled, for instance, and showing them a God they love and telling them that it's the most important commandment and showing them how he can give it to them and so forth.
He's taken up and transformed the background practices so that he's reconfigured them.
And how does this relate now to God?
What happens to God the Father?
Well, God the Father gets revealed in Jesus.
And now I'm trying to think, how do we ought to have a way of describing how God the Father gets transformed when the reconfigurer does what the reconfigurer does?
And how you don't get that in John.
Maybe that's another problem to think about for me.
Let me tell you clearly what I think the problem is.
I mean, if God is the understanding in the background practices, and you could have an articulator who just articulated that.
But if you've got a reconfigurer who changes the practices so that the law gets put into the love gets put as a new commandment and all that, that looks like that changes God.
And that's odd.
I don't mind, except that John doesn't talk that way.
Jesus keeps saying, I just do what the Father tells me to do.
All I do is already, I mean, I never do anything in my own, on my own.
I only speak for the Father.
That is, I only manifest what's already in the background practices.
Then, how can He reconfigure God?
Hmm.
I don't know.
That's really deep.
Yeah.
Well, I don't think so.
I don't think that John or Jesus claim that the God of the Old Testament was already into agape and nobody noticed.
I mean, the God of the Old Testament was into giving Moses the law and the keeping the law, and that was what was in the background.
And that was still in the God that was in the background when Jesus showed up.
Now, you could say, well, that God already really wanted people to have agape loved and being reborn and so forth.
But why wouldn't you want to say that?
I mean, it looks like that's something that...
But Jesus is sort of saying, I see what Beatrice is saying.
That is the easy way out.
Maybe you have to take the easy way out, but I'm going to try a harder one.
But the easy way out is to say, well, that's what God was trying to say all along.
Jesus keeps saying, I'm not saying anything new.
Everything I'm saying has been dictated by the Father.
You could read that as exactly what Beatrice says.
The real meaning of the background practices ever since Abraham has been this.
But they haven't, they didn't know it.
And once you know it, it changes everything.
I find that rather strange.
I mean, I think, I don't know what to think.
Yeah.
That's right.
And it's such a big change that now, if you ask Beatrice this question, and now if you ask, well, who is God the Father?
What is God the Father?
It would be better my way of thinking.
Well, no, he's not because Jesus says that, you know, he's more powerful than me.
Everything I say, I get from him.
And so I'm happy to say God the Father is the background practices, the background understanding of being, but then, of course, I get into the trouble.
Then, has it been already all what the reconfigurer has just discovered?
That doesn't feel right.
When Jesus reveals it, the background practices, if he's really a reconfigurer, he changes them.
And if he changes them, and God the Father really is the background practices, then God changes.
Yes, a new background is given.
Yes, that's right.
A new background is given.
But then you ought to say that God has been changed.
Since God is the background, God has changed.
And I don't mind saying God has changed, but boy, that doesn't seem to be what John wants to say.
Maybe that's just because it's so radical, John doesn't know how to say it.
I mean, but I didn't realize I was committed to this, but I begin to think I am committed to this, and that's what Beatrice has forced me to see.
It's just that the understanding of God has changed.
Okay, the understanding of being in the background practices has changed.
That maybe that's okay.
At any given stage, yeah, I think you're getting on the right track.
I think that we should, I mean, we're now getting really revisionary, I think.
You have to save the notion of God for Jesus.
I think who was saying that?
Maybe Barry was saying it.
I think Jesus is God because he's the one who now, no, I don't want that either.
The background practices are God, and they've changed.
Jesus is God because he changed them.
But I don't get it yet.
Beatrice, you started this.
This is very interesting.
The whole conversation of God Abraham, the whole thing before.
Oh, yeah, that's right.
This is Abraham.
Jesus replies, in all truth, I found him before Abraham never was by them.
Yes, that's very important and very relevant.
I don't know what to make of it, though.
We're telling everybody where that is.
What?
1256.
I mean, Jesus is claiming.
We're getting into really difficult stuff here.
Remember, I don't think this is going to help, but I put it on the table as part of what one would have to get straight if they ever got this straight.
Jesus is claiming, according to John, that he's eternal, that Jesus is.
He's the word made flesh, and the word was with God all along.
And Jesus was there before Abraham, Jesus claims, according to the Gospel of John.
I think that's all Johnish talk, is it?
Is it in the other three Gospels?
No.
See, this is, John is putting a very platonic Greek spin on it.
If whatever is the ultimate meaning of reality must have been there all along, and if Jesus is the ultimate meaning of reality, then he must be identical with the intelligible structure of everything that must have been there all along.
I mean, I think we should just ignore John when he talks like that.
He's doing the best he can with the vocabulary he's got, which is Greek vocabulary.
But it's not likely that the Greek vocabulary is going to capture this complicated Hebrew situation.
So we're free to try to capture it ourselves, but I'm not going to be able to do it, at least not right now.
Yeah.
Wow, another whole issue.
Okay, yes, that's a complicated question.
Let's put that on the table, too.
Then we'll see how many things we don't understand.
I mean, one of the things the Hebrews and therefore the disciples didn't understand is whether Jesus was bringing a new commandment for the Hebrews or for everybody.
And the disciples among themselves argued about it.
And you probably know better than I, what James said it was for everybody, and Paul said it was just for the Jews, or something like that.
They were the other way around.
Good.
Okay, Paul said it was for everybody.
That's right.
James said it was just for the Jews.
Now, I guess that Paul made this great line.
James said, well, look, you've got to be circumcised to be a Jew.
And therefore, this can only be for circumcised people.
And therefore, it's obviously for the Hebrews, not for those other tribes and idol worshipers and stuff.
And Paul said, Jesus really means circumcision of the heart.
This peculiar, weasel-way of dealing with this.
But once you say that, you clear the way for it being universal.
But I don't really think that it's intrinsic to Jesus's message.
I think that's sort of Greek influence.
I trust Paul.
He was the closest to this feeling for these things.
I think Jesus was a new variation in the Hebrew understanding of being.
I don't see why this should be relevant to the people in Japan with their thousands of gods or the people in Bali at all.
And it gets that way because James wins out, and Judaism, and the Hebrew thing claims to be universal.
It certainly doesn't start out universal.
It starts out with God making a covenant with Israel.
And I think it's that God that Jesus thinks that he's, we don't know why, changing, I'm afraid I have to say, reconfiguring.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, if he did, it certainly is a new covenant than the one he made with Abraham.
What?
Before.
Oh, yeah, well, then that's pretty peculiar because how come then Abraham thinks that he's got a covenant just for the Hebrews?
Well, I used to hear about this.
So there's this big debate, which now he's opened up, about whether this God is God for everybody or for the Hebrews only.
I just can't resist telling you that with the podcast of people all over the world, two rabbis from Israel have written me, claiming that in my other course where I talk about this and say that the God is really only for the Hebrews, that I got it wrong, it's universal, and I can see that it became universal, and therefore retroactively saw itself as universal.
But it's a complicated question, yeah.
God spares these people who aren't Hebrew.
I mean, Jonah sent to tell them to repent for your sins or God's going to get destroyed.
And Jonah does that.
God spares them.
God says you spawned.
Okay, now, and where, what's the chronology of that?
How does that you know about the Exodus story?
How does that fit with the I have to repeat what you're saying?
Exodus is one of the oldest texts, right, written even before Genesis.
That I didn't know.
It's certainly, you either have to say that later on a more universal understanding of God evolved, or that they lost touch with this local kind of God and universal thinking took over.
I mean, that's probably a big debate that's still going on, I imagine, at least in my head.
Well, yeah.
Right.
Good.
I think that's right.
Well, I guess we're back to square one.
I mean, some Christians did, namely Paul, but James, another Christian, one of the disciples, didn't, if I was right.
So it wasn't obvious.
It was a problem.
And it's, it's a, and I see it, but that's just me, as a question of how much of the Greek categories, which were definitely universal, and that were always and got more and more influential.
And by the time you get to John, totally influential, you're going to use to try to articulate this religion.
And as soon as you start using the Greek categories to articulate this religion, you're going to see it as a universal religion.
And at an earlier part, it looked like a tribal religion with its own private covenant with God.
And I'm trying to think that this is, yeah, go ahead.
He's God for everyone but the Hebrews?
Who, which is?
Jehovah?
The Christian God.
God for everyone but the Hebrews.
Well, it could have come out that way, I guess.
I think it hasn't.
That's why I go back to these rabbis writing me from Israel telling me it's universal.
And it certainly now Judaism, I think, sees itself as universal.
I must be.
Are there any, I don't know, are there any theologians of Judaism who sees it as a local, that is, as a religion for a people and only for them?
They're not, as who said, not proselytizing, that's right.
They're not going around saying you can't be, you should be one of us.
They make it very difficult.
So that makes it seem like it still keeps its local character.
And I sort of like that.
Well, luckily, we don't have to worry more about this.
And I think it's a fascinating question.
But let me just say this much, because there's only two minutes left.
In Dante, you are now in a view where Christianity has taken itself to be absolutely universal, where it knows the truth about the universe.
There are these pagans who didn't understand it, and there are these Hebrews who didn't fully understand it.
But finally, thanks to St.
Thomas Aquinas and Dante, everybody will has to see that this is j the truth and that you have to get used to reading it that way.
That doesn't mean that the Hebrews have to read it that way, but the Christians certainly did.
I saw one hand over here.
Was it you, Dave?
You just have your hand up.
You sure?
We have a minute.
Didn't I see a hand up somewhere?
You sure?
Everybody's happy?
Or at least ready to go?
Yes.
Why was what?
Why are we discussing it?
Well, that's a good question.
Not because it was brought up.
That's why.
It isn't anything you guys have to think about.
Nothing that we've talked about follows, it requires one way or the other.
That Jesus is a reconfigurer who changes the previous Hebrew understanding radically.
That much is what we're talking about.
Whether what he discovers, what he produces when he changes it radically, is a new universal religion or a new version of the local religions is what the Hebrews themselves didn't, and we don't have to decide.
Nothing I said about reconfiguring is involved there.
What is involved there, let me just say it again, is this other puzzling question.
Did God change when Jesus, who was identical with him, so to speak, reconfigured him?
That I have, that's something we should worry about, and I don't know what to say to you.
That could be local or universal, whatever answer you got to that one.
That is whether the local God changed or didn't change, or whether a universal God changed or didn't change.
It's the same problem, I think.
Okay.