The culture is a complete mess.
It's all turned out at the end of the libation bearers that Apollo and the Furies just can't stand each other.
They can't understand each other.
They find each other dangerous and disgusting and upsetting and so forth.
And at the most abstract level, Apollo can't stand the Furies' partiality, that they are loyal, they care about families and blood ties, but they don't, for instance, care about husbands and being rational about things.
Apollo can't stand that.
And that comes out when he says at the top of 143, we're just at the end of the, we're just at the beginning of the humanities now.
I see that one, that is one kind of murder, cause one cause moves you to strong rage, but on the other, clearly, you are unmoved to act.
That's just not the way rationality should work.
It should be impartial.
It should be universal.
If you define what a murder is, then every murder should bother you.
It shouldn't be a question of whether the person murdered was murdered under the aspect father or king or human being or what.
And family loyalty is irrational.
You should be loyal to everybody or nobody.
There's nothing special about the family.
As he says on 157, I've read this before, but it's the clearest statement of what he stands for.
Remember, he says, Never for man, woman, nor city, for my throne of prophecy have I spoken a word except that Father Zeus of the Olympians might command.
This is justice.
Well, that's an oblique way of saying, I treat everybody, man, woman, and city, equally.
That's rational.
That's justice.
And the Furies don't claim to be just and impartial, but they do claim to be consistent.
That is, they claim that they've got a certain job, which is to revenge blood relatives, and they do it always.
So you can count on them, and they keep order.
It doesn't matter whether they're rationally consistent.
And you see that on page where, well, really all through it.
I don't think I have a quote where they say they're consistent, but they're always saying we know what our job is, and they want to say, and don't try to undermine our sense of our job by giving us rational arguments.
They say that at the middle of 143.
Do not try to dock my privilege by argument.
Now that sort of shows the situation has become completely desperate because it isn't as if they all share some sense of what a good argument is so that they can have an argument.
So maybe one side can win or the other side can win or they can at least, or maybe they can see that there's arguments on both sides.
But it's worse than that.
Apollo thinks that the last recourse is arguments.
And if you have the winning, convincing, rational argument, then everybody ought to do what that says.
And the Furies thing, the last final convincing thing is feelings, is emotions.
And it doesn't matter what the arguments are, it's how you feel that finally matters.
Now, that might sound strange and primitive and distanced to you, but it's not.
I'll give you two examples of where it's not.
One is sort of really close to home.
Haven't you ever been in an argument with your partner, somebody you care about, or your sibling, or something, where clearly you have done, you've given good arguments for doing things your way or showing that you are right, and the other person says, I don't care what your arguments are.
I have a feeling that I've been mistreated, or I have a feeling that that's the wrong thing to do.
And that's still the Fury way of thinking.
Back before your time in the days of the Vietnam War, this was very, very important and clear that people didn't care whether arguments, one way or the other, they felt that the Vietnam War was wrong, the people who were against it, which were most of the students, so that, and this is the important thing, they felt that they could boycott and shout down and shut up any speaker who came to campus to try to give arguments why we should be in the Vietnam War.
They wouldn't listen because they said it doesn't matter what he says, it doesn't matter whether it's even convincing what he says.
We feel this is wrong and we're against this war.
And that's the way the Furies feel about Apollo.
And when you get to that kind of standoff, the situation looks hopeless.
And that's where we are.
The situation certainly looks hopeless.
And we're on 143.
And on 143, Athena comes onto the scene.
Well, no, she hasn't yet.
When they're in Athens, they're at the Acropolis.
They're at the temple and statue of Athena, and Orestes enters the scene.
And that's where we are, because that's all discussion and argument and respect and understanding has broken down, and it looks like there's no way out.
And so we, and now it turns out, so we switch to Athena at the Acropolis, and the furies that were up to now, the furies of Clytemnestra, become the Furies in general.
That's important to realize.
So, two things have happened that will confuse you if you don't realize it.
One, these furies are now on stage, as I said last time, because they're not psychological hallucinations as they were for Orestes at the end of the libation bearers.
They're cultural forces.
They're real forces.
I don't think Aeschylus and his contemporaries believed that there were these ugly, oozy, snaky ladies running around at all.
But he's putting on stage certain forces of revenge and emotion and so forth.
And he's putting on stage Apollo.
I don't think for a minute they anymore believe.
This is 500 years after the Odyssey.
And the Odyssey was already written down after the Homeric time that it was reporting on, which may have made it 700 years before.
And they're getting very rational.
That's what's upsetting the Fury so much.
The culture is getting rational.
And the culture, so Apollo represents the rationality, which is now an important part of their thinking.
And so there they are coming together in the Acropolis.
And the Furies who are up to now the Furies of Clytemnestra are the Furies in general, as the force in the culture that drives people to revenge, that gets them all emotionally upset when anybody kills a blood relative.
And Orestes, and that's my next point, has gotten over being upset.
Remember last time I said that what put the Furies to sleep, remember they're, was it the last time or right at the beginning of this one?
Right at the beginning of this one, of the humanities.
The Furies were asleep, and what put the Furies to sleep was simply time.
And they got tired chasing Orestes all over.
And they got so tired, they just went to sleep.
And Orestes doesn't feel guilty anymore.
That's the important thing.
I wanted to point out two things, by the way, in 137 while I'm back there.
I think I may have forgotten to say something which contradicts, which seems to contradict what I just said.
If I'm right, what puts the Furies to sleep is simply time.
And it better be like that.
Because they're the emotions of guilt, the feelings of guilt, the feelings of revenge, the outrage.
They're the feelings of outrage.
And you can't go around feeling outraged for years and years and years.
At least most people can.
And so the furies wear out, lose their force.
In the case of Orestes, he gets over his guilt feelings.
But there's a line that seems to contradict this.
This is the reason why you've got to have a copy in the philosophy library.
Apollo comes on the stage contradicting me.
On page 137, line 65, he says, See now how I have caught and overpowered these lewd creatures.
What's he doing overpowering them?
They don't need anybody to overpower them.
They just run down.
That's how emotion, if Apollo's not in the business of overpowering emotions, what would he use to overpower emotions?
Every time he tries to deal with them, they just get more upset.
Well, the translation says, see how these lewd creatures have fallen asleep, which is fine.
He can say that.
I don't know why the translator wants to give him anything else to say.
And the other thing I wanted to point out that I think I didn't point out on 137 was the mention on line 79, never fail until you come at last to Pallas Citadel.
That Pallas is Athena.
She's sometimes called Pallas Athena.
I don't know what it means.
I'm not sure it means anything.
I've never seen it explained.
But anyway, you just need constantly to get the code.
Whenever you s you hear about Pallas, P-A-L-L-A-S, that's Athena.
And now I'm going back to where I was, which is so Orestes has gotten over being upset.
We're now on page 145.
And he says it in various ways, but and he's gone through a lot of absolution rituals.
I mean, I don't know what they are, really, but whatever they are, they sort of take away his guilt feelings.
They're not expiation punishments.
Expiation is what you do when you're convicted of a crime and you have to go to prison.
Or, as I keep mentioning, all of you, most of you, I asked you this before, I think, how many of you read crime and punishment?
A whole lot, as I recall.
Well, remember, Raskolnikov has to go to Siberia, not to get over feeling guilty for killing the old lady, but to do his, to pay his debt to society for having expiating his guilt.
But Orestes doesn't have any guilt, he claims, and Apollo claims.
So he doesn't have to expiate his guilt, but he does have guilt feelings.
And the word for what he has to do is somehow feel absolved.
That is, feel okay about the fact that he slit his mother's throat, which is not easy to do and not easy to feel good about.
But he's supposed to, and he finally does.
And he's talking about that on 145.
Orestes says, I've been beaten and been taught.
I understand the rules of absolution, where it is right to speak and where it's silent.
It is this action now.
In this action now, speech has been ordered by my teacher, that is Apollo, who I said, but his name Luxius means speech like logos.
Somebody sent me an email when it's podcast.
You never know from where.
I think this one was from Algeria or someplace, telling me that it's not true that Luxius does not mean logic in speaking.
And now I don't know, so I ordered the book that this email told me to order.
I'm going to stick to think hoping that Luxius means speech because that's what Apollo is good at.
And logos is the word for speech.
So let's go on.
He says, anyway, where are we?
Okay, he knows when to speak and when not, as Apollo has taught him, his teacher has taught him, who is wise.
The stain of blood dulls now and fades upon my hand.
My blood of macricide is being washed away.
See, that's not, I've done the time in Siberia or prison for my crime.
It's that I'm getting over being so upset.
And a little skipping down in case you're not convinced yet, time in his aging overtakes all things alike.
Now from pure mouth and with good auspices, I call upon Athena, queen of this land, to come and rescue me.
That's pretty clear.
And now the question is: nothing's going to happen for a while to Orestes.
And in the end, nothing important does happen now to Orestes.
He's just a test case, and he just gets dropped and disappears from the action, as you know.
By the end of it, nobody's paying any attention to Orestes at all.
I think he leaves, but I'd have to go back and look if he leaves or just stands around.
But in any case, what's important is that it's now that he's gotten over being upset, we have to understand what the furies think about what's going on.
And of course, they are, again, always furious.
So in 146, they're starting to go into a kind of rant about what the rules are from their point of view, how they feel about it, to put it better, and how they feel about it is Orestes should be still upset.
And Clytemnestra sort of goes and yells at them at the beginning to wake them up and tell them, don't let yourself get calmed down.
Be upset.
So here they are stating again why they're upset on 146, line 311.
We hold we are straight and just.
Remember, they all think they're just.
If a man can spread his hands and show they are clean, no wrath of ours shall lurk for him.
Unscathed, he walks through his lifetime.
But one like this man before us with stained, hidden hands and the guilt upon him shall find us beside him as witnesses of the truth, and we show clear in the end, and we show clear in the end to avenge the blood of the murdered.
Well, that's their repeating their job.
And they say more at the bottom.
Mother, oh mother night, remember they're always in the dark, who gave me birth to be a vengeance on the seeing and the blind, hear me, for Leto's youngling, that's Apollo, Leto's his mother, takes my right away.
What?
Zeus, I guess?
Possible.
Zeus is his father.
Leto's his mother.
I didn't think half people who are only half gods got into the pantheon, or people, I mean, entities, creatures, whatever they are.
Is he the only one who's got a human mother in the pantheon?
Oh, Leto's another is a demigod or one of.
Okay, I suppose that's right.
I never could get clear how this works with demigods and who are, I think, half human, half gods.
Anyway, this is Apollo.
I shouldn't have even asked.
So Leto's youngling takes my right away, steals from my clutch the prey that crouches, whose blood would wipe at last the mother's blood away.
And they don't want that.
But now the question is, and this is very important for understanding something later in the play, which really seems sort of implausible and very important and very hard to understand.
And now I have to set it up.
What I want to show you is that the Furies haven't always been so stern and harsh and outraged as they are at this stage in the culture.
And that they've got a special gripe.
They weren't so upsetting at the time of Homer.
Of course, Homer didn't pay much attention to them either.
And to put it in a simple way, what's upsetting them is that Homer didn't pay any attention to them.
That is, they are losing their place in the culture.
People aren't taking them seriously.
Or people are repressing and controlling their emotions in the name of being rational.
And they are upset because they're being repressed.
You've got to see that Aeschylus are slipping this in all the time for reasons we'll get to.
But here you can see him starting to worry about that.
If you start in the middle of 147, the Furies are still ranting on.
They haven't reached their ultimate ranting, which I'll show you later.
I have chosen overthrow of houses where the battle god growing within strikes near and dear down, and so we swoop on this land, on this man, while the blood is still wet on him.
And now comes the important thing.
Here we stand in our haste to wrench from all others these devisings.
Make the gods clear of our counsels, so that even appeal comes not to them.
What?
Here was there and he's doing.
And they're trying to get the gods to pay attention to them because the appeal doesn't get to the new gods.
Since the appeal comes not to them, since Zeus, who's now here a new god, a pantheon god, has ruled our blood-dripping company outcast, nor will deal with us.
That's crucial.
So the coming in of the power of the pantheon, which is really Homer's doing, has pushed these other, more ancient, more primitive impulses into the margins, into the dark, and as repressed and in the dark, they get worse.
I mean, Aeschylus is having a kind of Freudian intuition about all this.
That only on a cultural level, not on an individual level.
And in Freud, what you repress gets more and more out of control and sort of dangerous to you.
Well, in a culture, what it impresses gets more and more out of control and dangerous to the culture, Aeschylus thinks.
And that's what they're complaining about.
Of course, Homer didn't completely write them out of the culture because they're still around very upset.
But he tried to marginal them, to marginalize them, and he did, and subordinate them.
So as I said last time after looking it up, there are only five references to the Furies in the Odyssey.
Therefore, he certainly knows the Furies are around, Homer does, and he doesn't care.
And boy, do they resent it.
Homer does have a place.
This is also interesting and important.
All of these things are setting up sort of why things are going to get going to be able to come out all right in the end.
If there was no place in the Homeric practices that have come down and dominated the Greeks, taking, sort of pushing the emotions, the Furies to the side, if there was no understanding of the emotion in the Furies, there would be no way to ever get these things reconciled.
So there better be, somewhere in the Pantheon, somebody who has some marginal sense, anyway, of the importance of the emotions.
And there is.
And you will soon you know already if you've been doing the reading that we will soon know who it is, and it's no surprise who it is.
But first I just wanted to say that I think that there that the primitive family emotions that the Furies represent are in the Odyssey.
They're not called the Furies.
What where do you find sort of family loyalty trumping all other forms of of reason and all the sort of rules of the new gods?
Yeah?
Absolutely.
Good for you.
I thought that was too hard.
It was only a rhetorical question.
Yes, here you've got Poseidon, his son, the Cyclops, is eating Odysseus' troops for breakfast.
And this is upsetting to the rest of the pantheon of new gods.
But Poseidon isn't upset.
He's loyal.
He doesn't care what bad things, from the point of view of the new gods, Polyphemus, the Cyclops is doing, eating his guests for breakfast.
I mean, how outrageous can it get to a new bunch of gods for whom treating guests well and not hurting them is what Zeus is in charge of.
But there it is.
He only cares that his son has been hurt, blinded.
And so he gets furious at Odysseus.
And through the rest of the book, every time Odysseus is out at sea, he's at terrible risk, and some big storm whooshes up and destroys his raft or his boat or whatever.
Poseidon is always after him.
Poseidon even persecutes the Phaeacians, remember, for being nice to them and takes away their harbor at the end of that episode.
So for him, these primitive emotions still have their place.
And how then do the other gods react to it?
Well, that's really interesting, I think.
How do you put together the fact that they are in general very tolerant?
And I was stressing that.
Polytheism has a place for all sorts of different emotions and reactions from erotic love to aggression to craftsmanship.
We've gone through all that.
How do they deal with this way that Poseidon behaves?
Well, they let Poseidon do it.
Even his primitive emotions are allowed a place.
They don't try to completely eradicate or eliminate or overpower or castrate or do whatever they've done among themselves before.
They let Poseidon do it, and nobody puts him down, not even the Phaeacians, who say that they have dinner with the Cyclopses.
But they do, on the other hand, sort of marginalize him.
It's very interesting.
What they do is try to do things behind his back that he wouldn't like, like help Odysseus.
So they go around helping out Odysseus.
I guess that's when did he, what do they do while he's off in Ethiopia?
They wait till he's away and they do something that he wouldn't like.
Anyone remember?
I don't remember.
Sure, one of you does.
Okay, well, anyway, you can keep an eye open.
They say when he's off in Ethiopia, they say, well, now's a good time.
If Poseidon isn't around, I think it's just we can help out Odyssey and talk about how to help him out.
And I take that to mean that they want, they do things that marginalize his kind of brute family loyalty.
They don't condemn him.
They give him a place in the pantheon.
But they are uneasy about it.
And they try to do business when he's not around.
So they have a certain kind of tolerance for this cultural primitive world with its own values.
They don't reject it, and they don't integrate it and respect it either.
It's a very funny, tenuous relation.
But it's important to have it around that tenuous relation because that's what's going to make them able to understand the furies at all.
So let's go back to that now.
So Homer, though it's funny, it's in his Odyssey that has a tendency to get rid of the Furies.
There's complicated things going on that nobody talks about because nobody knows about them.
They're happening, so to speak, in the culture, but they're invisible to the people in the culture.
Homer's conflicted about it.
He tells the story, presumably from old times, about how Polythemus is, I mean, how Poseidon is not.
Thanks.
So Homer, so Homer's both sort of telling us that Poseidon is marginalized and he's also marginalizing the Furies.
And it's all sort of, I think it all works, it all is coherent, but it's very annoying to the Furies.
That is, and again, if the cultural practices are marginalizing emotions, then those emotions are going to be upset emotions.
It's a funny idea, but it's definitely Aeschylus' way of thinking about it.
Let's see now.
And the crucial thing is that they become harsh and gloomy because they are being marginalized.
And this is on 148.
Let's start in the middle.
For we are strong and skilled, we have authority, we hold memory of evil, we are stern.
That's this, what I'm calling harsh and tough.
Nor can men's pleadings bend us.
We drive through our duties, and now they're complaining again.
Spurned, outcast from the gods, driven apart to stand in light, not of sun.
So it turns out they feel that they have been, they're the one, it wasn't their idea to go underground and into the dark.
They got repressed into the ground and into the dark.
That's part of what they're angry about.
They stand in light, not of sun.
That makes me want to read the translation.
I want to say they're just playing in the dark.
Maybe there's something going on there.
Let's look.
Okay, we'll see what comes out here.
I'll read it all.
We are mindful of evil wrought, awful, that's interesting.
Awful and inexorable to mankind.
That's stronger than stern.
That fits what I want.
They become so angry, so outraged.
So, awful and inexorable to mankind, pursuing our appointed office, dishonored, despised, separated from the gods by a light not of the sun.
It's equally incomprehensible.
An office which maketh rough the path of the living and the dead alike.
I don't understand.
Separated from the gods by a light, not of the sun.
Seems to me to be a very complicated way of saying we're in the dark.
I'm not sure.
I really can't figure it out.
So let's go on.
Where are we?
What's so they're complaining about being repressed, and they say at the end, privilege, now down to 395, roughly, privilege primeval is mine, nor am I without a place, although it be underneath the ground, and in no sunlight, and in gloom.
You see, that's what I wanted to hear.
Oh, dear, now I have to go back and see how the gloom works into it.
I want to put them in the dark.
And I want to say they don't like being in the dark, but nobody asks them.
You just got to keep this sort of Freudian sense.
You repress your emotions, and bad things happen to your emotions.
385, is that where 395?
Okay, here we are.
Mine ancient prerogative still abideth, nor do I meet with dishonor, albeit my appointed place is beneath the earth and in sunless gloom.
Good.
Okay.
I don't understand now.
I take it that means then you've got to think what could be sunless gloom and a light not of the sun.
It must be just dim.
It must be like Norway in November or December or something when there's only the midnight sun and the snow hasn't fallen yet.
I have friends here from Norway right now who are just telling me these stories and awed at the fact that here it's so nice when Oslo it's so dark and gloomy.
So they they are they're in the they're in the twilight zone and they don't like that.
Okay, let's see now.
148.
So they have no legitimate place at all, they feel now.
But there better be some marginal respect for even their world of feelings.
And otherwise they'll never be able to get any way to get any reconciliation between the Furies and Apollo, between reason and emotion.
And there is.
And at this moment, enter on the stage Athena, dressed like a man with armor and a spear, but clearly also a woman.
She's a kind of synthesis of male and female.
And she is the only one who can get them out of the mess they're in because she's got a feeling for feelings because she's a woman.
And unlike Apollo, who hasn't a clue about feelings, he's just a total theoretical, abstract, detached, rational viewer.
So Athena's now on the scene, and Athena's going to solve this somehow.
She's going to solve it, in fact, three ways.
Keep your eyes open.
We're going to go into the part of the book now, which things happen pretty fast, but there are three totally different solutions that she makes to the mess that Orestes has sort of come to represent.
And two of these solutions I think everybody has seen, but the third solution only you guys are going to be able to see, because you've got to be able to see with Heidegger's eyes to be able to see it.
And it's the important one.
But we've got to get there step by step.
All of her moves, all three solutions are important.
So here we go.
She's strong.
She knows, she says where Zeus' thunderbolts are kept.
She has access to them.
She never has used them.
She never will use them because she has a special kind of talent, which is persuasion, she calls it.
Persuasion is sort of like negotiation.
That is, she understands the other side, and she's able to put things in a way that the other side can understand.
And she'll say at the end that it was thanks to her power of persuasion that she could do it.
And persuasion is this middle thing between being just a kind of raving, primitive, emotional throwback kind of female, which the Furies are, and a total rational character like Apollo is.
She's got something in between.
And so now we have to go there.
And it's facet, it's fun.
I mean, just the little details in this will strike you every once in a while.
If you get struck by any little details like this that I haven't seen, which there must be plenty of, come and tell me at office hours or put them in your paper.
Here's one that I came across.
Ask yourself how these various figures in this debate, there are three figures now going to be important.
The Furies, Apollo, and Athena.
And Aeschylus, I think, like any artist, he doesn't ask himself, how am I going to deal with how they arrive on the scene, but he just has an intuition about that.
How do the Furies arrive on the scene?
Well, running and plodding along behind Odysseus and all worn out.
That's how we find them.
What's interesting is, how does Athena arrive on the scene?
Well, she arrives at the top of 149, sped on my weariless feet.
I came wingless, but in a rush of speed, and so forth.
So she's the opposite of the Furies.
She doesn't get tired because she's not like these feelings that go away.
So she can come on weariless feet.
But what about Apollo?
This is the interesting thing.
How does he get there?
Anybody know?
Well, that's a trick question.
He doesn't get there.
He's already there.
But he's already there in a sense that reason is everywhere.
He's universal.
He doesn't come from some local place trudging along or on weariless feet like the sun.
He's already shining on everything.
He's already thinking about everything.
So rationality doesn't come on feet, weary or wearyless.
I mean, that's the kind of little detail, I think, which is fun to see.
And what makes, I mean, probably part of what makes Aeschylus such an interesting playwright.
So where are we now?
Let's see.
We got there.
He's come.
And okay, let's, when I say about Apollo, he's like the sky.
He's everywhere, is another way to put it.
So, and now, notice Athena's reaction.
Remember, Apollo's priestess was terrified, knocked, literally knocked over by the sight of the Furies.
They were so disgusting and so awful, and something like she couldn't even understand what they were.
I talked about that last time, I'm pretty sure.
So now, what does Athena think when she first sees them?
Well, let's look on 149.
She says, I came on wearyless feet and so forth, and now I see upon this land a novel company, which, though it brings no terror to my eyes, brings still wonder.
Well, that's a very different attitude.
She thinks, gee, these are weird creatures, all right, but that's pretty fascinating.
And she's completely open to them and not disgusted or terrified.
And that allows her to play the same role for Aeschylus that she plays in the Odyssey.
She's open to all worlds, all forms of life.
Go where no one has ever gone before and try to figure out what that is.
So there she is confronting these completely bizarre creatures from all the Apollonian point of view.
And she thinks that's pretty amazing and is interesting.
So that's the same role, going from world to world, getting in sync with each.
And now she's going to have to appreciate this world, namely the world of the Furies.
And now that's where she's just like she was in the Odyssey.
But there's a very important way in which she's not at all like she was in the Odyssey.
And it's got to do with what kind of tolerance do you get.
In the Odyssey, they are tolerant.
The gods are tolerant of everybody, all the other gods, even Poseidon.
But Athena isn't just tolerant, though she is.
What is she trying to do with the Furies?
I'm jumping ahead, but you've read ahead.
Is she interested just in sort of setting up, sort of like maybe Israel and Palestine or something, two separate worlds, one for the Furies and one for the Apollonians?
That would be one way to keep them from fighting, to find another place, put them all away all together, put the Furies someplace else.
Now, that's not what she wants.
She wants to reconcile.
That's a new angle.
She wants to somehow merge them in something that they're some higher something.
It's very un-Homeric, this idea that you should harmonize them.
And it's clear that this is a movement toward monotheism.
She wants to find one unified force somehow that they're both aspects of.
And she does.
What it is, I'm not ready to say yet.
You're ready to say something good.
She revives what she's the border situation.
Well, she's, yeah, she, but the funny thing is, you can get attuned to different situations.
That's the Odyssey thing.
There's nothing there yet to get attuned to.
She's trying to sort of create a situation, create an attunement.
But, you know, even that's the wrong to say create an attunement.
She's got to create a.
Funny.
You have to wait till you get there.
She's got to create a new emotion, a new feeling, which creates a new situation.
And so she's sort of attuning, but she's not.
In the Odyssey, the situations are already there, and Athena just gets Odysseus in sync with them.
What you can get in sync with is just a mess, because the culture is a mess.
It's full of suffering and violence and so forth.
So she has to do more than attune.
She has to actually create a unified new emotion.
Okay?
And I don't want to jump ahead, but you'll soon see what it is.
But we've got to go through a whole thing before we get there.
So now we're just going to go through the trial, which is pretty bizarre.
And I don't know about you, but at one point I felt like, well, I don't want to teach this book.
This is just too crazy.
It's stupid.
Let's get there bit by bit, and I'll try to talk you out of that if that's what you felt.
So Oreses restates his case on page 151.
That's right where he said he was Absolute, but now skipping down to below the middle, he says, I came back.
He's talking about what he did.
I killed the woman who gave me birth.
Notice he doesn't say a mother, because remember how careful he was to say that she wasn't really his mother, but she sent him off to stay with friends at 11.
She didn't take care of him and love him.
So she's just the woman who gave him birth.
He can't deny that.
And I plead guilty.
My father was dear, and this was vengeance.
You've got all kinds of bad things that are happening in the translation there.
How can he plead guilty?
He wasn't guilty, and he's got over his guilt feelings.
You rush to the translation if you're writing a paper in this, and you hope that you don't have to throw away the book.
Well, it doesn't say I plead guilty.
He says, I killed the woman who gave me birth.
I can't deny it.
That's tape enough.
He didn't say, no guilty.
My father, and then that's this word for sire or lord.
And maybe he's not really saying father.
Maybe he's saying the king.
I don't know.
Because you can't tell.
There's one Greek word.
So let's hope he's not making a fuss about his father.
Let's hope he was, remember, killing, because that would be to kill in the name of the furies.
If he did it because of a blood relative, he better do it because something like my lord, the person, the authority I respect, or something like that, was dear, and this was vengeance.
Well, remember that there, you and the translator are free to do whatever you want.
There's only one Greek word for vengeance, which means either vengeance or retribution.
Vengeance is the fury thing, which you do in a fit of emotion and you slit somebody's throat.
Retribution is what you do legally when you punish somebody for something which it turns out is, in fact, wrong.
It goes against the law.
So I'm going to have him say, my lord was dear, and this was retribution.
And never mind before his blood.
That's not in there.
Period.
Apollo shares responsibility for this, once you clean up the translation.
He counterspurred my heart and told me of pains to come if I should fail to act against the guilty ones.
And that's right.
Just to remind you, remember, Apollo has no power to threaten him with any suffering or any emotions because Apollo isn't in the emotions business.
So Apollo, remember, at the very beginning of the libation bearers, threatens him with the furies will come after him because Agamemnon's furies will go after him because he's the blood relative who should avenge the death of Agamemnon.
Remember all that, I'm just reviewing.
And that's what Apollo has to do to get him upset enough to do it, that is to kill his mother.
But Apollo, at the last minute, they do it in the name of Apollo because Orestes asks Pylades what to do.
So at the last minute, he does it not emotionally, not in the name of the furies.
That's all taken for granted now.
Apollo said there'll be terrible things will happen to you if you don't kill the guilty ones, but you better do it in the right way, or terrible things will happen to you anyway.
And of course, terrible things did happen to him, even though he did it in the right way, because he went crazy with guilt feelings.
I'm just, that's where, and now he's explaining all that, justifying it, telling it just the way I told it, in effect.
And Athena hears it, and she says, the matter is too big for any mortal man who thinks he can judge it.
Even I have not the right to analyze cases of murder where wrath's edge is sharp.
That is, where the furies are involved, she doesn't have the right to settle things.
That would be already to beg the question.
If she said she had the right to settle things where the furies are involved, the furies would already be not involved.
So she's trying to say she doesn't have a way to settle things and not rule out the Furies.
But he's come to her as a clean and innocent suppliant, she sees.
She says that, which is certainly what the Furies deny.
So she's got a problem.
She sees that she shouldn't do what the Furies want her to do, but she sees that she can't just ignore them either.
And so at the top of 152, she's in a dilemma.
So he says, yet these two have their work.
That is the Furies.
We cannot brush them aside.
And if this action so runs that they fail to win, the venom of their resolution will return to infect the soil and sicken all my land to death.
Here is a dilemma.
Whether I let them stay or drive them off, it is a hard course.
It will hurt.
You're supposed to hear an echo there of another dilemma, which was hopeless.
Which one?
Whichever course you take, it's going to hurt.
Yeah, Agamemnon sacrificing Ephigenia is one of them.
And that was the first choice in which whatever you do is terrible.
What about the next one?
There's another one.
Orestes facing Clytemnestra.
I mean, he's got the problem.
If I don't slit her throat, it'll be a disaster because the Furies will get me.
And if I do slit her throat, it'll be a disaster because the Furies will get me because I'll be killing a blood relative.
And so, and that all reflects the mess the culture is in.
There could be three decisions like that.
This is the last one, because Athena's going to fix it so these kinds of impossible situations don't arise anymore.
And how is she going to do it?
Well, she's going to set up a court.
That's solution number one.
She says, I will select judges of manslaughter and swear them in, establish a court into all times to come.
That's very important because what happened with Orestes is that he had to be both the judge and the executioner of Clytemnestra.
He couldn't just be, so to speak, the, what's the opposite of the defense attorney, the prosecuting attorney, and show that she was guilty and should be executed, and then turn it over to somebody else to execute her who's not emotionally involved and not a blood relative.
That's how the court system works if you have capital punishment.
They didn't have a court system for capital punishment at that point.
That point being this mythical point in the past that Aeschylus is sort of making up to show the Athenians how they got the institutions that they've got.
And what they've got is a court system.
And so she's going to set up a court.
And she's going to set it up, and she's going to get 12 jurors who are just normal citizens to hear the case.
So let me catch up.
On 154.
Well, the furies are ranting on here.
Do I want to read this, though?
I think I want to wait and read this later.
But they say absolutely weird things, but I'm not ready for that.
Skip to 154.
Athena re-enters, guiding 12 citizens chosen as jurors and attended by a herald.
Other citizens follow.
Now I have to make an aside, a kind of annoyed comment about the transcription.
You notice anything amazing?
That they have 12 jurors?
And I thought, isn't that incredible?
This thing is written into 400 BC, talking about a culture which is even earlier.
And here we are, 2,000 some years later, and we still got 12 jurors.
Well, it isn't in the Greek.
It doesn't say how many jurors there are in the Greek.
I discovered this when I saw another translation had 10 jurors.
And then I just, that was Fagel's translation.
Then I discovered that there isn't any number of jurors.
See, nobody says anything.
That's all written in by the, what's in italics is written in by the translator.
Aeschylus didn't write any stage directions in italics.
So he comes in with 12 jurors.
But the point is that she comes in with an even number of jurors.
That's important.
It's funny that I just say, why there are an even number of jurors is very puzzling.
You'd think it'd be better if there was an odd number of jurors so that they couldn't get into a situation in which they were split, which is what they get into here.
They discover they're split X to X, whatever number that is.
So here they are.
She gets them in.
And now there's going to be a trial.
There's going to be an actual prosecuting and defending debate out in the open.
And then that's what takes place next.
Where are we?
Well, and now at this level, when the Furies are now not just the Furies anymore of Clytemnestra, and they're not even just the emotions in general.
However, there's something in between.
What I think the Furies are at this point is all righteous indignation when anybody breaks any law.
I'll say this in an alcohol, but this is complicated.
That would be too Apollonian, because that would say when anybody breaks any universal law, then you could have a universal kind of upsetness and the Furies would be out of business.
They're still very local and particular, and they are still moral outrage.
But they're now a funny collection of moral outrage at the top of 154.
And this is puzzling to me, but I'll do my best to explain it.
They say, let man see this and take care to mother and father and to guests, welcomed in the gate, all so forth.
Then, of course, I run, I run Polly, okay, thanks.
Okay, so guests really upset me.
I run to the translation.
I hope that it's a mistake.
It better be a mistake.
What in the world are the Furies doing thinking about guests?
Well, I can't find any translation that denies that it's guests.
And I believe, yes, I did.
I asked somebody who read the Greek.
I was getting really desperate.
It says guests.
Well, then you need a new story.
What are the furies now when they are the most generalized way of thinking about a certain aspect of the practices of the culture?
Well, they're certainly moral outrage, but moral outrage about what?
Well, my story is, but I just make this up.
Aeschylus isn't giving me any help, is moral outrage about any damage to anything that anybody, particular people, identify with.
So it could be your family.
It could be your school.
And if people do bad things to Berkeley and you feel really important part of your life is to be a Berkeley student, you could feel moral outrage about that.
Could be your city.
Whatever it is that you identify with, if that gets mistreated, then you feel moral outrage.
That must be what the most general level of the furies are.
And that keeps it from being Apollonian because it doesn't, it's very particular.
I get moral outrage.
Perhaps I identified with Berkeley.
If bad things happen to Berkeley, maybe you don't, particularly, you're just, you haven't been here very long.
I've been here a long time.
But there may be something.
I mean, maybe your family.
But if I'm an orphan, then I wouldn't even have any family.
Or at least not maybe I wouldn't.
Anyway, so everybody can be particularly morally outraged about what it is that is very important to who they are.
And I think that must be the job if you're going to take the guest thing seriously.
The other alternative is just to say some translator, some scribe early on when they were writing it down just blew it.
Yeah.
Well, there's sometimes it seems, that's interesting.
You're off to the other possible move, that they like to put things in a way that will seem to the Apollonians to be what is it?
Let's look.
Where what?
Okay.
Oh, by the way, guys, you talk to pieces over and over again in front of us.
Yes.
Okay, I want to talk about that.
That's important.
But I don't think it's exactly a kind of Apollonian argument.
But it is a kind of not exactly rational.
But I realize that I turn and told you not to talk.
I'll come back to this thing.
Yeah.
That's a very smart question.
I was going to talk about that.
Put it on hold for a minute.
His question comes first in what I want to talk about.
So for you, what I think is going on is they have certain universal, I can't say, principles or ethical things.
What they're saying is, and I'm going to come back to it, that if you don't have emotions of moral outrage, the culture will become completely anarchic because everybody will be able to kill everybody without any compunction.
That's not exactly an Apollonian argument.
It's a sense of, it's funny, it's a sense of the universal importance of emotions, of particular emotions of outrage.
And it says, in effect, let's read it, that if you get rid of us furies, where is that?
Every bad thing will happen to you because anybody will get away with anything.
Where is that?
It's somewhere around where we are.
And people will be killing each other and people will be killing their parents to get their inheritance.
It doesn't quite say that, but it sort of says that.
Let me see.
Ah, here it is in the middle of 152.
Here is the overthrow of all the young laws.
That is, none of your laws will work, you young gods, if the claim of the matricide shall stand good, his crime sustained.
Should this be, and now comes his generalization that you're talking about.
Every man will find a way to act at his own caprice over and over again in time to come.
Parents shall await the death stroke at their children's hands.
That is, if you don't like your parents, just kill them.
Because nobody will feel guilt about killing their parents.
If you let him just slit his mother's throat and go away just after a little bit of absolution and say everything's okay, boy, are you going to have a terrible culture?
I mean, if you get angry at your parents, you just kill them, and so forth.
And that's a generalization, but it's a different kind of generalization.
It isn't sort of what you should do or what you shouldn't do.
It's about they have an in principle view about the role of moral outrage in keeping order in the culture, I think.
Now let me go to him.
Oh, Beatrice, I'll put you in the stack.
What?
When they say on the 153, we like the life devoted to one man.
Yes, but it's a.
I mean, I worry about that.
All kinds of interesting things are happening in here.
And one of them is: so, what is the where is it again?
Okay, 153.
See, they are going to claim that there's a middle ground and that they're at it.
And Athena's going to claim a different middle ground.
And because she thinks their middle ground is going to end up with self, with with a kind of back to vengeance again.
Because when they say, and now where is it?
I don't see it yet.
Well, yeah, refuse the life of anarchy.
That would be no emotions.
Refuse the life devoted to one master.
I guess that must be Apollo's totally intolerant universal, but I'm not sure.
That's the best I can do there.
And what is the middle?
I think the middle for them is whatever it is you identify with.
That is, you can make it your family, or you can make it your city, or you can make it your company, or whatever.
But it's got to be for them a local middle.
And it's between a world in which there is no moral outrage and a world in which there is universal moral outrage.
It's, so to speak, in their thought, justified moral outrage when somebody does something bad to whatever it is that is yours.
It's not universal.
It's your identity.
I think that's got to be their middle ground.
But if that isn't, come and tell me another.
And now I've got to take up his question.
And remind me.
Can't say it again.
Good.
Okay.
Let me repeat it because I got to do it for podcasts, and maybe you don't hear it back there either.
It's a very good question.
She's just said this is too hard for any man, and that means any human being, at least, to come to a conclusion.
It's even too hard for her, which means even too hard for a goddess to come to a conclusion.
And then what does she do?
She just takes 12 ordinary people off the street to let them judge it.
What kind of craziness is that?
That's the question, right?
Okay, it's a very, very brilliant, very deep kind of craziness.
I owe this to my colleague again, Joe Tussman.
He's the one who explained why Artemis required Agamemnon to sacrifice Hippigania, which I never could understand.
Now the question is the weird trial that takes place.
And why is this a very deep thing to do?
When the situation is so hard that you can't decide what to do, why in the world go out and just grab some people off the street?
Now, since it's not really my idea, but Joe's idea, I have to read it because I don't want to get it wrong.
You're jumping ahead, but that's all right.
So, what in the world does the court system enable us to do?
Why can they just take people off the street?
And then, this is what Joe Tussman said: they're just ordinary citizens, and you can't expect juries to reach wise decisions that resolve deep moral problems that are tearing apart a culture.
But nonetheless, they could do four important jobs.
They do reach a decision.
No matter how arbitrary, they stop the fighting.
Or at least in some cases, they say, Well, now we'll give a billion dollars.
What's this, the latest thing I heard on the radio that some tobacco company was supposed to, was or wasn't going to give, I think, $500 million to some widow because her husband died from too much smoking.
Well, they settled it.
I'm afraid maybe they're a judge settler.
But anyway, you know, juries settle things, they reach a conclusion.
And now, that's point one.
And secondly, if the jury's decision is going to be respected, it better express the practices and values of the citizens.
That is, that if they don't respect that, they won't have authority.
But if they do bespeak the current wisdom, no matter how stupid, they not only stop the argument, but people will obey them.
Here's a perfect example of that, it seems to me.
Pornography decisions.
What is indecent?
Well, there is no right answer to what is indecent.
But let's say they're having a big fight about whether, you know, somebody dancing around naked is expressing themselves artistically or exhibiting lewd behavior.
And how do they find out?
They get these 12 ordinary people and they ask them whether it was indecent.
And when they tell you whether it's indecent, that's the answer.
It's indecent, let's say.
And that's not just completely arbitrary because that expresses what people in that community think is indecent.
And that's what you're trying to find out.
And third thing, they don't decide whatever they decide in the heat of emotion.
They're not supposed to be 12 angry men.
Anybody seen that movie?
It's such an old movie now.
You've seen it, somebody?
With Henry Fonda?
The jury, yeah, I mean, the jury is all having their moral outrage about what bad things happened to them, which they're projecting onto this poor kid who's being tried for having killed his father, I believe.
Isn't that what he's tried for?
It's a very Aeschylus-like thing.
And the important thing is that Henry Fonda, the only sane person on the jury, tries to get them all to calm down and realize that they're not supposed to have react their own traumas, but to pay attention to what happened to this kid.
And so they're not supposed to be 12 angry men on the jury.
That's important.
And I already said the fourth one: it's very important to separate the role of judge, jury, and executioner.
And so no one ever again has to kill their own family because they've done something wrong.
And then, like Orestes.
Okay, so there are four good reasons why it's even though nobody can really wisely decide, it doesn't matter, at least if you have a court system, there'll be some kind of decision.
It won't work.
That's your intuition.
It won't work to do the one thing that it really has to do, satisfy the furies.
But it works for these, at least it gets this far.
Orestes is off the hook.
Nobody will ever have to do that again.
Can't be the executioner to kill their own mother because it'll be the job of the executioner.
And it does express, when it finally comes, when the court finally comes to a decision, something interesting, namely, we've already mentioned it, it shows how split the culture is.
That six people are on one side and six people on the other.
When you get a hung jury like that, you're not going to get a solution that works.
But if it isn't like that, it could have worked.
It could have done something, stopped the whatever, got rid of the executioner, got the community on its side, settled something.
Okay, it didn't.
And that's part of, now we have to go back to what happens in the trial.
It is so nutty that this is at the, it was at the trial that I decided I don't want to teach this book.
And you know, how many know sort of how the trial came out?
You must have, I hope, read it by now.
Not any, not very many.
That's very strange.
A little bit alarming.
Anyway, the way the trial comes out is that they vote 50-50 on the side of the Furies and on the side of Apollo.
That is, whether Orestes is guilty or not guilty.
And then Athena casts the deciding vote, which I guess even now the case, maybe if the jury is split, they can't go on.
But in this jury system, the judge, in a way, casts the deciding vote.
And what does she do?
This is where you want to throw the book away.
She says, well, I'm going to vote for Apollo.
Why?
Well, I'm half woman and half man, but I'm really more like a man than like a woman because I didn't even, I wasn't even born of a woman.
I was born out of the head of Zeus.
So I vote for Apollo and Orestes.
What a jury system.
What a legal system.
It's the craziest reason for a decision you could possibly have.
And it has just all the features that a trial decision is supposed to have, except it doesn't work because you need more than that if you're in a totally conflicted culture.
I mean, it does, it could stop.
It looks like it's supposed to stop the argument, give a decision, take the matter out of Orestes' hands.
She does it without being upset.
It's not a question of the jury and her are all calm and rational when it happens, but it doesn't work.
And now we have to go and see about that.
I've got to catch up with where I am, so I'm catching up.
So Athena sees there's no right response.
I'm trying to catch up to where I am and not skip anything.
I may have already said this.
Yeah, that's where I can't deal with it.
It's too big a deal even for me.
And on 152 at the top, yeah, the dilemma, I did that.
So the Furies are all upset.
Now we've done that.
Well, I want to just repeat: the Furies have this big threat that Athena has to deal with, and she's trying to do it by the court system, but it didn't work.
That is, they have this passionate response to anything that threatens any particular local aspect of the social world, families, cities, whatever it says.
Then people get very upset, outraged, indignant, and they do something that perpetuates the evil.
So, and the two threats are, let's just get it clear, they could leave.
That's what we read already, where they then everybody could just kill anybody.
Where was that again?
Because it belongs at this point in the discussion, where you could kill your own parents and so forth.
152.
So they could leave, and then they said, and if they did, everything would be in this case sort of anarchy.
Or, and this is the other thing they could do, these are things the furies could do if you don't treat them right.
They have their own ways of retaliation that she's got to be careful of.
They could just turn off moral indignation, and then it would be total chaos.
On 152, also on one, let me see.
Here's the bottom is more of this.
We're the angry ones, but we should watch no more over works of men and so act.
We shall let loose indiscriminate death.
That's a culture, I take it, in which dudes are dangerous for the culture.
If they have no feelings of moral outrage, then everybody can kill anybody.
And what about if they have too much feeling of moral outrage?
Then everybody is going to try to kill everybody.
So that's their other threat.
Their other threat is that they will soup up the emotions.
And then everything will go completely crazy.
On 165, she's trying to tell them not to do this bad thing they could do.
At the middle of 165, do not inflict your bloody stimulus to twist the inward hearts of young men raging in fury, not of wine, nor as if plucking the heart from fighting cocks, engage, sorry, engraft among your citizens that spirit of war that turns their battle fury inward on themselves.
So don't soup up people's aggression against all the other people or against themselves, which is interesting.
I mean, how it's very ahead of his time to think that people could turn up their aggression, fury on themselves.
But anyway, everybody would be furious at everybody.
Everybody would be ready to kill everybody.
People would be so furious they'd even be ready to kill themselves.
That's what would happen if the furies souped up their thing.
So they're really, she's got a terrible problem.
I'm backing up to catch up where we are.
So she sets up the court system.
And they do reach a decision.
And but we go, but the trial is so nutty that you have to go through it just to see that it's the way the court system ought to work.
But if the culture is completely conflicted, it's not going to work.
But let's see what happens.
So there's going to be a trial.
The Furies get a chance to state their case.
Orestes is cross-examined.
It's all very rational.
In 155, first you have to establish that there was a crime.
They say in the middle of the page, you kill your mother or did you not?
And he said, yes, I killed her.
I won't deny it.
And then they say, well, how did you do it?
And at the bottom, he says, and this is where I got this throat slitting that I've been saying all the time.
He did it with drawn sword in my hand.
I cut her throat.
So there's the crime.
And he says, but she deserved to die.
That's the middle of the page, 156.
Tell me how and explain it to the judges.
She murdered her husband, and therefore my father, too.
So Orestes is getting all involved in the father business, which is probably a bad idea.
The Furies say death has set her free, but you're still alive.
And Orestes says, when she lived, why didn't you descend and drive her out?
That is, why are the Furies partial?
Why did they have to use Agamemnon's furies to kill Clytemnestra through him or try?
Why didn't they just do it?
And they did say, and their answer was really amazing.
Well, we don't have to worry about killing her.
Anyway, the man she killed was not a blood congenital.
So that's very tricky, you see.
Only a blood relative of Agamemnon can go after her.
Just the fact that she killed her husband doesn't do anything to get anybody after her.
Because from the Fury's point of view, there's no blood relation there.
Marriage just doesn't matter.
And he finds that amazing.
And then he says, so I'm, in effect, then he says, you've got to follow this if you want to.
It's just bizarre, though.
He says, well, but you're saying that I should kill my mother.
That is, if you were Agamemnon's Furies, you would say, I should kill Clytemnestra, and she is my mother.
How can you ask me to kill my mother?
And they say, in effect, well, but I'm involved with something, by the way, by blood bond.
So she don't have to kill Clytemnestra because she killed Agamemnon, but they're after Orestes because he's a blood relative of Clytemnestra and he killed Clytemnestra.
And he says, but then I'm involved with my mother by blood bond?
And they say, yes, she nurtured you and so forth.
And notice we're back to that.
We just have time to settle that.
This is this business again of him saying, she's not really my mother, not my emotional mother.
She's just my biological mother.
And they're saying, well, look, she gave birth to you and nursed you, so she's your mother.
At which point, he gives up.
It's so funny.
He passes the ball to Apollo.
He said, I don't know.
I can't deal with it.
And Apollo says, yours, Apollo.
And what does Apollo do?
He gives a whole thing about first, he gives his speech about how just he is and how fair he is and so forth.
But then he gives this sort of modern science story in which he says the mother doesn't do anything.
There's no blood from the mother in the baby on 158.
Apollo, I will tell you and I will answer correctly.
Watch.
The mother is no parent of what is called her child.
This is his defense to say, well, Orestes didn't kill his mother because the mother isn't even a mother.
The mother's blood isn't in Orestes.
Clytemnestra's blood isn't in Orestes.
The mother is just the womb.
That's what they believe.
He's just giving you the latest science.
And lots of people believe that.
The woman, the man planted the seed in the woman, and the woman was just the nurturing thing.
And it grew, but it was strictly the man.
And that's what Apollo says.
And that's supposed to settle everything.
But now let me get back because I just have one minute.
So Hapiklanus is not a, that Clytemnestra was not really his mother.
Apollo goes and gives the same argument scientifically.
Clytemestra was not really his mother.
And what happens after that is that he gives this scientific theory, there can be a father without a mother, he says on 158.
That's what he's proving.
And Athena says, yeah, I agree with that.
I've got a father and no mother.
And so Athena goes along with that.
And so she does, she votes for Orestes.
And I think I can stop with that.
Well, let me just see.
I've got the so the jury votes, it's tied six to six, and she casts her vote for Orestes for this odd reason, 166, 161.
The odd reason is there's no mother that gave me birth, and but for marriage, I'm always for the male with all my heart, and strongly on my father's side.
And if the votes are even, then Orestes wins.
Meaning, I'm going to vote for Orestes.
And that's when I say you want to sort of throw the book away, because that is the nuttiest trial.
But then all you have to do is remember: trials aren't supposed to come to deep decisions.
It's just, you might as well flip a coin.
At least it's supposed to settle things.
But it didn't.
And that's where we begin next time.
It didn't settle things.
The furies are not going to buy it.
So we have to see.
Now let me just remind you.
Remember, I said Athena makes three moves to save things.
She's made one move, set up a court.
Next time we do the next two moves.
Okay.