But I found something in reading Homer that I thought was so much sort of fun for me anyway, and so interesting and surprising that I have to talk about it for a minute.
In all the years that I've taught the Odyssey and told people to, you know, point out the exceptions and challenge my theory, and now that I'm even writing a paper on the special way that Helen is open to Aphrodite and how Homer calls that, you know, she's peerless among women, then on 436, nobody else got to 436.
In the middle of 436, you probably don't have the Odyssey with you anymore, but I'll read it.
Helen of Argos, daughter of Zeus and Leta, would she have joined the stranger, lain with him, if she had known her destiny?
This is Penelope talking to Odysse in their bedroom when he's finally home.
No one, the Achaeans in arms, would bring her back to her own country.
Surely a goddess moved her to adultery, her blood unchilled by war and evil coming, the desolation, and so forth.
Does that strike you as a counter example to what I said?
It sure does me.
I was really upset about it.
It sounds like it's saying that she is not a good person.
She's an adulterer.
There's another place which says the war is her fault, but that turned out to mean that she caused the war.
I don't mind that, because the question is whether she caused the war shows that she's a bad person or not.
And I want to say, no, she's not a bad person.
She's peerless among women.
She's somebody that Agamemnon is still very happy to be married to.
But this says she's just bad.
And I couldn't figure out what to do with it.
And I looked at the Greek, and the Greek didn't help.
It says something very similar, so similar that I hardly have to read it.
It says, in her case, a god prompted her to work a shameful deed, nor until then, and so forth and so forth.
That's enough.
So then I really got worried.
And I looked across the page from the English to the Greek, and lo and behold, there's a footnote.
These lines were rejected by Aristocratus and can hardly be defended in this context.
That means that the people who are sort of the editor.
I looked up Aristocratus in Wikipedia.
He turns out to have lived at 220 BC and be the most influential of all the scholars of Homeric poetry and wrote the, did the first important edition of Homer, and well, the first most historically important critical edition of Homer, which had presumably this footnote.
Because I knew, and this is the interesting part, that early on people lost touch with this Homeric picture, that you obey the gods and the moods no matter what awful things happen to everybody, because being open to these highest authorities that give most meaning to your life is the highest thing you can do.
And I read that already at the time of the Athenians, they couldn't believe it anymore, and they would rewrite the Odyssey, making her punished for the bad things and saying bad things about her.
Well, here it is.
There it is.
Somebody early on rewrote these ten lines to just make clear what a bad person she was.
And I'm so happy.
I'm so happy because it didn't shoot down my view.
And it even confirms the view that this Homeric way of looking at things is very strange.
And the Athenians already, that is the time of Aeschylus, wouldn't have looked at it this way.
And maybe they would be tempted, apparently they were tempted, to simply write a few bad things in there about Helen so that we don't get the mistaken idea that it's a good idea to just run off if you're shined on by the goddess of erotic love.
Okay, so that's all.
I'm surprised nobody saw it.
I'm surprised that when I saw it, it was okay.
And now I'm ready to go back to Aeschylus.
Okay, so here's where we were.
That Artemis, not wanting to see young people or animals hurt, sees the war as a terrible thing and decides she's going to stop the war by insisting that Agamemnon can't go to war if he doesn't sacrifice Ephigenia.
Remember, his daughter.
That's where we were last time.
And then it turned.
And then, so she does that.
And the amazing thing is, to her, from her point of view, I'm sure, that Agamemnon doesn't just give up and go home.
In fact, Agamemnon gets terribly upset because he knows that as a king who's got his armies to deploy and who's got all of them out there on this island of Aulus, which is sort of just outside the harbor of Argos, and where they can't get any further because there isn't any wind, he got them out there, and he's got to do something to carry on his job as king and leader to get them fighting.
Where they are, they're starving, and that's terrible.
So, and moreover, Aeschylus doesn't make any big deal of it, but he mentions oaths every once in a while.
He has, I don't see it in here, but maybe I missed it.
But the story is that Agamemnon has sworn an oath to Menelaus that if anything bad happens to him, Agamemnon will help out and vice versa.
And something bad happened to Menelaus indeed.
Paris ran off with Helen.
And so both out of as a promise keeper and as a king, or maybe three things, and as a general, he's got to fight the war.
But as a father who loves his daughter, he absolutely doesn't want to fight the war.
What do you think is going to happen?
Well, it looks like Artemis thinks, well, rationality will trump, feelings of fathers must be the strongest thing, and that trumps all these rational stories about what kings do and generals do and promise keeping.
That's what she thinks, but that isn't what he thinks, because he's not what turns out it's important that he's a man and she's a woman.
She puts feelings first.
We'll have to see what he does finally.
But whatever it is, things are in a terrible mess.
That's where we ended.
If he doesn't kill Ephijaniah, there's a big disaster for him as king and general and brother and promise keeper.
If he does kill Ephijaniah, there's a big disaster for him as father who loves his daughter, and he's going to get in trouble for that.
So, and that's where we stand.
Now, before we can go back to talking about what he finally did and what happened when he did it, which you presumably have now read it and know, there's lots of backgrounds you need to have.
Because I already was, couldn't even say as much as I've said already without beginning to lay out a whole thing about the two kinds of gods.
And the two, the gods aren't anymore personifications or focuses or shining examples, is my way of talking about it, shining paradigms of moods.
The gods are now cultural forces.
There are two value systems in the culture, and they are represented by the two sets of gods.
I don't think people think the gods really act anymore.
I don't think they really think people see the gods anymore.
But that's a way of expressing something that's very powerful and very real, namely the two sets of values that enable people to make sense of what they do.
And Aeschylus sets up this battle between the Olympian gods on the one hand and the Furies on the other.
That structures the whole book.
Now, now that you read it, I want to put on the board, with your help, because every year some new conflict comes out, all the different ways that Aeschylus has of talking about this conflict between the two sets of gods or values in the culture, because it's all over the place.
You can't really crack the complicated crossword puzzle that this is without constantly keeping track of which set of gods are we talking about and what are they doing.
So we've got on the one hand, we've got the Furies, and on the other hand, we've got the Olympian gods, the Olympians, we'll call them.
Now, what do you give me examples of what goes over here?
What gets associated with the Furies?
And contrasted.
I already had to give one.
What did I, or give two, really?
What did I say a while back?
What are the two forces around whether to kill a Fijiania or not?
Well, there's Artemis on the one hand, and female, exactly.
There's the females, or let's say women, and over here, the men.
That's a big contrast.
And what else did I say?
What's the main way that women sort of react to things according to this picture?
By the way, these are super stereotypes, but this is, I mean, after all, what, 2,500 years ago, we've gone a long way maybe, but try to see how it looks to Aeschylus.
What's the defining feature of women?
Yeah.
Feeling, yeah.
And of men, you must know.
Rationality, yes.
I think something a little narrow, I mean, a little less fancy.
There is a God for rationality, all right.
We'll get to him in a minute.
Just put thinking over here.
Okay.
Now it gets fancier.
Think some more.
Well, how else do they get contrasted in really surprising ways?
Surely somebody's noticed.
How are they related to sort of geography?
How are they related to light?
How are they related to all sorts of things?
Let's say sort of geography, yeah.
The ground and the sky.
Yeah, I think I'll call it Earth, but I'm not disagreeing.
Earth over, no, yeah, Earth here, right.
And sky god.
These are the sky gods.
Okay, how about just in the in the history?
How do they view themselves, each of them, in terms of the temporality, in terms of the time that they come from or go care about?
Yeah, that's right.
The Furies are old.
They're aged children.
And if Aeschylus says, I don't want to try to find the passage.
They're aged children because they have been around a long, long time.
They've been around so long that they go back to primitive responses, so they behave like children.
And they are the old gods.
And these are the new gods who have come in by the time you get to Homer, both are around.
And Homer, this is just, I keep saying this, is reading the gods sort of out of the story.
I found five places in all of the Odyssey where Homer mentions the Furies.
And very much in passing, and almost as if by accident.
If you find more, let me know.
If you find places where he really takes any serious notice of the Furies, I would be shocked.
And I would hope to find that it was this critic read it out of them.
Right.
Man, going back to the Olympians.
What does that mean?
Do you think that there's godlike men and women?
And that the Olympians are quoted.
I don't think, except for Zeus, which is, of course, a special case.
I don't know.
We have to look.
I don't think the Olympians are ever quoted by women.
We'd have to find out.
That would be very interesting.
And it would surprise me.
There are women, obviously, among the Olympians, but it's interesting what happens there.
You don't hear about Hera.
You don't hear about Aphrodite, you hear about Athena and Artemis.
What's interesting about those two women is that they're sort of men-women.
Both of them are virgins.
Athena carries a spear.
Artemis has a bow and arrow.
What else?
They're very androgynous types.
And that's important.
It turns out that it's very important that Athena is able to understand the Furies with her woman side more than Apollo.
The real man in it is Apollo.
He's pure.
I'll read you a quote in a minute.
Pure rationality.
That's what I was saving.
For he's even more rational than thinking.
He's a rationalist, but I'll explain that in a minute.
But so I think that even the women among the Olympian gods are being played down by Homer, except for Athena, really.
And she's very important because she's not really like a woman.
She's not born of a woman either.
She's born out of Zeus's head.
She's very, as unwoman as you can get.
Okay, did somebody, did I see a hand up over there?
Because what I did?
Yeah.
Okay.
I thought you were getting a story with my.
Hmm.
Because she's this funny mixture.
Only we don't see any mixture.
You're right.
Artemis is a funny one.
She is she one of the Olympians?
That's the next question.
She's certainly not one of the furies.
But where's my chart?
Anybody got their chart of the Olympians that I handed out a while back?
I don't think, I'm not sure.
I don't know whether Artemis is on it or not.
I'm a feeling she is.
But before I go out and make a whole speech about it, I better know.
Yeah.
And Paulo's kid sister, twin sister.
Is she on the chart?
Okay.
So we got a problem with Artemis.
That's good.
It's good to have problems.
You learn things when you've got a problem.
She definitely is into feelings.
That's why she thought that Agamemnon wouldn't kill a Piginia.
That's why she gets upset at the rabbit that gets eaten, whose babies get eaten by the eagles and so forth.
And it's important, certainly, that she is a woman, but there's something about it that doesn't fit.
I don't know what to say.
Yeah.
Yes.
But oh, oh, wait, well, Orestes.
He comes back to avenge his mother's death.
You are way, not wrong at all.
You're way ahead of the story.
The question is going to be over Orestes, and this is for the libation bearers, which you're going to be reading next week, not yet.
The whole cliffhanger of the libation bearers, which has the audience and the chorus on the edge of their seats, and will you too when you understand what's happening, is whether Orestes is going to kill his mother in the name of the Furies or in the name of the new gods?
Because they've gone against both.
And the important thing is he better behave.
Well, let's wait and see.
And which one would we want him to do it in the name of?
And why?
And does he?
All those are the questions to put aside.
His question, I have to just say, I don't know what to think.
And it's funny, I never faced it, even though I knew that she's that there's a woman among the Olympians.
All I can say is she doesn't have an important part.
The only people who have important parts are people, I mean gods, Olympian gods, are Apollo, who's super, super male, and Athena, who makes a point of saying that she's man and woman both.
And other than that, there's only Zeus.
And Zeus is sort of above being man or woman.
So I don't have more to say about it.
Yeah.
Saturn Nestor says the Argonauts are going to kill Agamemnon because he killed our daughter.
That's good.
Beatrice is right.
I mean, the important thing is where the Furies stand in this.
And it's in the name of the Furies that people go around killing or killing, or the Clytemnestra says that it's in the name of her daughter's fury that she's going to kill Agamemnon.
And that's so that's and that's a way of saying Artemis just comes in for a tiny cameo part at the beginning to demand this sacrifice because that's probably already in the myths.
I'm sure it must be.
And it's not fitting very well in Aeschylus' picture, but he drops her right away, and then we don't hear about her again.
Okay, so the big contrast, though, somebody we had old and new.
Yeah, well that's still right.
Let me go back to earth and sky for a minute.
Why should they be in there?
Well, because earth is local.
It's got to do both with fertility and it's got to do with, I think it's sort of interesting that the earth is always some particular earth that you're on.
But the sky is universal.
Everybody's under the same sky.
But in a certain sense, they aren't really all, you could say they're all standing on the same earth, but somehow they're standing on the same earth by standing in a different place.
But they're all just playing under the same sky.
I think that's how Aeschylus thinks about it.
And he certainly lines them up that way.
And so let's go on dark and light.
What goes with dark and light that we haven't got here yet?
When do the furies do their deeds?
And when do the high gods do their deeds?
The furies do their deeds in the dark.
They're always in the dark, under the ground.
I have quotes about that.
Let's see if I can find one.
Let's try page 48.
Yes, at the top of the bottom of 48, it talks about there lurks in the hooded night terror.
The gods fail not, the gods there are the furies, fail not to mark those who have killed many.
The black fury, stalking man, fortunate beyond all right, wrench back, that is, somebody who gets away with killing.
That would be the fortunate against all right.
Wrench back against, again, the set of his life and drop him to darkness, and so forth.
So that, yeah, the furies are always in the dark.
You'll hear more about that.
And the sky gods are in the light.
They're the gods, again, I don't think I can just open to it.
They're the gods of the marketplace.
I used to think that was strange.
What that means is they're the gods sort of out in the open in the daytime.
They show up and interact with people.
They don't just reach out and sort of drag them down into the dark.
And tying up with the earth and the sky and the day and the night, we haven't got day and night.
These are the day, this is the night.
And that's very closely related to another version, which is the dark and the light.
I don't think you'll say it because it seems to me in a certain way I've already said it.
Okay, what else have we got?
Oh, and I just said something about the local and the universal.
This is the local, and this is the universal.
I haven't shown that yet.
I'll show you right now.
The person who speaks, or the god, that is, who speaks most for the new gods, and I keep saying he's the real super male of the bunch in that he represents what the new gods are most good at and most different.
Yeah.
Did I get him on the wrong side?
Oh, I did.
Let's see.
Dark, local, universal, dark.
Oh, yeah.
Thanks.
That's not a good idea, is it?
So these are the night people, or I keep calling them people.
You understand that they're gods.
Okay, night.
And over here, of course, are the daywives.
Apollo of all is, after all, still a kind of sun god.
But what he really is now is what I'm going to call the kind of enlightenment fanatic before his time.
I mean, he has no respect for feeling or the local at all.
All he thinks about is sort of this detached, universal truths.
This is clear on 157.
I have to jump way back there to the speech of Apollo.
To you, established by Athena in your power, I shall speak justly.
Then he tells you who he is.
I am a prophet.
I shall not lie.
Never for man, woman, nor city.
I mean, no partiality, not even for Athens.
Never for man, woman, nor city, for my throne of prophecy, have I spoken a word except that which Zeus, father of Olympians, might command.
This is justice.
Recognize how great its strength.
This is just to say I'm completely honest, not at all devious, always ready to see and tell the truth, and it's the same truth for everybody.
I have no partiality, and that's the most important thing for the new gods, and that's the powerful new idea that the new gods have.
And so we have to we have that in there.
Fairness, universality, and rationality versus what is over here, sort of partiality.
I called it local here.
Maybe I should call it, well, local is okay.
And along with the local goes, I'll see how I can make this, see if anybody can understand, see this.
Who will be the god or goddess or whatever of the family?
Which, come on, you must know.
Well, come on, this is hopeless.
If you don't know that, that's very bad.
Which are families, universal or local?
Local.
Families, yes.
The furies are for families and blood relatives and everything local like that.
So when anybody does anything to anybody in your family, you get back at them by appealing to the furies who then attack the other family.
This is a very un-Apollonian way to do things.
So their family, they're also called hearth sometimes, goddesses of the hearth, which is the focus of the family, the fireplace in French.
It is foyer, which means focus.
So they're going to be the gods of the family and the hearth.
And over here, what's the opposite of family, I wonder?
What did I have?
Oh, strangers, of course.
This is the god of strangers.
This is one of the ways that it's still related to Zeus.
Only in an odd way, Zeus is, oh, that's sort of confusing, really.
Zeus protects the family, but he doesn't protect, he protects.
See, I told you last time, it's odd.
Zeus doesn't protect strangers anymore because Aeschylus doesn't really understand anything about going from world to world.
That's not his thing.
And he doesn't, and it's not a pirate culture anymore where people come from other worlds and tell you their story and that you try to be a good host to them and they better not do anything bad to you.
So Zeus was against what Paris did because he was a bad guest.
Well, now Zeus is the protector of the hosts from the guests.
But he's protector of them as hosts, not as families, not as hearth, but something much more, I don't know, masculine and abstract.
Yeah.
His what?
The hearth.
Yeah, Hestia.
And which, and is she one of the ones on Olympus?
I hope not, but she might be.
She's on what list?
My godless?
Uh-oh.
She's the goddess of the hearth.
I wonder.
I'm going to erase it, but I have to think about it.
Certainly, let's put it this way.
This is the question of blood relatives.
I will worry about later.
Is that how you spell blood?
It looks funny.
Okay.
Okay, the blood relatives over here and strangers over here.
Let me write hearth over here as something I don't understand where it goes.
And I don't really understand where Artemis goes.
Somebody who will help me out someday and tell me.
So did we do already?
We did pass.
What did we do about the old?
Old and new is fine.
Another one is tradition.
They're for tradition.
And these people are for progress.
The question is whether being new is a good thing or a bad thing.
These gods say being new is just a bad thing.
Things were fine in the good old days, which is what we stood for.
These gods say we're new and we're progress.
We get beyond your old-fashioned, archaic, childish tradition.
Yeah.
What's that?
Oh, wow.
Wow, was that an important question?
I thought I just said something about it, but I think you're right, I haven't.
She's asking, is Homer before or after the Orestea?
Homer is way before the Orestea.
I had that in here.
I wonder what happened to him.
I didn't say anything about that, did I?
Or did I?
Oh, yeah, the timeline is there.
But wait, I mean, just let me say, Homer was written down 500 years before the time of the Athenian Greeks.
And the Homeric Greeks were already something like 300 years in the past.
I think it is.
You can look it up on Wikipedia or someplace.
Before Homer was written down.
It was an oral culture.
And that oral culture was the culture in which there was Agamemnon and so forth.
And it really was there because archaeologists, I don't actually tell you this, really finally dug up Troy and dug up the palace of Agamemnon and so forth.
It really was a long, long, but it was it was as far away in the past from Aeschylus as the medieval time is from us.
It was just literally another world.
So and I'm glad you asked.
Yeah.
Ah, good, good.
Yes, she's asking.
So, how come it looks like the Furies are, where Homer is focusing on the Olympian gods, even though he's older?
Well, good point.
The Furies are even older.
The Furies go way back to the beginning of the culture, even before the beginning of the culture, way before.
Because the Furies are born of the blood when Cronus castrated Uranus and all these big, weird battles between the very, very, very old gods.
So the Furies have been around sort of forever.
They're practically like animal instincts.
They protect women in the sense that they protect their family and their blood offspring ferociously against any outside intrusions, the way animals do.
I mean, in my own backyard, I saw a deer attack my big dog because the dog got between the deer and the baby deer, which I didn't know was there.
So a pretty amazing sight.
The dog became so afraid of deer that he was traumatized for the rest of his life.
But anyway, so who had a hand up over here?
No, it's all from the text.
Everything is in here somewhere in some chorus speech or other.
As we go through it, I'll give you the sort of page numbers where it happens.
So there's the tradition, okay, and progress and feeling and thinking, and you defend the nest or the home or the family and so forth.
There's no sense of fairness or universal rights.
Everybody should be defending their own home.
I mean, I wrote down here because when I was in high school, I guess, there was this whole thing about people building bomb shelters, atom bomb shelters, because it was the Cold War.
And there were this argument among whether if somebody else is outside and they don't have a shelter or something's happened to their shelter, should you let them into yours?
And there was sort of on the one side the Olympian types who said the rationale, yes, you can't leave a human being out there in the radioactivity just because he's not a member of the family.
And there were the Fury types who said, We built this, this is for us.
We got to hoard our own food.
There's nobody we could care about but our own blood family.
And you could see that contrast.
And the Furies are still doing that, taking up the side of the blood and the family.
Okay, did I see anything else?
Now, I got to, let me see if there's anything more I have to say about that.
Well, only one thing.
Of course, the Furies are women.
We said that way at the top.
And the Olympians are men in general, with some minor complications.
Therefore, you should be upset, and I was, when the Furies are called he on page 83, for instance.
You don't see it because they're talking about the spirit in the middle of the page, the spirit thrice glutted that lives in this race.
From him, deep in the nerve, is given blood.
The spirit in the race is the Furies who are causing all this trouble in the family relations between Atreus and Thaestes, and then the next generation, we're going to have the killing of Agamemnon by one of the children.
You can figure this all out by reading Latimer.
I never can keep it straight.
But one thing is sure: and yet the spirit from him, deep in the nerves, is given what him.
The first time I read it, I practically gave up.
I thought, I don't understand this play.
I'm never going to understand it.
I don't even know if Aeschylus understands it.
And you get it again on page 86, middle of the Clytemnestra speech at the top.
Hereafter, let him go forth to make bleed with death and guilt the houses of others.
That's the spirit a little earlier, the spirit in the house.
This is all furies.
So what's going on?
Well, this is a very uninteresting grammatical mistake that Latimer is just too oblivious or literal or something to pay attention to.
You know, in some languages, there are neuter and masculine and feminine nouns in German, all three.
In French, too.
How many know this?
I've had already in some course, some language where, okay.
Well, this is just a case of that.
It turns out that the furies is a masculine word.
So when you refer to the furies, you have to say he.
Any sensible person translating it into English would just change it to the pronoun to she.
In German, the word for girl, Meijen, is neuter.
And I suppose you say it.
Do you say it when you refer to a young girl, Beatrice?
You say it, even though you're referring to a girl.
Because the pronoun goes by the way, the gender of the noun, then it has nothing to do with the gender of the person.
So, just whenever you see she, you just pay attention, and if you see he, then you better mark it if it's the Furies and make sure that you cross it out and put she.
The Furies are always female, always tied up with this fertility, mother, blood side.
So, now, what's the problem behind this when you get this all on the board?
Well, these two are okay.
I mean, they're both important aspects.
A culture ought to do justice to both of them.
But what's crazy about this culture is that they're fanatics.
Either they're fanatics who believe in the new gods and think that the Fury should be written out of the picture, like Homer, who was the first of the anti-Fury people.
And Homer practically did write them out of the Greek culture.
It's amazingly how close he came, but he didn't succeed.
Another thousand years later, the Furies are back, in spite of Homer, in spite of the fact that they're still reading the Odyssey and take it to be their kind of Bible, an example of how men and women, and servants, and children, and everything should behave.
They nonetheless are a vengeance culture in which they are back being appealing, just appealing to the Furies for revenge when anything happens to their family, to their blood relatives.
So it's a culture in which these two sets of values, which could, you know, in principle, sort of supplement each other if each stayed in the right place, each one claims to be the authority.
Each one claims just one second.
That when people do things in their name, it's justice.
You've got to keep your eyes open.
There are two kinds of justice.
There's the feud kind of justice, the Hatfields and McCoy's kind of justice, where if somebody does anything to your clan or your family, or it's kind of mafia justice, then it's just, it's right, it's required that you go and kill one of them.
And they keep claiming, the Furies, that they're in charge of justice.
And let's call that vengeance justice.
And then there is the, they've got their sense of justice, but the new gods have their sense of justice.
Let's call that retribution, or by which I mean legal kind of justice.
They did this, and thanks to the institutions of the culture, we will take them to court and we will put them in prison or chop off their heads.
But we don't just do it individually with kind of, what's the word?
What did I say about just a second?
Well, vengeance and retribution are the best words I know.
And these are in terms of vengeance.
It's old.
It's blood.
And these are in terms of, I guess, retribution.
It's legal justice.
And in the middle, I'll just put justice, because both they all there's only, I don't think Aeschylus has a word for these two separate things.
He calls them all justice.
But he knows there's a big difference, because the whole fight is about which kind of justice.
Now, go ahead.
How do you know that the reason that the Furies aren't really mentioned in the Odyssey is because they just weren't that important, and that they just became more important in the Orange Day.
I mean, I understand that they in mythology, they came from...
Good.
I think that's a very good question.
I don't know.
And I have no right to say it, really.
So I have to think about that.
Did you hear his question?
He wants to know how come I say that the Furies were being repressed by Homer, and how do I know that they just weren't very important?
And Homer was expressing this fact that once upon a time the Furies were important, but now they're not anymore.
And that's why, when he writes up the work of art for his culture and focuses it, he doesn't have a place for the Furies.
Am I understanding you?
They weren't important.
I see they were never important until Aeschylus made a big fuss about them.
How do I know that they were ever important until Aeschylus made a fuss about them?
Good question.
Yeah.
Why don't they just say that the Furies weren't worried about the budget?
I think I've got them in Balawk and T.
So now there was no competitive life.
Now about Hemer's life, how many possible people did it?
Protect the old way, the family way.
Okay, interesting.
But the way they do it is so much this kind of old-fashioned vengeance.
You kill a member of my family, and I'm going to kill a member of your family, no matter who.
It doesn't have to be anybody who did anything wrong, just them being a member of the other family.
That's how they act now, the way Aeschylus is portraying them.
It's all sort of plannish local interest.
Now, that isn't the way it's in Athens.
Aeschylus is telling the Athenians, and I didn't want to go into this yet, but I think you people are sort of forcing me to.
Aeschylus is telling the Athenians how they got to be the kind of people they are.
And the kind of people they are are not fury-driven people, and they're not enlightenment fanatics either.
They're better than either.
But that you don't find out how they got that way and what it is to be better until the third play.
So, but there, Aeschylus is either making up, I don't know, a time, or really dimly through, I don't know what people, old stories and myths and so forth, reconstructing a time in the culture in which the Furies and the Olympian gods were equally powerful.
And all we've got to go on, and that's what you guys are saying, there are no history books about this period, this was this archaic period.
And all we've got is sort of Aeschylus using the folktales and the myths to reconstruct this culture, which he claims was there all along.
That's this claim that it's the oldest, and that's why her question about which came first, Homer, or so forth.
And Aeschylus is really making up a story that I was following.
But I didn't tell you it was just a story.
I told you as if I knew that it was true.
But Aeschylus is making up a story in which Homer has repressed and ignored the forces for family and vengeance and all the stuff over here in the name of the pantheon, which he's promoting over here.
And he's telling you the story that this repressing this, which is what Homer did, is going to cause a great deal of trouble.
And you will find that the Furies, as you read it, are upset, are furious, indeed, that we still have the word around at the way they've been treated by the Olympian gods.
Now, and if anybody thinks that there's any historical evidence for this, let me know.
There are other myths and other poems by Hesiod from the same, from roughly the time of Homer.
There's a whole bunch of other myths and things that were written down later that come from the time of Homer.
I don't know what any of them have to say about the Furies.
But in the end, we don't care.
I mean, that's important.
I mean, we have to just, what's interesting to us is the story that Aeschylus has made up to show the Athenians what they stand for and why their culture is better than any culture there's ever been before or after in the world.
And he does it by this history.
While I'm talking about this, I wrote here the places where Homer talks about the furies, and you can look at them.
I'll read them to you.
They're very few.
And Homer doesn't seem to even understand them very well, because at one place, anyway, he says he's talking about Oedipus.
And Oedipus, Jocasta, Oedipus's wife, a lot of you read Sophocles.
How many read Oedipus?
As I recall, many, many.
Okay, so you know who Jocasta was, Oedipus's wife.
She hung herself because she married her son, and neither one of them knew it.
And she, her furies, attacked Oedipus, according to Homer.
So let's see where I can see.
So she thrust from a high rafter, throttled in her noose, she swung, carried away by pain, and left him endless agony from a mother's furies.
Because she is his mother and his wife, and she hung herself.
And according to Homer, the furies then pursued him.
But that seems pretty crazy.
And certainly Sophocles has dropped that from the story.
So that one, I don't even think Homer has lost any sense of what the Furies are up to.
He just knows people talk about them going after people whose mother who killed their mother.
And in a weird sense, Oedipus killed his mother, but certainly that that's pretty far-fetched.
So here's another.
So that was on page 194.
On 23, or was that already 23?
No, here, on 23, I read this, I think.
Didn't I?
I don't know.
Maybe not.
So about 15 lines down, Telemachus is saying, I better not do bad things to my mother the way you suitors want me to do, because if I do, the powers of darkness would requite it.
My mother's parting curse would call hell's furies to punish me.
And hell's, by the way, is something that I that, what's his name?
Fritz Gerald has put in there, I think, because Latimer says her furies.
That would be better.
My mother's parting curse would call her furies to punish me.
Speaking of that, we can add one more on this list that I never really thought about before.
Whenever people curse people for doing some bad thing to them or their families, you get over here.
What goes over here?
It's very interesting.
Well, you'll see oaths go over here.
Remember, I said that Menelaus and Agamemnon made oaths.
It's funny, you don't distinguish very clearly anymore in English between oaths and curses.
He swore an oath.
But when you, but in the really right English, when you swear an oath, you can swear it on the Bible.
You can swear it sort of in the name of God.
It means just a very serious promise.
But a curse, then you is different.
Then you invoke the powers of darkness and evil on the person you curse.
So when anybody curses anybody, they call on the furies.
When they make oaths and promises, they call on the Olympian gods.
It's just another aspect of the same thing.
Only I never thought about it before, so I'll write it down.
Here we have curses.
It's going to turn out to be important.
I'll tell you right now, because it's hard to understand, that what Agamemnon does when he kills Ephigenia is put is gag her so she can't say anything, so that she can't call down she can't curse him by calling on the mother on her furies.
And so, that's just part of the same story.
Now, yeah, I'm going to go on reading these because they interest they're interesting given that you, particularly, you guys are now sort of raising the question what were what was Homer thinking?
So, 2326.
If you find any more, you've got to let me know.
Yes, there are furies.
Okay, here's one at the bottom of 326.
I don't know who's talking.
Oh, this is disguised as the beggar.
He says, If beggars interest the gods, if there are furies penned in the dark to avenge a poor man's wrong, then may Antinous meet his death before his wedding day.
Well, again, Homer doesn't seem to understand the furies, they're not in the job of defending beggars, they're exactly in the job of only defending blood relatives against anybody.
I mean, their revenge against people who did anything to your blood relatives.
So, it's just I don't know, he just doesn't think about them at all, or he doesn't think about them very clearly.
275, were they not important in the culture?
Or he didn't care?
This one is so obscure that I won't even bother with it on 275.
But let's try 377.
Well, here's one.
You know what?
But it's on 377, about line 80.
Aphrodite and glory walked on Olympus, begging for each a happy wedding day from Zeus, the lightnings, joyous king, and so forth and so forth.
But even at that hour, the cyclone winds had ravished them away to serve the loathsome furies.
What's going on?
God only knows.
I don't know.
You'd have to look it up to find out.
But it doesn't sound like it's got anything to do with what Aeschylus has made of it.
So all we have to do is just say, look, we're trying not to do Greek history, though it would be nice if we could, but we're trying to understand how Aeschylus understands the history of the people of Athens.
And he's going to claim that the Furies were always there.
And after all, there was always feeling and dark and night and the family and blood relatives and tradition and so forth.
It was always there.
Homer just didn't have any place for it.
And therefore, it got worse because when you repress something and don't give it any place, it'll come out someplace else.
He's got a kind of Freudian view about that.
You can't just get rid of the Furies by denying them.
You've got to confront them and integrate them somehow.
And Homer, as you can just see from what I read, didn't confront them and didn't integrate them.
And Aeschylus' story is: so they got worse and worse until I suppose he thinks he's writing it about, well, who knows when he thinks he's writing, because he seems he's writing at the same time as Homer.
Obviously, the same people are involved and the same gods.
He thinks Homer just didn't see what was really going on.
The Furies were there and they were very upset that Homer didn't see them.
That's the way he sets it up.
Okay, so now we are, we got that settled.
I'm just giving you to see where we are.
Vengeance has to do with personal feuds.
It's not justice in the sense of impersonal.
It's not obeying the law and so forth.
We've got that.
And the question is, now, which side is Aeschylus on once you put all this up here?
Is he for the Furies or is he for the Olympian gods?
Well, I think Aeschylus just sees that they're both.
They both have their value, and they're both very dangerous if they become fanatics.
Apollo is just as dangerous as the Furies when he thinks that everything is rational and you shouldn't have any feelings or any local partiality or anything like that.
So he either thinks that the new gods are a decline, which is what the Fury is thinking, or that they're progress.
That's not what he thinks.
He thinks that both sides, I just read it, are absolutely important.
And if you leave, and it becomes clear in the third play when the Furies give a wonderful speech about what will happen if you leave them out.
There will be no more fertility.
There will be no more erotic love.
There will be no more loving and raising children and so forth and so forth.
And it's clear that they've got a strong case, that you couldn't have a culture if you just had people like Apollo or gods like Apollo running around.
And where is Zeus in all this then?
Well, that's another interesting story, which I want to be sure and get to, which I will.
So let me look at you some more.
So Zeus is one of the Olympian gods, obviously.
But just like in Homer, Zeus isn't for any particular something or other, not a particular mood, and not a particular way of life, like the Furies are for the local family women, children way of life, and so forth.
And the other ones are for the legal universal.
Zeus isn't for a way of life.
He's again connected with guests.
And we've talked about that, but I've now got pages.
Funny, because it made sense for him to be, as I say, God of strangers when they were going from world to world.
It doesn't really make any particular sense.
It's just left over from the old days and from Homer that he's now still called the God who takes care of strangers.
Now, where is that?
36.
Oh, yeah, at the very bottom.
So drives Zeus, the great guest god, the Atridi, that's the Greeks, against Alexander, whenever that's Paris.
So he's, but there he's, why is he driving the Greeks against Paris?
Because Paris has been a bad guest.
He's now on the side of the host, not on the side of the strangers.
That isn't a big deal.
It's just a funny fact.
And it's a kind of offshoot of polytheism no longer being something that really is what the culture takes seriously.
So they've got to find a new God, a new job for Zeus.
And it's not enough that he just protects households from bad things that guests might do.
We do hear on page 56 that he's kindly to strangers, but all that I think isn't interesting.
I'll tell you what it is in a minute.
About six lines down, Zeus kindly to strangers.
But that, I just don't know.
It's something that just seems to be dropped in.
Nothing important happens.
So what is important about Zeus?
Well, I think Aeschylus, being a very, very, very smart person, as you'll see by the end of the third play, he wrote, this is the work of art, the mother of all works of art.
It's the most perfect work of art.
And Aeschylus wrote it in a certain sense, knowing that he was doing it and knowing and purposely writing it.
And he also is a kind of brilliant theologian, though he hasn't got the language of philosophy to help him.
What he really thinks, I believe, is that Zeus is behind everything.
I'll read you the passage where he says something like that.
And what is behind everything?
Well, it's the understanding of being in the practices.
I mean, Zeus is all of it makes sense.
When anything happens, Zeus is behind it.
That's the sense in which he's not on any side.
He's beyond being on any side.
But let me give you quotes because it's so strange and interesting.
So Zeus turns out not only to be kindly to strangers, which is an Olympian thing.
I just quoted it.
I'm showing you still he's on both sides.
And not only is he Olympian, but he's also partial to the furies, or at least they belong to him too.
At the bottom of 83, surely it is a huge and heavy spirit bending the house to cry.
Whenever you hear this spirit's talk, that's the furies.
Alas, the bitter glory of doom that shall never be done with.
And all through Zeus, Zeus, first cause, prime mover.
For what thing without Zeus is done among mortals?
See, Zeus is behind everything.
That's bad translation.
I'll fix it in a minute.
I mean, first cause is Aristotle's name for the God that is controlling and making everything happen.
Prime mover is another Aristotelian name.
Well, surely Aeschylus is a, at least, I think, two generations before Aristotle.
He has no clue of that kind of jargon, that philosophical talk.
And the translation doesn't say that.
The translation says something like, Zeus is responsible for all.
Or I would just say, Zeus is behind everything.
That's what Aeschylus really is trying to get at, which gets translated to contemporary, but it's the right idea.
Zeus is the single power that makes everything meaningful and makes everything happen.
He's not a creator god.
That's a very Judeo-Christian thing.
But Zeus is the force or the power or something like that behind everything that happens.
It's, I think, the way the cultural practices are behind everything.
The way an understanding of being is behind everything.
And so that he's...
He's behind the Furies and their understanding of being as family and vengeance, and he's behind the Olympian gods and their understanding of being.
And in a way, he's beyond all of that because he's what makes all of that possible.
And he's also, seems to be the tendency in the practices that if they are conflictual, then they lead to suffering.
And then you keep hearing, and through suffering, things will get better.
What is it?
Man only learns through suffering and all these quotes where I would like a good suffering quote right now, but I don't have it.
This chorus is always talking about that.
Suffer, suffer, but good wing out in the end, they say every once in a while.
Well, Zeus is the force.
I mean, it needn't be like that.
Cultures could just be worlds in collision and destroy each other.
But if you're willing to suffer, or maybe you're not willing, it's not even irrelevant, a certain amount of suffering and the culture will improve.
Keep in mind, when you hear that, that what happened to Afro-Americans, how after a whole lot of suffering, they finally got more and more of what they were promised by the Constitution.
Or think about how the lot of women gradually has improved and will improve more and more as the world gets gradually taken over by Western ways of thinking, or think the latest is sort of gay liberation.
In each case, there's lots and lots of suffering, and it's nobody's fault, and nobody can really do anything about it.
But as suffering enough, and Goodwin's out in the end, I think that's, I think Zeus is behind that, or that is, that that happens is Zeus.
That there is practices, that they give meaning to your life, and that those practices can themselves evolve.
I think Aeschylus understands all that amazingly enough, though he has no language to say it.
And I think he just puts that all on Zeus.
And then, sort of more interesting of all in a way, is that he knows that he doesn't have any adequate way of understanding it.
Look on page 39, that is quite remarkable.
He says, it's mind-boggling, right at the bottom of 39, Zeus, whatever he may be.
And so in the end, he knows that it's something he hasn't been able to name.
He hasn't been able to, he hasn't got the language to describe it, but he knows that it's behind everything.
Yeah.
Yes, I think it's the divine power, and I think it is monotheism in a good way.
That is, somehow, Zeus is the unity of all this seemingly hopelessly conflicted culture.
And behind it, and making it all happen, and maybe making it all turn out all right, there is this power.
The one thing you don't want to say, and that's why I'm a little nervous with monotheism, is it's not a kind of creator god like our kind of monotheism.
It's not Judeo-Christian monotheism.
I don't think Aeschylus even glimmers that, wants that.
It's this Heideggerian, which I talk about every once in a while, kind of monotheism.
There is an understanding of being, it's behind everything, it makes everything intelligible, it tells you what it makes sense to do, it lets you understand things as the sort of things that they are, and that's and there's one such something or other, and that's about all he can understand.
The one thing I think you don't, he doesn't, he is moving away from trying to have one God like Zeus and making it something more like one force or one principle or something very abstract, I think.
So we haven't got much to go on.
We're not disagreeing about much either, I think.
It's it's okay, yes, Beatrice.
Yeah, Clytemnestra invoking Zeus.
Zeus is she's invoking Zeus on 65.
Oh, yeah.
Good.
I mean, I think we're agreeing, aren't we?
That Zeus is, you can invoke Zeus when you would invoke the Furies.
You can invoke Zeus when you would invoke the Olympians.
Aeschylus has got some idea that Zeus is beyond that conflict.
And keep your eye open for that.
If you can make up the story about Zeus, that would be an interesting topic.
I'm not sure that it's, I'm afraid it's probably sort of too hard to grasp for Aeschylus, and therefore too hard for us to grasp in Aeschylus.
Yeah.
Yes, oddly enough, and Beatrice's quote is very important there, that he, that Clytemnestra could invoke Zeus on the side of her constantly invoking the furies and the curse and the family blood on the house of Atreus.
What was that page again, Beatrice?
I think that's interesting.
What, 65?
Okay, because you want to see that Zeus is really above the conflict.
Zeus here.
That's Clytemnestra.
Okay, I'm going to write that down.
Okay, let's go on because I can't say more about Zeus.
I wish I could.
I think it's fascinating that Aeschylus is trying to do what he's trying to do there.
Now, we've got to get to the rest of the time, to something I promised I would get to last time, but there was so much to do in between.
Now, we get to Agamemnon's tragedy.
That is, finally, we've got to look carefully at what happens when he has this problem.
Problem is an understatement, this disaster, as he calls it, of having to either sacrifice his daughter or not, and both of them are going to be terrible.
So, let's go.
He's caught in a conflict because he's a father and a king.
He's got personal feelings, and he's got a public role.
And he has to choose one or the other.
Somehow, the way Odysseus' polytheism worked, he could be a father and a king, and a pirate, and an adventurer, but that's not how it works anymore in the way Aeschylus pictures it.
There are only these two forces, and they're both absolutely important, and he's got to choose.
So we're in trouble.
I just want to give you the whole picture now, since the poetry is so hard.
I want to make sure you see it.
Because what happened with her is going to turn out to be extremely important next time.
So we've got to get it right this time.
Okay, to begin with, as I said, the soldiers are starving.
Just, oh, by the way, look at this.
I just opened on 40.
Wow.
I wish I mean, that's what I want.
It says, Zeus, who guided men to think, has laid it down that wisdom comes alone through suffering.
That's good.
I wonder about the think.
I would go look at the translation for that.
But that wisdom comes alone through suffering is what will kind of, it comes again and again.
But that's not what I want to talk about right now.
The soldiers are starving.
Where is that?
Oh, yeah, the middle, a little below the middle, about line 186.
When no ship sailed, no pail was full.
That's the starving.
And the Achaean people salt fast against the shore.
Then the prophet's going to say something.
So they're starving, and Agamemnon has got to choose because the prophet who's speaking for Artemis says you can't get off and stay away until you do something.
And the delay is crumpling the flower and pride of Argos.
I never noticed that before at the bottom of 40.
That's good.
I mean, that's the problem.
They're not only starving, they're sort of falling apart, just sitting there.
And so then what happened?
Well, what does Agamemnon say?
This is a crucial speech.
Because next time you're going to be asked to judge whether Agamemnon behaved well or badly or what when he killed Ephigenia.
It's going to turn out to be absolutely crucial to Clytemnestra's approach to him.
But let's start at the top of 41.
He says, The elder lord, that's Agamemnon, the older brother, spoke aloud, My fate is angry if I disobey these, those are the soldiers, but anger if I slaughter this child, the beauty of my house, with maiden blood shed staining these fathers' hands beside the altar.
What of these things goes now without disaster?
How shall I fail my ships and lose my faith in battle?
That is his role as the leader.
For them, that is the soldiers, to urge such sacrifice of innocent blood angrily, for their wrath is great.
It is right.
So he sees that it's wrong for him to kill Ephigenia, that it's right for him to kill Ephigenia, and his reaction is a perfectly human reaction.
He says, May all be well yet.
He just says, let's hope things work out.
I don't know what to do.
I won't do anything.
Maybe it'll be all right.
But of course, it isn't.
So finally, he had to do something.
And then that goes on.
When necessity's yoke was put upon him, that is, the men are starving, he changed, and from his heart, the breath came bitter and sacrilegious, utterly infidel.
I mean, he sort of lost his faith in whatever.
And then, where he endured then to sacrifice his daughter, to stay the strength of war waged for a woman, first offering for the ship's sake.
And then we, and then skipping down to this bad thing he did about not letting her curse him, the bottom, with guards against the lips, sweet edge, to check the curse cried on the house of Atreus by force of bit and speech drowned in strength, and therefore, that's it.
He killed her.
And he gags her, kills her, and doesn't help him, by the way, that he keeps her from cursing him because Agamemnon curses him and calls on the fury, on Iphigenia's fury, later.
You can apparently do it for the person who can't do it for themselves.
Now, the question is: did Agamemnon do the right thing?
What do you think?
Well, you're right.
I mean, I can't imagine how anybody can answer that.
It's an impossible question.
From each, I mean, he did absolutely the right thing, and he did absolutely the wrong thing.
The situation was such that there was no way to do the right thing.
If he killed her, it was not going to be the right thing, and if he didn't kill her, it was not the right thing.
So, what happens then?
Well, the sky gods say he's a brave hero, willing to sacrifice his own daughter for a just war.
And if you're a president or a king who declares a just war, you better be ready to sacrifice your own children.
You're sacrificing everybody else's.
And he was.
What more could you ask?
A real hero.
And the army and the new gods are all on his side because they care about promises, oaths, guests behaving, and other non-family matters that govern social relations, kings and subjects, and so forth.
And justice for them is retribution.
That is, it's justice for them to go off and beat up Troy, destroy it completely, because Paris has done something wrong.
And that's at the top of 47.
Well, it starts at the top of 46, they say.
Oh, Zeus.
Our Lord and Knight Beloved.
Hmm.
That's not Zeus, of course.
They are calling on both Zeus and the Furies, I guess.
And the binding net.
Yeah, that's Clytemnestra's Furies.
And I gaze in awe on Zeus of the guests who wrung from Alexander such payment.
So it's all mixed up there.
But was it, it was the right thing to do?
Where do I find that?
Well, it's sort of about five or ten lines down on 47.
This was Paris.
He came to the house of the sons of Acreus, stole the woman away, shamed the guest rights of the board chaired, and so forth.
I think this is all supposed to say Paris did something wrong, and to fight and destroy him and Troy is the right thing to do.
It's just.
But on the other hand, and now we get on page 48, all kinds of innocents died.
Young, good people who shouldn't be out there having to fight this war.
And so, and their bodies come back in urns as ashes at the top of 48.
Many of them were touched by the heart of such things.
Those they sent forth, they knew now in the place of the young men, urns and ashes are carried home.
At the time of the Vietnam War, which is before your time, it was body bags.
And there were the bodies of the soldiers being carried home.
They're carried home from Iraq now.
And there was this period, we were around at that point, where they were trying to prevent people from taking pictures of the body bags stacked on the dock of the Americans killed.
Well, that's what they're worried about.
And at the bottom of 48, the citizens speak, their voices dull with hatred.
The curse of the people must be paid for.
There lurks for me in the hooded night terror of what may be told.
The gods fail not to mark those who have killed many, the black furies stalking the fortunate and sending them down to darkness and so forth.
That's the other side speaking.
Whoever killed all these men, who turned all of these young men into corpses, they're going to be gotten by the furies of the family.
I mean, the furies of the gold star mothers who've lost their children in the war are going to come after these people, people like Agamemnon, particularly, who's the one who took them all off to war.
So now let's see.
So the Khoras who lost their children, I just read that.
So would it have been better if he hadn't gone off to war and hadn't killed Ephigenia?
Not really.
I mean, then the soldiers would have starved or they would have gone home humiliated and he would have lost the authority of king and it would have been, I guess, an equal mess as far as the way it's set up.
There's something wrong somewhere, obviously.
But it's not something wrong with Agamemnon, is it?
Did he make the wrong choice?
I mean, that would mean that he should have done the other thing.
He should not have killed Ephigenia and not done his job as king and kept his promise to his brother.
I think there's, it's, it's, I don't think, or at least the question is, is there something psychological?
Is there something wrong with Agamemnon's character or personality or something that's behind making this big bad mistake?
You've got to be very careful.
I'm now trying to set you up for next time, what you have to look for.
It's clear that Agamemnon has freedom.
He's free to kill Iphigenia or not to kill Ephiginia.
He's free to act as king or as father.
But his freedom is very limited.
I mean, those are the only choices and bad ones.
I mean, it's quite, I mean, in another culture, he could have challenged Paris to a duel, or he could have asked God to forgive him, or he could have sought binding arbitration between the two sides and somehow got some compromise where everybody gave up something.
But in his culture, it looks like he's got a free choice, but the alternatives are very limited and very bad.
So then who's to blame for this mess?
Anybody?
Or what's to blame for the mess?
Anybody got an idea?
I mean, surely something's wrong.
Yeah.
Okay, but Artemis sort of could only do that in a context in which, yeah, okay, in a context in which these are the only alternatives.
I mean, she just sort of pushes out into the open what's going on, that to just go off and leave.
If he goes off, he's going to go against his being a father, and everybody in all the family, blood connections, and young people are going to die.
Or if he stays home, it's going to be sort of unacceptable humiliation.
Now, that isn't the way it has to be, but that's the way it has to be in that culture.
It's the culture who seems to be at fault.
I mean, what sets it up so that there's nothing that he can do that's right is that the culture is run by two fanatical sets of gods: the fanatical Fury people and the fanatical Apollo people.
Now, I'm just ready to where I want to be just a second.
So, who's to blame?
Well, the culture.
And now, the question is: for next time, finally, you get to read, you know, you read the introduction.
Now, you're going to get to see what tragedy means to Lattimore and what tragedy means to Aeschylus.
And you've got to ask yourself, and Lattimore's account of what happens, what happened when Ephigenia was killed, as told by Clytemnestra, and all of that, you're going to have to ask yourself finally.
Let me see how I wrote it, and then I'll let you go.
Well, we really got to ask yourself: is this a psychological tragedy or a tragedy of cultural worlds in collision?
Is there any personal blame, or is it something much more ontological?
Who, in effect, you could say, who's right about Aeschylus, me, or Lattimore?
And now, all you need to do to find out is reread the Latimore, only the part about Agamemnon when he comes home, and reread pages 56 to 65, which is what I'm going to analyze next time, and I want you to think hard about, which is Clytemnestra's description to the chorus of what you her version of Agamemnon's killing of Ephigenia.
And you're going to be asking yourself, is this a tragedy about a character who has a flaw and does something wrong?
Is it a psychological tragedy like Sophocles, Oedipus?
Or is it an ontological tragedy?
And what does Latimer think?
What do you think?
That's it.
Okay.