All right, so let's imagine the Roman Empire around 14 Anno Domini, which is the time of Augustus's death.
There, the Roman Empire includes all of the civilized world.
It includes what we now know as Spain, France, half of Germany, all of the Balkans, northern Africa, Tunisia, Turkey, Egypt, Greece.
And I say that it's all of the civilized world because everything that falls outside of its borders is thought of as barbarian territory.
Augustus had managed to establish the Pax Augusta, which is a time of relative stability, peace, prosperity for all of the provinces and for Rome and Italy itself.
Maybe we can see why, at least before the September 11th, the US was like the Roman Empire, because it unified for the entire world, accessible to it, was a unifying force.
It was giving an establishing culture and it was overriding national cultures or other native cultures.
It was dominating both in terms of cultural values and of economic force.
So whoever wanted to be someone had to do so in Rome.
Augustus now, Rome was a republic, and Augustus changed this system of government, or he stood at the end of a change of the government, and he was the first of the Roman emperors.
And he had inherited his power from Gaius Julius Caesar.
First, he was sharing the power with two other men, Mark Antony and Lepidus, in something that was called a triumvirate.
And his great uncle Caesar had done the same thing.
Then he proceeded on to defeat the other two triumviri, Mark Antony and Lepidus, and he also killed the biological son of Caesar, so to make sure that there was no blood lineage that was threatening him.
And then he was the undefeated holder of all power.
But that wasn't a very that wasn't such an easy position to be in because Caesar had been killed.
You guys know that Caesar was murdered and the reason for his the murder was that he had been offered the crown as king of Rome and the Romans said, we don't want a king, we don't want to establish a kingdom, we're a republic.
So what Augustus had to do was establish himself as a different ruler.
He couldn't rule Rome as a despot or king.
And so what he does first is keep the facade of the Roman Republic intact and he assumed only titles that were made him the honored first citizen.
He never assumed the title king.
He was first called Augustus, which is an honorary title referring to some religious authority, and then he was Princeps, which means first citizen.
So he always portrayed himself as the first of a number of citizens.
And then he spent the rest of his life building more and more power and assuming more and more titles.
He became emperor.
He pretty much held military power over most of the provinces most of the time.
And then when he had died, he became instantaneously deified.
So then finally he reached the status of God and had thus totally replaced the old system of value of the Republic with a new system of values.
Now, he wanted to establish himself as savior of Rome and as the rightful heir to the empire, and he wanted to glorify these new values.
And the best way to do that was to commission a work of art that would narrate this story.
And it would narrate the foundation of this empire with the Augustan rule as the finale.
And this work is the Aeneid.
It portrays the rule of Augustus as predestined historical goal.
And it links Augustus' family heritage to the founder of Rome.
Thus, the work served two purposes.
It was protection and glorification of Augustus and his war.
It was protection because it silenced potential Caesar murderers, and it did so by establishing a new virtue, a new emotion, namely theetas, or duty, towards the already fixed course of history.
So in the Aeneid, you find that to not serve your country, to not serve your people, to not serve the faith is a deplorable thing, and Augustus thus only did his duty in serving the Roman Empire as the first citizen.
And it glorified his rule by making it the happy ending of a long and arduous process of this new civilization, which was ruling the world by the will of the gods and of faith.
Another nice element of the Aeneid for Augustus was that it included a story of how the Roman culture of civilization that was now dominating came to overrule the previously dominating Greek culture and how it was ultimately superior because the Romans always had some sort of inferiority complex towards the Greek culture.
And the Aeneid told the story that Rome was as good as Greece.
And I think all of these are reasons why you can see how the Aeneid is some sort of anti-odysse.
It takes a lot of elements from the Odyssey.
You find a lot of the same people.
The gods have different names, but it's the same gods still.
And you have the similarity in story, in style, in outline.
Both are the stories of a homecoming.
Odysseus is coming home and Aeneas is coming home in a more metaphorical sense because he's founding Rome as the home of this culture.
But at the same time, you see that it's an anti-odysse because it describes how one of the Trojans is founding a new civilization.
And in the Iliad and in the Odyssey, the Trojans are the enemies of the Greeks.
So it's both attempting to create a link between Roman culture and Greek culture.
Aeneas has a passage from Troy to finally Rome, but it's also establishing Roman culture as a superior way of being, which I think is important for Augustus.
Now, let me come to the second point.
How do we all come from the Orestea to the Aeneid?
The Orestea and the Aeneid are structurally similar.
Both recount the formation of a civilization, and then this process is heightened in a certain way.
In both, the gods or fate or both play a role in bringing about what is perceived as a predestined history, a historical goal.
And both, if you remember, describe the heritage of a house and then the development of this house of this line over several generations, and both glorify the status quo of the time in which they were written, thus being a passage from a society in a darker age, in a darker past to a civilized and glorious present.
But I think it's also important to see the differences between the two, because we have actually kind of a counter-movement.
In the Orestea, we have the overcoming of the curse inflicted upon the house of Atreus.
And then finally, we have the overcoming of the system of tribal justice and blood feuds, and thus de-emphasizing the importance of family lineage and blood heritage, and the introduction of the importance of citizenship, of participation.
At the end, we have the police, that is the ideal, is not anymore a king's lineage.
And another frame of justice becomes important, namely, universal law and justice.
And now, when we see the opposite in the Aeneid, we see the re-establishing of a blood lineage.
That's precisely what the Aeneid is trying to do, linking Augustus' war with Aeneas all the way back.
Of course, as I said, Augustus was pretty careful.
He always said that he's just doing his duty and he's just the first citizen and he doesn't want to be the king.
But at the same time, he makes it makes sure that he is perceived as the son of a god at the very least.
Aeneas is the son of a god, so in the same line, he is the son of a god.
And then he's also adopted by Caesar, and Caesar was deified, so he's like double son of a god in a certain way.
And finally, he becomes God himself as the giver of law and peace.
I think the second point of comparison that's interesting is the two main characters, Orestes and Aeneas.
Or maybe not main character, but two.
Orestes, yeah, as the main character.
So we see that he does the right thing, but it seems that he doesn't do that out of a sense of duty, more out of a sense of ontological necessity.
He's more the tool of a cultural development.
And in the third play, we see that he is used as an example more than it's really about him.
As Professor Bruffin said, nothing really interesting so much happens to him in the third play.
He does what the god Apollo tells him.
He does that largely out of fears, too, I think, and not out of this notion of personal duty.
And he gives himself over to the protection of the gods, but overall, I think he shows very little awareness.
And that's very different for Aeneas because Aeneas is constantly reminded by the gods of his duty.
He has a personal duty towards state and historical development, like Augustus, his heir.
And he seems also to feel the sense of duty all the time because he talks a lot about it and it's the main motivation behind most of his actions.
So we see how, although the awareness of the faith is sent by the gods, he has dreams and he sees signs, it is already more part of the human history and the human historical goals and needs to be achieved through agency and action.
Different from maybe.
Okay, so much for comparing now onto part three: the myth of the failed authorship, which is a little story about Virgil, the author.
It's the year 19 before Christ, and Virgil is in his 60s.
His health is very bad, and he's very famous at this point.
He's very revered, one of the most important poets of his time.
And he has been commissioned by the emperor to write this great work.
And at this point in time, he has been working for 10 years on it, for a long time.
He hasn't been working on anything else.
And in the work that he wrote before that, that's called Georgica.
He mentions something that's interesting.
He says, I will write about a holy monument, a temple of marble dedicated to Caesar of Tavian and the forefathers of the Julian heritage.
And this he says in 30.
Now, it's unclear whether he really means that he's going to write the Aeneid.
And that would be very interesting because you remember who else has said that works of art are like temples of marble.
Heidegger has said that.
And it would be interesting to refer to a poem and compare it to a temple of marble.
But we don't know whether he really meant the Aeneid, but what's clear in this quote is that he was thinking about Augustus as the father figure and he was already researching the.
Now suddenly 19 before Christ, he decides to travel to Greece pretty suddenly.
And he says, yeah, I want to see the landscapes that I'm describing to describe them a little better.
And that seems strange because he has such a he loves Italy, his life is so settled there.
And at that time, deep traveling was really dangerous.
He also takes his valuable manuscript with him.
And it's not really clear why he does that.
And he indeed falls seriously ill while he's traveling, has to return to Italy quickly, and there he dies.
I think we don't really know.
It seems to be a little in the dark of why he does it because it's largely in the realm of legend.
We don't have many sources, historical sources that tell us about this clearly.
So maybe it's all just a legend.
Part of the legend is that Virgil had talked to a friend before he set out for the journey and has said to his friend, Various, you know what, if something happens to me, I want everything to be burned.
Don't keep any of the manuscripts I haven't published, just burn everything.
And when he dies, Augustus steps in and says, no, we're not burning them, we're publishing the Aeneid, it's a great work.
And he gives the manuscript over for publication and it's published and it becomes a bestseller right away.
Now why is this anecdote of the failed authorship important and what does it mean?
There's one interpretation that says that it's for protecting Virgil's reputations that the friends were worried that it wasn't so good and therefore they said, well, he himself didn't want it published.
Though, I mean, in light of the immediate success in the yeah, the it was had like raving reviews all around.
It seems not such a good explanation.
Then I think the second explanation is much better, that it's enhancing the state-building myths.
So Augustus steps in and says, despite the author's inability to see this, this is the real story of how we came to be a great civilization.
And thus it adds more to the myth or the legend of how the Aeneid is really this work of art.
So we see that there are several intentions here with this work.
First, of course, it's the poet who tries to write this commissioned work.
And then secondly, we see this effort by Augustus to glorify the work as depicting the cultural values that he wants to promote for his own security and power.
That brings me to part four.
Very quickly, I want to leave you with the question, is the Aeneid a work of art?
There's a passage in Heidegger's Origin of the Work of Art where he says with some sort of wry humor, he says, well, it's not the artists hanging out in the galleries, it's the works of art hanging there.
And what he's referring to here is that he doesn't think that there's this sort of agency and intentionality necessary for a work of art that you typically think of when you think of an artifact, of something that's made by a human agent or by another agent.
Because for Heidegger, the work of art functions very different from any other tool that you will make, and it functions largely independently or despite the intention of its maker.
Now, it is really true that anything could become a work of art, that if it glorifies and unifies a way of being, then it is a work of art.
And I want to leave you with the question: well, how do Virgil's intentions to create this work of art in Heidegger's sense and Augustus's intentions to hire Virgil to do just that, how do they stand in relation to this success of the Aeneid?
Do they contribute?
Does the intention contribute to the success as a work of art?
Is it of no importance or is it a hindrance?
Maybe you can think about that.
I want to ask you a question, but I haven't keep your microphone there.
I've always wondered about a certain passage I never thought of asking Herb and so what she was saying.
You must know, but if you don't want to talk about it, so next time, this passage in which it looks like he wants to say that the whole thing, the whole history of Rome is a false dream.
Have you ever thought about that?
No, but it's great.
It's a perfect quote for my interpretation from the case.
Look on page 160.
There's this which is the whole history of the Roman Empire of the world.
And then they're leaving the slight wavy type of a dream.
And then it turns out that there are two doors and in closed phase.
That is, in this case, there would be something like whatever is true about these people go out one door and the false dreams or the sort of false illusions go out the other door.
And guess what?
Aeneas goes out the illusion door.
I've always thought that was the hope.
Yeah, I think it would be wonderful if it means that it's a criticism on Augustan law.
But I think there is another interpretation maybe because in the underworld, in the Roman underworld, which by the way is now accessible via Italy, not Greece anymore, there is another cake where you can get there.
And it's organized in such a way that the souls wait for being called out again.
So it's a cyclical idea that you are reborn.
And I would think maybe they don't go through there because they're not sold yet.
They're not shades.
They can't go through the gate for the reborn shades because they're not reincarnated.
No, he's still.
No, I think he just has the description of the path.
I see, but by himself, he goes out the gate that isn't for reborn true.
I think so, because he's not dead yet.
So it's really ambiguous.
Yeah, it's nice.
It seems to me it could be open.
Remember, it goes with saying burnt.
It's another way of relating to his story that he said burn the manuscript.
Maybe he knew that it was propaganda, and maybe he regretted that he had written this sort of propaganda thing about Augustus.
And wants to say, in a cryptic way, don't take all this.
There's anything in the story.
That would be wonderful.
Yeah, I think that would be, that's also maybe another way of understanding this anecdote.
It's like, why does he suddenly leave for Greece?
Why is this sudden departure that maybe he wasn't so happy with?
He maybe saw that this was a kind of overweening expansion on Augustus' part.
But in any case, in spite of not believing it, he wrote a work of art.
To be a true work of art, it has to express, articulate the understanding of being of the people that it's written.
This is what I'm going to talk about next.
It's going to express the understanding of being, whether Virgil knows it or not.
I mean, understands it or not.
So he makes a work of art, even if it's propaganda, because it does capture and express and articulate and help form a certain Roman understanding of being.
Okay, thanks, Beatrice.
Beatrice will be back for an encore next time to talk about Dido.
But now it's my turn to talk, to put this not only in historical perspective, which Beatrice has done, but to put it in ontological Heideggerian understanding of being perspective, which is what I'm now going to do.
If once I get all these things in my pocket and understand whether they're all doing what they're supposed to be doing, this one doesn't seem to be doing anything, but let's hope it is.
Okay, when I left off last time, it was to make sure that I have told you the understandings of being of Thesis and Poesis, the Odyssey one, and contrasting it with the Orestea one, and saying that there was the understanding of being of Homer and the Homeric Greeks was that, and I didn't put it very clearly, but I want to say it again because I think I can say it clearer now.
Well, the kind of thing that was important to them was the kind of thing that whooshed up.
So I made a list of the kinds of things that whoosh up that they cared a lot about.
You'll see that Virgil doesn't care about any of them.
Passions, wild passions, like Aphrodite, hero ferocity, like Aries.
Wild animals, I think they thought were powerful, important things.
I don't know why I think so, except that there is a long story of a hunt and the killing of a something or other in the Iliad.
What's on the shield?
I forget.
Does he tell a boar?
And Odysseus has a wound from, remember, that the nurse sees, oh, there's another whole hunting story.
So I think hunting wild animals is important.
Certainly, because they go to sea, storms are very important.
And the thing is, and moods, didn't I write that down?
That's odd.
I mean, of course, moods are very, well, it comes under passions, I guess, but they don't have to always be erotic, swept away passions.
Moods are important, and all of them whoosh up and are, and this is what I also wanted to say, I said they well up, but I didn't use another phrase which seems to me important.
They're all overwhelming.
That's the whole point.
Storms, passions, ferocious fighters like Achilles are all overwhelming, and that's what impressed the Greeks.
And that's what Homer reflects in his understanding of being.
And their response was, they knew it was out of their control.
They admired all these things that were out of their control, and their response was wonder in the face of these things that are out of their control.
I already said that, but I wanted to say it again because now I want to go on to the next understanding of being, which is the one in the Iliad, but a little, I mean, the Aeneid, but just a little to keep sort of connecting to what Beatrice said too, so why we're reading this at all.
And not only is it a work of art and an important point on the way from gods to single god, because polytheism is gone.
If Augustus is the, or at least by far, I guess there are still other gods, but he's clearly the top god in this.
But there's more sort of mundane reason why we're reading it.
And it's important just to tell you that you notice we're only taking up little pieces of it.
That's not a good thing to do with works of art.
But there just isn't time to read the whole thing the way we could read the whole of the Odyssey and the whole Orestea.
And so we're really treating it as a step toward understanding the next big work of art, which is the divine comedy, which is certainly the focus of the understanding of the next understanding of being.
And we'll read a lot more of the divine comedy, though it's so big we can't read all of it.
So we're reading Virgil for three.
Oh, and since we're reading Virgil in this very kind of transitional way, we can't read it looking very carefully at every sentence and trying to translate or re-translate it so that it makes one very coherent picture.
We'll do that again when we get to Dante.
What we want to now is get this overall sense in this lecture and the next one and maybe half of the next one.
That's all we've got of what's going on here.
And what's going on here for us is a new understanding of being, which is what I'm going to talk about in a moment, a preparation for the geography of the underworld, which is, we've already seen a version of where the people go after they're dead in the Odyssey and how Homer thinks of death and mortality and the afterlife.
Now we need to be able to see how Virgil thinks about it because that sets up this poem, The Inferno, which is this amazing Dante whole book about the total details of mortality and the life of the people after you're dead.
We've got to, this is once you need this to get to Dante.
And as you'll see, Virgil shows up as the second, this main character in the Inferno.
He's Dante's guide, so it helps to know who Virgil is when you get there.
And we read it, as I say, as a step toward monotheism.
It's certainly the only, sort of one way to put it, I'm trying to figure out how to put it, how it's more monotheistic than the, certainly, of course, than the Odyssey.
But why more monotheistic than the Orestea?
Well, because there are lots of gods around.
All the Greek gods are still around.
You'd think it might be polytheism.
But the only God that really matters is Augustus when you get to the Aeneid.
And that's going to set you up for the supreme being, who's more than the emperor and the first citizen, namely the kind of God that we're familiar with from the Christian, Judeo-Christian story.
And so we can see this as a step in that direction.
Okay, now I have to look because I'm changing things around.
Okay, so I think I ended last time, as I can best remember, that saying, try to, as you read, try to see what the understanding of being is in the Aeneid.
What is the basic characteristic of what is the most important thing in life, and what is the basic, or things, and what is the basic characteristic of those things?
Just as whooshing up is what's the basic characteristic of these things which whoosh up are the most important for the Greeks.
And Poesis, just to remind you, is the expressive order of bringing out things at their best and the kind of things you nurture and cultivate.
It could have been friendship you nurture and cultivate, but it isn't.
It's citizenship that in the Aeneid, finally, you nurture and cultivate.
But it's not the kind of citizenship of a Roman representative kind of citizenship.
It's this total love of Athens where you want to bring everything out at its best.
That's what Athens stands for.
That's Poesis.
That's the expressive order.
If you repress things, they become bad.
I don't think I even said this very clearly, so I'll say it again.
If you repress things, according to Aeschylus, they become bad, like the Furies.
But if you let them all come out, it's sort of like hippie dungeon, let it all hang out, then you let everything come forth, it will come forth at its best.
And all you have to do is help by nurturing it, by cultivating it, by bringing it forth.
And that's the understanding of being.
And then I said at the end last time, I think, and what do you think the understanding of being is for Virgil?
And remember, now Virgil is writing a work of art not because he's trying to glamorize and promote Augustine.
I mean, that's what he's paid to do and fed and lodged to do.
And that's what he thinks he's doing.
And that's what he may have doubts about doing if that funny dream passage is read in that ambiguous way.
But what he's surely doing is expressing something that all these Romans share.
And in articulating it, in expressing it, he's focusing it and holding it up to the people and making it even more the way it is.
That's what he shares with Homer.
That's what he shares with Aeschylus.
And that's what saves it, whether or not because, what saves it is that's what it does.
It shows the Romans what they're up to.
And they treated it like a work of art.
They understood that.
They apparently learned it by heart.
I was thinking as I was writing this, that seems to be a kind of test of works of art.
The Greeks learned the Iliad and Odyssey by heart.
These guys learned the Aeneid.
The Christians, the really Christian Christians, could recite the Bible by heart.
It seems that if there is some work that is the articulation of what you're up to, you feel required or drawn to learn it and say it over and appeal to it on all sorts of situations.
To understand what you should be doing.
And then they went even further and they built shrines to it.
They really apparently thought of it.
I mean, the Aeschylus people already made it a, you could perform it every year.
And the Homer people obviously recited it at their very best parties, probably every year.
And this one, they actually somehow put the book in and worshipped it.
I don't know what that means exactly, but I read that they built shrines to it.
And what's going on in it?
Well, I'm changing my plan.
How are you going to find out?
I think I said this at the end last time, too, that Virgil's never going to tell you.
The understanding of being in here is production, which is what I think, what Heidegger says it is, and what I think I can show you it is.
He doesn't know that.
Heidegger talks about the necessary blindness of the great artist who's producing a work of art.
Why is that necessary blindness?
Because he's so inside the understanding of being, and he's so sensitive to it.
It's like a goldfish in water.
You can't see it if you're a great artist.
And the more you're open to it, and totally immersed in it, and unable to see it, the greater your ability to express it is going to be.
But of course, you won't know it.
So now I want to just read you a passage.
And I said, well, if he doesn't know it, how are you going to find out?
You can't expect him to tell you.
And you can't.
You've got to look, particularly at the similes.
There, he's copying Homer by long.
It was like such and such and such and such and such and such.
He took that over, presumably quite consciously, from Homer.
But the similes are very different.
I haven't gone back and looked at the similes in the Iliad and Odyssey, but I bet if you lined them up with the ones in here, you'd find them just strikingly different, and each of them hopefully giving you the Frusis and the production story.
But listen to, look at this.
Just on page 16, and this is where you might have gotten.
How many, how far have you gotten?
You had to write your papers, I know, and get them in yesterday.
How many have managed to read the first book?
That's good, that's good.
And book four?
Okay, well, try for sure.
You've got to read book four for next time, and hopefully, book six.
But Beatrice is going to talk about book four.
That's the Dido story.
Well, here, looking in the middle of 16, you find this funny thing.
He sees, and he thinks it's marvelous, all the activity and the enormous buildings, it says, six down, which were once mere huts.
And he's looking at what Dido has done in governing, what's the name of the place?
Not Carthage.
That's its real name.
But what's it?
Is it called Carthage?
Is it Carthage here?
A Carthage.
Okay.
So in the middle of the page, just as the bees in early summer busy beneath the sunlight through the flowered meadows, when some lead on their full-grown young, and others press out the flowing honey, pack the cells with sweet nectar, or gather in the burdens of those returning, some in columns drive the drones, the lazy herd, out of the hives.
The work is fervent, and the fragrant honey is sweet with thine.
Now, why does he like the bees so much?
Why not ants say?
They are equally busy and organized.
There's something very attractive about all this activity from the bees.
Can you get a feel for what it is?
I think it's because they produce something.
They produce honey.
It's not just that they're busy running around.
It's not even that they're busy running around in a very organized way, though that's part of the, that's necessary.
It's that all this activity produces this fragrant honey.
And that should interest him.
You'll see more, more similes later.
But for the moment, that's what I just wanted to jump to.
Now let me see where I am.
And Virgil is really making a product, too.
I mean, he's making what people nowadays call a deliverable.
He's got this deal, and he's going to produce the Aeneid, going to produce a work which satisfies certain descriptions.
But you don't feel that Homer did that.
You don't even feel that maybe there wasn't even a Homer.
Maybe the Odyssey just welled up in the sort of folk story and put together bit by bit and finally written down.
And you certainly, and you don't feel, I think that Aeschylus is producing a deliverable.
Because, why not?
Because you feel that sort of Aeschylus is out of control, that he's writing wild stuff that you can hardly understand.
I think probably he can hardly understand.
He's just so overwhelmed and filled with excitement and love of Athens that he just writes from it.
But you feel that this is a job and that Virgil is doing it very conscientiously.
And so let's see now else.
He's producing something and I wrote here too that Aeschylus is trying to cultivate something, something he's that's already i i i achieved and exciting and he's just helping it come to the full understanding of the people.
You I think I don't know whether you feel that about the Aeneid.
I think the Aeneid is more programmatic.
The Aeneid is trying to produce something.
It's trying to convince the people that their highest good is to be dutiful citizens.
Paietas, this new virtue.
He's trying to sell it.
And they've already got it, because you couldn't sell it to them if they didn't already have it.
But he's trying to articulate it and sort of, in a way, more produce it than just reflect it, I think.
But I could be just reading that in.
But I'm going to go on now and talk more about productivity.
By the way, you notice it's beginning to sound more like us as you go along.
I mean, certainly Frisus doesn't sound like us, overwhelmed, finding the things that overwhelm us and we cannot control the most wonderful, awesome things as what is the really best things.
And nurturing and cultivating doesn't seem to be our main thing either.
Producing is getting much, much closer.
At the end, before I at the very end, I'll try to say there is still an important difference between producing for the Romans and for us, but because we haven't got their understanding of being, there's at least one in between, maybe two.
I mentioned that, and we've got to do creation.
Notice that production and creation have a lot in common.
It's just that creation is a production by one supreme being who did who does the whole production.
And then after that, there's subjects and objects, and that's off in the future.
So here we are.
Virgil admires these ants in a way that the important thing I think for him is that they're organized and that they're producing something.
It's not a question of getting in tune with the situation nor bringing things out in their best, but it's producing a monumental product, monuments to themselves, so to speak, of what they're doing.
And now we can look at, if you look at, well, I don't think I want to do that yet, just a second.
Okay, no, it's not, it's not, I want to give out a pen.
Okay, it's, it's, you get what really is going on is dominating, governing, and imposing order that produces something, namely stable institutions, stable monuments, they're stable citizens, and so forth.
But I want to talk about this notion of dominating, governing, and imposing order.
That it sounds when you produce something, yeah, I've mentioned this once, but think about this.
When you produce something, one way to look at it, which is the way I think Virgil looks at it, is you impose order, shape, a form on matter.
Matter is just stuff lying there.
It doesn't have in it something that you could bring out.
There's no place for this expressive poesis, nurturing, cultivating, letting come forth.
My favorite way of understanding it is to ask yourself at each stage, what's the most perfect kind of entity in the world?
I gave you a list of good ones for the Greeks.
And there's these people who all love Athens, for Aeschylus.
But now, what's the perfect picture of just a, well, a kind of caricature, but I think it'll help you understand this.
I think you could say that their model of production, which has got to do with this business of dominating and ordering, is imposing form on matter.
I'll give you lots of similes that say that.
And the model for that is bricks.
I think if you, the bricks are just fine because there's just this mud.
It has no innate structure to bring out, like craftsmen bring out the cabinet in the wood or they bring out the sculptor, the statue in the marble.
There's nothing to bring out in mud.
It's, if anything, their mud is sort of recalcitrant to any form.
Not rebellious, but at least not any help.
And therefore, you impose the form on it.
You make it into bricks.
And what do you do with bricks?
Well, there's nothing intrinsically to do with bricks.
If you could build roads, as you know, the Romans built roads all over the known world and aqueducts.
Some of them are still around.
They're so well built.
So you build and monuments with your bricks.
And all of this is a way of getting, of producing something by imposing an order on what in itself doesn't have any order.
I mean, that's very important.
It's not an expressive order.
There's nothing to express.
It's more like a repressive order, except that its way of governing is somehow to get the unruly matter, which is, again, not really so much rebellious, it's just sort of, as I say, recalcitrant, it just hasn't got any form, to shape it up.
And the best statement of that I know, and I was going to save it till later, but I think I'll read it now, is on page six, because you ought to be able to see this in the gods.
And maybe I'll just skip to the gods.
Why not?
Just a second.
Let me see if that's a good idea.
Well, with one transition, but never mind page six.
Page three, because I'm going to talk in a minute about Zeus and Poseidon, and I don't want to read about them yet.
But here's a god that we don't hear much about in Homer that has a big job of imposing form on somewhat crazy, disorganized matter.
And that's the job of King Aeolis at the middle of page three.
The enormous cave, King Aeolus, in his enormous cave, King Aeolis restrains the wrestling winds.
Restrains is a good word, not represses.
It's hard to find a right word.
I decided that the right word would be tames.
If you started with nourishing or cultivating, I thought about that as Aeschylus is feeling, then you need something that's not like that, but which is not repression either.
And taming is, I think, just the right word.
I don't know why I didn't ever write it into my notes here.
It just came to me in the middle of the night, and I didn't have a pen.
Okay, so, and now you can see how what happens is, notice the next word in a minute.
He restrains the wrestling winds, loud hurricanes, he tames and sways them with chains and prison.
I mean, it's really sort of odd.
It's on the verge of repression all the time.
But you don't think when you tame something that you're repressing it, but you're sort of keeping it from doing what it wants to do and making it do and produce what you want.
And that's what's happening here.
He tames and sways them with his chains and prison.
They rage in indignation at their cages.
The mountain answers with a mighty roar.
Lord Aeolus sits in his high citadel.
He holds his scepter.
He soothes their souls.
You see, they're getting all upset.
And his job, when you tame them, isn't like nurturing them and cultivating them.
He soothes their souls and calms their madness.
Taming and calming, you'll see over and over in the metaphors, is what the what Virgil, and thereby speaking for all the Romans without knowing it, admires.
And let's read again.
But fearing that the all-evil father, fearing that, namely that they would get wild, the all-able father hid the winds within dark caverns, heaping over them high mountains.
They're close to repression.
And he assigned to them a king who should, by Jove's surely, understand just when to jail, when to command, when to set free, and so forth.
So you just have to keep thinking tames.
I mean, and taming is a way of imposing form on matter.
If you keep that in mind, and thereby producing something stable, productive, I mean, somehow useful.
I take it the winds are, when they get them under control right, do a good job of pushing the boats along.
Okay, now I think I'm ready to see here.
Another thing I've got here is channeling things.
That seems to be another way of thought, like chaining, only in this case, taming.
You tame the winds, you channel the winds, and you govern them, you dominate them.
Now, I'm going to talk now about the gods, where this is all clearer.
So let's just go through the gods.
Okay, Jupiter, that is Zeus, has now become Jupiter.
You all got copies of this thing that I handed out, which tells you that names of all these many names for Aeneas and many names for.
Would somebody come and help me pass?
How many need these?
Okay, wow.
It's on the website here.
I've got lots of them.
It's got on one side how to write a paper, but on the other side, it's got all the names for Troy, all the names for Rome, all the names for gods.
So I'm going to go on talking.
So we're looking at Jupiter now.
And he is taken over from Zeus.
But he's only taken over from Zeus in the sense that he has the position Zeus has.
He's the head god.
But his job is totally different, as you'd expect, since the gods are going to be expressive of the understanding of being.
He's going to have a different job.
Zeus's job was protecting strangers, going between worlds, a fascinating job, one that doesn't seem very important to us, but seems very important to the Greeks of Homeric time, given their polytheism and all the worlds that they want to visit and understand.
So Jupiter is the king and the father.
His specific job is commanding and governing.
That means controlling whatever would tend to get out of control, and that's again taming and so forth.
Just the middle of nine, who's talking?
I don't know.
Oh, Venus, her bright eyes brimmed and tearful, speaks to Aeneas.
Okay.
Oh, you who with eternal rule, no, to Jupiter.
Oh, you who with eternal rule command and govern the events.
That's where I get these words I want.
Govern the events.
And you can see that Aolus was governing the winds.
Govern the events of gods and men and terrify them with your thunderbolt.
With great offense has made Odysseus and so forth and so forth.
Now, it's really interesting.
The thunderbolt comes from the Greeks, of course, from the Homeric Greeks, but they thought, I take it, that it was overwhelming and exciting.
I mean, if you've ever been in a thunderstorm, which you poor people haven't, if you've come and been raised in California, or not a real thunderstorm, like in the Middle West where I come from, but if you've been in a real super thunderstorm, it's wonderful, it's awesome, it's just terrific.
But I don't think that's what they think.
They just think the thunderstorms are terrifying.
And where is it for Zeus having a thunderbolt is to do something really fusus-like, something overwhelming.
I think I don't know why Jupiter has a thunderbolt, because it doesn't have anything to do with his job as governing.
It's just something sort of dragged in, it seems to me, from the Greeks, and their reaction is not awe, but terror, which means they're just, they think it's frightening, all this storm going on.
And the Romans are going to be, skipping down about ten lines, born and from the blood of Choicer, rise up as rulers over sea and land.
That's the governing again.
That's the imposing order on things.
That's going to be, that's one of their job descriptions: to organize, tame, govern all everything so that it becomes peaceful and stable and productive.
I think that's their idea.
If you ask them, what do you want out of life, they would say something like that.
And Jupiter's not sort of behind everything in an ontological way, like in Aeschylus.
It looks like Zeus is behind everything.
It looks like he's a specific entity or being, namely, like a king, and he commands and governs.
That's a specific way of being behind everything, is you govern and control everything.
And he governs the cosmos.
That's what we just saw.
He calms and orders things that get out of control.
Look on page 10, the beginning of that long paragraph.
But then he smiled upon her.
Jupiter, father of men and gods, just as he calms the heavens and the storms, and so forth.
And he's constantly doing that.
You can see another one away on 158, which you will never have in your assignments, but I can just skip to it, because it's got taming in it again.
Whenever you see taming in it, mark it in your text and light up, because I think the fundamental feel for being and what people's job, what a job description for human beings and even for gods is, comes out whenever he says taming.
At the bottom of 158, about 10 lines from the bottom.
For other people, we'll no doubt, who's talking here?
I don't know.
Somebody explaining the future of Rome.
They go back to the beginning of the quotes.
Who is he?
At the bottom of 153, no?
And when he saw Aeneas cross the meadow, he stretched out his hands.
Who sees Aeneas?
I'm on page 153, trying to find out.
Anchises, okay, his father.
This is Aeneas' father talking, I believe, at the bottom of 158.
I'm going to write it down.
If it turns out to be wrong, tell me.
So, Aeneas' father says about 10 lines from the bottom: for other people will, I do not doubt, still cast their bronze to breathe with softer features, that is, make beautiful bronze statues, draw out the marble living, out of the marble living lines, make beautiful marble statues, plead causes better, trace the ways of the heaven, and tell the rising constellations.
I mean, do astronomy.
It's the Greeks.
That's this sort of inferiority complex.
It's saying, in effect, other people can do what the Greeks did.
But yours will be, and now comes their thing, the rulership of nations.
Remember, Roman, these will be your arts, to teach the people the ways of peace to those you conquer, to spare defeated people, tame the proud.
And that's the same, the story again.
So I think, and you could say, I'm just saying in many, many ways, order is absolute.
Everything makes sense in terms of how you set up and maintain order.
You can see that that would be a job for the citizens of a country that did set up and maintain order for a thousand years.
And a terribly, terribly stable, administratively organized country.
It always strikes me that in some ways they're like us, if it helps you understand it any.
But in some ways, in this way, they're like China.
China is this big, administrative, stable entity that lasted a thousand years.
I don't know, I don't think they had an understanding of being.
But not being Chinese and knowing their great texts, I don't know.
It isn't, not every country or culture has, in fact, not every country has one, you know, privileged understanding of being, that is, everything at its best or serves something or other.
But in fact, according to Heidegger, ours is the only culture, for better or for worse, and finally he thinks it's for worse, has a unified understanding of being forming.
We're watching it form, until it gets just one story about what it's all about.
And I doubt if the Chinese have it.
Certainly the Japanese don't have it.
It's easier to see in Japan that it's polytheistic.
I don't know enough about Chinese.
If anybody knows about the Chinese and how they relate to this, come and talk to me about it.
I'd love to know.
But here, order is absolute.
Everything makes sense in terms of setting up and maintaining order.
And if you ask, then why is order so important?
Well, partly, I think, that it hasn't been evident from these passages to produce things.
You need order.
That's where the B's come in.
But partly, I think the answer is order is just a good thing for its own sake.
That's what it is when you hit rock bottom.
You hit the understanding of being.
Aeschylus can't tell you why being an expressive order that lets things come out and nourishes them is what everybody should be doing and what the country should be doing.
That seems so obvious they don't even see it as a question.
And so, but so, but that's how it is.
And now, okay, so much for Zoom.
Now, Neptune, back to page six, where I started and then I decided not to read it.
Now, Neptune is the brother of Zeus.
And, of course, you've got to keep this in mind to see the striking difference and how illuminating it is.
Neptune was one of the most disruptive gods, the gods of the storms whooshing up, of nature, overwhelming and out of control.
Well, you take over, that was Poseidon.
I said Neptune.
Poseidon was that in Homer.
Neptune, which has the job Poseidon has, of being the god of the sea, what do you expect?
Well, have you been following him?
What do you think Poseidon's job is as god of the sea?
To stir up storms?
Hmm?
You think so?
Yeah.
What?
Yes, to calm the storms.
His job is just the opposite.
It's like almost like a joke.
Neptune is running around in a little carriage with a trident on wheels.
It's sort of a little like Disneyland.
But where was he?
What is this?
It's where he's got his little cart.
Neptune, I don't know.
It's not there.
Maybe it'll show up.
Anyway, what I want to read isn't that.
On 6th line 2007, 207.
He stills the sea and guides along the waters on light wheels.
Oh, there he is, running around with his chariot on the waters, leveling it into calm.
And just as often when a crowd of people is rocked, and now here's another version of it.
Pay attention to the simile.
Like when a crowd of people is rocked by a rebellion and the rabble rage in their minds, and firebrands and stones fly fast, for fury finds its weapons, if by chance they see a man remarkable for righteousness and service, piety, duty, they are silent and stand attentively, and he controls their passions by his words and cools their spirit so that all the clamor of the sea subsides.
So you get a double story there.
Just as Neptune calms the sea, so the great statesman calms the crowd, and it's always the same story.
They're sort of disordered and recalcitrant and unruly, and somebody comes along and puts, calms them down, tames them, governs them, orders them.
And that's what...
And both, so Poseidon and Zeus have become people in charge, or gods in charge of ordering.
And now, Venus is another funny one.
This is the last one I'm going to talk about.
The same switch.
Venus, if we can, is Aphrodite, remember.
And Aphrodite is the goddess of mad passion, of something so overwhelming that it can make Helen leave home and abandon her Menelaus and her son and so forth.
Now, Venus, just like every other one, what would you expect?
Is Venus going to be the goddess of mad passion?
You can already see it starting to happen in Aespylus.
Remember, what's Venus' job there?
The sweetness of married love.
That's already a big step out of Homeric Greece into Poasis.
But Venus gets even more, and you could say literally, domesticated by the next one around, where she's just the goddess of domesticity, of the family, calm and and serene, presumably.
So here comes Venus.
To begin with, though, all of this very interesting stuff happening on 47.
How would you think that the Virgil would feel about Helen?
Do you think he would think she was peerless among women because she managed to run off when the overwhelming overwhelmed her?
No.
He thinks she's awful.
She's terrible.
She's caused all this disaster.
At the middle of 47, about eight lines into the new paragraph, for she in the terror of the Trojans set against her for the fall of Pergamos, which is Troy, and the Danans, which are the Greeks, vengeance and anger that she, Helen, is afraid of all this.
And the anger of her abandoned husband, stop a minute.
According to Homer, was her husband angry?
That's the weird passage that I come back to again and again.
He said that it was a great story how she left him for ten years.
And then when they're in bed together, Homer says the lying beside him was Helen peerless among women.
Well, you wouldn't know it here.
She, the common fury of Troy and of her homeland, she had hid herself crouching, a hated thing, beside the altars.
And his soul, skipped to the bottom, was filled with vengeful fire.
So Aeneas is now getting out of control and mad at Helen for having gotten out of control.
And so it goes on.
And carried off at the bottom of 47 by my mad mind, I was still blurting out these words when, with such brightness as if I had never seen my gracious mother, that's Aphrodite, Venus, stood there before me, and across the night she gleamed with pure light, unmistaken goddess, as lovely and as tall, and so forth and so forth.
And she caught his right hand fast and spoke these words.
This is based on the Iliad where Achilles is losing his temper.
I mean, the beginning of the Iliad, I've said this before, the very beginning is about the wrath of Achilles.
Achilles is losing his temper and about to kill Agamemnon.
And Athena comes up behind him and grabs him by his ponytail, by his long hair, and keeps him from doing it because it's not the appropriate thing to do in a situation, kill the commander of the troops.
So here, she grabs his hand and spoke these words: My son, what bitterness has kindled this frantic anger?
Why this madness?
Why all this care?
What of all you care for me?
Where has it gone?
Should you not first seek out your father, worn with years, and Chises, where you left him?
See if your wife, Crusea, and the boy, and Chises are still alive.
Go take care of your family, in effect, she says.
And that's what's become of the, it's turned completely the opposite.
Whereas mad love was disrupting the family, and then it got to be at least still sort of erotic and between a man and a wife, the sweetness between man and a wife.
Now it's got, as I say, domesticated.
Venus of all things is the god of a stable family.
But that's all, of course, what you'd expect.
I'm skipping to catch up with myself here.
Then why don't you all think of some question or objection while I'm reading this?
Yeah, I'm just saying how strange it is that Aphrodite, of all people, as Venus, should show up in the role of calming emotions and getting them under control.
There is somebody whose job is that, Athena.
It's not that the Homeric Greeks don't think you should calm your emotions under the appropriate, you shouldn't go crazy if the situation isn't appropriate.
And she calms, but it's not, it's never Aphrodite's job.
It's okay, that's fine.
Now, does anybody have anything to say?
Good.
I'm tired of talking by myself, yes?
Helen and the photos are even more wrong.
Is that what you mean?
But she's, well, because she's protecting Helen, you mean?
Oh, yeah, that's fine.
That she should protect Helen isn't what bothers me.
It's that she should be the one to calm Aeneas.
I see what you mean, though.
If her job is protecting Helen, it's just she'll have to calm Aeneas.
It's not her main business.
Well, that's good.
Let me think about that.
So she's her, of course, that doesn't give her any job except a kind of story job.
Her job is protecting Aeneas.
I'm trying to see if I could figure out what sort of force she represents.
And the force she represents, when we could tell when it's Aphrodite, is mad love.
And it seems to me that maybe I'm agreeing, I'm agreeing with you.
There isn't any force she represents.
It's just because it happens to be that she's the mother of Aeneas, right?
Is that how she's related to him?
And naturally, she wants to why doesn't she just let him beat up on Helen and then go home?
But she's the mother of Helen.
I see.
Okay.
Venus, Aphrodite protects Helen, so it's natural that she's going to stop Aeneas.
Okay, Beatrice.
She says, well, heart, you should do your duty.
Yeah, does she say it in words, or are you just saying that's what it comes to?
Yeah, do your duty as a as a father.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, that's right.
That's true.
She's being given this sort of Roman twist.
She's come up to tell him what to do.
And what he's supposed to do is go do his duty.
That is, take care of his father, his wife, and his kids.
That's fine.
That's, in fact, exactly the transition to what I want to talk about next.
So, but I would love to hear from, I mean, I'm happy to hear from my TAs and I learn from them.
But I also like to hear from you people and learn from you.
Yeah.
And I thought that it wasn't particularly clear that it wasn't long, but she did.
Because first the story of his tells is mostly about Odysseus.
And then she says, and she says now, well, um, the next story is because I had already realized that it was the 90 was built.
And I thought that part of what you're talking about, or she's not a story about a gaze, that's what they were talking about.
And then also part of what he's done in Peter Bennett, then she realized that you should go back to her husband.
Well, that's all very good.
Can you hear him?
All of you that, I mean, maybe I'm getting too putting too much weight on this passage or misreading it.
Mostly Helen talks at this dinner party about Odysseus, and she does say how she now wishes and regrets that she ran off and wishes she would go home, could go home.
And I'm trying to put on that this claim, well, wild love, you know, calms down and gets boring, and Paris has gotten annoying and boring, running off to bed from the fighting all the time.
But when Agamemnon says that's an admirable story, it could mean either or both, a good story about Odysseus, and a good story that you finally got tired of running off with him and came back to me.
All I can do is, if it were only for that, I'd be in more trouble than at the end of the chapter, the last sentence practically is that Helen is peerless among women.
You have to read that your way as saying, well, she's not peerless because she ran off with Paris, she's peerless because she finally saw that that was a mistake and came back.
And I guess I want to say, no, I think it's because she's really open to all any kind of move.
And I don't know how to settle it.
There are some lines that seem to settle it, by the way, and I think I should bring them in next time.
Nobody noticed them and complained, or did I mention them in lecture?
There's about eight lines where Homer talks about how bad Helen is and how much disaster she's called, and what a, I forget a, isn't a whore, but it's a word like that, she was.
And do you remember that?
And it's late in the book, and I came across that and I thought, my goodness, my whole story about Helen is just wrong.
Homer does not think she's careless among women.
And I called up my student, Sean Kelly, who reads Greek, and asked him what's going on.
And we looked at the Greek, and I hadn't paid attention to a footnote which says these eight lines are obviously an interpolation, and since sometime by 200 BC, they've been considered not Homer.
And that's pretty amazing.
I can tell you where they are next time if I remember.
So there's nothing in Homer, I think, that treats her as a bad woman.
But you're not saying that there is.
The question is whether there's anything in Homer that treats her running off as admirable.
And I claim that it does, but I must admit that that's pretty strange and maybe wrong.
So nobody thinks it's condemnable, I think.
But those lines are interpolated for sure.
But being swept away as a super virtue that trumps everything, that's maybe, whether that's Homer or Dryfus, I can't promise to say.
You look like you want to say more.
Homer says that she looks very much bigger than people.
No, you're right.
That's right.
He's absolutely right.
I mean, I'm putting a spin on it.
It's the last of that chapter.
But that chapter isn't about her running off and her speech and her saying that she regrets it and came back.
That chapter is about all sorts of things.
And peerless among women might just be she's the most beautiful woman in the world, which is what everybody's supposed to have already agreed to.
Peeralist means you have no equal.
Could mean she has nobody equally beautiful.
So I would be so unhappy.
I love my interpretation of it as showing how far out a completely fruitless culture could get of being open to whatever grabs you.
But I must say, I have to put a lot of weight on it, and I don't know what to think.
But I worry about it.
And anybody who can help me, or either way, help me out of my misery, either show me that I have to just give this up, or show me that I can keep it.
But I'm sort of always torn back and forth.
Yeah.
No.
Well, I see.
Well, I think I understand what you're saying.
I don't want to say, it sounds much too Protestant or whether that's pure tanner or something to say you mean that we're going to condemn her as immoral or so for this.
Yeah, that doesn't seem right either.
There's nothing in the book that suggests that.
But this is becoming, it's so contrasted with this.
This is such a kind of Puritan outrage, that this woman who would do this and cause a whole war and leave her husband and so forth.
It's not certainly that.
Otherwise, Agamemnon wouldn't take her back.
I suppose I should at least put that down on the table as something I want to defend.
I mean, why couldn't he just say, well, you left me and the kid for ten years and now you come back to me after this war, you should be enslaved by the, by not, you know, queen on my island.
So there's something about the fact that at least he accepts that giving in to this wild emotion and running off is not so bad that you couldn't forgive her for it, particularly if she regrets it.
We agree about that, probably.
But you're saying, okay, but he's not saying you're a whore, you're a prostitute, you're just a disgusting, immoral person.
I wouldn't have you in my house and bed again, ever.
He's certainly not saying that.
She's the hostess at his dinner party, and everybody respects her.
So let me just keep repeating it.
I mean, there's nothing intrinsically wrong with just running off from your husband and kid.
That seems clear.
How to go on from there is less.
You want to say more?
What happened to her, you mean?
It's like getting sick.
Yeah, but that would be a middle ground that she was swept away.
But you don't get blamed for being swept away.
I think that's sure.
So we better keep what's sure.
I try to push it to say not only you don't get blamed, but you actually get admired for being swept away.
That's pushing it, and as he says, but surely it's, and I see, I don't want to say it's like a disease because that gets it too much into the Dido story.
I mean, Dido's love, I don't know what Beatrice is going to do with it, I'm eager to hear.
But Dido's love is described as a disease, and she can't help it, and we feel sorry about it.
But that isn't how you feel in Helen, that she was sick when she ran off at Paris.
That isn't quite right either.
So it's all fascinating.
And anybody, people should come and talk to me in office hours about anything, but particularly about this, because I'm writing a paper with this guy, Sean, that I mention every once in a while on this very subject, which begins with the dinner party and what happens, how to understand what happened with Helen and Aphrodite.
So anybody who's found any passages or had any ideas, I would love to hear them.
Yeah, Beatrice.
As same as what I do?
Ah, I see.
What page are you on?
That's in.
That's it.
That's interesting.
What page are you on?
What?
What page?
Okay, that's in.
Go ahead Victor Queen and find her husband.
That's very interesting.
That's very important.
You see, there are always more relevant passages.
So he reads the Homeric Greek story, the Homer story, in a way the way I do.
The cheat can, in spite of having done this, those stupid Greeks, in a way, will take her back as a victor queen in triumph because they won the war, presumably, among other things, and she'll live happily ever after.
And he thinks he'd better kill her because that would be disgusting from there, from his point of view.
Now, that's good.
I've got to write that down.
Okay, I think, yeah, I can stop now and write it down.
And next time, be sure and read book four, because that's what Beatrice is going to talk about the whole time.
Next time.