People keep talking on their minds that I give them to why does this work of why why have a work of art that it articulates and holds up to the culture if they've all got into their bodies anyway?
Well, because the work of art makes it more articulated, more glamorized, why that's how people got that's not probably quite right or for.
But if you have to sort of if it's not you wouldn't have to preserve, we cultivate, there wouldn't be any reason why you didn't preserve it.
But since it is just the practice of people culture, if there isn't something that holds up glamorizing the colours development department, Greek students love to be normally Greece, but yet he is far as we glamorize the owner.
It's just a way that for them, all of his life was final for us.
It was something that they decided to simply all with Jews to figure out what to do, to understand what was excellent, so that they had a kind of model of what excellent wise was.
Servants, you'll see there's a perfect model serving in there, and a model wife, that would be modern model father.
There's a model of every particular role because that policy of active policy would have been all of it yet.
So that's why it's not enough world.
So so let's go on.
Today I'll talk about why we call it.
Let's go on into what role the gods have.
So, roughly these were the listeners.
But this this falls of a harbor, as it's called, or the the internet is called the the gods who's pointed in the book.
But then if people think it's Homer putting himself into his own story, if there's this one person who was home, he just nobody can tell us the story.
It's a story but the perfect picture of what what is going on that is going on several hundred years, then another maybe uh six hundred was the time of Esther.
But even then, they were still appealing to Homer and knew it most everybody knew large parts of the gods and the other part and they appealed to it to settle moral or legal or diplomatic dispute and hold it really achieved.
So that's because again this glorifies unified picture of what they were once upon a time up to and still wanted to produce in the Homer does it or what does their policy Homer makes up this story.
I mean apparently it wasn't all people finally interested that were deep force got this kind of goddesses called the Furies, who were the goddess of the dentist.
And Homer just ruled them out.
He just to make up this story towards only the home to go build.
You'll see in that book you read, if the Furies really are terribly upset to take that rule.
And they're making a lot of trouble because it wasn't it wasn't uh what Homer prophetic say why?
Well, a view of a few are kind of rel polytheistic religion well of which it's a number of certain ways of thinking there are gods of God's state that nonetheless have a family resemblance and complicated relationship that Palmer's worked out.
Or well invented somewhere.
He focused on things to make not only do we part of a whole heresy that we thought the whole way to live.
And so part of the moral of the course I participated on it look us away is well they knew something to us.
Of course we know a lot more.
Not why they know this, but what it is to be a people.
They knew some things that we know a lot more or what it is a lot more.
Some stuff that we know more.
Things alter the case that they knew a lot more than we did.
Well it is a factor's fact that might be a good idea.
If that no delivers Movie lift.
That's why we will both the gods of old and if they did mostly do but the idea that there's something that Palmer see that we lost touch with is something that I don't know how any books have said this.
If you do let me know that that's what I think was that's what I think.
So why not?
Well because Palmer's got something that we have lost that if we had it we could get it all.
And of course if you're reading Homer at the Great Book, you'll miss that.
Because you think, well, it's an attempt to talk about remember the story of books being booked.
If we sort of as if literature and Black Einstein's, we know a lot more about electronics and about Lord than the Homer people.
Palmer misses a lot.
All of his resolves is just one whoa.
Uh, okay, uh, all of it.
So here's an authority on Greek culture at Oxford, I think, or maybe Cambridge anyway, about fifty years ago, saying that by all is given guess, uh, we believe that a man's justice is from throwing the situation to his own will, through his own power.
Remember all this about giving commonism.
To choose what to do and then do it on your own, that's by your will.
So each of them wants to explain the source of an incidental strength.
He has no force but to say that the responsibility lies with the gods.
The same is true in other cases.
Whenever a man composes or pronounces more than his previous attitude has led others to expect, Palmer connects this insofar as he tries to supply an explanation with the interference, with the interference of the gods.
He should be noted, especially that Almer does not know the other personal decisions.
Even where he always goes and pondering to alternatives, the intervention of the gods plays the key role.
Well, one, it's just plain wrong.
When we get to a place where Ogistus has to constitute it all by himself, he says, why weren't you encompassing it?
He had to figure it out himself.
So this is just wrong.
Whether this is what what happens with the limitists is that he isn't able to act on his own will.
It's just the whole interest will.
That the whole thing of what you need to do is do and why he doesn't do it is doing this and is not the case and we'll reflect.
And then having the data is there, Paul says things wrong.
Palmer has known liver effect.
He has a much more interesting.
But we'll we have to wait till we get to surrender this and it's hard to hear.
I know it must why would that be when I broke down this last year and I looked up it's not, you know, I just told that last time.
I could help that look up.
But right.
I said, oh well, okay, so the good both people can try to tell us kind of we're autonomous self-directed agents responsible for what we do and so forth.
Palmer has to go from the point of view we don't declare.
Uh because we all sort of lost faith in Christ.
And we're no longer so convinced that we're unified.
I think all the discoveries that are postmodernist non-spel put himself.
We're still thinking that he must have to do our one say Friday.
So I these people want more things anyway they say good good book and they say you've got a lot of clarity, wisdom, he appreciates curiosity, that all that sort of it's like he was a kind of funny life.
But according to the question is saying, what is it that uh Palmer speaks wrong?
Well to begin with, we've got there's a different understanding of the plurality of times of good.
Uh that you'll see when you read it, that God is so God has something which is that they're very good at the guidance of gold times or seeing it and so forth.
The other guy has always the rational, theoretical ones and the clarity.
Palmer doesn't feel any need to rank them or to tell you which of these literatures are really good good and which ones you know are somehow dangerous or viewers.
This is part of the way that the good one gets the plurality of goods all together under one good.
Watch them all.
It will tell you all of these things.
So that's one of the parts: to figure out what the really good is and then subordinate to them.
So we want to know too what aspects of human life that we neglect to don't think is important to express a richer and more diverse world.
Again, I can sort of spin it now.
So if you get one of those things, things always want a margin of our experience, I mean, up or that we don't pay much attention to, is the force of mood.
There was a reader that is what you read.
These people are artists that left off that list because they're feeling that's a wrong.
This is a false world dog.
He is good at going from world to world.
This is the virgin spot of life and cleverly getting stuff out of every time.
And work of artist folks is what this part is doing was times when they were worked of art, were works of art.
Philosophers think we focused the whole culture with life.
So there were works of art.
One, after these likeness areas, or works of art.
I think moreover, there's nobody once, and this may be coming back what we said.
We want to read this a world.
And we want to read this book and both because it's fo one reason because it's focused in the world.
Happens to be two things different.
One is that we're watching how it focus is a world with a lover and so forth.
So with how it's doing its work of art work, which is the work of art work of the art.
And then what is it we're doing?
It is we're looking at that particular world that Homer is poems that start talking about and living or how important these things are.
So we're looking at we're looking at the function of folks in the world and we're looking at students of worlds that just focus this is the first of them.
Moves are just kind of like people.
He's still got a chance with the friends who come in and a move.
Because a movie is something that's not developing people like covers their whole world.
I think it's the whole world.
So Homer's got a strong chance to color the whole world.
And he's moved out of people that don't have to keep that straight exactly.
Our great poets and artists will be thinking the part he is good.
Melanio is a good poet and thinker.
And he has that.
That's why he's waiting for the young son.
There's some way in which the enlightenment is, you know, you've got to experience your world.
It's like home.
Makes it remarkable in our world, but with this world that senses like moves.
And what a difference that would make to come to life if you understood that.
Uh live like that.
I guess Laura said we have to read this book first.
But um point the lenses.
We have all sorts of very well have sort of been put in medieval but there's simply with the word it's, don't know several different words, worlds.
There's the world of sort of early Christian gifts, the window of that.
Then there's the world of medieval Christian, maybe the world of early kind of world.
It was getting worse to God or uh milk and flaws.
We won't predict the course that works well, but well, yeah, hold up to account what the idea of these possibilities to put in all you know, I think he really thinks he was so radical that he just made up all identities.
And one of the one who said the cancer that said, What is going to work on something or other?
Kill any parts, take along, and work the bars for all this.
And legitimately, he's supposed to look afford and find bones confidential, which it looks like they're different to us.
Which one is there?
And if there's a reason that is so radical that nobody can understand what they're up to, including things, one of the things I've started putting under system is up to focus is there on fixed one.
It takes a palmer, it takes a bit of far fit, which is if people think that you know, it's supposed to be the ball, the young war, the prime, but you don't necessarily work that poverty is the alias.
The eyes are all taking various sides, but it's not clear because sort of the implications of the illias, let's suppose this is sort of disclosed, then they work at which one of the favors of these, why, so anyway, there's trust for him against the world as well, and they've also that it who comes along after the world in nature.
I mean, okay, that's you know, of course, but it's it's not off the course, it's been um words.
Oh, well, okay, now that God's back for people, how different they are.
You feel more at all in all of his world than in the world of the medieval Christians.
They like us appreciate beautiful, well-made weatherness, they speak with honesty, they loyalty, and they have these wonderful dinner parties, and then they they they're also very interesting where they uh uh tell us opium in there.
They get a joke.
They come into their voice and they get their hotels and they all act out terrible and then of course we've got our our uh phones.
Well, we've got our doctors by Bolax Johan, who in the 70s anyway, so it certainly told us what what we were up to and what the move was and so forth.
And maybe somebody's doing it now, maybe talking about some poets who pulled up for us the sort of wind-up for us what's going on.
It also might be all sorts of scary things.
Uh, but now we can't do this.
But then come to the side of the gods, the drunk being seen so uncommon.
They weren't just decorated, they took them very seriously.
They weren't living on the Olympus in the sense that you find up Olympus and they do strange things.
Once you get into the goddamn state of the home, we see very strange gods impersonate other people, they just hide themselves, they fight with each other.
I mean, angels, for instance, don't go and impersonate people.
Or, or at very rarely that's what maybe it is already in the total of these stuff.
It's of this topic, but most readings, all of which the cobbler has got.
So it's very hard to see how a bunch of people so much like us about this area of their lives, so far from having the past, they see things in a way that we don't, that the gods.
Okay, well, one more thing, which you're going to hear a lot about.
We think about what people believe, we think about their willpower, we think about their desire.
Oh, wow, that's going to be something people start to find by this design.
That certainly is not, well, I'll come back to that.
So when people write about the Greeks again, they say they try to, Homer is a college, but what Homer thought was going on.
Homer has designed his god in a book called Greeks in the Around.
He says we have surveyed the common trip to try this again for them and often resolve that in all the parties of normal human behavior whose causes are not a reason for feeling, whether by the subject's own consciousness, they wouldn't attract individuals, and they wouldn't have understood, I think, if you thought about their own consciousness.
Whether because they thought, I think, that they were open head towards the world, which is what we always see, that's why we get back to touch with this.
It isn't going, well, what's going on in here isn't going on the side of your head.
It must get away of your being open to the world and open to what is by the stresses of describing these psychic states.
He says, American steps.
Well, people in Born now are stepped forward.
What's those who think about the ideas we have?
But he said that women also have to head with grass degrees.
They're not eliminated from their national evidence.
The links were born on a primitive path.
Well, that's a long way to look.
It's not as good.
If the gods are that odds are doing something else, so now it's time to figure out what that is.
But first, dealing with worlds, the medieval world, or the world of the war world.
That it's not innovative.
Helen reads the her husband her newborn child and runs off with her but welcome born.
That's nobody.
Nobody's going to it's it's ontology, it's not psychology.
Nobody's going to watch this dream of it.
He thought going off in Paris.
It wasn't like that at all.
The only thing was that the ride watches the war and I was that is what that what needed to be done at that point.
So I want to just give you a hint that it's you're going to be will be not a psychology however, but this uh world.
So I have a bunch of questions to get to philanthropy.
Uh so let's go to talking about philanthropy.
Because the things I've been telling you will get a lot more the way I'm trying to read it will get a lot more time to give it up like that and the rest of you before I talk about that.
So really what first time before we talked about science and getting science back if it also wants to mark it up so when you lose you do, listen to the class and we have to look for it.
Yeah, but anyway, once this is a first time through, we just work for war.
So you don't have to read any more yet.
I don't think let me look at lectures through it.
Well, to begin with, let's see what the length is ignoring, we know that because he was born just before Odysseus went to the war about Croat and gets into techniques getting home.
So roughly, he's going all in line with his father, Dawn, with his father.
But draw out his kind of the pet of the of the students.
He's a king, sort of looking athletic, old enough.
He's there the first sort of psychological story that he could say.
Well, he's there.
He's daydreaming and sorry for himself.
And he's in teaches that what happened.
Okay, that's a little what happened if he draw any of those feed issues going on.
So what's going to happen to him?
He's going to go from being non-income and finally feeling sorry for the dump.
He's going to go to see how Homer describes.
So I think that's the sort of remember the page says, oh, did we get to put more spurs into the subject?
How could you follow up on the strand?
Hurry business away.
I'll just say it's plenty of time, which I will agree.
Anybody really don't know about this.
What I do is I look at all the other samples until I find one that says more what I think only for the state.
And that algorithm has the news.
Nothing like birds.
He's turned up.
I know that it's my home over my life is fairly walking.
So they would have some fun with these owners that I switched.
Also, just because it says, long before anyone else for Prince Telemetus now last night has been there, or he's who was sitting there unhappy among his food and a boy.
It's important that he's a boy.
And he's never had a father and he's never had to face any problems.
He's thinking, what if his grandfather came from the unknown world and drove him on his lordship because he didn't know it was a beast.
He thought he was making a mentor himself.
Psychologically goes up against the fact that he has over and used it.
That's all about sort of his votes, his will, his beliefs, so forth.
But that's not what happens.
So mentally sound up, mentally all things for the best psychology of him.
Telematus gets the idea, or even an idea of the right word, so he changes the world with him and moves over his role of the travel.
He says, or mentors that if I would take steps to make these mentors first, let's say, Paul for a temple and speak your will, and all the dogs to witness.
The tutors must go straight to their home.
And Methodist goes on to the bottom and says, You need not bear this inference of theirs.
You're a silent no longer to prove the line or something.
But God's power is going to be the transform telemetry from a silent to a mental.
It's not about his inner.
He's going to sing the whole world differently.
And that's the job of God.
He's going to sort of do this on the logical thing to him.
This mentor says, you need not bear this influence to theirs.
You are a title no longer.
Have you heard what Gloria John Orestes want?
I think in this part of the oriental young arrest is one of the title and his illustrious father.
He too, and many times have come with people.
What and when Paul tells you what happens?
If he tells you at the top of the leather, this is the telemetry says, you have just your kindness like a father to yourself.
Well, what really the people transform from a boy into a man.
But being a left hand is a third of the sentence on and on.
And he eats from his father what that phrase says, clearer.
So that he morrows to himself, defining that a god is getting his guest, then god-like in his, you know, when he says a godlike man, that he was a boy.
Oh, he was a boy, then he clearly, the what world is in, and what's important in that world.
His mother's domains and so forth, or anything like where we are.
What he used to see, but the meaningful distinctions of between, in this case, the honorable and dishonorable charge is attuned to what's going on.
What the Gods actually says is not a private psychological story.
It's an angle.
That the gods are our world, and people are in there in this world.
And the God's job is to atone people to the world that they are in.
It could be an erotic world, it could be an aggressive war world, it could be in this case, the world of us young kids who are taking over the kingdoms.
But he is now attuned to what's going on.
And he announces.
He just tells the Judas.
There was this, but then all of a sudden, he's no longer again.
He says, Go elsewhere, consume your own sword, burn, burn about, eat one another's houses, you can eat water, one another, and black dog, and pay nothing, and so forth.
And otherwise, you'll get what you deserve as water here.
Don't try that.
Forbid you to be seen there.
Though you are eligible as your father's son, it was at the end of that long paragraph.
So now these fees gives you all these are data to a god.
There is, oh yeah, the script is the one that says, and soon was dead.
Selemachus, no doubt, the gods themselves, if he forgave you to be sitting in messages, though you're eligible to survive stuff, I think we's struggle.
I think word is a transformed.
Psychology wasn't about being transformed.
This is the key going from being completely out of sync with the world of being.
To be totally interesting on top of his uh fully what I think they say he says seven four.
Why is he saying, Oh, yes.
So who did it?
We have this funny question.
Mentate did menace anything to win by coming in and giving him verifies, or is this really something only a god could do?
What some transform a world gets somebody to be go from being a title in the title's world?
Well, do who get it?
Well, I think the important thing to see is that Homer doesn't care who did it.
He isn't around and well, was it really the theme that I have to see?
They don't care, but mentally whether it was mentates or a theme doesn't matter.
What matters is that some bucket came up, some a godlike thing that transformed his world.
And I like it on seven four when uh Telemachus is complaining that Telemachus went to Center says run off with the bucket and go find out how to take back the island.
This is that the death depends what a goddamn who knows or his own heart uh sent him to learn a title if he thought alone.
So it doesn't matter.
What matters is that the whole I think part of the flying move the whole move what oh he's called moves nobody gets to be the boy.
Mentor tries to be a demon and when Mentor goes run the rest of himself uh world.
So Telemachus steps to Mentor's quietly different world.
And he new possibilities for him.
Paul's an assembly of the people.
And he's going to try to get them all together to throw out Cedars.
Now something clear.
A clear grasp of a new role.
He's a grown-up.
He's what God's plan to do.
The God function will not get him through.
But let's go figure first and he will completely transform the little tittle of the cottage.
But Paul stands out in the truth quickly to his feet.
A figure land is on him sternly grace and tells the telling I was all speed.
Old man made way for him as he took his father's father's place.
He's radiant and fintered and lying.
He's assumed with the situation of feeding.
What happens next with the land basically running off whether it was always full of surprise?
He tries to be wise.
He says, 5721, the whole thing fell out.
He has all the power of all things.
They turn face, and then he says, Friends, the lengthy Zeus, if the Holy Darkness, with old men, and so forth, make us into this.
And what happens when he tells it all?
He tells you something sort of psychological to him.
He tells you what he desires.
And nothing happens.
He doesn't in a world for him.
Uh they don't he just doesn't, he doesn't work.
He oh, I have to just leaves them old.
And what happens if he reverts to a boy?
He has a temperance into the bottom of that.
And I tend to have groups to upright his fears of when the temperature and so forth.
Uh what happened?
Well, interesting I think that a lot of the stories are here, it's a family negatives of Homer Artemis or something.
They've done their job, their job, their figure participates, is world principles.
You never have to fall world gods.
The first job is to follow his way, the orator, because he said the gods don't perform management.
And that Orestes has no skill as speakers to an assembly of older people, booming them, getting them in the right place to do what he wants them to do.
He's done with you.
God's substitute for having to have the relevance that is important and what you couldn't do otherwise, multiple of what you aren't normally able to do.
No, no, people don't become psychologically as a professor that was a great hitter.
He could see for homelands, then the rest of the hotel has helped him.
Well, that happens a lot in the other.
I mean, the gods don't think so to be something that politically strongly couldn't possibly be.
But it's been something that you know how unpsychological but the situation is.
That's not it going on inside when you older woman.
What happened?
And nobody can help it.
They can't do that.
So and these are our code masses of luck and so forth.