Okay, so the next thing is: I was trying, and this is closer to relevant now, this is about Moby Dick.
I've been thinking about the claim that moods are so important to Melville.
And I've given you examples now and then of Ishmael's moods and how he gets into every mood, from Ahab's mood to the only moods he doesn't get into is, say, Starbucks' mood, which is a Christian mood because he can't get in sync with anything monotheistic, but otherwise he can.
And I discovered a quote.
I mean, it doesn't seem to me much out of context, but I don't think it has much context.
And I think in a way, it means a lot.
On 475, at the beginning of the first paragraph, he talks about the moody Pequot.
The boat is moody.
They're all moody, in other words.
And he says, as this glad ship of good luck bore down upon the moody Pequad, there were sounds of drums.
This is the bachelor that's caught a lot of whales and everybody's in a very good mood.
And another one, he talks about the various moods of Ahab.
And on 118, the end of the middle paragraph, he says, and not only that, but moody, stricken Ahab stood before them with a crucifixion in his face and so forth and so forth.
So the Pequad is moody, Ahab is moody, and of course Ishmael is moody.
I've been saying that, but I found another quote that says that.
It was just another place where he shifts his mood in such a funny way.
He's worried about the Elijah's prediction.
Elijah's the prophet that sort of warns him he shouldn't go on this mission.
And he says, so he talks about ragged, about ten lines down, ragged Elijah's diabolical incoherencies uninvitedly recurred to me with a subtle energy I could not have before conceived of.
But poorly could I stand, could I withstand them, such as in other moods, I was almost ready to smile at the solemn whimsicality of that outlandish prophet.
Just typical of him to be in a mood right there of worrying about the prophecy of what's going to happen to them on the boat.
But he's in other situations, he finds them funny and he smiles at them.
And that's because he's in every conceivable mood at some point.
Yeah, I'm going to say something.
Okay, we're in now in chapter I wanna I don't wanna go back, but I'll we're in chapter 28.
And if you I'll try to say the chapter each time, but I don't really keep track of the chapters because there's about five different versions running around, and I just can't do more than how many finally have the this copy of it, the one I have.
Well, that's encouraging.
Are there still is there still anybody who hasn't found a copy?
I take it the bookstore did their job and every nobody, good, maybe a little late not to have a copy, I would despair for you.
But here we go.
Okay, so those are just mood things.
Now I'm going back to the main line of the lecture.
And I'm sort of picking up pieces, all of which I need, before I can really talk about the chase at the end, which is lucky for everybody, because I wonder how many have gotten to the end now.
Uh-huh, okay.
Well, I will do, it's up to you.
If you don't want to get, if you don't want to hear the ending, all you have to do is keep asking me questions.
And because I think I will get to the end if you don't, but I may not.
I've put in before getting to the end just because I figured I ought to be able to stall one more lecture that I think I may be able, just by filling in all the background things you need to know before you can really appreciate the whole end event.
Maybe we won't get to the end this time.
But this is definitely your last chance because I can't possibly not get to the end next time since I intend to finish the book next time.
Okay, but let's, I'm going to review reactions to perspectival whiteness, to the fact that all in in, in, that everything can have lots of interpretations, perspectives equal interpretations, and that when you add up all the interpretations, they don't add up to some right interpretation or better interpretation.
They just cancel each other out.
It's really interesting to me, and I'll probably come back to it next time, that Nietzsche, who is so close to Moby Dick, to Melville, isn't as radical in his talk about interpretations as Melville, though Nietzsche's writing a whole generation later.
I discovered in, I was looking for quotes, I'm going to give you a handout next time of about six quotes from Nietzsche, which are very, very close to Melville, but in each case, Melville gets it righter.
I like Nietzsche, but I must say, Melville's deeper.
But you'll see when I hand out a Nietzsche quote that for Nietzsche, the interpretations don't add up.
That would be really old-fashioned.
I mean, for Dante, the interpretations add up when you go around a house and you see more and more.
Then you finally get it right about the house, and that's obviously the right interpretation.
Ah, it's a house.
But then there's a middle view.
Nietzsche says everything is interpretations, but the more interpretations, the better, the more objectivity.
As if somehow the interpretations are all pointing in the same direction, anyway.
But it looks like, but what Melville sees is these interpretations point in opposite directions.
That's what we're going to talk about a lot today.
There are interpretations of Moby Dick, and the more you get, the less you have any unified picture of the meaning of Mobidech or the meaning of the universe, which are pretty much equated in the book.
Okay, so now I'm going to go through some of these interpretations.
But first, just perspectives on whiteness.
How do they deal with the fact that everything seems to be interpretation and they don't add up?
Well, one possibility is, and I haven't talked enough about this guy, so I'm going to spend a little time on Starbuck because he is the old-fashioned Christian response, but not bad because he's hypocritical or selfish, like Bildad.
And I never can remember the name of the other one.
What's this?
Oh, well, somebody knows.
The two guys that signed them up for the boat.
Peleg or something.
Yeah, Peleg and Bildad.
Anyway, they are really bad.
And they turn Twique against Christianity just observing how they're citing Bible passages while getting people as cheaply as possible to sign on.
But that's, we want to see a Christian at his best, so to speak.
And Starbuck is just that exactly.
And on 97, well, by the way, Father Mapple is a kind of radical Christian in this in his Kierkegaardian sense that there isn't any relation to God and you're swimming over water, but you can commit yourself to something anyway, the way Jonah did.
You can have a calling.
That's an even better kind of Christianity than Starbucks.
But that's such a special thing, and Melville obviously finds it, I don't know, fascinating, but he just doesn't get it or doesn't buy it, though he invented it.
He beat Kierkegaard by a year or two, I think.
But anyway, so I'm not talking about him.
I'm talking about a normal sort of Christian.
Starbuck is the best sort of normal Christian.
He is on the top of 97, which is the end of chapter 21.
When I know it, I will tell you.
And there we hear about Starbuck.
He's a lively cheap mate, that good man and pious.
And that's enough to get now.
But now we have to understand more what it is to be a good man and pious.
Well, to begin with, you should realize, of course, that this is always something you can keep your eye open for.
People from Nantucket are always people who want to turn the sea into the land.
Remember, that's the thing that people in Nantucket managed to do, that they made it into a highway for whale chasing.
And so on the beginning of chapter 26, the chief mate of the Pea Quad was Starbuck, a native of Nantucket and a Quaker by descent.
That is, that's his Christian and onso-theological.
That is, there's one right answer, it's the truth for all time and for everybody way of looking at things.
And he's a good guy.
He was a long, earnest man, and so forth and so forth.
And at the bottom of that same page, about five lines from the bottom, a staid, steadfast man.
In other words, a good guy, a really sort of responsible, good person.
But he's weak.
He can't stand up to Ahab.
He can't even, he doesn't know how to deal with this kind of monomania of Ahabs.
He's got a kind of almost peaceful assurance that Christianity is all right.
I say almost because in the Doubloon scene, he sees the Trinity, but he turns away from the Debloon.
He says, I shouldn't look at this too long in case it tempts me to not fully believe in it.
And so he sees that, you know, but he doesn't want to.
He won't let himself have any doubts.
And when Starbucks around, it's interesting, the sea even sort of starts to look like the land on 473.
That's chapter 114.
It's 472, the third paragraph in chapter 114.
There are times when in his whale boat, the rover softly feels a certain filial, confident, land-like feeling towards the sea that he regards as so much flowery earth.
And the distant ship struggling forward through the waves looks like it's coming through the grass or the prairie and so forth and so forth.
And he's talking about, I think, something in connection with Starbucks, or else I have missed what I'm trying to say.
No, there's Starbucks at the bottom of 473, the next page.
Loveliness, he says, loveliness unfathomable as ever lover saw in his young bride's eye.
He says to the sea, tell me not of thy teeth-teared sharks and thy kidnapping cannibal ways.
Let faith out fact, let fancy oust memory.
I look deep down and do believe.
So he's a believer, in spite of the evidence of all the other possible moods of the sea and all the other interpretations.
And that's why he just doesn't understand and can't stand up to Ahab.
That's on 180, which is the end of chapter 41.
Here then was this gray-headed, ungodly old man chasing with curses a Job's way around the world at the head of a crew to cheaply made up of mongrel renegades and castaways and cannibals.
And now the crucial sentence, morally enfeebled also by the incompetence of mere unaided virtue or right-mindedness in Starbuck.
And so when Starbuck has a chance to kill Ahab, when he realizes that Ahab's going to kill them all if he goes on like this, running around literally all over the world globe, chasing Moby Dick when he's supposed to be getting whales and bringing them home, then he, but he can't do it.
He just hasn't got, he's just a good Christian, and you don't go around shooting people just because they're out of control and dangerous.
Now, okay, another thing, remember what I'm doing now.
I'm listing four reactions to the whiteness.
The the fact that, in fact, you can't get any solid interpretation that isn't counteracted by some other.
And the and I've said one is even the best sort of Christians like Starbuck have this denial of the fact that it has the the whole world has no one color, no one meaning.
And philosophy, I've mentioned once or twice, Melville doesn't like philosophy, but I thought I owe you a quote or two.
I mean, of course he won't like philosophy because he doesn't like any view that thinks it's got the one right answer.
And of course not every philosopher is like that, but the great philosophers, the ones he sort of doesn't like, did each one think that finally with me, each one says we've got it.
And Melville's reaction to that is just to laugh at them.
That is, so Plato, he doesn't like, who is the original source of the notion that there is one truth, that that truth is divine, and to know that truth is a saving thing.
And all the story of the Republic.
How many know the Republic?
A lot of you know maybe, well, sooner or later you'll come across it.
And then, so that's on 334.
He's making fun of Plato and this happy picture that Plato presents of everything making perfect sense, if you only understand it and get in the right relation to it.
This is the very end of chapter 78.
He talks about how somebody, the risk of falling into the head of the whale while you're scooping out the spermaceti, which is all perfume-like.
And he says, How many think ye have likewise fallen into Plato's honeyhead and sweetly perished there?
So there go the Platonists.
Aristotle comes off equally badly on 459.
That's the first paragraph of chapter 110.
Top, this is when the whale gets hoisted up on the side of the ship.
Top heavy was the ship as a dinnerless student with all Aristotle in his head.
That's all Aristotle gets for interest.
And then Locke and Kant get brushed off in a hurry on 118 for a book that is so philosophical and which is so knowledgeable.
Although he never went to college, he seems to have read everything that a well-informed person should read and more.
He really just doesn't take the philosopher seriously at all.
And now on page 118, hmm, I am wrong.
I don't see, I've mismarked it.
I don't see anything about Kant and Locke on page 118.
I wonder what I did wrong.
I copied it wrong.
Anyway, there's a place where he dismisses Kant and Locke.
I owe it to you.
I'll get it by next time.
So, and it's funny to put Kant and Locke together like that.
It's dismiss them.
I mean, he certainly didn't take, say, 25B, where those are the opposed, very opposed positions.
Okay, so onward.
So, philosophy and Christianity, even at its best, are both onto theology, meaning they think that there's a supreme being that explains everything.
And if you believe in that, you don't face the whiteness.
So, then there are those, and I'm just reviewing, who affirm the whiteness, who stand in the infinite and the indefinite, and can't stand the illusion that there's any answer at all.
Who is that?
Baltington, somebody said, right?
Who said that?
You?
Okay.
Yes, of course, that's Baltington standing there, not wanting to spend a minute on the land, ready to hang out in the total open.
I thought again today as I was looking back at Nietzsche, the interesting difference that Nietzsche has his notion of a free spirit over man who can face up to what Nietzsche calls the death of God, which is like the whiteness of the whale, but there's no onto theological right answer.
And Nietzsche says that this is a very attractive view.
I'll give you that in the quotes I hand out, because such a person will be joyous.
It tells the name of the book that I'm going to get these from is the joyful wisdom, sometimes translated the gay science.
Well, Melville, remembers, main objection to Baltington is that Baltington is grim.
He's not happy.
He hasn't, you can't just be what Heidegger calls the lieutenant of nothingness, which standing out into the nothing and be joyful about it, Melville thinks.
So he sees this as a possible position, but he doesn't see it as a position that he wants to hold.
And in a way, maybe it's not even livable for Melville because Balkington gets bunked off by the end of that paragraph where he's godlike, but he can't live in this world.
And then another reaction, now we've got two: the onto theology and the standing in the indefinite, and then you could go mad.
I mean, Balkington is sort of willful.
He's pushing himself out into this total, bottomless, ocean water world.
Then there's Pip, who actually got to the bottom of the oceanless, the ocean, bottomless water world, and saw the God's foot on the loom and saw these coral insects that were making the orbs and so forth.
And Pip's response is to go crazy, to lose his identity completely and to lose everything.
And that's another possibility.
Balkington is willful and strong.
Pip is receptive and in a certain sense, weak.
But, and this is a quote about Pip that I didn't read when I talked about Pip, so I'm going to read it now.
On page 515, it's the end of chapter 27.
He's saying, oh, they had in the peak, what's he, where was, where am I?
Black little Pip, he never did come back.
That is.
Oh, no, he went before.
That is, he's dead.
Whatever happens to the rest of the crew, Pip is gone already.
He went before.
On the grim Peak Quad's forecastle, you shall ere long see him beating his tambourine, perlusive of the eternal time.
This is all weird Melville talk, but perlusive of the eternal time when sent for to the great quarter deck on high, he was bid to strike in with the angels and beat his tambourine in glory, call the tower here, hail the hero there.
Well, of course you don't take that literally, but what it means is something like he has at least the ability to be open to the way reality is, and though it blows his mind completely, instead of thinking of him as sort of pathetic as everybody else does, the right view, the view of the angels, will be that he's gone in the right direction as far as you could go.
Namely, not willfulness, but where you impose your own idea on the universe, or stand up to the non-meaning of the universe, but where you're open to whatever it is that's really going on.
So Pip is a kind of funny hero.
And then comes number four, which is a special case, I think.
It's not like philosophy, Christianity on the one hand, or heroic nihilism, which is Balkington, or sort of receptive nihilism, which is Pip.
There is this willful force and answer from the universe.
That's, of course, whose job, who wants to strike through the mask.
Everybody knows, I hope.
Ahab, one person says, this is sort of eerie.
But anyway, yeah, Ahab.
So, but Ahab, and now comes a quote I don't understand.
So I, in the hopes that somebody will, although it's very hard, I think, but probably very important.
A quote about Ahab and his relation to the whiteness, to the blankness, and to his determination to find an interpretation on page 195, the end of chapter 44.
There's something, lots of Melville is pretty strange, but here's what, and sometimes I could decode it, but this is, I haven't decoded this one.
About 15 lines from the bottom of one of that book, of that chapter 44.
Therefore, the tormented spirit that glared out of the bodily eyes when what seemed Ahab rushed from his room, it was Ahab, was from the time, was for the time but a vacated thing, a formless funabulistic being, a ray of living light to be sure, but without any object to color, and therefore a blankness in itself.
That is a mouthful.
What in the world is he trying to say?
My stab at it is something like: by trying to force one final answer on the universe, somehow Ahab gets blankness.
You get blankness if you try to embrace all the interpretations.
You get blankness if you try to fit it all into one interpretation, I think, though I don't understand exactly how it's supposed to work.
If anybody understands why he, when he's really in his most monomaniac state, becomes, and see the right words are in there.
He becomes something without an object of color, a blankness in itself.
He seems to confront whiteness and become whiteness at the end of his most extreme craziness when he's trying to impose a meaning, but he can't, yeah.
I mean, I can't, if anybody has anything better to say, come and tell me in office hours.
I just don't know.
You got something to say?
You look like you might have something to say to that way.
Okay, well, that's encouraging.
I mean, I think that that might be what it says.
Two people thinking that might be what it says is some comfort.
Okay, now, so much for the people out to get Moby Dick in their various ways.
Well, no, that's not fair.
So, never mind.
So much for all the views about whiteness that are running around.
We now, I mean, the people out to get Moby Dick is really only Ahab.
And so I'm not ready to talk about Chase yet.
I mean, Ahab's the one who wants an eyeball-to-eyeball confrontation with Moby Dick.
He wants an answer about the meaning of everything, and he somehow, in his crazy way, thinks that if he gets this, gets in fronting Moby Dick, he'll find out.
What will he find out?
Well, he'll find out whether the universe, which is sort of personified in Moby Dick, is malevolent, is moral, is indifferent, and so forth.
And that's what the chase should reveal at the end of the book, where you aren't yet, so I'm not going to get there yet, maybe.
But I have, because I want to say more about Moby Dick.
And I haven't said it enough and hadn't said it right.
But, of course, Moby Dick is tied up with the sea, the ocean, and the ocean is boundless and bottomless and indefinite as God, which is just indefinite, totally indefinite.
And Moby Dick is kind of, the sperm whale is the king of the boundless sea.
Isn't that what it's called?
That song at the beginning?
Where a giant in might, where might is right, and king of the boundless sea.
That's the sperm whale.
That's the last of those weird extracts.
And Moby Dick is also white.
So that means a dumb blankness full of meaning.
And sort of, but what, if there was one sort of word for Moby Dick and the sea, we have to have a word for them.
What would we say about them?
I mean, I've said in just in passing every once in a while, they're unrepresentable.
That is, they're ungraspable.
That is, you can't state what they mean.
And it's as if Moby Dick keeps open the fact that there's something very sort of big and important which is unrepresentable.
Remember, I go back to the very first lecture on Moby Dick and to the picture in the Spouder Inn, where it's almost impossible to tell what it's a picture of, and then it turns out to be a picture of the sperm whale.
But then you get all this about the whale has no face, its tail makes gestures, but you can't read them.
It's covered with hieroglyphics and you can't read them.
And if you try to get him out of the whale, out of the water, it loses its shape, and that therefore there is no way to find out what the whale really looks like.
And the crucial thing is, that wouldn't be the right way to put it.
There is nothing the whale really looks like.
The whale is unrepresentable.
That's what I want to stress.
And why is it important that the unrepresentable is sort of the bottom line, covers most of the, is like the ocean and covers more than half the world and everything.
Why is it important that Moby Dick never can be gotten rid of?
We'll talk about that in a minute.
Well, what I think is that there is something unrepresentable keeps open all the possible interpretations and makes it clear that what is most basic and most powerful and most important can't be captured in any interpretation.
And it's very important to have that around because that replaces the onto theology.
That's the tricky thing.
That is the sacred.
The sort of where the ultimate meaning is is in some way not something you can spell out.
That doesn't mean that there isn't, that it isn't, it is sacred because it's, I mean, now we're back, the unrepresentable is like the Heidegger understanding of being.
That's the Moby Dick is Heidegger, in a sense.
That is, the understanding of being, remember, is this meaning in our everyday practices and in our language and in our institutions, which makes us show up as the kind of people we are, makes us some kind of human being, a Quequeg kind of human being or a Western kind of human being, or it would make you a Farsi, you know, Zoroaster kind of human being.
But there is something that we cannot, but of course we can't know it.
Remember, Queque is, it's carved into Quequeg's body, his understanding of being, but he can't know it.
It's not the kind of thing you can represent and know.
You can embody the truth, but you cannot know it.
That's the Yates quote I mentioned.
So Moby Dick is this important feature of reality, that there is something which gives people's lives meaning and gives them a culture and gives them an identity and gives them a sense of what matters and what's important to do and what's not important to do, and that it can't be captured, expressed, painted, described in philosophy, and so forth.
It's pretty amazing and pretty tricky.
Yeah.
No, I say it's the practices themselves.
I mean, what's going on?
Que Clegg's body can't be read by Que Clegg or anybody.
Of course, it doesn't work quite because it looks like the guy who carved it on his body knew it.
I think that's a sort of just a mistake.
No, what we can't know, well again maybe Heidegger helps.
This is nearest to us but furthest away.
It is so our way of being, our way of seeing what it is to be human, our way of understanding objects, our way of having things matter to us, that it's too close for us to see.
And you get a sort of sense if you try, remember, to think about the distance we stand.
I mean, we can get a little bit of a grasp of that and see, because there are contrasting ones, that it's different than other cultures.
Or what it is to be feminine or masculine in our culture.
All that is so built into our bodies and into our language and into our sort of way we relate to each other that it's like another way to put it it's like the water to the fish it's transparent because it's so near because it's so pervasive and because it's so embodied instead of it's in your body and not in your mind all of that all of that sort of sense that there is something now how do you put it in Melville he understands that there is something unrepresentable which is more basic than anything that you can describe or paint or or say or philosophize about and which makes all that other things you can do possible and keeps you from ever thinking you, if you understand if you if you have a sense of it, from ever thinking you have the right answer that it keeps open the source space for making interpretations, which is all that you can do.
But if it weren't for that unrepresentable, people would be going around believing that they had the right interpretation, and then they would be finally losing any sense of something more important than their willful interpretations.
You're looking on, I don't blame you, all a little buzzed.
It is so weird to try to explain, one, what Heidegger's talking about, and see that this is how Melville is, what is Melville doing.
But I go back to Melville's talk.
The whale turns out not to be describable, paintable.
Science can't deal with it.
And what is that?
There's something about the universe very important about reality.
I try to avoid universe because of science.
There's something about reality very important, which you cannot think or describe.
And Moby Dick is, in this book, represents that.
Now, lest you think I make this all up, I'll go and give you some quotes about how important it is that Moby Dick stays around.
And without Moby Dick, I think the world would just come to an end, according to Melville.
Yeah.
How does it form of mind?
Like Moby Dick.
How should we approach something unrepresentable?
He's asking a good question.
Write a book like Moby Dick, obviously, describing the the attempts to to describe Moby Dick and how, and that Moby Dick has no face, and then describing the the ocean and and the sense in which it's bottomless.
I can't I don't know I mean let me try a little more.
You you don't try to represent the unrepresentable.
That was the wrong thing to do.
You try to point to it somehow.
You can tell me if you're looking like you have an idea.
I don't know things like ordinary humans.
They're something I represent.
Good, good.
Yes, if you're not out on the ocean chasing Moby Dick, good.
This may help because I see I've lost you and it's not your fault, all of you.
So Larry, you are, you're not out on the ocean chasing Moby Dick.
You've never seen the light whale and you never will and you may never be out on the ocean.
How do you relate to this fact that there is something crucial that you can't represent that makes your life, if your life has any meaning and mattering, it's got to have this unrepresentable.
Well, how do you deal with it, relate to that?
Let me think.
Well, I'll just sort of think out loud.
First, they're mostly statements about what you don't do.
You don't try to get a philosophical answer.
You don't try to get a religious answer like Dante gives you.
You don't, now that's the first thing.
Secondly, you, I'm trying to think how you appreciate these things like the meal and so forth, the list of things after the squeeze of the hand that he, that, how does that relate?
Well, that's sort of like you don't try to get this ultimate answer.
Well, what do you do then?
Well, you have a sense of the sacred in whatever way, in whatever local, fragile, temporary way it shows up.
And one of the ways to talk about that is you let your moods guide you.
And so you never face it head-on.
I think this is part of the answer to you.
If you try to face it head-on, it's not going to work.
I mean, that is, in a way, what we're going to find out when we read Ahab, who's been trying to face it head-on.
That is definitely the wrong way to deal with it.
So you have to deal with, get meaning and mattering in your life in a way that is available if you don't try to get control of it, which means get the answer to it.
Is that any help?
It's what?
Queque.
Kweklig is doing much better.
He has his own local sacred for his tribe, and he's not trying to go after Moby Dick, and he isn't doing philosophy, and he walks out on even Father Mappel, who I called sort of multiple monotheism, each person getting their own ultimate answer.
You've got to give up the search for multiple answers.
As Moby Dick, the relation to Moby Dick is a kind of negative thing.
You appreciate that there's something important you can't deal with, and you don't try to get the Dante answer that everybody's been trying to get in the West ever since Plato.
Boy, is that weird and hard.
But we're on the right track.
David, you want to say something?
Somebody over here.
I saw a hand.
Oh, yeah, go ahead.
I'm just running away?
Yes, of course.
Yeah, yeah, Ishmael has it.
Exactly.
I mean, he's right to pin it down.
I sometimes forget what's obvious.
If you want to know how to live in the light of the Moby Dick and the boundless sea and so forth, you are like Ishmael.
You're totally suspicious of any one answer, and you're totally suspicious of any one mood, and you're open to all the sacred and all the moods that come along.
And you live like the catscale eagle, never down in despair, although you could be a man of sorrow, that's another possible mood.
And never sort of constantly manic like Boomer and Bunger, though that is also a possible mood.
But you've got a lot of moods, and you can go to those extremes, but mostly you have lots of moods in between, and you are open to them.
And okay, let me go on.
It may help and it may not, but I think it might that you had this discussion before we talk about the things that you can say about Moby Dick, which are pretty strange.
So one of the last ways that everything could be taken over as a whole and given a meaning beyond Christianity and all mono views and beyond philosophy and all of its mono views, there's another tendency in our practices, in our way of dealing with things, which would like to take them all over.
And that is technology.
That's a whole new angle.
One of the understandings of being, which is the dominant one now, is to gain control of everything and make it serve our purposes.
And Melville's gone to that too.
That's why he talks about the spaceship Earth.
I mean, he has the sense that everything is being turned into an object.
And that would be, that's what the Nantucket people stand for.
They've got the whaling technology, which, if they could do it, would turn all the whales into objects and make them all exploitable for their oil and for serving our ends.
And that would get rid of the indeterminate and the indefinite.
It would just treat everything equally as an object to be studied by science and used by technology, including Moby Dick.
And so he worries about that.
And he's again ahead of his time.
He has a sense that the whole world is going to be understood and mastered.
And Melville thinks of that, and he thinks of that as what if whaling could, and it's now comes, this is all weird and mind-boggling.
What if you could combine ontology with ecology?
That's something that Melville does.
If you don't, if it would be disastrous to get rid of Moby Dick and the ocean as holding openness indeterminate, then you better not fish out all the whales.
But unfortunately, this technological holism, this technological totalism wants to fish out all the whales, and he worries about that.
What if it was what if the well, before we get to that, this whole tendency would objectify everything, and I didn't say that, but it would of course take over the pagans and their religions and wipe them out.
It would take over the sacred and wipe it out.
It would get rid of divine intuitions.
Everything would be scientifically intelligible and technologically manipulable.
And that is a big problem for Melville.
He really worries about it.
Now I have to catch up.
So there's got to be this kind of permanent resistance to this kind of conversion of everything into objects to be used, into commodities, into resources for us.
And that gets into this problem of what's happening to the whales.
The ontology gets him into ecology in the weirdest way and gets him the weirdest views on ecology because it's all sort of in the metaphor of whales.
So he's worrying about the fact that the whales could be fished out.
This is in page 444.
This is chapter 105.
Does the whale's magnitude diminish?
Will he perish?
And he's worrying about that.
About the because of that.
Because of the Nantucket people.
Now it's the Japanese who are fishing up all the whales.
But whatever.
If they if we don't he's worried that they're going to get rid of all the whales.
But still, another inquiry remains.
This is the second paragraph on 444.
But still, another inquiry remains, one often agitated by the more recondite Nantucketeers.
Let's see now.
They've got thousands of harpoons and so forth.
The moot point is whether Leviathan can long endure so wide a chase.
This is very relevant.
And so remorseless a havoc, whether he must not at last be exterminated from the waters and the last whale, like the last man, smoke his last pipe and then evaporate in the final puff.
This is the whole save the whales story.
Why are people so upset that the whales could be fished out?
Well, Melville would say because they have a sense that this would be a way the technology would be taking over something important.
At the bottom of 445, furthermore, concerning these last-mentioned leviathans, they have, this is why the whales are not going to be fished out.
A funny story.
They have two firm fortresses, which in all human probability will forever remain impregnable.
So he thinks you can't get rid of the unrepresentable.
And as upon the invasion of their valleys, the Swiss retreat to the mountains and so forth, the whales are going to retreat to the Arctic and the Antarctic.
And it better be like that.
Because if the whale, without the whales in this symbolic role of the unrepresentable, there won't be any meaning, any culture, anything.
I mean, if everything could be taken over in technology, we'd be, everybody would be happy, presumably, and have all their desires fulfilled as clearly and simply as possible.
But the kind of mattering that people need, whether it be the kind of mattering that goes with the squeeze of the hand or a kind of mattering that goes with the sacred, they're closely related, would just be taken up and eliminated.
But he thinks it won't happen at the bottom of 446, the end of the chapter.
Wherefore, for all those things, we account the whale immortal in his species, however perishable in his individuality, and so forth.
So that's because the whale stands for something, the saving something that religion and science and so forth can't get rid of.
It's a kind of ontological optimism turned into a kind of ecological optimism, and I can't really do more with it than that.
I mean, these are possible subjects in here, I'm sure, for interesting papers that you have to, remember, clear it with your TA before you try them.
Yeah.
That's right.
No, he's really sensitive to science, and he's really, I think, worried about the question whether the whales will be fished out.
But you're right.
And he turns it into not a question about how to save the whales, but that the whale stands for something.
The white whale, the sperm whale anyway, stands for something ontological, which can't be wiped out, but is but science is the big enemy of it, because science would like to get it all represented, all put into a system and controlled and understood.
And so he thinks that this tendency to sort of fish up the whales has got to be a dangerous tendency, which isn't really fish up the whales.
That's the crucial thing.
It's technology taking over everything.
That's, he thinks, is dangerous.
He thinks, but he isn't sure, that it's impossible.
But if it were possible, there wouldn't be any us anymore.
There might be nice, happy kind of Homo sapiens running around, but they wouldn't be human beings and things wouldn't matter.
That's what he's intuitive.
Yeah.
Yes.
Yes, every once in a while he gives a whole rant or he jokes about this attempt of scientists to understand the whale.
Of course, that's the very first thing in the book where he gets this higgly-piggly random bunch of quotes about the whale that don't add up to any understanding of it.
But again, everywhere, but of course, if the whale has, it can't be drawn, can't be measured, can't be described and so forth, science is not going to get it.
And of course, science, well, period.
And yes, that's part of the same argument.
That's another version.
I see what you're saying, of the fact that the whale can't be taken over by science and technology.
You could say it's going to hide under the polar ice caps, or you could just say science and technology with their methods can't get the unrepresentable basis of our meaningful existence.
Something like that.
You're looking worried.
That's okay.
You're looking less worried.
That's good.
Yeah.
I see.
Yeah, I bet he worries about surveillance too.
Where does he talk about that?
444, back to 444.
I'm interested.
He's got this.
Remember, this is 100 years ago.
100 and what?
This is 1850, so there's 150 years ago, that he's already worrying about things that lots of people are worrying about now.
And I don't just mean ecology.
I mean the whole worry that science is going to try to take over and explain and manipulate everything and so forth.
Yeah, where does he say it now?
Ah, the mastheads of the psoas over the wet.
Ah, so the almost omniscient lookouts are the ones who are the ones who make it possible to get all the whales.
And of course, they're going to be more and more.
They're going to be GPS and all better, more omniscient lookouts that guide the, I guess, at least the Japanese and the Norwegians to hunt down the whales.
By the way, just for your information, there was a student who wrote an interesting PhD thesis about this whaling thing.
This is just an aside, but it's something one should know.
This woman wrote a very interesting thesis about the power of rhetoric and the power of the slogan, save the whales, and the money that that brings in to these really right-minded people who want to save the whales.
But the whales aren't endangered, it turns out.
There's something called Minky Whales, whatever they are, which are many, many, many, many of them.
So that it turns out that if the Japanese and the Norwegians would just stick to fishing the Minky whales, there wouldn't be any problem.
But they will go on saying, Save the whales, because that slogan is going to bring in lots of donations to help them with their worthy cause, even though the whales aren't endangered.
Not whales in general.
Now, I don't know about sperm whale.
I don't think people go after sperm whales anymore to get the perfume in their heads.
I think they make their perfume other ways.
I don't know.
Ambergris Weddood, which is the special sperm stuff, I don't think that's, I don't think that's a valuable product anymore.
They go after the whales for meat.
And any old kind of whale will do for me.
Okay.
I think I go back to, okay, let's see now.
Ah, we're getting right up to the hunt.
Okay.
After much suspense, Ahab has finally tracked down Moby Dick and prepares to fight him.
And it's the long postponed showdown of the adventure story of this kind of pursuit and revenge that's the story of the book.
But it's also a metaphysical contest between this willful, insistent demand for an ultimate answer and the blankness, the very almost intolerable blankness of the white whale that won't give us any clear answers to what it's all about.
And in the course of the hunt, we've been told that Moby Dick is maliciously intelligent, awkwardly intelligent, a dumb brute.
Starbucks.
I'm going to fill this in, by the way, in a minute.
I've been saying this, but I haven't given you quotes to back it up.
He's a fulfiller of prophecies, an instrument of moral retribution.
I mean, we could make a kind of quiz out of it where in which these stories come out when they meet some other ship.
And now I'm going to just sort of call your attention to the fact that every time they meet some ship that knows something about Moby Dick, what would you expect?
Of course, a totally other interpretation and evidence of what Moby Dick is up to, which cancels the other interpretations, or unless you can just hold them all in mind at once, which is the right thing to do, and then you could have a kind of rainbow of interpretations.
But that is, for Ahab, that's impossible.
But anyway, so here we go.
I want to give you some of these.
So he's maliciously intelligent on 176.
That's the one we know, the familiar one, where he takes off Ahab's leg.
That's chapter 41.
It's a long chapter toward the end.
I'm just going to quote a quote just to put maliciously intelligent on the map on 176 second paragraph.
More than all, middle of the paragraph, more than all, his treacherous retreat struck more dismay than perhaps aught else.
For when swimming before his exalting pursuers with every apparent symptom of alarm, he had several times been known to turn around suddenly and bearing down upon them, either stave their boats to splinters or drive them back in consternation to their ships.
That sounds like he's smart, he knows what he's doing, he's not a clumsy, dumb brute.
But there's also, and this is what we haven't ever talked about, these ways that he seems to be moral and have a purpose.
So we've got to talk about two of them.
One of them is the town hoe story, and that's on 250.
So where are we?
250.
Okay, long chapter.
The town hoe story.
It's a long story.
Whoa, is it a long story?
Gee, it's chapter 54, and I am in the middle of it or near the end of it.
No, I'm near the end of it, about three pages from the end of this long one, in which there's this bad guy, Radney, and this very good guy, Steelekild.
And Steelekilt's about to kill Radney because Radney's such a bad guy and has turned everybody against Steelekill.
And then in the middle of, and somebody's telling this story, and in the middle of 250, but gentlemen, a fool saved the would-be murderer from the bloody deed he had planned.
Yet complete revenge he had, and without being the avenger.
For by a mysterious fatality, heaven itself seemed to step in and take out of his hands its own and take out of his hands and into its own the damning thing he would have done.
Okay, that's he would have killed Radney, but who was really obnoxious.
But Moby Dick kills Radney instead on 251, the middle of the page.
The mutineer was the bowsman.
The mutineer is Steelekill of the mate.
And when fast to a fish, it was his duty to sit next to him while Radney stood up with his lance in the prow to haul in the slackened line and so forth.
And then at the bottom, the whale, well, about three-quarters of the way down, the whale comes up under the boat, and suddenly the boat struck as against a sunken ledge and keeling over, spilled out the standing mate.
That's Radney the bad guy.
The instant as he fell on the whale's slippery back, the boat rided and was dashed aside by the swell, while Radney was tossed over into the sea on the other flank of the whale.
He struck out through the spray and for an instant was dimly seen through that veil, wildly seeking to remove himself from the eye of Moby Dick.
He's got eyeball contact with Moby Dick.
That the whale rushed around in a sudden maelstrom, seized the swimmer between his jaws, and rearing high up with him, plunged headlong again and went down.
That's the end of Radney, and that's the whale as moral avenger.
That's the Town Ho story.
And that, in other words, is not a malicious intelligence.
That is a moral intelligence on the good guy's side of the pictures.
And then there's Moby Dick as the fulfiller of prophecies.
That's the Jeroboam story.
There's a mad sailor named Gabriel.
He predicts the death of the chief mate Macy if he pursues Moby Dick, the way Moses predicts the plagues that come to Israel if the Pharaoh won't release the Hebrews.
That Macy disregards the prophet and pursues the whales.
Now we're in 306.
306 and the bottom of 306, we're in chapter 70.
We are two-thirds into chapter 70.
And it's the bottom of 306 where Gabriel solemnly warned the captain against attacking the white whale, skipping a little.
Moby Dick was sighted from the mastheads.
Macy, the chief mate, burned with ardor to encounter him, and the captain himself being not unwilling to let him have the opportunity, despite all the archangel's denunciations, they call Gabriel the archangel.
That is the name of the, that is really the name of the archangel in the Bible.
So then you get another one of these stories, which starts at the top of 307 in this long paragraph.
It seemed that, about half into the paragraph.
Now, while Macy the mate was standing up in his boat's bow and with all the reckless energy of his tribe, was venting his wild exclamations upon the whale and essaying to get a fair chance for his poised lance, lo, a broad white shadow rose from the sea by its quick fanning motion, taking the breath out of the bodies of the oarsmen.
Next instant, the luckless mate, so full of furious life, was switting bodily into the air and making a long arc in his descent, fell into the sea at a distance of about 50 yards.
Not the chip of the boat was harmed, not a hair of any oarsman's head, but the chief mate forever sank.
So Moby Dick did exactly execute the prophecy.
And now we are ready, I think, to go to the chase.
But we are also near enough the end of the hour that you have been saved for having it told you until next time.
But I will get very close.
So let me see where we are.
Well, let me see if you can predict what's going to happen in the chase.
I'll tell you that there's going to be three separate encounters with Moby Dick.
Each time when they go out to get him, something happens.
And what are you going to find out, do you think, that when you finally get Moby Dick close enough, when they get close enough to really encounter Moby Dick, so to speak, head on, which is going to turn out to be right?
Maliciousness, indifference, stupidity, moral determination, how to get Ahab?
What do you think?
Which?
None of them?
All of them.
Right.
Good.
Several people said that.
You get it?
Yes, all of them.
That's what happens in the chase.
Keep your eyes open when you get there.
It's a brilliant tour d'Eforce.
And keep your eye open for what kind of confrontation Ahab finally gets when he gets really up close.
And let's just start.
Well, what do we do?
I have to think a minute.
I think I should stop while we're ahead here.
And you have you've got the right answer, all of them.
How many let's say how many again haven't got up to the chase in the end of the book?
How many would be there?
How many wouldn't be there even if I waited until Thursday?
How many can you can you think you can get there by Thursday?
Well, I'm sir I would rather you get there by Thursday and that we stop now than just by a difference of 15 minutes.
I spoil all this exciting prose.
Okay, so next time I'm going to finish the book.