So since the first sentence of Moby Dick is, call me Ishmael, the first thing is to talk about Ishmael, who is also, that's Melville's, so to speak, name in the book, but it's really Melville himself is Ishmael.
And Ishmael is a wanderer.
He was Abraham's illegitimate son, cast out by Sarah when they had their own legitimate son, Isaac.
And he then became an outcast and a wanderer.
I take it from Melville's point of view, he's the perfect example of somebody that has no world of his own, no identity of his own.
And notice that the writer of the book isn't even named Ishmael.
He says, call me Ishmael.
We don't know the name of the writer of the book.
And also Melville, in the copy of the book that you all have, The Signet Classic, I was struck, I never saw before, a brief summary of Melville's life, which sounds pretty Ishmael-ish.
His father's bankruptcy and death in 1832 deprived him of higher educational opportunities and put him outside the conventional view of life.
So I didn't realize he's self-educated, knowing all the Shakespeare and Milton and Bible and Farses and so forth.
But so what did he do?
He taught school.
He sailed to Liverpool and back.
Then he shipped on another whale, on a whaling voyage, he deserted at the Marquis Islands, lived for a month among the cannibals, and came out alive.
And then he got picked up by an Australian whale ship that took him to Tahiti, where he was jailed for mutiny.
But he escaped and spent some months as a beach comber until a third whaling ship took him to Hawaii and then he lived there for a while.
Talk about somebody who is rootless and has just a whole bunch of jobs, none of which define him.
And he says that he's been teaching at the beginning of this book.
So he obviously goes from teaching to whaling to writing.
And through it all, and this is what begins to make it polytheistic, he's very moody.
And his moods really tell him what to do.
So the book begins, Call Me Ishmael, and then a little further down, whenever I find myself growing grim about the mouth, whenever it's a damn drizzly November in my soul, whenever I find myself bringing up the end of every funeral procession, and so forth and so forth, then it's time for me to go to sea, he says.
So he's dictated by his moods.
He doesn't freely decide to go to sea.
There's a certain time when he just has to go to sea.
On page five, he says that there's a fate that has constant surveillance of me and dogs me and influences me in some unaccountable way.
I take that to mean that it's always my moods that lead me and influence me.
I don't decide what to do and when to do it.
And that makes him all remind you of Homer and the gods who are the moods who attune people to their situations and lead them to do whatever they do.
Now, normally I don't really pay attention to the letters and the sort of critical stuff, but there's a letter from Melville to Hawthorne, which is so illuminating and so much agrees with my interpretation that I often read it.
So, Melville always admired Hawthorne and thought he was, Hawthorne was the great one, and Melville was sort of a failure, even as a writer.
And that's sort of ironic, because Hawthorne is still read, but Moby Dick is more and more counted the great American novel.
At the time, people didn't know what to make of it.
So he says to Hawthorne, in me, divine magnanimities, magnanimities are spontaneous and instantaneous.
Catch them while you can.
The world goes around and another side comes up.
I take these divine magnanimities to be the moods that catch him.
And then he says the famous line, I've written a wicked book and feel spotless as a lamb.
Why it's a wicked book, you have to read the whole book to find out, but roughly, because it's totally anti-Christian, but it's anti-any form of supreme being, any view or culture that thinks it's got an answer to the meaning of the universe.
It's, from Melville's point of view, everything is interpretation all the way down, which from a Christian and Hawthorne-like point of view would be a wicked book.
But he doesn't mind.
In fact, he's sort of the next sentence says, I don't mind having written a book that's wicked from a Christian point of view.
I'm a polytheist.
He says, ineffable socialities are in me.
I would sit down and dine with you and all the gods in old Rome's pantheon.
That he should have said Greeks, but he doesn't seem to know much about Greek.
He knows all the antiquity stuff from the Roman.
But there it is.
He feels fine.
He's written his book.
His book is utterly anti-anything which later in the course or already in the course, starting with Dante, we've called onto theology, the idea that there is some supreme being in which everything is grounded and which you can make sense of it.
And one more moody remark, which is, if anybody knows Foucault, you'll recognize Foucault said the same thing 150 years later.
Or is it 200?
200?
1850, this is, well, 170 or something.
I'm bad at arithmetic.
So here's what he ends up saying to Hawthorne in this letter.
This is a long letter, but you're not bound to answer it.
Possibly, if you do answer it and direct it to Herman Melville, you will missend it.
For the very fingers that now guide this pen are not precisely the same that just took it up and put it on this paper.
Lord, when shall we be done changing?
And that's just so perfect for the way the book works that I couldn't resist reading it.
So here we are.
Ishmael is like Odysseus, only even more of a wanderer, because Odysseus has a home to go to, finally, where his wife and Penelope and Telemachus are waiting for him.
Ishmael is a total wanderer.
He has no home and no family, the way it's uh set up here.
No job, no olive tree bed that's anchored in the earth because as uh Odysseus has.
And in fact, he has no roots at all.
And he lives in a whole range of possible worlds.
Now I wonder why I said possible worlds.
I think a whole range of worlds is all it is that I want to say.
And he wants to be at home in all of them.
And he says this on, I'll keep reading little things because I want to keep you in touch with the text.
So he says, I love to sail, listen to Ishmael now, I love to sail forbidden seas and land on barbarous coasts, not ignoring what is good.
I'm quick to perceive a horror and could still be social with it, would they let me?
Since it is well to be on friendly terms with all the inmates of the place one lodges in.
And that is, in other words, be at home in all the worlds that you can travel to.
And he gets pulled into lots of different worlds, as Ads did Melville, as you could see from what I read.
And in each, he respects the gods of that world.
And when Kleequeg, the black savage, shows up and is worshiping his god, Yo-Yo, then Melville, or Ishmael, worships Yo-Yo.
And he's the total enemy of what I sometimes call monolithic monotheism.
What I once said Nietzsche calls monotonot in a theism.
I think he would agree.
And he's against it because it excludes being open to all those gods and all those worlds, all those understandings of the sacred that you can be, let yourself be pulled into.
No willpower.
Just get in, if you get attuned, if your mood attunes you to them, then you take up their sense of the sacred.
And that doesn't mean that any of them are true.
Being true or not true just isn't the point.
Being sacred, being something that is important to people in a way that I'll explain in a minute, is what makes them valuable, not that they get it right about the universe.
There is no way to get it right about the universe.
Later he'll say that Moby Dick has no face.
That is, there's no right way to draw the way Moby Dick looks, because there's no way Moby Dick looks.
But anybody who thinks there's one right answer to the world and our place in it is humorless, fanatical, dangerous, a philosopher, which he thinks is somebody who tries to think they've got the one right answer.
So he says that he wants to be at home with every religion.
See, this is a kind of higher polytheism, as you can see.
I mean, in the polytheism, there was one religion, and something like ten gods and goddesses.
Now it's polyreligionism or something.
There's a whole bunch of religions out there.
And not only do you get in tune with the various, say, ten gods of, you know, Aries, the aggressive god and Aphrodite, the erotic goddess, and so forth, and you can get in tune with those we talked about in the Odyssey.
You can get in tune with all sorts of religions.
And the place where he explains that most is on page 79.
He says in the third sentence, I cherish the greatest respect toward everybody's religious obligations, never mind how comical.
See, he thinks that it's comical that Kuikleg worships this little wooden statue, Yo-Yo, and kisses Yo-Yo on the nose before going to bed, but he does it too, and not ironically, and not laughing, laughing at it or with it or something, but in no way putting it down.
He thinks that Kuikweg is a sort of saint and that his religion is a very good religion.
But he says in the next paragraph, I say we good Presbyterian Christians should be charitable in these things and not fancy ourselves so vastly superior to other mortals, pagans and whatnot, because of their half-crazy conceits on this subject.
And then comes a very important sentence that he never explains at the end of that paragraph: Heaven have mercy on all of us, Presbyterians and pagans alike, for we are all somehow dreadfully cracked about the head and sadly need mending.
There's something fundamentally incomplete or wrong about human beings.
I mean, from a Christian point of view, it would be sin, but in some pagan culture, it would be something else.
But there's something that people need that religion can satisfy, that the sacred can satisfy.
And it doesn't have to be the supreme being, as in Dante, that gives you the total satisfaction when you stare into God's depths.
But something has to heal you.
And since I was just reading near the end of the book today, when Quique gets very sick and almost dies, he doesn't die.
And he looks completely serene and happy in his illness.
And it's clear that he's been, though he's fit physically, he's been healed spiritually.
And those words are connected.
Being healed, being healthy, being holy, in German, Heil, which does all this job in one word, is what he's talking about here.
Human beings need that.
He needs that.
In his view, the more versions of the healing that you can get attuned to, the better.
If anybody wants to say anything, by the way, feel free to interrupt.
This vast number of people out there must have many questions on that.
So now we're on the next issue.
That was the sort of background polytheism, which will become clearer as we go on.
Now comes Ishmael on the mysterious, the fundamentally mysterious and indefinite nature of reality.
It's the experience of this kind of indefinite mysteriousness that keeps you open to all the worlds.
Once you think you've got an answer, then you just have the answer.
But if you understand that not only you don't have the answer, but the very idea that there is an answer is wrong, then you're open to everything.
Aha, I knew you'd have to.
No, no, you don't need the variety, but you're onto something puzzling about this whole book because it, let's try to think about it.
Certainly, he thinks that any one of the particular ones will do.
There's only one kind of religion that doesn't heal you, and that's Christianity and all the onto-theological religions who think they have one, the one truth.
But otherwise, he talks about visiting various places in the course of the book where he sits down and goes to their temples or drinks their drugs or whatever it is that their religion has.
Now, why does he think, or does he, that it's better to be open to many of them than to just be living in one of them?
That's a very, very, very good question.
It should have been a paper talk.
And the first thing to say is, generally, he doesn't think that many is a good thing.
He's perfectly happy with Quequeg's pagan religion healing him.
But there's something about the situation of Western 19th-century human beings that makes it necessary.
I'm thinking out loud, I don't know the answer yet, makes it necessary for them to collect the sacred here and there wherever it locally manifests itself.
At least it's necessary for Ishmael for some reason.
Now, and I take it it's for Ishmael qua modern, uprooted, post-Christian person.
Now, why can't he just settle down with one of these religions?
Why is he collecting openness to the sacred?
Yes, but that's just the name of the question in a way.
Why does he think being open to cross-cultural sacredness is a good religion for him instead of settling down with Quiqueg, for instance, and taking up his religion?
It seems somehow this is not very satisfactory, what I'm saying, but that there's just a feeling of the more sacred, the better.
And that once you've gotten loose from any particular culture, you go and experience them all.
And that's somehow, I haven't really answered you, an advantage over the ones that are in each particular one.
Somehow you get more of you healed, or different ways you're cracked about the head get healed, or something.
Ah, good.
Yes, you're right.
Let's put that in.
We're coming to that.
But yes, there's something about the indefiniteness which is important.
But you see, you turned it the other way than I turn it.
I think it's because there is this basic indefiniteness in the universe that he's open to all these sacreds.
And you think that what?
I will say what you said again.
It seemed to me not what I said just.
The mood is important part of it.
That's the sort of super polytheism.
Just as there's not just one goddess, a god or goddess in the pantheon, how you have to be sensitive to being aggressive, to being domestic, to being erotic, to being a sort of nerd like Festus.
Why?
And it seems that it just takes all of these because you have all these various capacities to exercise.
So since there are all these moods, and since different religions you get attuned to through different moods, somehow, of course, we're getting to the same non-question.
Somehow, the more moods you can use and the more things you can get attuned to, there's a place where he talks about why he doesn't want to be just looking at the sun.
Well, no, this is the same thing.
He certainly doesn't want to be just looking at God.
And he certainly doesn't want to be in despair.
We'll talk about that later.
But we're still back to the question, what's the advantage of experiencing all these different moods?
I think all I can say is they're there, if you're capable of them, and each one of them gives you some insight into what you are and some kind of satisfaction or meaning, then the more the better.
That's the best I can do.
Yeah.
I wish that every school plays this level of connection to one world to another.
Then you can find all these different.
And he that's nice, but why not embody just one sacred?
You don't know this yet, really, unless you've, I don't know how far you've gotten in the reading, but Quiqueg, I talked about it in the last lecture, embodies one sacred.
It's carved on his body by the prophet of his tribe, and he's saved.
So what's the advantage?
I think, again, I get this feeling.
Well, that would be fine if Melville had a tradition that had in it the sacred and the divine anymore, if it hadn't lost it, and if he had been brought up in those practices and they were carved into his body, he would be saved.
But he can't, he's this postmodern person.
He can't just take over his tradition the way Quiqueg can as a saving theme.
Yeah.
Well, education is kind of trying to learn a little bit about it.
I think that may be a sort of psychological explanation about Ishmael, but the fact that he didn't go to Oxford or Berkeley makes him open maybe in some special way.
But he's certainly trying to say that given the way things are, openness to moods and worlds is, of course, he says it's how he is, but I think he means is that's how anybody is who's sensitive to the way things are and knows how to get healed.
Okay, now that'll give me plenty to think about.
Now let me see.
So now comes the next thing we want to, I have been saying, but I haven't really given you any examples of this important way that everything is indeterminate.
And there is no way anything is.
There are only interpretations.
He does it in this funny way in chapter 3, the Spouter Inn on page 10, where he sees a picture.
And he goes and what he does every once in a while when he's about to say something important, he switches from I to you and sort of brings you in.
So here we go.
We're brought in.
Entering the gable-ended spouter inn, you found yourself in a wide, low, straggling entry with old-fashioned Wayne Scotts and so forth.
And then on one side on a very large old painting, oil painting, so thoroughly besmoked and in every way defaced, in the unequal cross-lights by which you viewed it, it was only by diligent study and a series of systematic visits to it and careful inquiry of the neighbors that you could in any way arrive at an understanding of its purpose.
Such unaccountable masses of shades and shadows that at first you almost thought some ambitious young artist in the time of the New England hags had endeavored to delineate chaos bewitched.
And it is chaos.
That's another word he's got for it.
And he says, a boggy, soggy, squinchy picture, truly, enough to drive a nervous man distracted.
Well, that's just a pointing ahead.
There is a nervous man in the book who is completely distracted by things he can't get a grip on and understand.
And of course, that's A, who even says that he wants a solid grip in this slippery world.
Well, this is not a solid grip.
There was, but he loves it.
Yet there was a sort of indefinite, half-attained, unimaginable sublimity about it that froze you to it till you took an oath with yourself to find out what the marvelous painting meant.
And then he goes through this game of interpretation.
Every, ever and anon, a bright but alas deceptive idea would dart through you.
It's the Black Sea in a midnight gale.
It's the unnatural combat of the four primal elements.
It's a blasted heat.
It's a horborean winter scene.
It's the breakup.
This is my favorite.
It's the breakup of the ice-bound stream of time.
Go far and further out.
But at last, all these fantasies yield to one portentous something in the picture.
That once found out, all the rest were plain.
But stop.
Does it not bear a faint resemblance to a gigantic fish?
Even the great Leviathan himself?
In fact, the artist designed, seemed this, a final theory of my own, and so forth.
So, one, he says it's a whale, but he also says it's just the way it seems to him.
It's his theory that it's a whale.
He's got all the pieces in there.
And moreover, it turns out the whale has no face, so you couldn't really paint the whale.
You can't paint the whale, he says later, as it is under the water, and you can't paint the whale as it is when it's out of the water, because then it's just a kind of floppy mess and it ceases to look like a whale.
So that's okay, that's the first version of the game of interpretation, which the book is all structured by.
And he's got these playful interpretations, and he says it's his own, it's what he thinks.
So the whale, in its ungraspableness, and even more of the white whale, become symbols of the inscrutability of the universe.
And we get from the very beginning every possible interpretation.
And now we see this funny thing in the book where he collects at the beginning the extracts supplied by a sub-sub-librarian, these higgly-piggly gospel zetology, all funny ways of talking.
I mean, zetology is science, but it's gospel zetology, but it's not reliable at all, and it's got all kinds of crazy stuff in it.
And it's collected in he gives you biblical quotes, poetic quotes, mythical quotes, scientific quotes, completely nutty quotes, because these are all supposed to be quotes about the whale.
And then, if you read them, which you probably don't need to, all of a sudden, having had the whale did this, the whale did that, the whale did that, each separate quote.
Here's a a quote: If you make the least damn bit of noise, replied Samuel, I'll send you to hell.
Life of Samuel Comstock.
Just in there, a quote which hasn't even got a whale in it.
So, and all of this is this kind of randomness, which he plays with.
And that's it.
Now, and it takes a long time for him to explain more and more about how the whale is the unrepresentable, to talk like philosophy.
You can't draw it, you can't describe it, it's got marks on it that you can't decipher, it makes gestures with its tail that you can't understand, it has no face, and so forth.
But now I want to stop that, although it'll come back again and again.
And you who know more about the course already know that the whiteness of Moby Dick is the culmination of all this side of the whale.
But now, the basic dichotomy of the book, which some one of you mentioned already, the sea and the land, is the way he expresses, on the one hand, the indeterminate chaos, and on the other hand, the need for something solid, something that you can take a stand on and count on, and so forth.
And he does it by just contrasting the land and the sea for pages and pages and all through the book.
But I will just read you and give you a list.
If I were writing it all on the board, which I won't because there's nobody here very few anyway, you've all got it to copy down.
I can give you a copy.
So, but I would have a big list of land versus sea, and here is a bunch of them for you out there in podcast land.
I'll give you always land and then sea.
Land is closed, closed off.
The sea is open.
The land is marked off.
There are landmarks.
The sea leaves no records.
To take just when he goes to sea, for instance, just to not just keep reading, but interrupt this every once in a while.
He says, gaining the open water, the wind blew, he's going off in the tugboat toward the Pequad.
How I snuff that tartar air, how I spurned the turnpike earth.
That's the slavish marked off.
That common highway, all over dented with the marks of slavish heels and hoofs, and how I turn me to admire the magnanimity of the sea, which will permit no records.
See, no landmarks.
So then you've heard it's slavish, the land, the sea is freedom, the land is certainty, the sea is mystery, there's comfort versus rigor, safety versus danger, solid ground versus bottomless, that's a nice one.
I mean, there are landmarks, but there are no sea marks, and there's a bottom, and you stand on the land, but you don't stand on the bottom of the ocean.
And then there's the definite, that's very important, and the indefinite.
I'll read you a sentence for that, because one of his favorite things is the indefinite.
If there were ever a God, that would be indefinite for him.
He says, but in landlessness alone resides the highest truth.
Sh, shoreless, indefinite is God.
So it's the definite versus indefinite, bounded versus boundless.
I like that because I want the whale to be the symbol of the sea is the unrepresentable.
The whale is kind of the incarnation or mammalization or something of the sea.
It's focused in the whale, the sperm whale particularly.
And then the white whale is the most extreme of all these things.
But so there's this little, at the end of all these funny extracts, which I have read you only the craziest, the last one is the most important.
Oh, the rare old whale mid storm and gale in his ocean home will be a giant in might where might is right and king of the boundless sea.
So that's to say he's the exemplar of the paradigm of the boundless.
And he's another thing is his distinction the land is finite, the sea is infinite.
It's not quite clear what that means, but you've got the general idea.
He talks about, we'll see again how at sea you could perish in the howling infinite, and how that would be better than to be ingloriously dashed upon the lee, even if it were safe.
And he contrasts philosophy and which goes with land and thinking or meditation, which goes with sea.
Those are those two extreme attitudes.
And now I see if I skipped anything.
Well, everybody has got a certain cautious attraction to the sea because the land is so constricting, according to the way he s sets it up.
So everybody wants to get as close to the water as possible and yet not fall in.
And he talks about that.
And he talks about this tendency to try to get everything clear and determinate.
And I'm going to talk about that now.
There's this tendency to try to grasp the meaning once and for all.
And that's what philosophy and religion try to do.
And we saw that at its best in Dante.
But his way of talking, he thinks it's very dangerous to try to grasp it once and for all.
And he thinks that the myth of narcissist is about that.
He says on page three, about the deeper meaning of that story of narcissists, who, because he could not grasp the tormenting, mild image he saw in the fountain, plunged into it, was drowned.
But that same image we ourselves see in all rivers and oceans.
And it's the image of the ungraspable phantom of life, and this is the key to it all.
This whole, I don't know, again, you look puzzled, this very sort of puzzling.
But the drift of it is that most people try to get an answer, and that's disaster.
And that's what happened, and that's what Narcissus shows.
But his hero is going to stand in the howling infinite.
We'll talk about that more in a minute.
You shouldn't be trying to grasp the final meaning and truth.
Of course, Ahab is dedicated.
That's his life obsession to forcing the universe to give him an answer to whether there's a God and whether God is malicious or good and so forth.
And that's all going to turn out to be disastrous in ways I can't tell you about yet.
And I just wanted to say, it struck me as interesting that Homer loves light and clarity.
The Odyssey is so clear and so beautiful, and every chair and every dish and every person is outlined in absolute clarity.
And Poseidon, who is the dark side, the water side, is played down in the Odyssey.
He's the sort of outlier of the pantheon who they don't usually get along with, but since he's the brother of Zeus, they have to deal with him.
But Zeus is superior to Poseidon.
But it's, and for Melville, as you can imagine, what makes the sea so special is that it's dark.
And darkness is more important than light to him.
It's just as it should be, in a way.
He says on page 52: it's as if darkness were the proper element of our essences.
It's a very anti-philosophical, anti-Western, anti-Greek idea that darkness is superior to light.
Now, people are constantly trying to turn the ocean into the land.
And that's where the people from Nantucket come in.
And I try to go quick over them.
I said more about them in the lecture, but we don't really need to know too much, except that Ahab is from Nantucket.
And the Nantucket people, I quote on 61, issuing from their anthill in the sea, overrun and conquer the watery globe, like so many Alexanders.
Two-thirds of this globe, this terraquatous globe, boy, terraquacious.
What in the way?
It's a mixture of land and water?
I don't know what that means.
Two-thirds of this terraquatous globe, well, I see we are a mixture.
The globe is some land and some water.
Okay.
Are the Nantucketers, for the sea is his.
He owns it.
He goes to the sea, there is his home.
There is his business.
He lives on the sea like the prairie cocks in the prairie and so forth.
It's just important to know that there is this kind of technological force of taming and making objects out of and getting control of everything.
And the Nantucketers are the ones who do that.
He's got a sense that everything, that science and technology will get rid of all the dark, try to get rid of all the darkness and all the mystery.
And for instance, he has a sense, I couldn't turn to it, but he talks about this frigate Earth.
I think he's probably the first person I'd love to know who thinks of the Earth as an object, a spaceship, in effect, and sees that it's been objectified by, and the Nantucketers are sort of doing the same job.
Now, the last important thing, I promise to tell you more about the openness and the groundlessness.
And maybe I didn't promise, but that's what's coming up.
And the right way to relate to them, almost right, except that it isn't the right way because it isn't this getting in tune with the sacred and getting healed.
You'll see.
It's a fascinating, weird feature of this book, which is full of fascinating, weird features.
One feels that Melville couldn't possibly have understood what he was doing.
That's what makes it such a great book.
He must have just got up in the morning and started writing and was totally blown away by what he had written.
Okay, so here we go for that, for what I call heroic nihilism.
The other attitude from trying to turn the sea into the land is to accept the groundlessness and enjoy the constant challenge and constantly avoid the temptation to try to grasp it and make sense of it.
And there is a hero who does that.
And it looks like somebody who did that would be able to rejoice in their freedom because they will certainly have total freedom and they ought to enjoy the play of perspectives and they should certainly stand firm against the temptation to settle for any fixed answers.
And now he's going to give you a hero who is, you'll see in a minute, I mean, that he has, that he's able to stand against the temptation of fixed answers is sure.
That he enjoys it and rejoices in it is not the case for Melville.
I mean, those who any of you know Nietzsche, I mean, always in the back of my mind, I have Nietzsche.
You recognize some of this Nietzschean thing.
I mean, this is the overman in Nietzschean turns.
So let's find out about him.
There is this fascinating, handsome man who appears on page 14, and he has a sober face.
He's very good looking, s full six feet in height, with noble shoulders, uh a chest like a cofferdam.
I've seldom seen such a brawn and such brawn in man, a face deeply brown and burnt, marked with dazzling white teeth by contrast, while in the deep shadows of his eyes floated some reminiscences that did not seem to give him much joy.
That's the interesting thing.
The way he differs from Nietzsche is he doesn't think heroic nihilism can be joyful.
But the man disappears unobserved when everybody else is having a good time and they all run after him saying, Baltington, Baltington, and that's but we don't see him anymore for a long, long time until page 101.
And 101, they go they set out from Nantucket to the and the great line, we gave three heavy-hearted cheers and blindly plunged like fate into the lone Atlantic.
And now they're off.
And what does he see at the helm of the boat?
Baltington.
When on that shivering winter's night the Pequod thrust her vindictive bows into the cold, malicious waves, who should I see standing at her helm but Baltington?
I looked with sympathetic awe and fearfulness upon the man who in midwinter, just landed from a four years dangerous voyage, could so unrestingly push off again for still another tempestuous term.
The land seems scorching to his feet.
That is, that he can't stand these certainties and these happy parties and and so forth.
And now this is how he describes the way the wor the way it seems to Baltington.
The port would fain give fain give succor.
The port is pitiful.
In the port is safe oh, the port is, yeah, pitiful.
In the port in the port is safety, comfort, hearthstone, supper, warm blankets, friends.
All is kind to our mortalities.
In the course is the, well, never mind.
That list is important.
I wish I had.
Well, I can remember.
So here, let's go on.
But in that gale, the port, the land, is that ship's direst jeopardy.
She must fly all hospitality.
One touch of land would make her shudder through and through.
With all her might, she crowds offshore.
All the land seeks all the lashed sea's landlessness again.
Okay, that's the picture of how it looks to Baltington.
And then comes this amazing two paragraphs where you get the essence of what it would be like to be at sea all the time.
Know ye now, Baltington, glimpses do you seem to see of that mortally intolerable truth that all deep earnest thinking is but the intrepid effort of the soul to keep the open independence of her sea, while the wildest winds of heaven and earth conspire to cast her on the treacherous slavish shore.
Now, now, this comes this praise of Baltington, but in landlessness alone resides the highest truth, shoreless, indefinite as God.
So better it is to perish in the howling infinite than being gloriously dashed upon the leaf, even if it were safe.
Take heart, take heart, O Baltington, bear thee grimly, demigod.
Up from the spray of thy ocean perishing, leaps straight up thy apotheosis.
One or two.
What an amazing thing.
And you just discover that Baltington drops dead that night.
We don't know why.
He's never mentioned again in the book.
He's become a god, so that up from his ocean perishing, his apotheosis is godlike.
But I think the interesting thing is, Melville pictures what it would be like to live this heroic nihilist life that Nietzsche admires too very much.
And Melville thinks that it would be grim and joyless, and he doesn't buy it.
He doesn't see why we should have.
He thinks we are, I don't know whether we are incapable of it, or I guess at least this, we don't have to settle for this.
And though he admires Bulkington, obviously amazingly, he's the, if God is dead, we have to become gods ourselves, Nietzsche says, and Balkington does it.
He thinks that there must be some other way to heal us besides, and he just dumps Balkington.
And we never hear from him again after that paragraph.
Do you want to say something?
Oh, okay.
So, you have to resist all the answers.
And so, God for Melville, remember, indefinite is God.
What does that mean?
God is not the supreme being that's ground of all intelligibility and explains everything.
God is the groundlessness.
It is the indefiniteness which makes everything endlessly interpretable.
That's another way of saying the same thing I was saying.
But just living in the groundlessness, like Balkington, isn't somehow satisfying.
It doesn't give you the healing you need.
It's not enough to be the lieutenant of nothingness, which is a Heidegger phrase for this thing.
It's a grim job, and that's about all that he has to say about it.
I think I have read all the quotes that I need to quote for that.
So there's a truth, it's a truth, this heroic nihilism.
It's a truth that it's all bottomless and ungrounded and non-representable, and can't, and that is a truth that just like that, no normal mortal human being can tolerate it.
That's what Balkington is supposed to be.
It's like Leitzene, Nietzsche.
Because Nietzsche says all these things about the Oberman, the free spirit, that sound just like Balkington, except Nietzsche keeps telling you he's joyful.
And I think Melville wants to say he's pictured him, and he's not joyful.
He's grim, and we don't want to be like that.
And I think that's a great move on Melville's part.
So the Oberman is grim and perishes in the Holy Infinite, and that's that.
That is, there is this extreme possibility of the absence of all meaning.
Don't even trust any divine glimmers.
Take no comfort from any interpretation.
Confront the indefinite head-on.
You'd have no hierarchies, no center, no even gods, no meaning, no land, and that's just not going to work.
And so Balkington is never mentioned again.
But then this is the last thing to say for this lecture.
But if we've rejected onto theology on the one hand, which is the land and the, so to speak, the religions that have an answer, and we rejected heroic nihilism, so what can heal us?
A lot of the rest of the book is about what can heal us, what can save us in the end.
And his answer really is: it's going to be a kind of polytheism.
I didn't expect to read this to you, but I feel it's so interesting and important.
Yes, I just opened to it, probably because I look at it every once in a while.
Because I was just, when I said it was polytheistic as I was reading it, because of the moods and all that, I never would have believed that Melville would just say it, but on 336, if hereafter a highly cultured, poetical nation shall lure back to their birthright the Merry May Day gods of old, though that's the pantheon, and lie and livingly enthrone them again in the now egotistical sky, that means the sky that's become just our technological sort of projection.
In the now unhaunted hill, that is the hill that's, the phrase he's unhaunted?
Is his phrase.
The famous phrase from Weber is the disenchanted.
So disenchanted nature.
Then, to be sure, exalted to Jove's high seat, Zeus's high seat, the great sperm whale shall lord it.
So the picture is that where does the meaning come from?
Instead of standing in Allen Gale of the Infinite, it comes from a pantheon of moods or gods in which there is the ultimate God, namely Zeus, who isn't representable.
He's like Moby Dick.
To the people who've had the Course, you will recognize this isn't Homer's God, since you can sort of see and hear Zeus and so forth.
This is Aeschylus' God, where Aeschylus says that he doesn't know what God is.
God is sort of what's behind everything.
It never comes into the light.
That's Melville's understanding.
So you'll get a pantheon of gods.
You'll get a spectrum of moods, which he compares to the rainbow.
You get as much meaning as you can from all of them.
And you preserve them by seeing God is the indefinite, the boundless, the unrepresentable.
Okay, now I've done my job of catching up on the lecture.
Thank you all for coming.