Okay, then I'm going to go back, starting with Pip, and then I'm going to go on and talk about Ahab, which I've been putting off.
And then I'm going to talk about three different ways to get meaning in your life after the you don't you can't believe in this mono mono meaning anymore and that well that's what that's today's assign I mean that's what I want to cover today and it's all and and also one of those is about moods so I want to talk about the the mood on one of the on the Enderby one of the ships that they meet but first Pip is so important I want to go back and send it's been so long a week since we talked about Pip and we ended saying what I thought was interesting stuff about the sense in which he's a bat that I want to get back to so let's just start by reviewing Pip so what why is he so important well because he actually saw what goes on that makes the he saw creation he saw God's foot upon the treadle of the womb the womb is the way everything gets woven together to create the I don't know what to say the world the universe the creation it's it's I don't there's no word for it I guess then I Melville says the something orbs as I call I think where is it now so he was at the bottom of 401 carried down alive to wondrous depths where strange shapes of the unwarped wrapped unwrapped when I read these things aloud I suddenly, discover words that I don't expect.
Unwrapped primal world.
Am I seeing it right?
I'm dyslexic, but it certainly looks like unwrapped.
Unwarped?
Unwrapped.
Unwarped.
That's better.
Although it's still pretty mysterious.
At least it's what's there.
The unwarped primal world glided to and fro before his passive eyes, and the miser merman wisdom revealed his horrid hoarded heaps.
And among the joyous, heartless, ever juvenile eternities, Pip saw, and now comes what?
These crucial things, the multitudinous God-omnipresent coral insects that out of the firmament of waters heaved the colossal orbs.
The colossal orbs is his word, since he can't say creation, because that's for the Christians, and he can't say universe because the scientists have taken it over.
And I don't think he should say world, because world is something that human beings are in, like the business world or the academic world.
So he's got a problem, and he solves it in this interesting way.
So out, so he see, and the coral insects are these fat, the are, what can you say?
That it amounts to a kind of random activity on these insects that don't know what they're doing, which, because they all do it, produces, guess what?
Another rainbow, the coral.
And that's pretty weird and amazing talk.
He saw, and he goes on, he saw God's foot upon the treadle of the loom.
There's this Melville belief that the bottom line is a kind of random gathering of, period, of anything and everything that produces this world or universe, well, this bunch of orbs that we live in.
So he saw the foot upon the treadle of the loom and spoke it, and his therefore his shipmates called him mad.
And we might as well go on because it's all Nelville-y here.
So man's insanity is heaven's sense.
I don't know what that means.
I think it means, I mean, what looks like insanity to the people who see Pip is really a sense that Pip has seen more than anybody else deeply into the nature of things.
And wandering from all mortal reason, man comes at last to that celestial thought which to reason is absurd and frantic and wheeled and woe, feels then uncompromised, indifferent as his God.
Boy, when Nelville is on to these very deep things, he writes, I'm sure he writes without thinking at all, but he's tuned in in his moody way to something which he expresses in this brilliant, beautiful, and barely comprehensible story about what Pip saw.
And I want to repeat that it's so interesting that he saw the sort of random activity of the coral insects, which with no plan, but which kind of accidentally seems to produce all these orbs and all these rainbow of meanings.
But what he saw blew his mind.
He can't understand it.
I think this paragraph is probably supposed to blow your mind in the same way.
And all he's got left is pure openness.
He's lost his identity.
He's lost his perspective.
He doesn't have any perspective anymore.
He's open to all interpretations because he has no interpretation of his own.
That gets us up to where we were last time, which is how he interprets the chapter about the Debloon.
Only, where am I?
I am lost.
Oh, no, I'm not.
Okay.
So in the no, no, I see.
I'm quoting on 500 at the top.
I'm just arguing at this point that he's got no identity.
He says, Pip, whom call ye Pip?
Pip jumped from the whale boat.
Pip's missing.
And that means, that's what I mean by saying it blew his mind.
He can't think anymore.
He has no identity anymore.
But that enables him to give this amazing interpretation of the doubloon.
And now what I don't see, help me find the doubloon chapter.
I didn't mark it, oddly enough.
4 what?
415?
Okay, well that's what we want.
And now at the end, we get Pip.
The thing I want to comment on is 420.
But I want to say that how totally blank Pip is.
I think you get the impression, I don't know any quote for it, but not only does he see that everything is an interpretation, well, the Debloon chapter is the quote for it.
It looks like he understands that everything is an interpretation.
Remember, I look, we look, they look, and so forth.
Everybody sees a totally different interpretation in the Debloom, which represents the world, and that there aren't even better and worse interpretations.
Because usually people who have this kind of interpretation view, people whose names you won't recognize, but Charles Taylor and Alexander Nahamis, famous philosophers who talk about Nietzsche's view that everything is interpretation, make a big fuss about that there are good and bad interpretations.
But I think Pip has seen the sort of total randomness of the way all this hangs together, although it all hangs together, it's woven together, but I don't think he has any sense of better and worse interpretations.
And that's really no wonder he went mad.
I mean, there's just no place from which to understand anything for him.
So he just says, and this is what we read it last time on 420, I look, you look, he looks, we look, ye look, they look, and so forth.
And he says it three times.
And I've just said what I think it means.
But now comes these funny lines where we stopped last time.
And you've got to be aware of overinterpreting all this, but I'll do my I'll do I'll give you an interpretation.
We talked about it.
They they're all bats.
I, you, and he and we and ye and they are all bats.
I'm a crow, especially when I stand at the top of this pine tree here.
Well, one reason they're all bats is they are blind and crazy, all of them, because each of them runs up to the doubloon and, in spite of the fact that the other ones have given it a totally other interpretation, gives it as if it was the only right interpretation, their interpretation.
Each of them, Stubb and Flast, and Ahab and Starbuck.
And what Pip sees, what Ishmael Melville sees, is that there's just a plurality of interpretations.
None of them's right, none of them's better.
And nobody sees that except Pip when he's at the top of the mast.
I think now, I used to think that Pip saw the same thing as Ishmael saw.
But I think Ishmael isn't viewing the whole thing from some external sort of meta-perspective the way Pip is.
Pip hasn't got his own perspective, but when he's up in the crow's nest, he sees there are all these perspectives, they're all equal.
And when he sees that, he's not in any of them.
And he's not able to get into any of them.
That's the sense in which he's gotten no identity anymore.
And so that Ishmael is able to get into all of them, or at least many of them.
He also sees that there are many interpretations, has many moods, but he's always in one or another.
He isn't crazy, and he hasn't lost his identity, and so forth.
And there's a big difference between the two.
But Pip's got a sort of valid meta-interpretation.
I mean, he really does see from an open, totally receptive position or something like that, the way the whole thing works.
He sees it from the very bottom at the ocean, and then he goes up and he sees where the insects are making all these weird colors.
And then he goes to the top of the crow's at the crow's nest and he sees the whole thing from the top.
So he's seen more than anybody.
And that's important.
And he says, and now this is when somebody said and gave me a hard time, that they're all bats.
I'm just looking at my notes.
I still believed when I wrote these notes this morning that his view was the same as Ishmael's.
I don't believe it anymore.
But now, how can he say that he's a bat?
He's seen it, he's seen everything, as I say, from the top to the bottom.
And you can't really say he's understood it, because it's not understandable.
It's supposed to blow your mind when you read it.
But he somehow got it from the top to the bottom.
Even though he can't understand it or say it, he does live it, namely, in his crazy way.
But he's not really crazy.
He's got heaven's sense.
He's got, again, that's another way to put it.
He's got the ultimate perspective on everything, which isn't even a perspective anymore.
And he's not crazy.
And he's not blind.
The other people are all blind as bats.
Or they're bats in the sense of your batty, crazy.
But I don't think either one of those fits him.
So why is he a bat?
Well, here's where I risk, I worried about that.
This is where we ended with me running after you, sort of yelling at the last lines.
And I went back and listened to that part of the podcast for saying, I don't know what to say.
It's very interesting.
I wonder in what sense he's a bat.
And somebody said, who said it?
He sees in the dark, bats see in the dark.
Okay, good.
I think that's the right thing to say.
That's not being crazy, and that's not being blind.
But what I found was a quote to back up that view of yours.
I mean, I felt uneasy just, I thought, well, that's a nice association of bats, but we've already got two.
That's blind is a bat, and batty, now we're supposed to believe a third association about bats.
Well, it is true that Melville thinks that on 52, he says darkness is the proper element of our essences, about 20 lines down.
So if he's a bat, it's because he's in the dark, but he's in the dark, not sort of bumping into things, but somehow deeply understanding things.
That's all that's about two-thirds down on 52.
I don't know if that's the right answer, but at least it's an answer.
If I saw it on a paper, I'd be impressed.
So I think we should stick with it unless anybody comes up with anything better.
So, okay, now I've finished talking about Pip and reviewing and going a little further.
I'm ready to go on to the next one.
And the transition is on 501.
It goes right naturally from Pip to Ahab.
And that's the last thing of that chapter in which Pip is the main character.
And then comes the end.
There go two daft ones now, muttered the Manxman.
Remember, they think Pip is crazy, but we don't think Pip is crazy, and Melville doesn't think he's crazy.
But anyway, there goes two daft ones now, muttered the old Manxman.
One daft with strength, the other daft with weakness.
Well, he's crazy with weakness in the sense that he's lost the capacity to interpret anything.
That's, again, the openness, the non-identity, the sheer receptivity that he's got.
It certainly is a kind of craziness and a kind of weakness, and that's all that the Manxman can understand of it.
But now, all I want to do is use that to make a transition to Ahab.
We haven't talked about Ahab, who is certainly crazy with strength.
Only what in the world his craziness consists in, and in what way its strength, is what we want to talk about.
But I just want to make sure before we leave Pip, because it's so interesting and obscure and fundamental, that there isn't some other bright remarks brewing somewhere that I should learn from.
You don't have to have an opinion.
It's pretty hard to have an opinion, but just in case you do, I don't want to miss it.
Okay, well, then I'm going on.
And yeah, good.
Kevin.
But you've got to yell real loud.
I can't hear you.
In the crow's nest, he's here.
That's right.
He sees it from the point of view of the crow's nest.
Well, he's seen.
I'm not sure why that's important when you're saying he's at a point where he doesn't get involved at all.
Maybe you're sort of agreeing with Anson, in anything.
He has no perspective, no goal.
He's not in charge of anything.
So what are you saying about it?
He can see it, and he can't control it, and in a certain way, he can't even understand it because there are all these conflicting perspectives.
We just saw in the case of the doubloon, and all these people are running around, each one in their world doing their thing in their mood.
He can see it, but so he doesn't do anything with it.
I mean, it doesn't seem to need a help.
What don't I?
He just accepts it.
Okay, I think he accepts it, but I think he sees that everybody's crazy, everybody's giving interpretations, everybody thinks their interpretation is the interpretation.
That's what he sees.
Okay, and that's what he sees from above all these interpretations, because he doesn't have an interpretation, and he's the only one who doesn't have an interpretation, except perhaps for Ishmael.
And Ishmael, it isn't that Ishmael has no interpretations, he has them all, the rainbow.
He has lots of interpretations.
And that's not what we're interested in at this point.
Let me go on.
If you have more to tell me about it, come and tell me.
Okay, I'm ready to go to Ahab.
Now, Ahab is called, I'll give you the quote later, a monomaniac.
I mean, I think he's the kind he's a monotheist, but a kind of no normal kind of monotheist.
But he wants, he demands one answer to the meaning of the universe.
So he's a monomaniac monotheist.
That's his job in the book, so to speak.
It's more, it's not that he has what he thinks is the answer the way the Presbyterians do and the philosophers and the scientists, all of those are mono people too.
But he thinks there must be an answer to the one single meaning of the universe, and he absolutely demands the answer.
He can't stand the indefiniteness of not knowing.
So he's sort of the drive toward, he's the monomaniac drive toward monotheism in the book.
And I just have to tell you, but you should be able to figure this out.
I don't want to give away too much of the plot.
Of course, he's very dangerous.
And Melville thinks that this kind of monomaniac monotheism is some sort of disaster in the culture and some kind of sickness in human beings that's gotten really out of control in our culture.
So now, but now we have to look at Ahab in more detail.
And again, he's very sort of obscure and confusing.
Melville's treatment of Ahab is certainly not my favorite thing in the book.
I can't understand, but I'll do my best to lay out what I can understand.
What is in detail Ahab up to?
I mean, that he's got this big problem that he demands to understand the meaning of it all.
That's clear enough.
But his way of going about sort of expressing this problem is very obscure and confused.
And maybe it's that way on purpose.
Maybe that's what Melville wants us to see.
But so after, here I wrote: after 2,000 years in the West of onto theological answers, starting with really the Aeneid already, where Rome and Augustus were the meaning of it all, leading it, it all led up to them, and certainly in Dante, where it all culminated, as you know, in this one total picture of the universe, every detail created by God to bound as in one volume and so forth.
After 2,000 years of that, people have become addicted to that.
This is sort of Nietzsche's view, but I also think it's Melville's.
And Ahab is addicted to that.
And he doesn't, he's a whole hero ahead of Peleg and Bildad, who are just Orthodox Christians, for instance, who think it's easy to get an answer to the meaning of it all.
He's not satisfied with any of the answers that come down from this tradition through the institutions and how people are brought up and in the language and everything.
He wants a personal answer which gives him evidence, personal evidence, finding out what's really going on in this world.
So you're going to, but now it becomes what's weird about him.
He's going to try to force the, I guess I'll call it the universe, because that turns out to be a word that goes back to the Latin already, I think I told you, and it doesn't, it was only modern science now has taken it over.
So it means this meaningless but law-governed thing, the big expanding thing that we're in.
But I'm going to use universe for God, some more general term.
So he's going to force the universe, or maybe God, if there is a God, to give this answer, or he's going to find out for sure there isn't.
And if there is a God, he wants to find out whether he's a good God or a bad God.
And then there's this further complication.
I'm saying all this ahead of time, and I will give you the quotes to back it up.
He wants assurance that this God, if there is one, takes account of Ahab, that Ahab matters in the universe.
All that he wants to settle.
And his way of going about settling it is to try to provoke this God or gods or whatever, the force, whatever it is, provoke it into manifesting itself and manifesting whether it's good or bad.
That's what he's trying to do.
And this is tied up in a very peculiar way, which I think I understand, but if I do, it's funny because nobody else does.
But you'll see, you can judge for yourself in a minute.
This is all, of course, tied up with somehow with the fact that he's lost his leg to Moby Dick.
You've got to get a very thick stew of ideas and issues that are involved here.
And Ahab, I'm still sort of giving you the background, can't stand uncertainty.
That's just another way to put this.
This question has been answered, and he's done have his answer, and he needs an answer.
You get this, for instance, on way off back in 453, but nothing about the plot is given away.
I just want to read you a little quote: Ahab says to the carpenter, two-thirds of the way down.
He has a vice, you know, the kind of thing carpenters have to squeeze things.
This is a cogent vice thou hast, Carpenter.
Let me feel its grip once.
So, so it does pinch some.
Oh, sir, it will break bones.
Beware, beware.
No fear, I like a good grip.
I like to feel something in this slippery world that could hold, man.
That's it.
He wants something solid.
He wants an answer.
He doesn't want this constant play of interpretations and rainbows.
That's just a short version of it.
It comes up, I'll show you again how it comes up with Quequeg, that clear demand on his part.
And that clear demand on his part, it isn't me that's calling him a monomaniac.
I don't know how many times, but he's called a monomaniac, but at least on 177, where they were talking about his losing his leg at the bottom paragraph, is it not probable that this monomania in him took its instant rise at the precise time of his bodily dismemberment?
So now we've got the problem of how to get all that together.
And so here, we're now going to talk about things that Ahab does because, well, no, we're going to just first give you a description of Ahab.
I really haven't ever done that.
I've told you sort of his metaphysical demand.
On 118, you get a description of him as the kind of person that he is, the middle of 118.
There was an infinity of firmest fortitude, a determinate, unsurrenderable willfulness in the fixed and fearless forward dedication of that glance.
Not a word he spoke, nor did his officers and so forth.
And then a little further down, and not only at the end of the paragraph, and not only that, but moody, good old moods again.
Moody, stricken Ahab.
He's stuck in one mood is another way to describe.
Moody, and that's part of being a monomaniac.
Moody-stricken Ahab stood before them with a crucifixion in his face and all the nameless, regal, overbearing dignity of some mighty woe.
So now we have to, that's way back at the beginning of the book.
And you might think the mighty woe is, after all, Moby did bit off his leg, but it's that's part of it.
But I'm trying to prepare you for the idea that his really mighty woe is that he absolutely wants a firm grip on things, a real answer, a ground, and so forth, something like the land, but he wants it at sea and he wants it total.
I mean, he is from Nantucket, which is trying to turn the land in the sea into the land.
And there is that side of him, and always.
So now, oh, there's another place I wrote down that he can't stand uncertainty.
It may be the Queque one.
No, that's the one I just read.
Okay, I did that.
So he manifests a lot of strange activity.
And the prophet talks about that at one point that they run into before they board the boat.
And I want to talk about that for a moment.
This is before, and I want to emphasize that it's important, that this is before Mohi ever encounters Moby Dick and loses his way.
He's already got a, so to speak, chip on his shoulder vis-a-vis the universe.
He's already doing everything he can by a kind of defiance to get the universe to declare, one, whether it's good or evil, and two, whether he's important or not.
So it starts on 89, where you hear a lot of the weird things he's done prior to Moby Dick.
The top of 89, the bottom of 89.
The prophets saying all the things they don't know about Ahab.
But nothing about that thing that happened to him off Cape Horn long ago when he lay like dead for three days and nights.
I have no idea what that is.
And as far as I know, it's never mentioned again, so I can't tell you.
But there's plenty of other stuff.
Nothing about the deadly skirmish with the Spaniards before the altar in Spain.
Now, I suppose he was going to desecrate the altar, and they stopped him.
Because if you go on, nothing about the silver calabash he spat into.
He spits into the holy water.
It's getting clearer that he's trying to provoke.
And nothing about his losing his leg last voyage, according to the prophecy.
That's the last of the outrageous things that's happened to him.
And Ahab says that he's trying to provoke the gods to show themselves and define what the universe is like.
On 161, about two-thirds down, he says to the gods, whom he doesn't know whether there are any, you've knocked me down, and I am up again, but ye have run and hidden.
Come forth from behind your cotton bags.
So the meaning of the universe and whether there are any gods is hidden, according to Ahab on 161, and he's going to make it give an answer.
Now, we get to see this in first person, I mean, real life, so to speak, not just told by the prophet.
Ahab says, now we're on way on 486, two-thirds of the way down.
He's holding on to the lightning rod, and lightning is striking, a kind of feet lightning, ocean lightning effect.
And he says, O thou clear spirit of clear fire, whom on these seas I as a Persian once did worship.
Heaven only knows what that means.
Here in the sacramental act, so burned by thee that to this hour I bear the scar.
He does have a scar on his face.
I now know thee, thou clear spirit.
I know that thy right worship is defiance.
And so this is sort of summing up.
That's what the fight over with the Spanish was.
That's what spitting in the silver calabash was.
That's what the fight before the altar was.
They were all defiance.
And at the bottom, about 10 lines from the bottom, in the midst of the personified impersonal, a personality stands here.
And that's again to say, in effect, pay attention to me.
You want to say something?
Good.
What?
What page am I on?
Sorry, 486 at the bottom.
Well, two-thirds down.
Oh, thou clear spirit.
You see where I am now?
Okay, good.
Just stop me when I go too fast or forget to mention the page.
So, where are we now?
So he's holding on to the lightning rod, and he said, when he says all that, he's defying the gods.
He wants to provoke God into striking him down with the lightning or striking him down for spitting in the holy water.
And why?
Well, because one, that will show that there was some meaning in the universe, namely that by some ultimate standard he had done something absolutely unacceptable, and that Ahab was important, that the universe wasn't just totally blank and meaningless, that the fact that there was some meaning gave him a meaning, namely, he was being responded to because what he did was important.
And now, all this turns, I think, around how you read his encounter with Moby Gate.
I think I can make sense of this in a way that nothing I've seen about this makes sense of it if you understand how he experienced the losing his leg.
So, way back on 177, you've got to have some careful reading, but it's not all that subtle.
Really, it knocks you in the face.
But let's read it.
At the top of 177.
And then it was, this is Ahab was going after the Moby Dick, and they were close to the whale.
And then it was that suddenly, sweeping his sickle-shaped jaw beneath him, Moby Dick had reaped away Ahab's leg as a mower, a blade of grass in the field.
No turban Turk, no hired Venetian or Malay could have smote him with more seeming malice.
Now, I think it's very important and interesting to ask yourself: is there something odd about those two sentences?
You figure it out.
Surprise to the first person who sees that there's something wrong with those chairs.
They capture how it looks to Ahab, and it's a contradiction.
See the contradiction?
How does the mower relate to a blade of grass in the field?
There couldn't be a more indifferent relationship.
The mower isn't interested in the blade of grass.
The mower doesn't even know he's cutting down this particular blade of grass.
There is nothing vindictive in any relation.
So look at that.
He takes away his leg like a mower of blade of grass in the field, and then no turban Turk could have smote him with more seeming malice.
Now, do you think the mower has malice for the great blade of grass?
I think what you're supposed to see there is that Ahab doesn't know whether the meaning, the universe is completely meaningless, and the whole thing that happened to him with Moby Dick and his leg has no sense like a mower with a blade of grass.
But he wants it to be a confrontation with Moby Dick in which he gets to experience Moby Dick representing the universe and God for him that it's malevolent and that it's directed at him.
That's how he interprets it.
But it's a crazy interpretation.
And it's, and that's why, I think, and I think there are texts that support it, but I have to wait till the chase of Moby Dick.
But why he's chasing Moby Dick is to settle once and for all which of those two incompatible sentences is right.
Once, if he could only confront Moby Dick again, he'd find out whether Moby Dick and the universe were completely indifferent to him and what happened to him made no sense.
Or he could have an eyeball-to-eyeball confrontation with Moby Dick, get recognized by Moby Dick, and Moby Dick could go after him definitely, maliciously, and so forth.
That would be fine for Ahab.
That would be a solid answer, like getting your finger pinched in the vice.
It may be an answer that hurts, but it doesn't matter.
It's an answer.
And he hasn't got an answer from this first encounter.
But it says, Going, Small reason was there to doubt then that ever since that almost fatal encounter, Ahab had cherished a wild vindictiveness against the whale.
And that it's hard to understand.
I mean, if it's if he cut in, if he swallowed the leg in this blade of grassway, it would be fine.
I mean, it would make sense if he did it with malice.
And I don't think Ahab knows.
But he has a wild vindictiveness against the whale all the more fell for him in his all the more what?
What?
I'll try reading it again.
Small reason was there to doubt then that ever since that almost fatal encounter, Ahab had cherished a wild vindictiveness against the whale.
All the more fell for him in his frantic morbidness.
He at last came to am I reading it right?
I can't, does it make sense?
Am I got the grammar?
All the more fell for him that oh, fell, is there such a word?
I mean, such an adjective.
Okay, wow, got a big vocabulary there.
All the more fell for him in his frantic mindedness.
He at last came to identify with him not only all his bodily woes, but all his intellectual and spiritual exasperations, namely not getting an answer about the universe.
The white whale swam before him as the monomaniac back again, incarnation of all those malicious agencies which some deep men feel eating them.
See, it's getting more and more murky.
I mean, he's blaming Obi-Dick for going after him.
He's describing it as if it was vindictive.
And now he's thinking that the whale is sort of the center of all that makes him unhappy.
I'll go on.
The last part of that paragraph.
All that most maddens and torments, all that stirs up the leaves of things, all truth with malice in it.
We're back to that.
All that cracks the sinews and cakes the brain, all the subtle demonisms of life and thought, all evil to crazy Ahab were visibly personified and made practically assailable in Moby Dick.
He piled upon the whale's white hump the sum of all the general rage and hate felt by his whole race from Adam down, and then, as if his chest had been a mortar, he burst his heart's shell upon it.
More marvelous Melville prose.
What seems to be going on is he projects onto Moby Dick all the meaning and malice of the universe, and at least it's an answer.
I mean, if it were, if he could be sure that Moby Dick was malevolent and after him, that would be, he would have a goal in life, so to speak.
He could go and fight Moby Dick.
And he does have a goal in life, but, and this is what I'm trying to say, but I see you all looking puzzled, but I can't do it any more clearly.
Maybe you can.
His goal really is to make sure whether what happened with Moby Dick and his leg was sheer meaningless accident or was proof that there was a meaning and he was the center of the universe and it was after him and so forth.
And the reason I say this is that when he explains what he's doing to Starbuck, I have to find that now.
Let's see.
Since he can't stand uncertainty of I I keep getting going around in circles about that quote I think.
Ah, I'm looking at the wrong page.
So, 118.
Is that it?
I want to strike through the mask.
Is that 157?
Okay, good.
Let's find it.
Because it isn't as if he knows already what.
Yeah, okay, that's it.
Thanks.
First, let's say what Starbucks says is important.
But let me get up to this.
So he says to, I want to just make sure that I read what leads up to this.
Okay, there.
The gods have hidden themselves.
He holds onto the lightning rod.
And that's his first encounter.
I just read it.
And now Starbucks' view, 157.
Starbuck takes the view of the, you know, the mower and the blade of grass.
Vengeance on a dumb brute, cried Starbuck, that simply smoked thee from blindest instinct.
Madness to be enraged with a dumb thing, Captain Ahab, seems blasphemous.
Okay, now does Ahab say, I know that he did it out of malice, and then in other words, believe the second sentence?
Or does he really reveal that he doesn't know which?
And he has to go find Moby Dick again and settle this.
And that's what he says, in effect.
Hark ye again, a little lower layer.
All visible objects, man, are but postcard masks.
But in each event, in the living act, the undoubted deed, there's some unknown but still reasoning thing puts forth the molding of its features from behind the unreasoning mask.
If man will strike, strike through the mask.
This is what he's trying to do when he gets his harpoon to Moby Dick, if he ever does.
How can the prisoner reach outside except by thrusting through the wall?
To me, the white whale is that wall, shoved near to me.
Sometimes I think there's naught beyond.
You see, he hasn't really settled the question whether Moby Dick has any mind at all.
That tis enough.
He tasks me, he heaps me.
I see in him outrageous strength with an inscrutable malice sinewing it.
The inscrutable thing is chiefly what I hate.
And that's everything's in there.
That he thinks that he sometimes he thinks that it's not malicious at all.
It's just a dumb brute.
Sometimes he thinks that it's malicious.
He hasn't settled the question.
So he has to chase Moby Dick around the world, as he says later.
Literally, he does, around South America, into the Pacific, from Nantucket, to settle the question.
Yeah, go ahead.
I think I agree with you, but I have trouble hearing you.
Just say it again.
What's the malice, according to you?
Okay, good.
Ah, that's exactly right.
Yes, there's a place, I have to find it right away now because you just said it.
There's a place where he talks about something like demonic indifference.
I mean, it could be, and I'll find it in the course of going through here, I think, that the most malicious thing that Moby Dick could do is to take off his leg in a way that doesn't make any sense and doesn't take him as serious as a person, but just does it accidentally.
That very way of treating him is for him a kind of maliciousness.
That's one way to read it.
Because Moby Dick did this thing to him, which is the worst thing you could possibly do to him.
Ignore him and take off his leg without even noticing it.
And that's somehow it's so confusing.
How could he do that on purpose?
But it's as if he maliciously ignored him.
And that's there are lines like that.
That seems to be what drives him crazy.
Yeah.
Well, kill it is too simple.
I mean, he wants to strike through the mask.
I mean, killing it just means killing it.
No, he somehow wants to find out whether Moby Dick is, who stands a member for the universe, has some meaning, has some goal, which is the source of all the evil and suffering in the world, and moreover, has something in for him, Ahab.
So that's more than just killing it.
That's somehow, he wants somehow an eyeball-to-eyeball confrontation with Moby Dick in which it will be clear whether Moby Dick is after him or not.
And that's what he's been, and he literally has pursued Moby Dick around the world to get that.
And what I don't want to tell you, because I want you to read it for yourself, because it's so fantastic, what he finally gets when he gets to Moby Dick.
Yeah.
That's right.
And he spent.
And he just can't stand it.
Yes.
Okay, good.
That's right.
That's good.
I wonder if Melville, no, Auguste, he couldn't have known this.
He had to figure it out on his own.
How many have read Notes from Underground?
People do often.
Well, it's the kind, except that this guy, it's interesting, those of you who have read it, I mean, Ahab is like the guy at Notes from Underground, only with a lot more sort of energy and directedness and so forth, because the Notes from Underground guy just sort of broods about it.
But Ahab goes out and chases Moby Dick all over them.
It's as if the guy goes out to try to kill the guy who bumped into him.
And it is what happened here.
But the basic insult that he bumped into him without even noticing looks like exactly what it is to cut off the leg without it noticing like a mower the grass in the field.
And that is, I agree with both of you, the most infuriating thing is the indifference, the seeming indifference.
And that's why he spits in the calabash, and that's why he holds onto the lightning rod, and that's why he pursues Moby Dick around the world, because he can't stand this indifference.
He wants to settle it with Moby Dick.
Okay, let me go back to where we are.
So we got the response, 0157, to Starbuck saying, no, we've got to figure out what the universe is really about, and we've got to do it by confronting Moby Dick.
And he hates it and he thinks that it must be malicious, and that's all we got there.
We've got to force an answer from the universe.
And there must be one total meaning.
That's the monomania of him.
And of course, just on the side, it makes Ahab miss all the meaning that there is, this monomaniac quits from Moby Dick.
There is a place, I won't try to turn to it now, where Ahab is thinking of his wife and going home to domestic satisfaction back in Nantucket.
Just before he left, he married a young woman, as I recall.
I haven't looked back at that part, but I see now.
But he can't enjoy that kind of human meaning and satisfaction because he's got this monomaniac thing about Moby Dick.
As soon as he starts thinking about his wife, the farcy double that he has, I can't tell you more about, but he comes back at the end of the book too, comes by, and he sees the shadow in the water, and he stops thinking about the wife.
It's just, I mean, it's, it's, once you get in this kind of obsession, nothing else matters to you.
Every bit of meaning is gone.
I mean, this is again the sort of essence of monotheism, according to Melville, is a kind of monomania which focuses on the total meaning of everything and loses the meaning of anything specific.
I can explain that in just a second, which I will.
But just for it first.
And it's interesting, just I'd say here to relate Ahab to Balkington.
Ahab is really sort of the absolute opposite of Baltington.
Starbuck is just not on their dimension.
He's happily accepting his Christian monotheism about the universe, but he's a pious believing Christian.
Balkington was this kind of demigod because he totally accepted meaninglessness.
And Ahab has this kind of godlike quality because he totally refuses to accept meaninglessness.
And Ishmael, and that's now another aspect of it.
What does Ishmael think about this?
This is as far from Ishmael's way of life as you could get, both the Balkington story and the Balking story and what.
And I guess Ahab's quest are the two.
I mean, they are, so Balking accepts meaninglessness, and Ahab can't accept it.
I think that's what I was trying to say.
But what I want to say now is that Ishmael is so, and this is so interesting and important, able to get into any mood, even a mood as far from him as you could get.
Because after all, I mean, this Ahab obsessing to find the one answer to forgetting every other little bit of meaning and sacredness and comfort and everything in the world for that couldn't be further than Ishmael.
And yet, on 171, chapter 41, he gets into the mood of Ahab.
When Ahab does his thing and puts the harpoon in the blood and makes the harpooners all swear to go after Moby Dick, that chapter 41, I, Ishmael, was one with that crew.
My shouts had gone up with the rest.
My oath had been welded with theirs.
And stronger I shouted, and more did I hammer and clinch my oath because of the dread in my soul.
A wild, mystical, sympathetic feeling was in me.
Ahab's quenchless feud-themed mine.
With greedy ears, I learned the history of that murderous monster against whom I and all the others had taken our oath of violence and revenge.
The crucial thing is, he has a sympathetical feeling.
He gets even into the Ahab mood.
He's able to get into every mood.
And there is also a place where I think, but I couldn't find the quote that he talks about Ahab's tragic greatness.
If anybody finds that as you read along, try to remember and tell it to me, because I think that's his being on Ahab's side, so to speak, sometimes.
Okay, now it's time to stop because that's for Ahab.
I mean, I'm ready to go on, but first we have to see whether anybody wants to say anything about Ahab.
Yeah.
Serious what?
Yes, he has all these weird people inside his head.
In Starbucks' head.
No, Starbucks is just a strange, not a strange.
He's perfectly normal, boring, pious Christian.
Yes, yes, that's right.
But he never gets him to appreciate him the way Melville appreciates him.
What Starbucks says, I happen to know that little piece by heart.
My soul is more than matched.
She's over-manned and by a madman, insufferable sporing that I should ground sanity in such a field or something like that.
Starbuck admits that he was not converted by Ahab, it's simply sort of overwhelmed by Ahab.
And he, Starbuck, is criticized by Ishmael for not having killed Ahab, who's endangering the whole crew, but he's just, I can remember the quote too: something like: he's weakened by his Christian piety, or something like that.
That keeps him from being able to shoot Ahab, which he almost does, but just can't bring himself to do.
Yeah.
I'll say that again.
Again, I have to come up so I can hear you.
Yes.
The whale just manifests itself as.
That's right.
He would, that's right.
The whale is the sort of focus because he can't stand the indifference, both because he wants a final meaning and because he doesn't want to be just nobody.
He wants to be recognized as sort of the confrontation between him and the source of the final meaning.
So his monomania consists both in insisting on having a final meaning, triple thing, also insisting on being recognized by the universe as important and putting all that on Moby Dick.
I mean, those three things are all part of the monomania and all come out of the way his leg was cut off, which was, I think, supposed to be, I mean, we're told, cut off with complete indifference, like a mower cutting down a blade of grass in the field.
That's what happened.
And all the rest of it is his crazy projection onto what happened.
I mean, that's how I read those two sentences.
The first sentence is a fact.
Moby Dick cut off his leg the way a mower cuts down a blade of grass in the field.
He's a dumb brute, the way Starbuck says.
And the second sentence is how it seemed to Ahab.
Nothing could be more malicious.
And then we've got his point: that, and you can either say malicious because it really, really aimed at Ahab and thought Ahab was important and hated Ahab and was going to hurt him, or malicious because it made it clear, completely clear to Ahab, that nobody cared about Ahab and that Moby Dick was completely indifferent to Ahab.
Either one is outrageous for Ahab.
That the universe is out to get him is outrageous, but he would like that.
That the universe isn't out to get him, you'd think that would be comforting, but that makes him even more unhappy.
This is what I mean by this being complicated.
I guess it's not confused.
Every once in a while, I think I can state it clearly.
I mean, that's the two things on Ahab's mind that get sort of intertwined all the time: the meaning of the universe and his importance, his place in it.
And it all gets heaped up on Moby Dick.
And period.
I'm going to go on.
Okay?
The next thing I want to talk about, and it'll take talking next time too.
So now, I have to switch completely and talk about things that I could talk about without going into the exciting ending events.
And the general topic is: where can you find meaning in a sort of random, meaningless world?
Random in that it was just the coral insects wandering around that made these orbs.
And the weaving has no plan.
There's nothing specific being woven.
And yet, and of course, Valkington sees that this, thinks this is just sheer meaningless.
And it certainly is sort of indefinite and indeterminate.
But can't you somehow find meaning anyway?
That's the interesting question, because Ishmael is clearly not a fan of Balkington's and not a fan of Ahab most of the time trying to make sure you get a meaning.
So here goes three different ways that you can get meaning in your life and in your world according to the way Ishmael has set it up.
One of them is what I'm calling the pagan.
That is, there's something about those civilizations, if you can call them that, those societies or something, that have been totally uncorrupted by monotheism, by the whole idea that there should be one unified answer for everybody.
They can have a culture in which you can lead a totally sublime, meaningful life and die perfectly, contentedly.
And this all happens on 460.
The pagan person who lives in a sort of constant sacred mood, or I don't think it's one mood, who is attuned to the sacred in his way, which doesn't mean that it has to be one mood, I think, but it has to be something that he's got from his pagan religion.
This is on 460.
This is when Quequeg is dying, the middle of the page.
How he wasted and wasted away in those few long lingering days, till there seemed but little left of him but his frame and tattooing.
But as all else in him thinned and his cheekbones grew sharper, his eyes nevertheless seemed glowing fuller and fuller.
They became of a strange softness of luster, and mildly but deeply looking out at you there from his sickness, a wondrous testimony to the immortal health in him, which could not die or be weakened.
So he's got some kind of spiritual health, and he's a model of how to die and how to live.
Skipping down in the sort of about 15 lines from the bottom: no dying Chaldee or Greek had higher and holier thoughts than those whose mysterious shades you saw creeping over the face of poor Quequeg as he quietly lay in his swaying handle.
So there's something absolutely holy about his life.
Healed.
If anybody's healed of the sickness that seems to be almost universal, according to Melville, I don't know whether he thinks everybody's cracked about the head or everybody but virtuous pagans.
I think maybe he thinks everybody is, but the pagans managed to find a life in which you can heal.
He's holy, he's healed.
And that's because he's saved from non-total from totalizing religion so that he can see the sacred power of the various things in his religion.
And there are several features of Quequeg now that are very important.
This is Melville, one of Melville's attempts to show sort of what the ideal way to live in this meaningless universe is.
So, one, Kwequeg doesn't try to put his religion and his gods off on others.
That happens only if it all happens at all, because he gets corrupted by Christianity.
And even then, I don't think you see him ever trying to even get Ishmael to worship Yo-Yo.
That's Ishmael's idea.
And now comes a new element.
Kwequeg understands in a funny way, not an intellectual understanding, something about the sacredness of his own background practices.
There is that he's got an understanding of being, but a plural understanding of being, not a mono-one.
He was just socialized and raised up in a culture that has that, and he understands that that's sacred.
So, how do we see that?
Well, very peculiar.
When he's dying and he's in his coffin, he copies out the markings on his body.
This is Melville at his best, I think, because at least I can understand him.
And yet he's saying weird, far-out things.
At the 464 with the first full paragraph, with a wild, whimsic whimsiness, he now used his coffin, this is Kwequeg, for a sea chest and emptied into it his canvas bag of clothes and set them in order.
And now comes the part for us.
More spare hours he spent in carving the lid of all, carving the lid with all manner of grotesque figures and drawings.
And it seems that thereby he was striving in his rude way to copy parts of the twisted tattooing on his body.
Now, that's very interesting.
By the way, the coffin turns out to be very important and what's carved on it.
I can't tell you more about why for a while.
And this tattooing had been the work of a departed prophet and seer of his island, who, by those hieroglyphic marks, had written out on his body a complete theory of the heavens and the earth and a mystical treatise on the art of attaining truth.
So in his body, he contains, so to speak, an understanding of the universe.
Now, I think it's a big mistake to say a complete theory of the heavens.
That's too scientific and too modern.
Melville just slips up there.
He doesn't believe.
He says explicitly that he doesn't believe there's any complete theory of anything.
And that's right.
That's his view about science and everything else.
I don't know how he could do that.
But it is something like an understanding of the universe and our place in it.
That's the theory, that's what he has of the heaven and the earth and the art of attaining truth.
He's got all that carved on his body, but so that Kleeque in his own proper person was a riddle to behold, a wondrous work in one volume, but whose mysteries not even himself could read.
Now, what does that mean?
That's very weird.
What is Melville talking about?
And the answer is: we are all that, each of us have in our body an understanding of being that we get from our culture, which is in a certain way sacred because it thanks to it, anything shows up as anything.
And anything makes whatever makes sense to do makes sense to do.
I think I gave you examples last time, but I'll talk about it again a little.
We all stand a certain distance from each other in this culture, and that's related to how much whom we put our arms around, and that's related to what intimacy amounts to.
And I made another one here.
It's in the culture where women are submissive, then there's a whole understanding of their role in the world.
Then they don't have to think about it, they don't have to notice it, they won't think about it, they don't notice it, but they stand stooped over, they don't look people in the eye, they speak quietly, they follow behind their husband, they don't interrupt the men when they're talking seriously, and so forth.
That's the truth about women in the culture.
That's what it means.
And in those women, that truth is carved onto their bodies, and they don't understand it, they don't see it, they can't read it.
That's exactly what Melville has gotten to here.
He may be the first one to say this.
Philosophers have never, never noticed that.
Yeats noticed it, poets noticed it.
I've got a thing in my office, a poster, where Yeats, in the last letter he wrote, says, We can embody the truth, but we cannot know it.
That's exactly what's happening with Quiqued.
He embodies the truth of his culture, and he understands, he lives that truth, but he can't think that truth.
He can't understand what's carved into his body.
And Ahab at the end is wonderful.
I said I would give you another quote about how Ahab can't stand uncertainty.
And this thought, namely that he can't understand it, and it will remain unsolved to the last.
This thought it must have been which suggested to Ahab that wild exclamation of his when one morning turning away from surveying poor Queque, oh devilish tantalization of the gods.
And see, that adds a whole element.
I mean, it's all very well to have the meaning of being in your culture carved into your body, and it's sacred, and you go to put it in your coffin and die happily with it.
But Ahab can't stand that.
He wants, it tantalizes him to read the hieroglyphics, to have the theory, to state the truth that's carved into Quequeg's body, and presumably the one that's in his body too.
Ahab sees it as this unacceptable uncertainty, something like that.
For him, it's got to be explicit, and if he can't read it, then he can't stand it.
And that's just typical Ahab.
So, and that's, and it's saving power of these sacred practices that are in the body of Quequeg.
It doesn't require that he understand it.
In fact, I think it would be lost if you understand it.
Picture the women in that culture who have all this built into them that they are submissive.
It would be the first stage of feminine rebellion and consciousness raising and breaking out of it if they saw that they had been socialized into it.
And they would lose that understanding of being.
And in a way, of course, that would be a good thing.
Not all understandings of being are as good as any other.
From our point of view, they could become women like women are in this culture.
From maybe from their point of view, women in this culture have lost their essential femininity.
We shouldn't get lost into those issues.
The important thing is that it doesn't have to be made explicit, but Ahab can't stand it unless it's made explicit.
Ahab can't stand.
Remember, it's unrepresentable.
The tattoos should remind you of the hieroglyphics on Moby Dick.
Hieroglyphics are signs that mean something, but we can't tell what in Moby Dick, in the book.
And what Ahab can't stand is the unrepresentable and the ungraspable and the uncertain.
So he can't stand the Kwequeg squiggles.
Now, I'll begin the next one because I don't want to.
Well, no, now I, I mean, you want to say anything about that?
That's a fascinating little riff there that it seems completely out of place.
But when the time comes, remember that there's a, like, on Kweequeg's coffin is carved the saving meaning in the practices of the culture.
And that will turn out to be interesting and important.
Well, now let me, I'll start the next because I want you to be sure and read it.
Yeah, go ahead.
Oh, and you put it a little too weakly.
You can have meaning with an adult without knowing it at all.
In fact, knowing it would undermine it.
I mean, one, luckily, you can't, you were never going to be able to know it.
It's unrepresentable.
If you could know it, if you could have a science of proxemics, which I think I mentioned once, which had the whole theory of distance standing in our culture, I think you'd probably get so inhibited about distance standing you wouldn't be able to do it anymore.
All these practices only work when you don't think about them.
It's like trying to think about while you're riding a bicycle how you do it or dance or how you do it.
So being in your culture, standing your way and looking people in the eye your way and so forth is something you can only do when you don't represent it.
And that's good though to make that point.
It's not just, however you put it, sort of better if you don't understand it.
I think it's one understand, it's one, it's not representable and understandable, and two, it's a very important and positive thing that you can't understand it, according to Melville, and according to me, and Heidegger, at least and Nietzsche, I think.
Okay, let me just set up the next thing because I want you to have it to read.
The second kind of meaning, this is all sort of pure pagan meanings.
And now, a meaning which we still have, by the way, but which we are sort of lost a sense of the sacred of it.
And in a way, I think, could we be losing our practices?
Hmm.
That's a long story, I think.
But there's something to be said for the fact that in our culture, our practices actually operate so as to try to force us to make everything explicit and understanding.
The latest version is try to get it all so you can represent it on a computer, so that you can make a computer that will behave like a human being.
Well, if a lot of what makes people behave like a human being is the non-representable stuff in their way of dealing with everything, then you'd better be able to make to represent it into the computer so you can have artificial intelligence and make a computer that behaves like people.
And people try that.
That's proxemics, for instance.
Let's make a computer that has all the theory in it of distance standing, whatever.
And so our practices lead us to try to make them explicit and try to cover up their unrepresentableness.
It's a funny situation.
Heidegger worries about it a lot.
That isn't what you should be thinking about or worrying about.
It isn't.
But Melville does, in a funny way, worry about it.
He worries about what if they fish out, what if they get rid of all the sperm whales, which are the source of the unrepresentable?
Where will we be then?
And his answer is they can't do it.
The whales will hide under the Arctic ice cap and they won't let that happen.
So there's some hope for Melville that no matter how much the culture tries to get rid of this sacred truth that we all have inscribed in our bodies by making it explicit and thereby putting it in computers, for instance, you can't do it.
I wrote a book about that, what computers can't do, and all dealing with this issue.
Okay, now I did want to say, and I have one minute, I want you to be sure and read chapter 94.
It's very peculiar.
And it's the second way and a very important way of getting meaning in your life.
It's the way Ishmael gets the most powerful, most sacred meaning in his life.
Chapter's called the Squeeze of the Hand.
And you'll talk about it next time.
And let's see what else I want you to look at.
Mainly that.
And that's it for now.