So today we're going back to talking about death.
And it's, you know, how you're getting used to it, I hope, sort of important, but hard to put this back of the page numbers because of the way I've cut it up in different forms.
But it ought to begin to already impress you that we can talk about.
We've talked about guilt and we talked about resoluteness without talking about death, although the death chapter is prior to them.
So that Heidegger's going to have to go through the awkward move of next time bringing back the story of death, but put it again after guilt.
The way the book is actually written, we're supposed to have done death already, then now, and then guilt.
But that's not how we're reading it.
So sometimes you've got to just keep in mind that we've done guilt, because that's the past, and that gets you resoluteness.
And today we're going to do death, and then next time, Heidegger's finally got to do the job, which he had to do anyway, but not in that crazy order.
Get the resoluteness together with anticipation, that is, get guilt together with death, and get anticipatory resoluteness as the way of life that a Dasein lives when it is authentic, that is, when it manifests in what it does transparently, or Hoagland has a nice new term, I just realized, loosedly what it is to eat them as well.
And Hoagland says, and I think this right, Heidegger uses the term explicitly, Australich, but that makes it sound as if you could say what it is and sort of have a credo for being authentic.
And that's not how it is at all.
It's a way of understanding, that is coping with yourself and other Daseins and the world.
But you can do that lucidly, meaning, and now we'll have a word from Kierkegaard, transparently, which is Kierkegaard's way of avoiding it.
When you say lucidly or transparently, you don't mean something that you can put into propositional form and state explicitly.
So I think the parenthetical.
So next time, we will get to the way you live at a formal level.
Of course, everybody has to do it their own specific way.
But the general shape of the life which you live, if you manifest transparently or lucidly in your activity, what a Dasein, what Dasein essentially is, instead of covering up, which you can do, what Dasein essentially is.
And Dasein, what is Dasein essentially?
Well, it's the throwing, projecting, falling being whom I think, although it isn't so clear in Being in Time, the main job description is being a world disclosure.
But we won't talk much about that unless we talk about Sarah White's introduction to the paper I put on the website.
So there's a kind of problem.
I might as well just find out now what you want to do.
I'm open to.
I mean, there are just two different something or others on the table, though not utterly unrelated to each other.
Namely, the assignment that we read for this time about death as treated in Being and Time, and my paper that I put on the website, which tries to sort of present the comments on death and being in time in a broader context following Farrell White, in which the death of cultures and the death of understandings of being plays a more important role than the death of individuals.
I take it.
Here's my proposal.
First, I talk a little while about our assignment, and then we discuss that.
And then if there's still time, we discuss how many read the piece I put on the website.
Not more, not even half.
Okay, well, then, and you don't have to.
I mean, I think it's really illuminating her book, and therefore, my talking about her book is also really illuminating, but it's not necessary for understanding what goes on in Being and Time.
It's more like it prevents certain misunderstandings of what is going on in being in time, but we can prevent them anyway.
Does anybody got any want to say anyone?
Is there any better way to do it?
To me, wish I could just go back and forth between them, but I'm not, I don't think you're able to do it given what you've read.
I don't think I'm able to do it just keeping too many things open on my desktop.
I've cracked.
So let's go to this.
Starting with a running start, that is a quick review of last time, because it's so important to keep from getting lost in the death chapter.
Much, much more easy to get lost in than the guilt chapter.
But on the same grounds, it's important to realize that when you do this kind of hermeneutic understanding, that is, you want to get at the essence of death and guilt, and you want to do it by sort of getting an overall picture of Zazine in which these various components fit together in a holistic way and then reinforce each other.
The method you have to use is formal indication.
That means you have to start with not only isolatable components like death and guilt separately and resoluteness and anticipatory resoluteness separately and finally put them together.
That's part of what makes it hard.
But what makes it even harder is if you do formal indication, you have to start with an understanding of whatever you're going to be talking about, in this case, in the last time, guilt, an understanding of it which is wrong, which is a cover-up, which is not a distortion, it's an understatement.
It's a 180-degree wrong denial of exactly what death is or guilt is.
We saw it last time, and I want to remind you.
So, guilt normally means that you're responsible for some bad thing you've done, or that you, or you're responsible for obeying the laws and standards and principles of your society, and you've broken the law, you owe something, you have to go to prison to make up for it, and so forth.
All that talk, and of course, conscience too, tells you what the laws are and tells you when you've broken them, the moral principles and so forth.
All that isn't just wrong about ontological guilt.
I mean, Heidi's not going to tell you that's wrong about the ordinary meaning of guilt.
That's a good analysis.
I didn't do it elegantly, but you could make a good analysis of the ordinary meaning of guilt based on how it looks when you just look at the phenomenon of first sight.
That's what I was just saying.
Guilt is indebtedness and owing something and obeying rules and so forth.
You have to start with that, because that's how we normally take it.
But you know when you start that if you work it out, you'll discover that ontological guilt, as opposed to sort of common sense understanding of guilt, the real structure that the word guilt is pointing to, that the guilt is pointing to, the word guilt is pointing to, the real phenomenon is buried and covered up.
And moreover, and this is something I think Heidegger really thinks, but he doesn't say it, except more in fact against African.
They wouldn't know how to open to it right away, that it's not just covered up, but it's a motivated cover-up that is trying to exactly deny what guilt and death really ontological as ontological structures of God's sign off.
And therefore, the wrong answer is a clue to the right answer.
Because if you can see that, if you can understand what guilt is denied, namely that there is no basis for what you ought to do, and conscience doesn't give you rules and goes when you do wrong thing.
Conscience is silent.
It's a silent kind of call.
You can see that putting a voice into conscience, putting guilt and debtiness, responsibility, and so forth into the notion of guilt is precisely the cover-up that there aren't any world guidelines and you don't know anybody, anything specific and so forth.
That's going to be a clue to the right answer.
I'll say this one more time.
It's the more semblance, the more proof or something like that, Heidegger says.
I'll have to find a line that I see as I talk that I should have looked for.
But anyway, the point is, you've got to see that.
We're going to be told a story about death, which is dead wrong, you might say.
Okay, well, you want to say something.
Well, I didn't say there's nothing.
Oh, wow.
We had this.
No, we nearly, I'll see you've got to think about this whether I want to we might just think back into a discussion that was the first meeting, but I'll see if I can say something that doesn't start a whole discussion again.
Heidegger thinks there are wrong ways of behaving, ways to cover up what it is to be Dasein.
But those ways of behaving might well be arranged in the moral law and doing whatever you do in a way that you can generalize it.
What's the word in the Kantians use?
Universalizing.
I mean, if you're doing stuff that's universalizable, that's certainly a clue that it's wrong.
Because remember that the pharonomist responds to the unique situation.
So Heidegger has plenty to say about all the wrong ways of wanting in order to cover up the true structure of Dase.
But I'm trying to think: is there anything I can say about well, you can say very formal things like Dasein responds to their unique situation.
Well, consciousness calls Dasein to respond to the unique situation, but it's a silent call that doesn't then tell you anything.
And it doesn't say three people's means, names and neighbors' means, or love your neighbor, or have them do unto them as you would have them do unto you, or more specific things like vote when when an election comes around.
It doesn't say anything like any of that.
So it's in the end, I don't know whether this thing gives you moral guidelines or not.
I mean, if let's say it tells you a wrong way to behave when you're diasaring, it tells you in a very abstract way the right way to behave when you're data design.
It gives you no specific guidance of how to act in specific situations, according to Heidegger.
And if conscience is telling you, this is what put it in the most provocative way, if conscience is telling you what to do and what not to do, you can be sure that that's a cover-up because that's telling you general things.
And that's not that those aren't better than nothing.
I mean, it may be better to be told the general thing that you should help me to kill them, but it doesn't help you really know whether when somebody asks for money on the street in Berkeley you should give them money so each fake is is unique.
Now there's something one more thing I want to say about it.
Okay, yes, so so you could be sure, back to your question, if conscience is telling you rules and principles that are universalizable and rational or based on revelation or based on human nature or or based on the way your parents socialized you, if your consciousness is giving you ways advice about how to behave and telling you when you're doing wrong in any of those ways, you can be sure that it's covering up, not doing uh what what you should be doing.
So yeah, but I'm trying to think clearly, that doesn't mean that you shouldn't do what one does.
I mean, it's better to do what one does in your culture than to do outrageous things that one doesn't do at all, I guess.
Though, in the back of my mind, I'm teaching fear and trembling right now, and Abraham's the hero for being ready to kill Isaac.
I mean, Heidegger, I think, is sort of in the Kierkegaard position in the sense that you can be called, if you're really a world-isclosing being, you can be called to do things that look on the basis of the current ethics of the culture as outrageously wrong.
And you can't even say what I just said, you should trust it if it tells you at least at first approximation what one does.
Because it may be just absolutely wrong what one does, or totally stupid, silly.
I mean, you, I mean, in other courses, know my favorite example of this.
If your conscience tells you you should send Christmas cards, and it's telling you you failed to do something you should, and now you owe everybody a Christmas card, that's not just wrong.
It's silly, and it, and particularly, I mean, if there are people across the street who send me Christmas cards, then it covers up the idea that whatever it is that you could do to relate to other people in some daily, unique, interesting way.
Okay, I don't know if I've helped any.
Did that help any?
I just, I mean, the same sort of a summary digress of what we may have gone through last time.
Okay, I'll go back to this.
Where were we?
Okay, this is still supposed to be an introduction, so let me get through it fast.
So, oh, yeah, I forgot.
And just again, and why is consciousness calling into all these sort of high-level, deep, religious, rational, and trivial things that you should be doing in heaven or should be doing and are doing and so forth?
Why is it doing all that?
Because of the unsettledness of Dasein.
There isn't any way to find out, because Dasein has no normal sort of nature.
What is natural, what is what God wants, what reason demands, and so forth.
And now I get to back to where I was.
It's not only not telling you what's what, it's covering up this way that we are not able, unsettled, ungrounded.
There is no way to appeal to any specific principles of any sort to guide you or justify what you do.
It's a very existential point.
And it starts with Kierkegaard, I presume, or with Pascal, maybe.
Okay, now let's see.
Okay, so we're going to go on today.
That was supposed to prepare you for how hard the death chapter is, because when you start, you start with an ordinary sense of death, just as you started with guilt, with the ordinary understanding of guilt.
That's how it happens in formal indication.
You've got to start where you are.
But the normal sense of death is certainly something that happens to people at the end of their life.
Something that happens to people on their deathbed.
What John Hoagland calls croaking.
That's what it's about.
And that's exactly not.
I mean, it's got to be not only wrong, but sort of motivatedly wrong.
That is, it's got to be a cover-up.
Why would it be a cover-up to think that death had something to do with what happened at the end of your life?
Well, because whatever it is, you can then think of that as something in the future.
Didn't I say this last time?
I'm beginning to get found as if I heard myself.
You begin to think that this is something in the future.
This, well, the word's going to be demise, finally, this demise, this final event.
You think of this thing as something in the future.
It isn't even a normal event because it's gone.
By the time it happens, you're not there anymore.
But you think of it as in the future.
And thereby, sort of not right now.
Well, that's rather reassuring.
And then thereby, you can take all these homeopathic medicines that will make you live longer and exercise every day, and that'll make you live longer.
And don't do stupid things where you might get hurt and so forth.
There are ways to postpone anyway indefinitely, because why shouldn't it always be in the future?
You're ceasing to exist.
So the very idea that demise is about something that's going to happen to you in the future but isn't happening to you right now is not only wrong, it's covering up your somehow a kind of emptiness, a kind of unsettledness, a kind of nullity, which is structurally part of Dasein, and which Dasein is in all the time, or lives all, or a what?
It's its structural, whatever death is, it's going to turn out to be some structural characteristic of Doddheim, and it's not going to turn out to be an event in the future which hasn't happened yet and may not happen for a while.
So I told you both that the common sense meaning of death is demise and that it's not just any old mistake that you might think it is.
It's that it wants to get, it wants to cover up something and get a kind of control on something.
And another Heidegger way of talking, death, authentic oncological death, makes you constantly anxious in a positive sort of way.
That turning death into an event in the future makes it something you can fear.
And already fearing it, then you can avoid it, try to prevent it, at least delay it, and so forth.
And that's much more reassuring than anxiety.
Okay, so that's the formal indications thing.
We know we're going to have to start with an event that happens to people, terminal event when people live, where they just get annihilated.
And we know that that's not going to be what death is.
But whatever death is, that's a denial of it, a cover of it.
Okay, so now we get to what death is.
But we don't get there very directly.
This is a very hard chapter and very confusing.
And it's given rise to those of you who've read the Carol Whitepiece, who at least, I don't know how many I listed by, I didn't count them about getting different, very different, and all wrong, every one of them, the interpretations of what, according to Heidegger, death is.
And why is this chapter so hard?
Because Heidegger, again, it's the formal indication story.
And he starts by telling you what everyday understanding of death is.
And then he says he's ontologizing it and formalizing it.
Dead by dead, he gets it more antologized and formalized as he goes through the chapter.
And the trouble is, he never can tell quite exactly when he's finally said that death really is and gotten rid of all the cover of it.
I mean, I couldn't tell you, maybe one of you can tell me if you do come to office on it, I think I totally know roughly where it is.
At what point does he finally get to the formal, ontological, correct, essential description of that structural phenomenon of Dasein, which we misnamed, but nonetheless indicate.
You know, it's this, we're pointing at it even though we're using the wrong properties to point at it.
What we're trying to get to when we talk about death.
And so now we go through, and I just want to tell you sort of there are these stages in the account.
There seem to be at least four stages.
Even if you reorder the book and make it into a linear argument of some sort, it's still hard to see, though it's linear in some sense, what the steps are in this story.
So first there's the everyday interpretation.
That's what I was giving you already.
So, you know, one dies.
And that's a franchising fact about events far off in the future and not applying to you, but just one in general.
It isn't that Lord Geyser dies.
In fact, he's dying right now in some sense, but it's this general thing that one dies and one dies some other time.
Now we're talking, clearly, he's not going to, that's not what he's talking about.
And there seems to be something like an existentialist, in which you live somehow facing up to this terminal event, which is normally called dying or death, and which I either call demise.
I have to do this in funny order.
I'm not really, I mean, we could define demise right now, but it was just complicated thing.
So just think of it as old death.
The existentialist thing is, well, what attitude should you have toward death?
And it's clearly not the event at your end of your life that matters.
It's how you relate to the event at the end of your life that matters.
That's already pretty much a definition of demise.
Demise is pariquin, which is just what animals do too, but parry thing the way humans carry.
And whatever that, sorry, yeah, the way humans carry, and that means taking a stand on the fact that we are, we organisms carry.
And that stand takes that event, the pariquin, and gives it a meaning.
And depending on what meaning you give it, you live some one layer of life or another.
But so the most influence move is then, how to how to live in terms of this final fact, the Dasein that faces the possibility, well, on through 94, the possibility of no longer being able to be there.
There are all kinds of possible statements on this.
The most interesting one is really Star, because Star criticizes Heidegger on death in being in time because one thing that is that Heidegger must mean that there is this, that death must be the name for this kind of annihilation that's going to happen to you at the end of your life.
And then when Heidegger decides in effect that you could live in terms of it, Star says, well, if you live in terms of it, if you thought about how absolutely you, I mean how totally you're going to be wiped out and all not that all you care about will be wiped out, that you're caring about everything will be wiped out and so forth.
There'd be no reason for you to do anything rather than anything else.
You know the story of the wall.
I don't know how many know Star's story of the wall.
When somebody's sentenced to death and they, the next morning they will be killed.
And overnight they get clearer and clearer about what it is that there's going to happen to them the next morning.
And by the next morning, it's sort of like a Dostoevsky story.
When they're before the firing squad, they suddenly get pardoned.
And then that they've given up, they sort of distance themselves from the person they loved and the cause they're serving and the friends that they are protecting and everything.
So that when they finally find out that they're not going to die, the end of the court story is the guy just falls on the ground laughing because there's nothing anymore that it makes sense to do.
Well, that makes a sensefulist view of death all right, and it certainly isn't what Heidegger is interested in.
It isn't as if he even exactly wants to deny it, it's just that he's not interested in what, or he's not going to tell you about anyway.
Maybe he's, I mean, the book, the ontology of it, isn't going to tell you about how you could feel about the fact that at the end of their life you're going to be wiped out and all you're caring about anything is going to be wiped out.
That's not the question.
Now, here's already the first confusing thing.
And if anybody can tell me how to fix it, I would be happy.
Remember that there is then a footnote to Ivan Ilya's death, the Tolstoy story.
I can't understand why Heidegger's got it in there, because that looks like an existentialist account of somebody on their deathbed and what they're learning when they're on their deathbed.
Yeah, you want to find it and we'll look at it?
So maybe if we looked at it, somebody could explain to me what's going on there.
Where is it?
It's in the footnotes.
Anybody found it?
495.
Why did he do that?
We haven't got any troubles already.
Where is 495?
In the English?
I don't see it yet.
Note 12 on page 495.
Oh, yeah.
I think it's the longest thing.
In this story, The Death of Ivan Illy, in his story, The Death, Tolstoy has presented the phenomenon of the disruption and breakdown of having someone die.
That's already wrong.
It isn't having someone die.
And Spruitt talks about that, but he talks a lot more about what it feels like to be dying and go and exist in Cel.
And that gives nothing that Heidegger could be interested in.
What he tells you.
How many read The Death of Ivan Ilyich?
I mean, not very many.
Well, that's interesting.
It's a story about how he feels more and more withdrawn because he sees that his death isn't important to anybody the way it's important to him, not even to his family, not even to his wife.
And he also feels that he's wasted his whole life, and that's all very touching, but it just isn't the point.
Yeah.
Ah, that's why it's having someone to just die.
Ah.
That's right.
It's inconvenient to the family that there he is in his bedroom dying and they're trying to go on with their life's work.
Ah, good.
Well, you six good.
I mean, I've always thought he was good, but that's not really what Tolstoy is interested in, I don't think.
The very tiny part of it.
I don't know if Heidegger's a very good reader of actual texts, but he gets interesting things out of them, even though they may not be very important to the text.
Okay, so that's another example of sort of optical quoting and what Effective has on the people who are doing it and the people around them.
And I just remember something so crazy that I'll tell you, because it's just an anecdote that it's amazing.
And not very complimentary to Heidegger, I must say, but it's good.
When Heidegger had been barred from teaching, he was desperate to get in touch with the rest of the world.
He was so desperate that he talked to me for an afternoon.
And that's pretty desperate if you're Heidegger, but I had written him and said I was going to teach him at MIT, and he was so happy.
But he also wanted to talk to Star.
So there's a letter from him to Sartre, who says to Star, I understand your criticism.
And Sartre's criticism of Heidegger's view of death is, of course, all wrong.
It's the criticism from what I told you already in the wall.
But if you actually thought about your death, you'd be paralyzed and not be able to do anything.
The desperated act, Sartre says, in effect, is to cover it up.
You have to cover it up if you're going to go on.
Living, Heidegger writes a letter to Sartre.
He says, I see what you're saying.
Yes, I accept your criticism of my view about death.
I see that we're on the same time, but why don't you come by and talk?
In effect, and today I was rather reading Zapransky, really, he set up a meeting with Sartre.
And Sartre had the good sense not to come.
I don't know whether we just screwed him up or said, I'm sorry.
But when I talked to Heidegger, who, as I say, was desperate, he had on his desk Sartre being a nothingness because now reading this biography, I see that he was preparing, hopefully, for this visit of Sartre.
But when I said, I see you're reading Sartre, what do you think about it?
And he said, these voice must be in effect on Fine.
How can I begin to research Lubbock?
Or maybe it's a crap, I don't know.
I mean, it'd be more like that, right?
Yes.
I mean, that's the way.
He never believed a word of it.
Anyway, he's just a total hypocrite.
I don't think we can do anything about it.
Let's separate the man from the moral of that.
Okay, back to where we were.
The next one, after the everyday reading and the existentialist reading, then we get to Heidegger, who says he's doing a formal ontological existential, not existential, that which is existential with, but in full existential impression of death is what he wants.
Now it's time it's, by the way, I see that I wrote something that fits with what Eugene has said on 308 is where he's saying what it is that Tolstoy gets my book untangled here.
308.
Suddenly, my book seems to be going backwards.
Let's try it this way.
Okay, good.
308.
What do I say about it there?
This is what he thinks I've been illusion is about.
I now understand it.
So I want to look it up.
Yes, about ten lines down.
When we're facing our death, it makes manifest that all being alongside the things in which we concern ourselves and all being with others will fail us when our own ability to be is the issue.
Now, it's interesting that, and he says Tolstoy sees that.
I don't know what he does.
What's strange is that Heidegger, who's now in the middle of his existential projection of authentic gain towards death, which starts on 304, is ready to bring that in as part of the true structure of death, namely at the top of the page that it's non-relational.
This is supposed to say that it's non-relational.
And let's put it in a little bit.
His concern and politics fail us.
This does not signify at all that these ways the Gaussian have been cut off from its authentically being itself.
As structures essential to Gaussian, they are still there and so forth.
What I'm going to say is, I don't know what level of analysis this is.
Is this, it seems, it sounds sort of existential, that the existential with other relations, the relations of others, will fail us.
I don't know what it is, because is it really structural?
Is it true that all relations with others will have to fail us when we're on our deathbed?
We can't, love can't transcend that, or commitment to some incredible cause, but going to do something about it.
Again, I just don't know.
He's going through a whole lot of characteristics of death here, and he says he's doing an existential discussion of them.
So I guess we're supposed to think that it's a necessary structural feature of having the right relations to demise, which is that you will become isolated.
Yes, Heidegger into all sorts of trouble because now I don't know whether I can find this, because I wasn't going to say it.
Help me find it.
There's a place where he talks about Dasein's existential solar system.
Anybody remember that?
Habermas gets onto that and gets very concerned about that.
And this is all tied in with the non-relational thing.
Maybe it's under anxiety and not under death.
It could be in either place.
I doubt if we could find it.
Oh boy, 233.
Oh, it is back in anxiety.
But it's tied up with this thing that Heidegger couldn't be saying, I think, that there is, or if he is, well, maybe it's all right for him to say it.
I don't know.
But it's not all right for Habermas to think that Heidegger is thereby saying that Dasein is, in some sense, totally independent and self-really independent and self-sufficient.
On 233 in italics, he's talking about anxiety, and it individualizes, it makes claim that with the phenomenon of anxiety, a distinctive disposiveness, there's a theme of interpretation.
Anxiety individuals individuates Dasein and discloses it as solus ipsis.
That means isolated by itself.
Well, I don't know what's the exact translation of anybody in the Latin.
Alone itself, alone itself.
And this existential sola system, and now Habermas, and it's always hot too, to stop with that and say, aha, Heidegger thinks that human beings are ultimately self-sufficient and isolated.
That's just so wrong.
I mean, that's just so Cartesian, where every individual self-contained mind is off in its warm room doing geometry or writing philosophy or whatever.
Of course, Heidegger thinks that it's part of Dasein's structure to be being in the world.
And it's the next sentence.
Anxiety individuals takes Dasein and disposes it as solids.
But this existential soloism is so far from the displacement of putting an isolated subject into an emptiness of a world occurring.
In an extreme sense, what it does is precisely to bring Dasein face to face with his world as world, with itself as being in the world.
And of course, that includes being with others.
So I don't know back to where we were now what is going on.
Most of the stuff I just don't know what's going on, right?
But lots of the time, how isolated is Dasein when it's dying?
And what difference does it make?
Because it isn't as if it's going to be going to reveal the fact that we were and we always will be alone, some dramatic thing like that.
Where were we on 308, right?
So there's a problem.
Ask yourself, sort of, why is Heidegger so clear that death is non-relational?
And what does he expect to get out of it?
And what is it supposed to reveal about Dasein?
Yeah, Eugene.
One thing, the first thing is that it must be taken over by Dasein alone.
That's the part about how no one can do it for you, and you can't do it together.
Ah, that's fine.
Good.
That's true.
Yes, you have to do it alone.
Nobody can do it for you.
But if that's all that non-relational means, that's interesting.
Let's see.
Let's look and see if there's any clue there.
I read it to refer back to the anxiety condition of being alone.
Dasein lays claim to death as Daseine as an individual Dasein.
That's fine.
As I'm just doing this, it individualizes Dasein down to itself.
It makes manifest that all being alongside things, if we concern ourselves and all being with others, will fail us when our own most potentiality for being anything is with us.
Isn't that wrong?
I mean, why would he say that?
I mean, you're right, that's what he thinks.
That death individuates us, but that's what leads people like Habermas to think, that he thinks that when those people in the ships are down, then all our relation to everything but ourselves is just canceled or not important or seeming to be not important because that's going to be what it says.
What does it take?
Try again.
Well, I thought I was going to read the first thing, but I think I was a bit knowledgeing that for you.
It is you.
And after death, you have...
Certainly, after death, you have no relation to anything.
I don't think that's one of the things he's talking about.
Really?
Huh.
That sounds wrong to me.
Let's try the first thing.
Okay.
I think you do have to do it alone.
But I'm not sure that he really has a right to say it's individuating.
But what he doesn't seem to have a right to say is that just because you have to do it alone, that you are isolated from that you can't, that all concern for others and for other things fails you.
I see that it fails you if you expect any help.
That you should somebody should hold your hand.
But that it fails you in any stronger sense and it doesn't.
Well, but then it's what's wrong to call that non-relatable, isn't it?
Let me try it again.
Being alongside things is fail us or not all of us.
It can be authentic only if it makes this possible for us of its own accord.
But if concerns us fail us, this does not signify at all because those who die that have been cut off from their sociological stuff.
Uh-huh.
So they fail us only in the sense that we have to die our death ourselves.
That's the right way to read it, I guess.
That's what you wanted to say.
It brings you into your unique situation.
In that sense, it individualizes us.
Well, except that why do the other things we concern ourselves fail us?
Why aren't they part of our unique situation?
They can't get you out of it.
Well, they can't get you out of it.
That's core.
I think there's also a just of a estrangement on the unheimless or on use of the homelessness, where he's, I mean, on 233, if we test reading, he goes down to this last part of the second paragraph.
He says, As Dazine falls, anxiety brings a fast from its absorption in the world.
Everyday familiarity collapses.
God's line has been individualized, but individualized as being in the world.
Being in intros into the existential mode of the not at home.
Nothing else is meant by our talk.
Where are you all on being and?
233, just right after 189 in the system.
I mean, that whole paragraph is so, you know, we're not individualized in the sense that we're completely pulled out of the world or something that was, you know, counter strings.
Our world is a world, if we're also.
And so everyday familiarity collapses, which is totally the episode on every day.
I mean, the kind of familiarity that you get from as the one and just sort of how you how things normally matter and what don't how we normally deal with them and all that collapses.
So much that we don't recognize that we are thinking about.
Yeah, we're still in a room.
We're still in a familiar room and all that.
In some ways, in this case, the estrangement that Heiger is trying to bring out the phenomena of us, that world even becomes more present to us, even though we become estranged from it.
I mean, it seems like he wants to make both of them.
We're not.
Okay, yeah, so it's a world that we have to get back in touch with somehow or that we're in.
We're not completely solid cystic.
I mean, part of it seems like part of the anxiety is that we recognize that we are worlded creatures and we have an estrangement from that world.
That we have to get that we better get and that's not our that's not our true state.
I mean, it sounds like it sometimes sounds like, and I think that's the view I'm trying to both explain and believe it.
If you get more and more authentic when when you get estranged and and set off from others than when from the familiar, and that's the wrong way to think about it.
You know, it's okay.
So 'cause they ought to say, well, that being in the world is essential to Dasein and it stays that way even when it's dying, even when it's uh, you know, having it uh in touch getting in touch with anxiety, you'd better still be in the world with people and so forth.
Uh you look really worried.
Good.
No one can take away your death from you, but also no one can uh get you out of the breakdown situation.
Like if you if you have a breakdown with a hammer, someone can give you a better hammer and and then someone else gets your breakdown.
But if you have if you have anxiety, no one can help you out of it.
Oh, well that's that's good.
I mean let's read it the ingenious way.
I mean, so this is it says anxiety and death are isolating in the swim south.
Nobody can help you get out of them or or feel at home in them.
You've got to get out of them by feeling at home in them, really, but on your own.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, I think arguably helps you in excitement, but there's something that you have to do yourself to deal with.
Where does he talk about this?
In that one.
I read that one lately, but I don't remember that.
We may be on something about the relation of this fruit to depression.
What that?
Yeah, but treat them as the same phenomenon.
Yeah, some things depression and anxiety are the same.
I I would get all upset and annoyed about that if it weren't that later Heidegger wants to say the same thing.
Uh well, but only after he's had therapy and like gotten over his if input anxiety and the occurrence of Finlay's type the most prevalent exposedness.
I mean they're not we think that depression is our most prevalent uh if uh removed and that would be in a way that's what so he so so those wouldn't be God wouldn't be being in time anyway, I think, treating a lot of depression.
Tyler, do you have your hand up?
Say loud person.
He said that, right?
And I think so they don't fail you in your particular things of bringing you morphine or something.
You don't think that's the right thing.
Well you guys will have to discuss each other with it.
What do you think that's the stronger part that you have, all being alongside collapses or fails you?
What's failing you?
And I see that's all you that's the only thing that would matter at this point is that they could die for you and they can't.
And in that sense they fail you.
Okay, well that that sounds that sounds good.
I mean you're really just taking which is good.
You don't really disagree with Eugene.
The main because you're both saying the the way it works is that death is such that nobody can save you from it or or they die for you.
And that's that means that at on that point, at that level, they are irrelevant.
Everybody and everything is failing you and irrelevant for you.
That's what you both think.
Yeah?
Well, he could have meant that, but in the text it's clear that he doesn't.
It's he it's it means stand in for you.
I can't quote the sentence, but that's what it's certainly about, yeah.
294, stronger things.
Okay, let's work.
So like two thirds of the way down, where he introduced this non-relation, all right, before that, he says, um, when Dasein stands before itself in his way, all relations and the other Dawson has been undone.
Hmm.
Yeah, that's the stronger one, all right.
And that's really the one that gets him into trouble because if Dasein is being with, then you couldn't be in a state of where it looks like in authentic dying as well as inauthentic dying, all relation sellers are undone.
And that means then you begin to think like Habermas and Tugenot.
Well, look at that.
Authentic Dasein doesn't need anybody.
Yeah, so that's unfortunate.
I didn't mark where you saw it.
Where is it?
Okay, ice cream.
Yes, there's the possibility of the absolute impossibility of Dazan.
If that doesn't think you'll be in pain, I don't see it yet.
What?
Oh, I see.
Ah, that was.
Ah, I see it now.
Guess what?
I have a question mark in the margin there.
Now I see why.
Okay, yes, but I don't think he could say that.
Get carried away into his more existentialist side.
Maybe that's where you could take the card.
Yeah, we're on the same wavelength, but you couldn't.
Let's see.
Okay, where are we?
Authentic existential.
So now I say go to 305, but I don't know why, where we are yet, so I get to 305.
Well, that's just, I mark that as the sort of antique art.
I mean, Sartre thinks that Heidegger thinks that dwelling upon the end is what you should be doing.
And Sartre's right.
Dwelling on that end, that final moment is certainly how you're going to be wiped out by it.
Certainly not what you should be doing.
Neither dwelling on it as something awful or dwelling on it as something terrific.
I mean, I've been listening lately to Bach, many, many places where Bach is just thinking about his death while you're talking to Lynchunda, the fact, ring the final bell.
That's really going to be terrific.
And I think Heidegger would say that must be inauthentic.
I mean, Bach is thinking, oh, it's going to be even better in the next world.
And the sooner we get out of this one, it sounds like he's saying, the better.
Yeah, yeah, it's a common theme in German music and I guess a lot of poetry at the time.
Well, that's equally bad.
I mean, looking forward to your death is just as bad as regretting it.
I mean, it's not a kind of event that you suppose to have an attitude about.
At least, I mean, you can, it is an event of a sort, and you will have an attitude about it of a sort, but Heidegger's just not interested in what attitude you have about it.
You're not supposed to be dwelling on it.
You're supposed to be an important event dwelling in it.
It's supposed to color everything, whatever this death characteristic is, it's going to cover your relation to everything.
That's the next thing I want to say here, I guess.
I get there quickly.
Well, I'll drum ahead.
Death, this is something Hoeman takes out and makes a lot of fuss about, but it's important to say it here.
Dying is a way of life for Heidegger.
It's not something that happens to you at the end of your life.
It's a general characteristic of Dasein, and authentically you face up to it.
This is the bottom of 289.
It's always had to think you know where one is, how formalized one is.
You never know.
This is supposed to be prior to 293, which is the preliminary sketch of an existential ontological structure of death.
Yes, you could be saying something existential ontological here at the bottom of 289.
Just with Dasein is already its not yet.
I'm just reading that paragraph.
And is it's not yet constantly, as long as it lives, it is already its end too.
The ending which we have in view when we speak of death does not signify Dasein's being in an end.
That would be perishing or taking a stand on perishing by having to be demised.
Rather, it's a being towards the end.
Death is a way to be, which Dasein takes over as soon as it is.
And that's, I mean, you've got to get used to that.
That's the, where am I?
About five lines from the bottom of 289.
Death is a way to be, which Dasein takes over as soon as it is.
Well, that means death is a way of behaving or a core comportment that colors everything you do and everything you see and how anything shows up for you.
There's nothing special about that final event.
That that final event is just a why.
It's a kind of oh boy.
I never can understand this.
How can you be non-relational the non-relational state, for instance, is supposed to be a general characteristic of Dasein's dying all the time.
But it can't be that Dasein is non-relational all the time.
Anytime I try to think about it, I have it tied in notch.
You get any help and you think, how can non-relational be a way of life?
Or is it because now you can always bitter?
I'm demonstrating why this chapter is so confusing, because now you could say, well, that's not really the that's that's not even the preliminary sketch of an existential ontological structure of death.
That's on 293.
Who knows what that is?
That's on 290, how the existential analysis of death is distinguished from other possible interpretations of this phenomenon.
Now, maybe that makes it all right.
Because it sometimes seems to me, or often seems to me, that what Heidegger is doing is gradually ontologizing and gradually taking back our understanding of death.
And see, and so 299, he hasn't got to the full existential conception of death.
And even that may not be the final story.
As I say, I don't know exactly, and I'm ready for anybody to come and tell me where exactly the final story is.
By the time you get to the top of 311, you've got it all in there in italic.
You keep keep that little beat in mind whenever you get lost.
Anticipation, that's I'm jumping ahead because anticipation and he's jumping ahead because he on 311 he shouldn't he really isn't any ready to talk about anticipatory resoluteness because he hasn't done guilt yet or am I lost?
I get lost in his craziness.
No, that's right.
So but let's do it anyway.
Anticipation reveals to Dasein its lostness in the oneself and brings it face to face with the possibility of being itself, primarily unsupported by concern for solicitude.
That fits the idea with nobody sort of being able to take your place, but of being itself rather in an impassioned freedom towards death, a freedom which has been released from the illusions of the day and which is practical, certain of itself.
And I that's that's okay as long as you don't build into the idea that all relations to others and fall away.
So where was I?
I was reading something 311, the other before that.
I was saying, how I don't understand, I was saying how Heidegger can say that we are always in this being towards death.
Where was I reading it?
And yet, say that being towards death is non-relational.
Somebody who must have been writing things down, where was I before 311?
Yeah.
Well, I don't know what to say, except that other human beings play no potential role in Dasein's way of being in the world.
At the time, when, when he will, if Dasein is on its deathbed, no, presumably all the time.
But that can't be right because he helps, again, it's because I can't tell anymore which is which.
You're having a relational possibility, like if that's what he's on, and you have to be sort of that.
Okay, sure.
So what's non-relational is that no one can take your place, and that's going to stay there no matter.
That's a possibility.
Is that the possibility?
Non-relation.
Okay.
And that and that you will always be related to in the way you live.
And yeah, okay.
And so what's non-relational is not the way you live, but right now that you, that insofar as you are living a relation to demise, you are alone.
And is that right?
And that's what's going to be.
What's that relational is that possibility?
The possibility of you having no more possibilities is a unique individual possibility.
Okay.
Yeah, that's the best way to hear it.
That helped you.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now I don't remember where I was, but it doesn't matter.
I want to be on page 291 because I've been talking and talking about demise, and I didn't know where, when to bring it in, but since it's in front of me, we'll put it in at this point.
We want to distinguish perishing, which is this event that happens at the end of any living thing.
I don't know whether it happens to germs, but it happens to mammals anyway.
And perishing is not what he's talking about.
And this is what he's saying on 291 about 15 lines down.
The ending of that which lives, we call perishing.
Daseine has its death of the kind appropriate to anything that lives, that's the perishing.
Insofar as this is the case, Daseine too can end without authentically dying.
That is, whatever dying is, which is a way of facing up to the structure of Daseine, you can just live a life in which you never actually face up to the structure of Daseine, and then you end without dying.
Though, on the other hand, quadsine, it does not simply perish.
We designate this intermediate phenomenon as demise.
Now, that means that demise is the stand you take on the fact that you'll perish, I think.
That's an intermediate phenomenon in that it's not the perishing, but how perishing is an issue for you.
And all Dasein are into that intermediate state.
Even the ones who don't face up, I think, to the end without authentically dying.
That's right.
But even they don't just perish, I think, because any, just even having the attitude toward your possible perishing that you have if you're in Datman, that it won't happen for a while and maybe could never happen to you, and it's all in the future, even that's a form of relating to your perishing already.
So, demise, I think, is the way that beings like us who have to take a stand on their being and also the impossibility of their being take a stand on it.
You look worried, is that right?
Into demise.
Really?
Where, where, where?
Right there.
Well, but I wonder if that's really what LaCorn.
Dasein never perish with you.
Daseine, however, can demise only as long as it's dying.
But now medicine doesn't change into quote demising.
I think that's supposed to be not what he means by demising.
That means really perishing, I guess.
Let me see if you can obtain results, which may even become significant.
What do you think?
What would it be for medicine to have a view about the stand that you take on the possibility of having no more possibilities?
I have no idea.
But I see the sentence.
Yeah.
Would detone in a similar way on the context of how we lead our demise, how long that takes, and we only worship houses because medicine and understanding better how we lead our demise might understand better how we are under maybe.
You just don't know what medicine could under medicine could understand about how to meet our demise.
It could try to keep you from being aware of it and so forth, but I don't think he's talking about that.
I think the quotes around demising are pretty important.
I think he thinks that what they really are investigating is perishing.
But maybe not, because he goes on and says, sort of, maybe death in the thickness can be understood from a medical point of view as an existential phenomenon.
Well, I don't know what it means.
So, yeah, the Tyler, you know what it means?
Monarch is an intermediary thing.
I think demise is what happens at the end of a person's life, understood not as perishing, but as something that they've interpreted.
And that's demise is carrying plus having a stand on perishing in the way you normally, in the way you live.
Yeah, it's an attitude toward an event of perishing.
That's let me think now.
And yes, demise, well, that's not quite right.
It's the event of perishing having a demise to it.
I mean, having a uh interpretation to it.
I mean, there is only there's this event, this thing that happens to you finally when you have no more possibilities how you relate to that thing.
But it really is that thing.
It's just it is something that everything happens and demise also happens at the end of your life.
That's what I think.
Do you think that's wrong?
I think I think demising is is something that really is in the future, but it's the future thing understood and taken over, you know, as whatever your exit way of doing it is.
Ah, Curtis was going to tell you, yeah, go ahead.
Wait, what?
Well, wait, wait a second then.
Let's look where on the next paragraph.
Let's look.
Where are you in the next paragraph?
Well, um, I thought the sustainable interpretation of the couple lines down in any typology of drawing or characterization of conventions under which the demise of interity in the way through a sort of experience, because I was already referring to a psychology of drawing is information about the living of a person who enjoyed rather than about the dying itself.
And simply reflect the fact that we've got one dies and even when it dies off entirely, it does not have to do so with an experience of a practical demise or well, I take that to be sort of on my side, right?
I mean, the important thing is the factical demising is perishing under some interpretation.
But what's important isn't perishing under some interpretation.
It's the kind of life that has got the structure it's got because it's got a certain interpretation of perishing.
So that seems inscrutable.
Okay, Curtis, your turn is.
The Dasein demise.
What's it in the truth of what?
It follows demise.
And demos the other way around.
Organic stuff, yes, bodies perish.
And what do you have to add to perishing to get demising?
Something only the Daseine can do.
What?
Can do.
I think, yeah, I think.
It's just a matter of how demise would be.
Paris would be only biological life.
That's all right.
But what makes the end of Daseine different than the end of biological life is that it's been taken up into a Dasein life and given an interpretation.
Okay, we agree about that.
Yes.
I think, I mean, well, I think that just can't be right because I think Heidegger thinks that demise is something that the Dasein does.
I mean, it is an intermediate phenomenon.
Yes, dying is...
Dying is, that's right.
See, you're just adding one thing.
There is perishing, which is what organisms do and who do too.
There is demise, which is a stand-on, what it is to be a perishing kind of creature, which we exhibit in our behavior.
And then there's authentically dying, which is, so to speak, the right stand, which is not to cover it up, for instance.
Whereas the way Dasman, the one, deals with perishing, is already dealing with demise, which says demise happens to other people in the future, or parr perhaps it happens to other people in the future.
And that's a way of dealing with parishing.
That is a kind of demise because you've already taken a stand on it in what you do.
That's what I think.
Yeah.
Passing away is a way to describe this intermediate phenomenon.
And it's an event at the end of your life.
Yes.
And but we have to add in there something like, what is it that people can do at the end of their life called passing away?
It's got to be something for which there's been their which has already affected how they live, something like that.
Otherwise, I don't see the difference between passing away and parroting.
There isn't much difference.
Oh, they're making a big deal about the difference, though, isn't he?
Well, dying is a way in which being is towards its death.
According to the Daseine never perishes, however, it can demise only as long as it's dying.
And dying is what, it's the way of being in which the Daseine is towards its death.
That's what I'm trying to get.
I mean, the way of being, it is, well, everybody's got something to say about this, but the Stephen, you haven't said anything.
Daseine interpreted it.
It essentially decreases.
I mean, you're making it seem as if somehow demising, I mean, maybe this is right, but I'm on the wrong track then.
I thought demise was an okay term, but demise describes even the end of authentic Dasein, doesn't it?
I mean, all the Dasein demises.
All Dasein perish too, but whatever, but those are two different things.
A Daseine perishes or organisms that come to the end.
And a dodge demises has an already interpreted version, uh, or version of what it is for a Daseine to come to the end.
And I still hold on to that.
I think I don't worry.
I want to go back to this just because I don't think we're going to get any further, and I've got a lot further to get.
So if I mean with me, I may not say anything in the term.
Doddine has been authentic to die.
I think that wait, wait, does that come in?
No, well, that's the other view, the one I'm denying.
So we have to find some that I want to say, all dodge, even authentic dodge, demises.
This is the question.
You're saying, no, no, the inauthentic Daseine demises, but authentic Daseine dies when it doesn't demise.
Authentic Daseine demises and dies, and we haven't really gotten to it.
Now you're looking unhappy, Curtis.
Well, I was saying, good, that makes me happy.
And so does the agreement.
So a lot of people.
I'm playing a while in the head.
Okay.
So I'm going back to this.
Where are we now?
This is this is the sense in which you dwell.
What I'm trying to say is you dwell in it, not on it.
So then you're dying.
Then you're not only perishing, but you are living a certain, an authentic attitude toward the fact that you're a kind of being the characteristic.
Let me see what I think from 306 that I want to talk about something.
Well, I just say being towards death is a possibility.
I don't see why that's important.
And it's a way of living the fact or the living the structural possibility of the impossibility of any existence at all, he says on 307.
It's not just a way of relating to perishing, but it's a way of relating to perishing as the impossibility of any existence at all.
And a specific way of doing that, I think, that we were talking about.
Let's see now if I want to say anything more, just so I'm just summing up where I thought we got more or less in agreement.
Yeah, I think that's okay.
So then I write anxiety gets it right on 310.
Let's see what that is.
Anxiety is just being introduced there on 310 in Titalics as the Dasein finds himself face to face with the nothing of the possible impossibility that's existed.
That's, I just mentioned, that's the anxiety of death.
There's going to be, I mentioned this once before, but keep your eye open for three kinds of anxiety.
This one, which this gets defined, there's an anxiety that goes with choice, in which you make a choice, a furious choice, while getting married to one person excludes all the other people you might have married.
And that's an anxious making, I think, for him.
You'll see the choice one.
I don't remember where it is.
It goes by very fast on one page.
He doesn't care about that kind of choice.
And then there's the anxiety of guilt, which we've already talked about.
How can I stop the anxiety of guilt that partly that you couldn't get behind your thrilliness, but I don't think that's the whole thing.
Well, it is that you can't get behind your throwiness, and that means that everything, the true that might have been guidelines for your existence turns out to be ungrounded.
And that's the anxiety of guilt.
You can't make explicit what it is to be an authentic person.
And you have to just do it.
And then so then there's this anxiety of death now.
It's what you feel in or the experience of the possibility of the impossibility of your existence.
And then we're right back on page 311, which is so important to me because it says that anxiety can't be depression.
I said this to Bill Blattner because it turns out that anxiety is a disposedness that Dasein, authentic Dasein, is always in.
That's the end of that long thing where it says freedom toward death, a freedom which has been released from the illusions of the day, which is practical, certain of itself, and anxious.
That's what you've got when you've got anticipatory resoluteness.
That's the kind of life, the kind of experience you're having of your life.
I got stuck on this earlier thing again, rereading that.
Every time you hear one of these things, it looks a bit different.
The topic 311, I go back to the beginning of that italics.
Anticipation reveals to Dasein its lossness in the day itself and brings it face to face with the possibility of being itself primarily unsupported by concerns or solicitude.
That's you know, I can see that that's just a generalization of that nobody can help you out when you're dying, but this is it's getting toward the wrong one, the strong one that Eugene mentioned.
It sounds too isolated and too much like you don't want any.
But if you've really got this basic attitude toward demise, if it's demise, and this is your attitude toward it, to put it that way, then you're all alone and you're always anxious, and it sounds so heroic, neoliberal, potentialist, which is what it's always risking being, putting into.
That's why it's important to read the Tara White chapter that I gave you, my version of Tara White, because she's the antidote to that.
She's the one who's trying to say, in effect, that's much too personal, isolated, and so forth.
If you want to unpopulize death, it's got to be a much more general phenomenon.
It's got to be, I'll just say it, the possibility of world collapse in your world and in our cultural world collapse.
And it's got to be that possibility taken over in a positive way.
Only if you're in the world disposing business, then the fact that your world collapses if you do it right isn't a bad thing at all.
It gives you another chance.
Or you one way of my slogan is you've got to die in order to be reborn.
Christian way of thinking about it.
But I mean, that's, I mean, this is much too much of a dark side because you don't get the sense how important it is that your world could collapse or that you could then have the thought that you would that's the vulnerability.
The possibility that your identity could collapse, that your world could collapse.
It isn't just that you're going to perish someday and go find yourself in the middle of perishing.
Then you can make more sense of how this could be a positive thing, and it just could be a positive thing, but you can't make much sense about why you don't have any support in terms of solicitude.
That just seems too strong.
I want to say something more about that just a second.
Oh, yeah, I brought along a book I wanted to show you.
I'd tell you at some point.
If you want another slance on the sort of greater Heidegger or the more formal, more ontological issue of world collapse and how to deal with world collapse, and you want to sort of echo of John Hoagland's actually applied.
There's this interesting book.
Has anybody seen this, Radical Hope by Jonathan Lear, who's a philosopher at Northwestern?
Yeah, sorry, yes, University of Chicago.
And what it's about is the collapse of the world of the Crow Indians when they were suddenly taken out of their world where they were hunting animals and scalping enemies and put on a reservation so that nothing anymore was worth doing or made any sense because they couldn't do all the things that they used to do, which were heroic and worth doing.
And then what Lear is interested in is how does this world collapse get taken up?
And what is the Crow Indians way of doing it versus Fitting Bull's way of doing it?
Hoagland is playing a big role in this, and therefore Heidegger is playing a big role in this at secondhand.
Because what Jonathan Lear is trying to understand is how the group of the Crow Indians was able to help them from the prayer in the face of world collapse.
And if you read it, and you'll see, you get a very interesting sense of, well, I have to tell you, this way we used to give a discussion on this at the American Philosophical Association meeting in March.
I mean, what I'm going to talk about anyway is the fact that Hoagland and Lear don't make a very important distinction.
You can't tell when he says world collapse, what do it with buffalo burgers, which is the way he does it.
There are no more buffalo, so you can't have any buffalo burgers.
That just means that sort of something in your world is missing and you feel bad about it, and you can feel nostalgic for the good old days when there was buffalo hunting.
That's not the Heidegger way of thinking about it.
That's probably Jonathan Lear's way of thinking about it.
But Hoagland, towards the beginning of the book, is thinking about it in a much more Heideggerian way where it's not meaningful anymore what these Indians do.
The whole world of meetings that supports never mind buffalo burgers now, the hunting buffalo and so forth, isn't just that they're no more buffalo to hunt.
Maybe that is the real problem.
But the way Hoagland sets up the problem, it means that you can't understand anymore even why you wouldn't want to hunt buffalo.
And the big difference.
Try to think of it this way: that if you've got real-world collapse, and not just you can't find any more buffalo to hunt and eat, real-world collapse, you won't have any nostalgia for the good old days when you had buffalo and you could hunt them and eat them.
And why won't you have that?
And that's what sitting ball is.
Why won't you have that kind of nostalgia?
Because if it was real-world collapse, the whole meaningfulness of the world would be gone.
And I'll give you two examples.
Suppose you, it's like falling out of love.
I mean, but one, you made, I mean, one thing you could just not be able to get the loved one.
I mean, I'm stuck in tears here and trembling, of course.
But anyway, the falling out of love is different.
You can't understand why you ever wanted them.
And you don't feel nostalgic about getting them back.
What would you do with them if you got them back?
Well, they're just boring people like everybody else and so forth.
So, and you've got to, and this big distinction is you've got to keep in mind if you're thinking about what's happening in the death chapter.
The death chapter isn't about some things just happening to become impossible, like buffalo burgers.
It's about a way of life, your way of life, becoming unintelligible.
Let me get this across in another way.
I mean, the Hoagland example, which is about science.
When Newtonian science collapses and you get Einstein in it, or when Aristotle, it's even more dramatic, sort of stopped working for the medievals and Newton copes over.
It isn't as if he could build nostalgic for the good old Aristotelian days or the good old Newtonian days that nobody can even understand why anybody would have believed such a weird thing as that there's the sublunar sphere and the superlunar sphere and things are speaking in their natural place in the middle of the earth.
What kind of nonsense is that once you've got Newtonian?
And so what this old canton is about, that's because this is sort of the Hobran-Carol White point, is that in your life, and that's the falling in love kind of example, or in the culture, and that would be like what happened to the Indians, if you understand it one way.
Never mind, the Indians are so confused because of Jonathan Lear.
What happens in the culture, let's try this the medieval understanding that we're all creatures of God, goes away and you get the modern understanding, thanks to Descartes, we're all self-sufficient subjects.
Then nobody's going to be, who's got it in the modern world, nobody's going to be nostalgic for the good old days when the hills were enchanted and we were all creatures of God.
Couldn't even understand why anybody would have believed such a thing, or if they could make any hope to believe such a thing.
Now comes the point.
It's not clear in being in time.
When you're thinking about individual world collapse, which is the possibility of known or taught ability, you're thinking of perishing with this thin on it that it's turned into demise because you've got to ban toward it.
Or are you thinking of a kind of dying that could happen when you lost your cultural background, your cultural background, or fallen out of love, when your identity is collapsed, or your personal world collapses, or your social world, or your scientific world.
What's confusing is Heidegger sometimes seems to have gotten up to the level at which it's so abstract and formal and ontological that he can deal with any form of world collapse.
And then it becomes the possibility of no more possibilities.
And that doesn't mean on your deathbed.
That means when your world is gone, or your sense of who you are is gone.
You can get it by even having a mission that fails, but you can get it even by having a mission that succeeds.
When, I mean, when Martin Luther King, let's suppose, really gets justice for the black people, and he's been on the mountain, and he's seen the promised land and all that, and he's ready to die.
It doesn't matter anymore if he says all that.
And then what is he?
But suppose he didn't die.
Well, then he's sort of lost because world collapse doesn't really mean that somehow bad things happen to the world.
It just means that your world doesn't give you anything to do anymore.
So if you, if, and Martin Luther King was sort of lost for a while and then he became anti-Vietnam, anti-Vietnam War, and he didn't do that very well because there were no peace marches to call and so forth.
So I think world collapse is so general and supposed to be so general when Heidegger was doing it right.
And this is what I tried to say in the thing I gave out, that anything that causes your world is significant, which grabs you and tells you what's important to do and what's not important to do and what you've got to do now and what you don't have to worry about because it's trivial, when that disappears, however it disappears, that's the kind of thing that death is.
And demise, I think, is just a special case of it.
And Heidegger got all too much entangled because describing what happens to people, so to speak, on their deathbed when they're not just perishing, but demising, and worrying about, he could have been worrying about the very general case of what can happen to a Dasein that's revealed in anxiety, namely that their world can collapse.
I mean, what attitude one should, now, and this is what I'm preparing next time without realizing it.
What standards could one take in the light of the possibility of world collapse on all these levels?
That's called anticipatory resoluteness.
How could you live being the kind of being who has to have a world and has to have a world of the sort that can collapse?
That's the really big question for next time.
Yeah.
The possibility that it's not part of the concept.
That's right.
Good.
Yes.
Good, good.
So, what I think, what I understand to write this, I think that he's talking about this very general thing about Dasein, that its world can collapse even though it's not, you know, and he's explained several times in the course of his life, but he gets hooked on a kind of paradigm page for world collapse, which is this thing that happens to people at the end of their life.
But I think that when he gets it really formalized, namely the possibility of having no more possibilities, that's what happened to the Crow-Indians, and I think he should stay at that level.
And one thing is poor, and again, read the thing that Carol White is so good on.
Heidegger Later is more interested in the death of civilizations than he is in the death of Dasein.
How could he, what's the connection?
Well, civilizations can collapse that where it doesn't mean anything anymore to do whatever they were doing.
That ought to fall under this.
Yet, this path that you're reading, and it's the one we should be paying attention to, and I'll go back to it now to paying attention to it, is certainly using demise.
This one time was ungetaroundable, what I always say, inevitable thing that's going to happen to Dasein.
It's not inevitable that your identity is going to collapse, your love is going to collapse, your world is going to collapse, your science is going to collapse, but there's something inevitable, namely the thing that happens when you're on your deathbed.
Now, now you want to sort of come.
Yes, I'll take that so well.
Yes, good.
Yes, that's right.
Death an example, a paradigm case.
For mine is a paradigm case of world collapse, but the possibility of having no more possibilities is not an event.
Okay, but but I'm a little worried because, in a certain way, world falling out of love and getting from the medieval to the modern world is an event.
It takes a while, but it was dying sometimes.
And it's a funny kind of event.
I wrote something about that.
Let me go back then because I skipped it.
You know, you could, I mean, it's not an event, and yet it is an event.
But the possibility of that is, also, the possibility of that is not an event.
I don't know how to get a possibility of that.
Okay, that's right.
So you should, whenever you hear about the possibility of no more possibilities, you should think of the vulnerability of your identity, of your culture, of your life.
That vulnerability is not an event.
See, that's what you're saying, right?
The event is the actual collapse of those things, and that happens too.
And okay, now, well, I don't know what to think.
Well, I haven't, you had your hand up every once in a while.
Part of the minds is dying, but I mean, for example, world collapse in the general sense that you're talking about, is that also non-relational to us?
No, and that's one of the problems.
I think you're pointing at a problem from a kind of angle.
Namely, if you make this event that happens at the end of people's lives, your paradigm, you've got to be careful of what you say about it.
For instance, you couldn't say it's non-relational.
I don't know what it means for, you know, a call for collapsing being non-relational or falling out of love.
Maybe that's non-relational, I'm not sure.
But there are certain, I mean, what I would like anyway is that he could give us the general ontological condition of how anything that the world becomes impossible and tell us how we could live in such a way that we are constantly expressing in what we're doing that we're the kind of creatures whose world can become impossible.
That's what he could be doing.
But if he sticks to the example of what happens on your deathbed, then I don't think non-relational is the right thing to say.
I also don't think inevitable is the right thing to say, because some people get through their whole lives without any collapse except for the one at the end of it.
Whereas I want, and therefore, inevitable, and you say it's inevitable, it's all just collapse.
I'm not sure.
I don't know.
It's not as inevitable as anything.
It does think it would have been the case, though, though time is going on pretty well still after several thousand years.
So you have to look, if you're interested in this, as you read it, ask yourself which of these characteristics of death or dying are applicable only to the event at the end of people's lives and which are general enough and ontological enough that they apply to a kind of being who, as long as it's as it is, is vulnerable to a collapse of all that makes its life meaningful.
That gives it a world, what gives it significance, that that's constantly vulnerable.
But now, I'll let, yeah, yeah?
Demise, the dawn of the people on the aspect of demise, is that part of the harmonic that you think is necessary for kind of reaping the authenticity?
Death in general type of general understanding?
That's interesting.
Sorry, I have a kind of gay feeling that you've asked me this question before in some words, but I really think about it and ask it again.
That's sidetracked by my feeling that I heard it before.
Say to you.
Paragraphic case, which is demise, is necessary for the harmonic general part of the formalized case to get to a general understanding of learning.
I see that's a good question.
Already have a good grip on demise, and that be his way into or not find his way into a general understanding.
That's good.
That would be the right way to do it.
To start with the cover-up, namely the therapy, and then see that that's not the question, but that demise is the question, that that's not the event, that that's not an event necessarily at the end of your life.
You may have several, I think.
Then you generalize some more.
There is that event at the end of your life, and it's inevitable, but you're still doing harmonious formal indication, and you see that that's still not the phenomenon.
That's not a cover-up anymore, but that's not the right whole story.
Then you see that even cultures can die and so forth, and then you finally get to the basic realization that that there's a certain kind of being whose world who has to have a world that has to have significance and can lose it.
Then you finally see that that's what the essential feature we're going to call death is, which I've covered up in several stages and we've uncovered it in several stages.
I'm answering you all right.
So, okay, now let me go on for a while because I'm going to discover that it's 4:30 and I haven't even done covered half of what I want to cover.
So I think I've got a lot of it covered, but let me look.
Did we look at 291, which is where I claim, I think we did.
Oh, yeah, we did that.
That's fine.
It's Dasein and Demise is not an event.
But look at this.
I've written this down now, kind of seemed to contradict myself.
Dasein is demise is not an event, not a future event.
That's true, because it's not something that you can ever experience your own demise.
Remember, we talked about that.
So this is an argument about demise, particularly, that it has a peculiar character of not because I said it's wrong to tell it's a cover-up.
That demise is something that happens in the future.
And we've been saying, oh yeah, but if demise is perishing, but from a certain perspective, then it looks like it is something that happens in the future.
And I think he's got an interesting view about that.
So let me look.
I think he thinks, well, you're going to speak from the outside and not as a s some thing that you're experiencing.
Demise is an event that happens in people's future, and it's an event that will happen in your future.
But it's never something that will actually happen in your future, because when it happens, you'll be dead, and you can't experience it as an event.
And he's got that in mind on 284.
I don't know why I think it's important, but I so let's see now.
The end of the paragraph: Dasein is not an event.
It's a phenomenon to be understood existentially, and to be understood in a distinctive thing, which must still be, okay.
So, let me see now.
Dying is not an event.
Is that about demise?
Is that telling us that demise is not an event?
Certainly, dying is not an event, if that means it's being always vulnerable.
But I think he thinks that even demise isn't an event.
Let me see if I can find that.
Look like 295.
There's a peculiar way, I think, I'm just trying to say this, in which world collapse is unintelligible.
Because when you're in it, you can't make any sense out of it.
And you're either in a world or you're lost, and then there's a kind of leap and you're in another world.
Let me see if I find it.
295, the name can say something, Chris.
And I want to say something about this framework, this weird stuff on 294 in the paragraph that has 251 written beside it.
Rise of ability to be dodzine cannot outstrip the possibility of death.
Death is the possibility of the absolute impossibility of dodging.
Thus death reveals itself as that possibility which is one's own low sorts of non-errational Datre scripts.
As such, death is something distinctively impending.
So that's a funny thing.
That's what I got puzzled about.
Really, everything is just plain something impending.
But demise is something distinctively impending.
What I want to say is, you can't even imagine it happening.
It's not something you can expect or await or even avoid.
That's why you cover it up with this parity that you can expect and be afraid of and avoid and so forth.
You can't, since you can't imagine what it would be like not to be in love with this person while you are, or what it would be like not to be a modern person while you are.
There's a sense in which you can't really have a sense of that collapse as something that's going to happen in the future because you can't have a sense of what that collapse is going to you that makes collapse makes no sense.
That's what the collapse of all intelligibility, though it actually happens, can't be something you can think about.
Wow, what would it happen if all the meaning of being me would disappear?
So what's the sense in which it's distinctively impending?
You can say, yes, it could always happen.
It can happen anytime.
It could happen right away.
And you can't picture that it could happen at all.
You're looking at puzzling.
But I realize, but how big do you distinguish between dying and lying?
Okay, I keep mixing it up, you should.
You say I think you think.
I do, I okay.
Yes.
Dying is a kind of way of acting.
It's a way of life.
Dying is a way of life.
Dying is what anticipatory resoluteness is a name for that way of life.
That's dying.
Perricing, we get protein.
And demise is what?
World collapsing.
World collapsing, right.
As opposed to the possibility of world collapsing, I take it.
Yes.
So the oncological structure of death is the constant possibility of world collapse.
When there is something called world collapse, I don't know what his name for it is.
What, dying?
No, such as we just use dying.
Right.
So what is the name for actual world collapsing?
That must.
Well, that part of the little confusion.
I don't know whether you can preserve it in dying for a certain time, what happens during your life?
Okay.
Demise, it seems, is a stand you take on parroting.
At least the way it comes up when he introduces it.
And maybe we should think that also gets generalized, so that after all, well, we talked about that, cultures can die and so forth.
So the demise better be a name for the event of world collapsing.
That's why, yes, he started terminal world collapsing.
Yes.
Okay, so let's get that for everybody.
Demise is terminal world collapsing.
Dying is the poss is a way of life in the face of the possibility of terminal world collapsing.
Sounds right.
Okay.
Wait now, where are you?
Where?
Okay, now okay.
We designate the intermediate phenomenon as demise.
What's the phenomenon?
What's that?
It's in between perishing and world collapsing.
World collapsing is dying.
This event at the end of people's lives is perishing.
And in between, I guess I'm all right, is the actual not the possibility I misspoke again, didn't I?
Yes.
Yeah, possibility of world collapsing, I keep wondering.
Dying is living a certain way of life which takes account of the constant possibility of world collapsing.
That's right.
When there is this intermediate phenomenon, actual world collapsing, then there is this terminal phenomena for organisms and maybe propulsive food.
Right?
No, no, no, but demise we need.
Oh, demise is world collapsing, right?
And there and being on your deathbed and ceasing to be alive is a case of world collapsing, actually happening, wi which we call demise.
It's a special case of world collapsing, I think.
Does that make sense?
It's the kind that happens to people on their deathbed.
We didn't say that last time.
We said any time a culture dies, it's a demise.
And there's other kinds of both.
Yeah, I think he does it because the way he set it up, demise is seems to be taking a stand on perishing.
If that's true, then he thinks only this special terminal one is demise.
And then we just haven't got a word for a world collapse, have we?
I mean, if we sort it out that way, we need a word for what happens to you when everything that gave your life meaning goes away.
Right?
Dying.
Dying is a way of acting.
Yeah, now I got you confused.
Okay, that's bad.
Yes, yes, you're right.
You're right.
The demise is.
But then again, you keep saying it in a way that confuses me.
Demise is not a stance you take on world collapsing.
Demise is world collapsing viewed in a certain way.
There's not another.
Oh, I misspoke.
I'm sorry.
Demise is heroing viewed in a certain way.
Heroicing is an event that happens to organisms at the end of their life.
That very event taken up and interpreted and lived in a certain way is, if you look at the end of, if something happens at the end of people's lives, that's you're going to call heriting.
But dying is a way of life, namely how you integrate into your life not only the possibility of that kind of perishing, but the general possibility of having no more possibilities.
Is that all right?
I think that I wish he did, but I think in fact he's got demise on his mind in here, which is a simple kind of terminal world collapse, which is happens to people on their deathbed, but within an interpretation.
But here's my question, and then we've got to stop going around in this.
What is the world, what is his term for this more general ontological, absolute possibility of no more possibilities, which could cover world collapsing this deathbed phenomenon?
I don't know it.
That's death.
Maybe that's death.
I actually, okay, that's, I think you're right.
Maybe we should write that on the board.
Now we may have an, but I've never understood how far all these words gave out.
So there's everything, there's demise.
I don't know how to spell it, but that's all right for the moment.
There's possibility of no more possibilities.
Is that death?
No.
Death is, is it?
What did you come up with as death?
I mean, what have anybody else think about the possibility of death?
I mean, I think you defined it as the possible.
That's death.
Okay, let's try that.
Where's red?
And that means this is also possible world collapse, right?
Possible world collapse.
Okay, and now we've got actual world collapse.
And what's the name?
You said the name for that is death.
That's what's confusing me now.
Right?
So we don't have a name for actual world collapse.
And we have this possible.
I thought it was a great.
Well, I thought it was a big breakthrough to put death down here.
And I think possibility of no more possibilities is dying, isn't it?
Dying is a way of being, right?
Possibility is our.
Which of these is death?
Death is a possibility of no more possibilities.
So maybe Curtis is right.
Since he doesn't care about this, I mean, you need to talk about world collapse.
Up here, everything gives you the event to talk about.
And this is what the event interpreted.
This gives you the structure.
It looks like you would want to have a name for the more general event, that this is a special case of, where this is what happens to individual Dodd Zions on their deathbed, this is something that can happen to cultures and everything.
What do you think?
Yeah?
Everything is the end of life, right?
Yes.
Anyway, let's put that up here.
End of life.
And here's the end of Dodzy.
And this is what, I'll say, down here is the possibility of absolutely no more possibilities.
What do you want?
Where do you have world collapse?
And you want to point out the world collapse.
He never says that.
But that's all right.
We say that.
Having no more possibilities.
Your whole world breaks down.
You can't have another double circle.
You can have another world.
That's right.
It's not terminal.
That's what's interesting about this is this is the possibility of no more possibilities, um and this is death.
And this is terminal.
Well, this this isn't terminal because this is a possibility this is the possibility of no more possibilities.
If it's the first to it, this is terminal, this is terminal, right?
This is a a possibility.
And this is actual world collapse, which is like a revolution.
We don't have a name for it.
But it's it's we call it world collapse.
And if it's noticed, by the way, just it's terminal in a certain sense.
I mean, it's the end of that whole mode of intelligibility.
It's you can't get it back and so forth.
But it's not terminal for the culture, for the person undergoing it, because they can do it several times.
They can fall in love and collapse.
Yes.
Yeah, but what's interesting is the structure of this one, which is really the important one.
I mean, this one is just one instance of this one.
Okay, for most.
What's that?
World collapse is before demise.
You mean it's more general when there is up here?
Okay.
Okay, I don't I don't think it's what the impact, you know, during your life.
You know, they got those back.
Okay, well, and I suppose, yeah.
When I make it stronger, you can say, well, it collapses the end of you.
Right?
That's why.
End of you, well, okay.
Possibility, a world collapse of you.
That's right.
It's yes, you get a new that could be.
Dasein can go through these ends of you several times with anxiety, falling out of love, losing all your chance to hunt buffalo, and so forth.
Yeah, okay.
Dying, you know, dying, that's right.
Let's put it in.
Let's put it in there.
Dying, we said, was here.
It's the way of life in count of this, right?
In all your behaving.
We'll see that clearer next time.
Takes account of vulnerability.
Ability, the world, the world collapse.
This is dying, right?
So let's put your dying over here.
Somebody write this down for me so I know what I've committed myself to.
If anybody can read it, let me try to read it.
Perishing, the end of life, demise, the end of.
What have I got here?
Dasein.
Okay, end of Dasein.
The possibilities of no more possibilities.
That's death.
That's lots of a world collapse.
Dying is a way of life.
It's a way of life that takes account of the vulnerability to world collapse.
Then finally, there is something natural world collapse, the end of you for which we don't seem to have a word other than natural world collapse.
Okay, did you write this down or could you, please?
Okay.
Now, now I'm going to go on.
If there is any place to go, on from here, let's see.
15 minutes, I can see how much I have to cover.
Yeah, I think I can do this.
Back to Donaldson's Stalinist way of life.
Huh?
That's just where I asked for what would be.
Okay, let's try this.
Now, just as guilt is supposed to make possible, oh, yeah, this is a terrible for me.
I'm giving this really as a course of a feminine or something, you're supposed to help me understand this stuff.
So, and you are helping now.
You can think of it.
So, well, all this or this is going to go into the second edition of the commentary.
All right, it helped a lot.
Now, I need help with the following.
So, the final move that Heidegger makes, we're back to formal indication now, and we're back to guilt.
It turns out that the cover-up story is made possible by and motivated by the new story.
That is, so this ontological guilt, he says, is the prediction of the possibility of having, of owing people money, of doing bad things that you feel guilty about, of having caused a loss which you now have to fix.
Why is the fact that you can't get behind your throneness and that there is no ground for what you're doing the prediction of the possibility of the ordinary meaning of guilt?
Where that doesn't mean now that it motivates that meaning, we saw that, that's right, fleeing motivates the cover-up by telling you that there are all kinds of laws that you better not violate.
How does this ontological structure called guilt make possible the everyday understanding of guilt?
And I hope somebody knows, because every year I go through and I don't know, and you guys are supposed to help me.
And then, oh, why do you can't figure that one out?
Think how much harder the next one is.
So it looks like dying, that is living, where's dying now here, living a life that takes account of vulnerability made, how to make demise possible.
Yes.
The thing that you started with in your formal invocation as what everybody thinks is guilt, and now the thing that everybody thinks is death, namely the event that happens to you at the end of your life, in which your world collapses for good, it looks like that meaning that everybody's thought that there is this event and it ends your life, you have no more possibilities, ought to be no, sorry, start again.
That the fact that you are vulnerable, but that you can express in your behavior your vulnerability, and then you live in anticipatory resoluteness, perhaps the structure, the ontological structure.
How does that make possible having a sense of demise and having an interpretation of your part of parity as demise?
Maybe when I say it, it doesn't sound so crazy as I thought.
So why do we understand parity as demise?
Not only because we're fleeting.
And sorry, oh, nobody's talking that nonsense.
Now let'm going to start again.
Why do we understand the end of our life as demise?
That's the question.
And the answer is supposed to be because structurally we are the possibility of our understanding the end of our life as demise is that we have we are vulnerable to world collapse.
And yeah, I mean I'm beginning to believe that there's something here.
Why are we thinking of our perishing as special?
Not just like all animals perishing.
It's because we are the beings who are vulnerable to world collapse.
And now you read that back in and you are able, you are led to interpret perishing as something special, namely demise, namely world collapse.
So what, I'm just working it out.
So what the formal indication finally discovered for death really was, namely the possibility of no more possibilities, gets read back into perishing and demise meaning we come up with the idea that what death is really about is an event in which where it are where there are no more telling.
Is this an event?
Yes, this is an event, isn't it?
Demise, the end of Dasein, it's an event.
And this is an event.
Dying.
No, this, the actual world collapse.
But when we come to understand that there is an actual possibility of world collapse, when we understand that living in it is death, then now we ought to get to, then we understand why, I think almost getting it, why we have almost, why we have to take a stand on perishing and why we just don't perish like animals.
It's got to do with ontological structure that we've discovered, is somehow making us able to see our perishing as a special thing.
I just about got it.
Is in each place mine?
The possibility of world collapse, demise, ending of Dasein, event, let's say, each place mine, that makes it demise.
It's what happens to me.
I put to my death on my deathbed.
Well, yeah, I mean, that helps.
Now, did we, I mean, I wish we had gotten as far as that with guilt.
We didn't, did we?
Nobody came up with an idea why the fact that you can't get behind the thronus and everything is ungrounded makes possible owing people things and feeling feeling guilty.
I just don't know what to say about that.
You want to say something about it?
You can't suddenly die and don't have an opportunity to have a woman who lives as well.
It doesn't.
Yes, I think that's right.
You can perish without actually dying.
Doesn't it just say that?
You said Daseine can.
Wait, wait, you said we should, did the sentence say that we can perish only while we're dying?
No, don't think that.
That's right, good.
Daseine can demise.
Daseine can demise only as long as it's dying.
Did we write ever dying on here?
Dying is where's dying?
No, you're dying, fine.
Okay.
Daseine demise only as long as it's dying.
Yeah, yeah, that makes sense to me.
That is, if it's living in a life that takes account of its vulnerability to world collapse, which is exactly the issue for next time, the life you've called anticipatory resoluteness, but we don't know what that is yet.
As long as it's living this kind of life, then it can understand that it's not an animal that perishes, but it's about a special way of doing somebody we call demise.
Is that what you're just saying?
And that fits the line you just read.
That's okay.
So, and I think I've just come to the end of what I want to say here, and I'm not a thing.
Dying makes life possible.
What did you just read?
291?
Yes.
That's what that's the next thing in my notes.
Okay, how many T, I've got only two more sentences.
So I'm just repeating myself.
What we need now is to describe the way the permanent possibility, no more possibility, permeates my life.
That's what we call dying.
And that's anti-preparatory resolution.
And also, I think it would help if everybody read the paper I gave out.
Now that you've heard all this, you'll see how that will sort of crystallize in your mind what we've been talking about.
Anything else anybody needs to say?
You want to make the last remark?
It's okay with me.
Yeah.
That's the possibility and the other possibilities.
And there's no more clear information.
Well, in the you mean you mean death on your deathbed is because you can experience the collapse of your world, of your love, of medieval science, of all these things.
And what you can't experience what's special about what happens on your deathbed is that it wipes you out even more completely.
I mean, I had something written about that, but I didn't talk about it.
It looks like there's something that has to be around even after your world collapses.
And that's this minimal thing of minus and that it is and has to be.
Those are the two ways he describes minimal diezo.
And what happens in, so to speak, everything kind of death, which really wipes you out.
You even get wiped out as a the that it is and has to be and a minus and so forth.
That there's important in a funny way because that shows that there is something special about this paradigm case of what happens to you on your deathbed.
But it seems that it should we we always pay pay attention to that if we're looking for a general ontological, structural understanding of death, which shouldn't emphasize with the kind of terminalness of death.
Because you can have terminal death for cultures and for science too, but they're not as terminal as what happens to people on their deathbed.
They just don't get another chance to have another world.
Okay, so it looks like there are, and there are probably more, sort of, asymmetries that get him into trouble that he should take this event on the deathbed as the paradigm case.
And you put your finger on the main one, I think.
And yeah, okay, Eugene gets the last word.
That's fine with me.
We still have four minutes.
Good.
We need a final trenching thing.
So let's hope this is it.
The bullet is an opportunity.
Okay, well, let's see that.
Of death may now be defined.
Death is the end of Dasein.
The Dasein's own most possibility, non-relational, certain, post-definite, not to be outstripped.
Death is a Dasein's end in the being of its entity towards this end.
That's the full final.
No, that's the full thing.
Death is, and it's the same thing that gets spelled out with all that with anxiety thrown in, you mean, when I said, is that before or after that other one?
No, it's the same thing that comes up on 311, in other words.
Is that right?
No.
Well, maybe not.
Let's stop and think about this a minute.
I think what's interesting is one of them, the topic 303, is about some definition of what death is.
And the topic 311 is about anticipatory resoluteness.
It's about how you live that structure.
You write that down.
So if 303 is about the structure of death, then that means 311 is about dying, as we put it on the board.
How you live it.
Yeah, three eleven is the authentic one.
Yeah, right?
Okay.
And three oh three is the structure that uh authentic dying has to will.
That is anticipatory resoluteness.
Okay.
Did that did you write that down?
Okay, good.
So for your next week.