So, the first one is the methodological issue.
And I just want to constantly sort of stress my reordering of it.
It looks like finally, with guilt, conscience, resoluteness, death, anticipatory resoluteness, historicality, fate, and destiny, we now ought to have the whole of authentic Dasein in our grasp.
But anything short of that, we wouldn't.
So, it's a good, so that's why I think you have to put all those pieces together first, and then you get to a point where you ask, have we now got the whole of the phenomena so that we can, and how are we going to, and what kind of hole have we got, and how are we going to deal with it?
And it seems, we remember we didn't know what whole meant and why somehow you didn't have a whole when he starts the problem and brings in death and the ahead of itself.
I think it becomes pretty clear that normally by whole, he means the total structure of Daseine.
And what's funny is he's got the total structure of Dasein when he's got the structure of care, and he's got the structure of care already in Division I.
So it's still not clear to me what is missing.
He seems to be using, as far as I can see, synonymously, Dasein being authentic, being whole, and the totality of the totalness of the phenomena being exhibited in what Dasein is doing.
I'll just read you 358, one of the places where you get these three all coming together.
At the beginning, well, the very first sentence of that section on the hermeneutic situation.
And by the way, I saw, I see, well, care and self-hood aren't in the same section.
I said they were.
They're just as contiguous.
And selfhood might as well be there as anywhere.
So let's go back to now.
At the very beginning on section 63.
So, in its anticipatory resoluteness, Dasein has now been phenomenally, has been made phenomenally visible with regards to its possible authenticity and totality.
And I'm pretty sure that the authenticity, totality is the same as the whole.
And we've now made it visible.
This is connected with the thing I said at first, but how he wouldn't be able to say that if he wasn't lucky enough to be reordered by me, because he wouldn't have everything there in its totality and whole yet.
He'd have a lot of lots of explaining to do about historicality at the very least coming up.
But he's got it the way we've got it.
We've got it all total and whole.
And now he tells us that as we study Dasein, we're always in a hermeneutic circle.
And that's a new, that's why this is the hermeneutic situation.
And it's interesting that he seldom ever makes explicit the sort of rules of the game of doing a hermeneutic analysis.
He goes over that very fast.
It's funny how famous he is, I guess thanks to Gottamer for having introduced the hermeneutic method, when he says practically nothing about it.
But he does say, when he introduces it, that there's a four-haba, a four-zicht, and a four-grift, a for-having, a foresight, and a four-conception, it gets translated, involved in hermeneutic investigation, and that it moves in a circle.
And he's going to bring up explicitly the circle.
But if you look for it, you can see that he's doing the forhaba, for zicht, Four Griff story as from the very beginning of the section.
If you just read you the little pieces, the next sentence says: the hermeneutic situation, which was previously inadequate for interpreting the meaning of the being of care, now has the required primordiality.
Dasein has been put into that which we have in advance.
See, that's the forehaving.
And this has been done primordially.
That is to say, this has been done with regard to its authentic ability to be a whole.
So there's the whole coming in again.
The idea of existence which guides us.
Well, now, stop with that.
So the first thing is we've got in our forehaving the whole structure of Dasein.
And we don't so much have it because we're in it.
We are it.
And that turns out to be important.
You have to think, well, Heidegger's telling you, and he'll come back to this, I will at the end, that he's authentic and that he's speaking from within, a total understanding or experience, primordial experience of what it is to be Dasein.
On 360, there's more about that.
Well, I'm getting it out of the sentence at the end of the top paragraph.
Every ontologically explicit question about Dasein's being has had the way prepared for it by the kind of being which Dasein has.
That's a reference to the forehaving.
That says, in effect, it's from within it that Dasein is going to describe it.
And then he comes to the four Zicht, that is the four sides.
And there he says, the idea of existence which guides us is as that which we see in advance, that's foresight, has been made definite by the clarification of our own most potential ability to be.
And now that we've concretely worked out the structure of Dasein's being, his peculiar ontological character has become so plain as compared with everything present at hand, that Dasein's existentiality has been grasped in advance.
That's the four concept.
That is, grasped in advance with sufficient articulation to give sure guidance for working out the existentialia conceptually.
See, so we now, that's somehow a four-conception.
I don't find all that very illuminating.
He never explains enough about what these terms mean that you know whether why he's sort of got them in here.
But I'm just telling you what he clearly thinks, that he's operating out of a forehaving and he's got a particular sense that he's already committed to looking at existence, which is the being that takes a stand on its own being.
So we've got, we're inside of an understanding of being and of understanding of Dasein.
We've got as our way of describing that its being, that what's essential about it is that its being is an issue for it.
And we've got as our goal to work out the existentialia.
Conceptually sounds sort of strange to me.
Sometimes he says articulate them.
I mean, I don't know what he means by conceptual, but it's now gotten such a meaning that it sounds too much like a lot of intentional content.
But all it means is that he's going to now spell out and describe in explicit detail the aspects of the existential structure of Dasean.
Now, so far, and we're always moving in a hermeneutic circle, telling us on 358.
On 358, I don't, I become surprised.
That's totally the circle, yeah.
Well, what I just read is moving in the hermeneutic circle.
I just, that is to say we are inside it.
And that's all we're going to hear about the hermeneutic circle for a bit.
Because a great big issue comes up in the next paragraph on 359, and I have to talk about it where it comes up.
And to me, it's very important, and maybe it isn't important to anybody else, and maybe I made it up, and you know, worry about it.
But I think there are two different meanings of falling, or three, really.
One of them means being absorbed in what you're doing.
Another one means, I think, being so well, it'll get clearer when I can only explain it when we're in it, so let me tell you more.
But he's going to explain why, let's try this angle, that he's going to tell us right now, but I'm going to come back to it, that when you do this kind of hermeneutic study of Dasein, anyway, you have to do violence to the subject, you have to wrest the truth from the subject, and so forth.
Now, that means at least you have to do formal indication.
And we're going to come back to that too in a minute.
But what I think is that there are two utterly different reasons that he's going to give us.
And he doesn't have a very distinguished, I'll show you a place where he messes up, I think, right, in putting the two different ones together in one sense.
And what are the two different ones?
One is, coming up right now in italics, the entity which in each case we ourselves are is ontologically that which is farthest.
And remember, that goes back to Division I, that the being of Dasein is nearest and farthest away.
And that's the claim, I think, that the background of intelligibility has to be transparent and not something you can study, or not something you normally thematize, and not something you can ever completely thematize.
It helps to think of it as the illumination in the room.
Just as the illumination isn't something you see, but it's that on the basis of which you are able to see things.
So, what Heidegger thinks is our understanding of being isn't something that you normally thematize and think about, but it's that in this famous word with that Vor Alf Hin, everything is intelligible.
Remember, being is that on the basis of which, that's the Voralfin, everything is understood.
And I'm saying the basis of which part of this is the background, and the background is pervasive and near, so pervasive and near that it's hard to talk about.
And it's covered up in that structural way.
And that's one of the meanings of falling.
Because so far, I'm just he hasn't said anything about why it's nearest or why what he wants to talk about is ontologically farthest away.
And he's going to go on now and say something that sort of goes in a different direction.
Our being amidst the things with which we concern ourselves most closely in the world, a being which is falling, guides the everyday way in which Dasein is interpreted and covers up ontically Dasein's authentic being, so that the ontology which is directed toward this entity is denied an appropriate basis.
That's still compatible with, you can't understand the background, the understanding of being.
Normally, you understand things and our vocabulary and our way of studying is directed at things.
And that's covering up our understanding of our being as we deal with particular beings.
And that's one meaning of falling.
Then a little further, the primordial way in which this entity is presented as a phenomenon is anything but obvious.
Even if even ontology approximately follows the course of the everyday interpretation of Dasein.
And now you begin to get this sort of violent language.
The laying bare of Dasein's primordial being must rather be wrested from Dasein by following the opposite course than taken by the falling ontico tendency of interpretation.
Well, now falling is also fleeing, in which Dasein is motivated to cover up its structure.
I don't know, I haven't got a reference to the word fleeing yet, but it will come around.
Or if it doesn't, anyway, it has to be in there because if the cover-up is an attempt to hide something, I mean, there's two, there's what can what is hard to get a grip on because we don't have the right kind of concepts and so forth.
That's the structural story about how it is hard to do the, to have a theory of the back, an account, a phenomenological account of the structure of the background.
That, I wouldn't call that a cover-up, but that he says that Dasein covers up its authentic being, and that you have to do violence to find it.
That's a fleeing story.
I mean, the ontological story isn't a cover-up.
It's just a structure that what is nearest is also farthest away, least accessible.
What is nearest and most pervasive is least acceptable.
That isn't a question of a cover-up.
And that's not a question, I wouldn't even want to say, of falling, though I think it has to come under his category of falling, as does absorption.
It's a very broad category.
But when you start saying that you've got to actually violently get to the truth about Dasein, that must be because Dasein is making a positive effort to fend off the it's, it's, and your, and you're Dasein, getting at the truth.
So you get this sort of, I mean, it's, I think, always in what he's doing.
Look at the paragraph now that begins: Dasein's kind of being, we're still in 359, thus demands that any ontological interpretation which sets itself the goal of exhibiting the phenomena in their primordiality should capture the being of this entity in spite of this entity's own tendency to cover things up.
Now, that's a hiding and a fleeing story.
It's not a structural ontological story, I think.
It sounds too psychological, really.
I hate it.
I think the whole theme in Being and Time, that Dasein is actually involved in fleeing and covering up its structure, is what Foucault calls the hermeneutic of suspicion.
And I think Heidegger is an example of the hermeneutic of suspicion.
Foucault's got this nice category that covers Freud, Marx, and Heidegger.
That puts Heidegger in very bad company, it seems to me, ontologically, anyway.
And that's what he's doing right here.
Because the hermeneutic of suspicion says that for some reason or other, human beings, each one, Freud and Marx and Heidegger have different arguments, are motivated to cover up the most important truth about what's going on.
And that the job of somebody studying human beings, whether Marxist, Freudian, or Heidegger, is to get at this deepest truth about human beings that's covered up.
And moreover, when you do get at it and can face it, it's liberating because a lot of the misery and distortion of social life or psychological life or just plain Dasein is caused by this tendency to flee and cover up.
So the job of somebody who believes in the hermeneutics of suspicion is to force people to face up to what it is they're motivated to hide.
All of that I just wish Heidegger didn't have.
I don't think he needs it.
I think all he needs is the structural point that it's hard to do a phenomenology of a being whose basic structure is to be the basis of all intelligibility.
Okay, now you can say some things about this.
Yeah, Ariel.
What?
Well, I have figured out that he's confused.
Let me give you one more thing before you say something.
The clearest place where the confusion comes out, let's see, I just wrote confused in a page number.
I have to find where it follows in the normal development of things.
I don't know whether to look in here or to look at all of my marks.
It's going to be an anticlimax, I'm afraid, but I find it very interesting, confused, and confused.
Oh, here we are, okay, on page 363.
Okay, now, what is distinctive, sort of almost exactly in the middle of the page, what is distinctive in common sense is that it has in view only the experiencing of factual entities in order that it may be able to rid itself of an understanding of being.
That's a fleeing story.
It's just trying to get rid of an understanding of being.
It fails to recognize that entities can be experienced factually only when being is already understood.
That's a structural point.
One of them is a kind of motivated cover-up, and the other one is, you know, failing to do something isn't like trying to get, failing to get rid of something.
It's not, failing, I'd have to find the right words not to beg the question.
You can't get rid of something without trying to cover it up, but you can fail to see it for just plain structural reasons.
And I'd so okay, now, yes, I'm not mixed up.
He's mixed up.
But go ahead.
Don't really, I realize I'm just a few years, and I haven't read that much higher, but I really don't like the notion of things.
I mean, the thread marks on the basis of the psychological.
I can't take it.
It's not like there's any like sort of psychological fault, but pushy if there's down or anything like that.
It's just sort of the way we fall in.
Yeah, one of the best statements of it is of all people, John Searle.
I would have brought it along.
He says, we are not normally in the business of dealing with the background.
We don't have the language to talk about the background.
And it's very hard to be able to get people to notice it without turning it into some object.
And the whole point is it's supposed to be not an object.
And I like that argument.
That's fine.
You don't have to attribute any sort of tendency to flee or cover up or what was this that I just had, whatever that word was.
What was it?
Get rid of.
You don't, it isn't as if there's anybody trying to get rid of anything.
Okay, well, you want to say something about this.
Oh, you're really, you're a straight man for this, because one of my favorite objections to Heidegger is that he has no right to base the fleeing on the fact that Dasein is exposed to anxiety.
And why?
Well, that's interesting.
That's because in the end, Dasein, and this is again, it would be the structure of the hermeneutics of suspicion.
When Dasein finally holds on to anxiety, guess what?
It's joyful.
So in the end, it makes no sense to say that Dasein is always fleeing or tends to flee anxiety.
Why would he need to flee?
Remember, anxiety isn't painful.
It isn't sort of breaking out in a cold sweat and wringing your hands.
Anxiety is a sense of the sort of basic spookiness of everything.
And okay, go ahead.
That's right.
I was trying to say.
Yes.
Yeah.
But that just reintroduces the point.
Why should we be upset by ungroundedness?
I mean, this is a kind of Wittgensteinian point.
I mean, it's only because we is it really true that we ask for the kind of ground that Descartes was asking for and Plato was asking for and that human beings all over need that kind.
Are the people in Bali suffering from the anxiety of groundlessness and rootlessness?
Or put it another way, once you accept groundlessness, you can lead a happy life.
You can get married and have children and climb Everest and do whatever you want.
You don't need grounds to lead a good life.
Yeah.
Okay, well, and then okay, then I'll okay, then I'll just put it into Western terms.
I mean, why uh should we think that ordinary people are suffering from this peculiar need to have grounds instead of just what well, but are they well that's what you'd have to think that they really are everybody really is Cartesian and and moreover that that and therefore not having grounds is very upsetting to them.
I mean Heider's got this sort of Wittgensteinian distinction between people who think that we're all grounded somehow and that there is in reason or nature or something the basic intelligibility that we can rely on.
Then there are the people who see that there isn't any basic intelligibility to rely on, and they think there's you've got to say it in German, they think instead of a grunt, there's an Avgrund.
An Avgrund is an abyss.
This is sort of a Sartrean thing.
It looks like, boy, there's no ground.
We are a feudal passion.
It's nihilism and terrible.
And then Heidegger says, why can't we just have an ungrundt, which is a non-ground?
And that's what I'm saying.
And why should we be fleeing the un-ground as if it were an abyss?
And the answer is, somehow, if it's the Cartesianism has invaded our culture, then he's got another problem.
Because he says he's doing transcendental study about Dasein Uberhaupt, supposedly, not just Western post-industrial Dasein or something.
And so the problem occurs all over the place.
I just think fleeing is you never should have bought it.
It starts in the first hermeneutic of suspicion is Kierkegaard, I think.
But that's a long story.
Kierkegaard at least got an interesting story about what we're fleeing.
But go ahead.
Oh, yeah?
It seems right that he's been sort of planning and kind of defying the structure and saying that anxiety can be positive.
And yet that's what he thinks.
Yeah.
Anxiety is a good thing.
Yes.
Sense that there's a leveling involved that it's in us, that it's somehow not easy to do that.
And that it's much easier to have an average intelligibility and be part of Das Ma.
And that that's what most.
It's sort of why and why do people want to be take it easy?
I mean, there's some psychological motivation being smuggled in here.
And you could sort of push it around, but it shows up someplace.
Very explicit is all the structural points that he makes.
But I really do think that smuggled in there is the sort of sense, like when you read the part on Das Ma, Either seems to have this negative attitude about leveling, even though he could never assert that it was somehow negative.
Well, the interesting thing is, I think, that he thinks that intelligibility is essentially leveling, and there's nothing wrong with leveling.
And that's again that he when he says authentic Dasein is always in the one, because there's no way you've got to have the one to have any way to do anything to get outside the concrete immediate situation into some generality and so forth.
So he's got to accept the one.
So then the issue comes again, then why this tone of shape up and you're fleeing into the one.
Why not just say, of course, the one has got to be there, but the one is something you also have to resist, but not in the sense of the you don't have to resist your tendency to flee into it.
You've just got to it's a complicated story, but I'll say it again, I say it often, work your way out of the one, not by getting more and more aphronomous like, getting more and more able to respond to the unique situation.
And even then, never completely, because there's always got to be this generality of the one in order to have anything intelligible.
And so now we get this question: why the motivation to what's the what's what's the bad motivation?
It's to use the one to cover up our nature.
And now where I'm asking again, what what's this how does he explain this motive to use the one to cover up our nature?
I mean, it you know, it looks like, well, it's because anxiety is terrible or groundlessness is terrible or resisting television and banalities and leveling is hard.
But none of it seems to make any it doesn't make any sense to me.
Yeah.
So the only difference between an inauthentic from the standard being an authentic one is that the inauthentic and fallen everything certainly you have to sort of work your way out of a kind of banality and a standard way of looking at things, which covers up what we are and everything covers up everything practically.
And now but the question is, wait, I just slipped my mind.
I have to get it back how I want to put it.
If you have to get out of that oh, I know, yes, but the idea that you have to you we have to use violence to get out of it and rest the people out of it.
Why don't you just I mean Wittgenstein manages to do a lot of this work without violence and without resting.
And it it only requires violence if the people are resisting the the the news you're bringing.
And that's what again I think he has no need or right to to say.
Once he points this out to us, we should all just say, yeah, that's how it is.
That's hard to see, but now that you point it out, I see it.
Well, that's that's a different issue.
We've got to put that aside.
I mean, how you get to be authentic is you should, I don't, you do it, whether you do it by Wilporn out is a deep point we're going to come to.
It's got to do with this choosing to choose issue.
How much in the background of what I'm talking about, there is going to be a problem about just how much receptivity and how much activity.
But not yet.
I mean, this is all I want to talk right now is, and I've done it, is just talk about that I don't think he's motivated the violence story.
Yeah, I guess Eric, I'm going to worry.
Go ahead, but be brief, folks.
It seems like maybe kind of just like stuff that hasn't made it in mind or hasn't streamlined it enough, and it's kind of stuck between your ontological statement, the whole world and story of the whole structural story, which is very fruitful and great.
And this like weird ethical statement that you're talking about.
Well, that's what I think.
Yeah, that's and he doesn't need it.
And I don't even understand where he thinks he gets it because it sounds sort of haunted and psychological.
No, you guys are monopolizing this discussion.
Tyler wants to say something.
To what?
Okay.
Yeah, well, I thought you would think that, and I'm eager to hear what you have to say about it.
So at the startful level, there's a sort of fault, which is what fallen from the world decides to think of remote structure within which God is so far.
So it has the sofa.
We take on basically some ordinary motivational structure, taking all the violence.
Which is which is what?
Oh, absolutely, absolutely.
That's fine.
And that's a, isn't that interesting?
I like that.
But it's a funny thing.
It's a third angle.
Because it isn't a, I'm a fleeing, resisting, facing, but it isn't just structural.
It's, as you say, something like genetic, or I mean, I can't find the word, developmental.
Let's say it's developmental.
The way we grow up and get socialized has this built into it, that we are all going to want to do the standard thing.
But I'm not sure that.
Okay.
And this violence and resting on your version is that he just has to shake you up.
And he needs to shake you up because you're in the tranquility of saying, I already know how to do it, there's a standard way to do it, and so forth.
Okay, but it doesn't actually transform the motor structure.
So it doesn't mean that one is a main thing on one vessel.
Okay, so we have to change that structure.
And that's the violence that's going to happen.
Except that it's sort of in this book a kind of methodological violence, and that's not going to change anybody's structure.
So I'm happy if you all just have seen that there's a problem here and if anybody wants to write a paper about it, you're welcome to do it.
And I'd be shocked but interested to see an account that makes fleeing work or motivates the fleeing.
Yeah.
I think if nothing else, it remains compelled.
And it's dangerous, of course, the fact of the concept of that.
But I mean, I think it's a lot imagined situations, say, where you know somebody and they're they're doing a lot of work along the regular subject and they're really caught up in the world of the work they're doing.
They can't find the answer to what they're doing.
And they're confused.
You look at that without making a value judgment at the time and saying, well, look, you know, you're really caught up in what's going on.
You haven't really considered that, you know, these terms that you're using, you know, the definitions are very vague.
You don't really understand what's going on.
The grounding that you think you have, with which you perform whatever you're doing, isn't really there.
And you tell this person this, and then you become very expensive.
And you get eggs.
And they're like, oh, you know, we can't just tell you what I'm doing.
Okay, but wait, that's enough.
I mean, because that's not going to be a cover-up.
The way you tell the story, that's a different issue again.
Yeah, you can explain why they resist what you're telling them.
And that's part of it.
But the basic claim is that the whole way Dasein sets up the understanding of themselves and the world is to hide the fact that Dasein is ungrounded and to not have to experience the anxiety that comes with that realization.
And that and so and you're telling me all kinds of other stories about why Dasein d ca has trouble facing the structural things that Heidegger wants to describe.
And I just want to say, well, each one of them we could discuss on its own, but I think the least tenable of all of the candidates, the developmental and the perseverant one, and so forth, the least tenable is that it's built into Dasein structurally across the board that it's fleeing anxiety is the main motivation for why it has the wrong understanding of the world.
But I'm going to go on.
I mean, I would be very unhappy if I discovered that we've spent the whole day on this.
So let me see where I am.
There's a harmoneutic circle.
There's a whole lot of questions I just run through that I just don't think he's got he's answered satisfactorily.
Is why you believe anxiety reveals the truth that nothing has intrinsic meaning?
Why say that it's a basic disposiveness?
Does guilt really show that all our practices are ungrounded?
And what does that even mean?
And why, and let's see what else.
We have to start with the aurantical everyday understanding, but we have to get out of it.
So let me see, I'm skimming to get out of it here.
And we want to understand why there is this systematic cover-up that obscures the structure of our being.
Okay, and why isn't there enough cover-up just in the way the illumination in the room is, quote, not really covered up, but not easily accessible to us and describable?
So let's see.
So here we get to the violence on 359.
And so then we get finally to how can we know that the ontological understanding we've arrived at is phenomenally adequate?
That is, how can we ever know we're not just part of a cover-up and that there's any that you could ever get outside of it?
And now, then, Heidegger's, that's when we're back to formal indication.
The method for getting, if you're dealing with any kind of distortion, it doesn't really have to be a cover-up.
But the way to deal with it, and if you're all in it, because you already have this forehaving, you're not working from outside, if you're in this hermeneutic circle, the only way to get out, not to get out of the hermeneutic circle, you don't want to do that, but to get clear about the structure from within the hermeneutic circle is formal indication.
What's sort of interesting is Heidegger wrote pages and pages about formal indication in his lecture notes, and the ones on religion have a big thing about it.
I could, if you want me to, you can ask me and I'll give you references.
And it's hardly visible in here.
And yet it does the crucial job.
And I just want to show you, the translation just covers it up, misses it.
Absolutely, probably the worst moment in the translation, it seems to me, is where he says at the top of 362.
No, that's not it.
361.
Yes, 361, middle of the page.
Look at this.
How many realized that they just, when you read the sentence, you just read a mouthful of gibberish and didn't, and did you notice, or how you so, is it all so much like gibberish to you that it doesn't seem like any more than any other?
Look, in indicating the formal aspects of the idea of existence, that's the beginning of that, of the second full paragraph.
What in the world can that mean, indicating the formal aspects of the idea of existence?
Well, it doesn't mean anything.
The German just says, but in formally indicating existence, which is what he did remember way back at the beginning when he said we'll formally indicate God Zein as the being that's being is an issue for it, and we'll call that existence.
And it happens again at the bottom at that paragraph.
The idea of existence, which we have posited, gives us an outline of the formal structure of the understanding of Gasein and does so in a way, and that's also formal indicating.
But there's also a place.
Oh, I just want to say that Joan Stanban, I think that's nice because it's nice that I've always beating on Joan Stanbaugh, but this page is so much better than the translation.
It just says, her translation, our formal indication of the idea of existence was guided by the understanding of being, so forth.
And that's straightforward and right.
Okay, now, where am I?
I jumped there.
So this is, we have to, so how do we do it?
How do we find out, get the phenomena undistorted if for whatever reason, and now we're just putting this under the general category, never, I don't want to say it's covered up.
Not that there is a cover-up, just that our experience of the phenomenon of us and the world is distorted and covered up.
What do we do about it?
Well, we use formal indication.
We assume, by the way, I worried once, which I want to, I understand now.
I ask myself the question: how come Heidegger provisionally gets it right about Dasein when he gets it wrong about guilt and wrong?
I mean, Heidegger thinks that we all get it wrong.
Our whole shared understanding gets it wrong about guilt and death and the self, we'll see today.
And informal indication always has to start out with where things are wrong.
How come where the most important thing, Dasein, is at stake, he doesn't start out with something like, we're a rational animal, or a part of nature or something.
He jumps right in and tells you the real right answer.
Well, I always realize that's because he has written the book already, so to speak.
He knows the right answer.
But what puzzled me was: why then does he call it provisional?
Why doesn't he just say, I know, and you will be convinced by the end of this book, that Dasein is the being whose being is an issue for it.
Well, I now see what's going on.
There are two sort of, he doesn't explain altogether what, what's going on, but one, he's understood that we are a being whose being is an issue for it.
But what's provisional is that that's our essential structure.
He hasn't, something is provisional, and if he hasn't shown it, and he won't have shown it till the end of the book, what would he be showing?
Well, that if you take us to be the being whose essence, if you take if you believe that Dasein has an essence, and you take its essence to be that it takes a stand on its being, then you can explain all the other phenomena.
That's the test for the essence.
I mean, the essence of gold, if it's 79, explains the ductility and the malleability and the yellowness and the conductivity and everything about gold, every causal property of gold.
And in a similar way, if he gets it right about the essence of Dasein, then all the other stuff in here has got to be following from it.
And explain, it worked out as our structure.
And that's what he thinks.
He thinks that he knows what's he provisionally, one of the things we do is take a stand on our being.
And he's just observed that.
But what he wants is to show that we have an essence and that's our essence.
And so I just wanted to say that because for me that sort of helps a little understand how.
Unlike, see what I'm saying is, unlike all the other forms of formal indication that he's got, why, yeah, you want to close it?
Good idea.
Is it the noise or the draft or both?
Okay.
So he gets the formal indication on 361, even though thanks to the translation you can't see it.
And he's, and he helps us understand something on 362, which is a confusion.
What is it?
Oh, yeah, this is just the next point.
I'm not deriving anything from that point.
But it's related.
The essence of Dasein is its existence.
And now I want to just talk about this fact that he's using this term existence.
Existence is the name for a way of being for which its being is an issue for it.
That's why we study these existentials.
Now there's something that's going to sort of disturb you.
And it disturbed Heidegger finally.
He realized he was confused.
At the top of 362, and it's all over the place.
He talks about a threefold distinction of existence, facticity, and fallen.
And all over the place, you will find that existence is his name for the future projective dimension.
But existence is also his name for the whole structure.
That is, that's the way of being of Dasein.
Well, that always annoyed me.
And one day I discovered, thanks to the fact that the footnotes are in the Stanbaugh translation, but now I have to find where it is.
315.
It's right at this point where he writes something in the margin.
So that means in the German 315 in the margin, I marked it.
Oh, here it is.
No, it isn't.
Yes, he notices and he writes existence, one, for the whole of being of Dasein, and two, only for understanding.
Understanding is the projecting dimension.
And so he realizes that he should have used two different terms.
He certainly should have.
Existence is a nice term for Dasein, and it had the way of being of Dasein, and existentialism is already around.
Kierkegaard has defined himself as an existential thinker, and doing these existentialias all very well.
Then you need a new word for the future directedness.
One of the words is understanding, but we need a bigger, more, a broader category, more abstract.
And I don't have any proposal.
That's his problem.
But you have to realize when you come across the term existence, that it almost always means the future dimension of Dasein's activity, projection.
And that, but of course, when you come across existentials, that always means the threefold structure of thrown, falling, and projecting.
Okay, I don't know.
There's nothing to discuss there.
We just have to sort it out and go on.
Let's see now.
And now we're back to the hermeneutic circle, which he didn't name before.
I named it.
On 362.
You get the whole hermeneutic circle going by again.
And you get it carefully sort of wrapped around formal indication this time.
The middle, the second paragraph, he says, This understanding is, he's talking about understanding Dasein's being.
This understanding is to be grasped primordially only on the basis of a primordial interpretation of Dasein in which we take the idea of existence as our skew.
There, I take it existence as opposed to being taking a stand on your being.
Does it not then become altogether patent in the end that this problem of fundamental ontology, which we broached, is one in which we move in a circle?
And there we are, where that's the hermeneutic situation.
So we go on a little.
We have indeed already shown in analyzing the structure of understanding that so and so it moves in a circle.
That was that quick run through of the four structure in division one.
In spite of this, if the problematic of fundamental ontology is to have its hermeneutic situation clarified, our investigation must now come back explicitly to this circular argument.
When it's objected that the existential interpretation is circular, it said that we have presupposed the idea of existence, and that Dasein gets interpreted accordingly, so the idea of being may be obtained from it.
But then it turns out, and we don't have to read it all, that that's the way things work.
You've got to stay inside, and you've got to do formal indication to do hermeneutics.
The one place that comes out, and I think it's nice to see how that hangs together, is the bottom of 362 in the italics, which are, of course, completely mistranslated, so you can't see it.
But I will read it so you will see it.
Skimming down, starting so that it may decide of its own accord.
Where do we have to start?
We want to let that which is to be interpreted be put into words so that it, Dasein, may decide of its own accord whether, as the entity which it is, it has the state of being in terms of which it should be.
It's always the getting the Voralfin wrong.
So the state of being in terms of which it has been disclosed in the projection with regard to its formal aspects.
No, it's been disclosed in formal indication.
I mean, so there you can just see that that's the method you've got to use when you're in a hermeneutic circle.
It's in the German you can see formal and on its formal and formal and seigen Erschlossen.
That's no formalen onseigen.
Yeah, that's form formal indication is what you're doing.
So now we're in the hermeneutic circle and it does that and that it needn't be violent.
I'm just summarizing where I am.
And so we're back to fleeting again and the cover-up story.
I just wanted to show you that it's coming up again on 368.
'Cause when I mentioned it I hadn't I didn't go directly to the fleeing quote 'cause I didn't know where it was 'cause I put it later in my lecture.
Here, I'm in the middle of 368.
The everyday interpretation of the self, it's going to do it, we're going to do it with a self, has a tendency to understand itself and terms of the world with which it's concerned.
Now, that's fine.
Nobody wants to say that we, that's the John Searle version, which is all you need.
When Dasein has itself in view onto, it fails to see itself in relation to the kind of being of that entity, which is itself.
That's fine.
What is the motive for this fugitive way of saying I?
It is motivated by Dasein's falling, for as falling, it flees in the face of itself into the one.
Okay, so there, that's the right way it says 322 in the margin.
Now, I'm not quite ready to get to the self yet, though.
I'm going to get there in just a minute.
On 363, you know, we still have to look at something.
Oh, well, that's the one I showed you, where they get rid of an understanding of beings and fail to recognize an understanding of being are put side by side in a way I don't think they should be.
Common sense misunderstands understanding.
That's sure.
That's because we normally cope with the kind of things that you understand as things.
But therefore, common sense must necessarily pass off as violent, anything that lies beyond the reach of his understanding.
There is always this thing that because the fleeing is lurking in this trap, in this paragraph, so is the violence.
So, Heidegger, one of my things, and this is what I listen to.
So, this is how this is Heidegger explaining how we're going to get to the phenomenon when it's covered up and so forth.
And the first point I was making was formal indication.
And now I've got a point: our pre-ontological understanding of being is on grounded, according to Heidegger, motivates a tendency to flee, which in turn justifies not taking Dasman at face value.
This sort of just, I think this justifies formal indication, I mean, in Heidegger's picture, because guilt as something you owe is covering up the fact that it's not a question of owing at all, but not getting behind your thrownness.
Death as an event at the end of your life covers up the fact that dying is something you're doing all the time, and so forth.
And why is this all happening?
Because there is a tendency to flee and into Dasman.
Therefore, not only is Dasman too general and banal and standard to get at the real unique situation, it also doesn't have a clue as to how to deal with Dasein.
And Heidegger's explanation of that is that in order to flee ungroundedness, Dasein flees into Dasman, and Dasman has a view of us as objects.
Let me see if I can.
There's more to say about that.
I don't think so.
And Das and Heidegger, now the final point is: I'm still asking, how does Heidegger get to the phenomenon?
Well, Heidegger experiences anticipatory resoluteness.
He's authentic.
I mean, how you get to be authentic, I haven't talked about yet, whether you do it by willpower or by grace or whatever.
But Heidegger's clearly sees the phenomenon, and therefore he's in a position to break out, I think, would be better, the ordinary way of doing thinking about it, telling us his way.
And this leads to something I want to get clear.
Well, first, there's the problem of wholeness.
So, what happens here?
He does see the whole, starting right below 64.
Through the unity of the items which are constituted for care, look at this now, the same puzzle, you know, that he should have fixed.
Existentiality, facticity, and fallenness.
There, it's quite clear that he's using the term in a different way than he should.
It has become possible to give the first ontological definition for the totality of Dasein's structural whole.
So, now he's got the story of Dasein's structural whole.
Remember, now this is just me trying again to justify my reordering.
The issue at the beginning of Division II was we haven't got Dasein's structural whole, and we have to do all kinds of things to fix that.
But we've already got existentiality, facticity, and fallenness all over the place in Division I.
Then, so what else do you get when you get the structural whole?
Well, I don't really know.
It's obviously what you get when you get, when you're authentic and you get the authentic totality.
This is what he's talking about at the top of 364.
By exhibiting anticipatory resoluteness, we have brought Dasein before us with regard to its authentic totality and with it with authentically whole.
There must be some kind of inauthentic whole so that we now have it in advance.
The authenticity of the potential, the ability to be a self guarantees the primordial existentiality, guarantees that primordial existentiality is something we see in advance.
He's still getting, whoever wants to write a paper on the hermeneutic, there's, you know, seeing in advance is the fours issues, the four sight.
He keeps using the terminology of the threefold aspects of hermeneutics just without signaling that he's doing anything special with it.
Partly because I don't think there's anything interesting about it.
I mean, he's just pushing it in here.
But why there are these.
I never understood why there are these three, four having, four sight, and four conception, why there couldn't be four or two.
But they do a good job these three.
I bet you could think of another one.
But anyway, the three are supposed to map onto the temporality structure, presumably.
All right, no, I don't really know.
That's another paper topic.
He never tells us that they do, and I don't know if they do.
The past, let's try it, is something like the four-having, because the past is the always already.
He's already built that into the care structure.
So that what you are, what you're always already in, the four-sight will have to be the present, alongside entity.
That's very far ahead.
And the future one is going to be the four conceptions.
Why, why you know, I I give up.
No, you can't do it.
I can't do it anyway.
Map it onto the threefold temporal structures.
So, let me go back to where I was.
The the so now the problem of wholeness has got to be something more than just knowing this structure, it's got to be, I take it, actually experiencing fully what it is to be a thrown, falling, projecting being.
And though he had the wholeness all along, he didn't have it in its richness or something is one of the words he uses.
But pilots ask the five senses I think you know, I just richness or best the market's working.
Yeah, I think so.
You Deli or I think that's right, but let's think about why that is.
What does he say that even?
I don't remember.
Well, he could okay would be because he realized the structure to just give us care as being ahead of his development.
Seems to preclude an existential identity that he could never