And it it starts with the discussion of death, and which is the sort of ultimate most extreme form of experiencing a design.
Then it goes back to guilt, which is a language form.
Then it goes to conscience for you, something in it just all over the place.
And why does it begin with death?
Because somehow Heidegger pumps up his problem that have we got the whole book on it in our forehead.
And he asked me, No, of course you haven't.
Then why did you have it in the no?
How about I could you just open the book of the family of content sort of carelessly with whatever explosion is the amendment.
In fact, I'll give you had a book that there's many books, but I'm going to tell you what worked because I knew I really have to address this one.
Why the quote was parallels in individual minds, throwing this always comes before Hosea only asked because throwing us as what we are already have to do with what we're pressing into in a serious way.
The past doesn't want to all come before the future, even so on 172.
And remember, all I'm trying to do is convince anybody who's skeptical that I've got a better plan for this negative.
I claim about which anybody might well be skeptical.
Well, I have to convince you.
Okay, so if you look on 172, where he starts to talk about the structure of Hosea, he does it by starting with the state of mind, that is disposable, that is within the space, and then having done the state of plan, he gets to the next thing, which is to do understanding once on 188.
That's the way it makes sense to do it.
Now, what is going on in 170?
Well, there's a topic of 174 and he starts laying out the relationship with throwing them to understanding.
Who says, and he starts out explaining that he's going to talk about throwing this, which is where he gets thrown from the beginning, being through there.
And funny guess that thank you.
I'm just trying to tell you after all throwing us into live or over, because trust me know that.
Oh, I'm going back to 172.
So when he talks first about that disposing was right to be a human.
And then he goes on, as I said, to talk about drawings and that they go together the anthropoprimordial table, but he also lines up the hook in the order he does.
I mean, there is not in a kind of circular relation that since the understanding affects the group or the children of the children affects what possibilities you press into.
You could sort of do it either way, but the natural thing is to take where you started, throw it into the world already, and put that before the standard and play on it, which is the understanding part.
So that and put the path before the repeat, but that's not how he does it in the food.
On page 11, that would take a front.
He does on 168 the temporality of the understanding and then the temporality of stable.
I think he does it because he led what it is to the fact that he started with death, which is got to do with getting into the deeper and understanding, and then he dealt with guilt, okay and so forth.
So now so he's consistent in the data.
But he isn't.
That I think is evidence that he doesn't know what he's there's sort of various different digressive levels of his manuscript that he suddenly ended in.
Because on 275, I was just looking through the days, he many surprises where he didn't work, but on 275, for instance, he thought by five lines four adding and then four sides and fourth instead.
That's been the piece of it, then the order they're on and always in division one.
And but why did he switch that?
Why not take the same problem?
Oh, yeah, okay.
On 326, here's sort of something kind of about raising about two ways.
Having taken up this first, I'm assuming you know that this is the way you're looking here.
Yes, that's what you've got in speech.
On 311, you've got to do the less the where you've got your visitors.
You see, because of course, no, the first chapter of division two is depth, and the second chapter is resoluteness, and the middle of the second chapter is 58, and that's a crazy way of organizing it.
Lo and behold, the one is 66.
He does it in the other world, the right way.
This is 20 lines from the bottom.
He says, All oncology all on the line is going to just be different to such phenomena and you don't say this, but make up your mind items.
Why not make this field?
If that's how you go to write your book, he doesn't he has a great together.
Okay, so that's my argument for that.
But the right way is to put your first, not only because, but it's also wrong here.
Because yes, there's a more random guilt, which also has a kind of play in the radar.
And it isn't not such a it isn't such an extremely form of dung.
And so that's part of the problem.
And that related what I think is really confusing.
So far it sounds for having said to me probably emerging briefly.
But that is really important to pedagogical issues.
You'll see it when you you don't have to go through all the suffering I want to do and everybody else really in the order you publish it.
Because you forgave him.
I think if you imagine how it is, you can see how confusing it is when you see how you behave.
Because in the face of guilds, for example, you have red faces, you have anticipatory.
Resoluteness is a lesser form of authentic activity than anticipatory.
Resoluteness and then possibly bills.
And resoluteness, then you keep getting told that having resoluteness, this isn't really the whole thing.
The whole thing is only apparent and death.
Well, you wonder why you have to feel it that way, right?
Just do it.
And then one of the other things, which makes it even more whatever.
And that when you do it my way, you do bill, time, and resolution.
And resoluteness, and it's as inclusive, you I'll give you a quote.
And for authentic resolution, well you ought to do that next.
And if you read it my way, it it's pedagogical, yes, that doesn't make sense much.
Why this why did why they used to do it that way?
And uh, for instance, on just one example in K49, I want to show you this, and 154 resolutions become more forward, more pioneering, more and more dealers, just plain resolutions, and you would think you would start with the general number, and we walk to the hardest, the more complicated way.
That was your NIPA now gotten to you've got to make this move a certain you've got to keep mechanism of a plane resolution is in point towards.
It started half there in its understanding.
So he's saying this resolution is a home point forward, and take it as well.
If I told you, X points toward Y, which do you think comes first in the guy's book?
You say you have the thing point towards the X would point toward Y, and then the Y they point towards.
Now you're this one.
Never anybody was appointed.
And the order in which I think it makes sense, got hold on here, and so you both dispose the idealized.
Now that's the same and 11.
I'll just use these numbers to test.
Roman numeral two is one.
Let me just go.
I call it error one, just so I go the resolution in number two.
Then comes this.
That's so the setup, so the staff of Roman numeral one is the mile paradigm.
Then we finally put the thing together as a whole in section Roman English three, numbers 62, which goes without anticipatory.
And then you've got the whole picture almost, although really, you have to go over and grab historicality.
And it'll be founded on the whole 55 and it's gone through a whole hand of friends discussion from the reality and remapped all the time.
How temporality is beyond people can free the last part.
Really number two.
All of the most are lost to them.
Once you've done that, you then map all the feet that you fix.
Are you with me?
This is I bossed everything.
Why did I try to add another four?
So I'm going to say one, two, three, then four.
Then finally you're going to say boss where you've got five five.
Then four six seven over oh my god yeah that's nothing but then we seven.
I think that's it.
Do we try to read anything I said previously?
I now have anywhere on the fourth.
I didn't quite like me to change up if you had if you want to see it.
Put it up there, but uh I don't agree it's no much.
Are you all having trouble thinking?
Bunch of people having trouble going to one six.
One, three, five, four, six, six.
It's there.
That's what I gotta do.
You got to make it work.
Okay, that now.
That's the end of that, which is, I'm never going to talk about that again.
Why I was finding it gives you things why I'm doing it.
Yeah, there's two things you can look for and do.
I'm sure I haven't seen all of them.
And I would like to have some.
Every time you see the order, those three other, I think that's why sometimes they're closer and anyway.
These kind of pairs, which I presume after a semester, you got used to, which are always, they would give you steel in either direction.
The more interesting one, which I began to map out, but I didn't want to bring it in today because it'll make much more sense for you, but that's a phenomenon, is how many ways the resolutions somehow leave up to his keyboard, or you can control anticipatory.
We rethink that, because it starts with, well, this resolution somehow must be something else beyond that or something.
So they have to keep telling you, well, resolution is really something we've got to anticipatory.
So keep me close to it.
Yeah, I found about ten such places.
Maybe I found them all.
Now, where you go on to the next, all this formal stuff, I'm sorry to say, you have to get out of the way.
You're good then.
We will get into the content of what is coming.
The next thing on my list is formal indication.
Really, that was another thing I didn't know.
You can't take any stance out of what he has to say about guilt and death.
You don't understand it was all done to the method of phenomenal indication.
Remember, phenomenal gifts is always finding some provisional way of describing and then investigating those.
And almost always I'm getting we'll for you, maybe next time.
Phenomenal indications always start out when it's property what he's talking about.
Not always.
But descriptive what he's talking about is the dead wrong.
And you can be almost sure that the first way you pick up whatever it is we're trying to describe is, from a kind of point, not only dead wrong, but those days in the scripture, it's got cover up.
This is one step beyond Christian and Richard's designation.
But Scripture doesn't think they're golden and easy for you by showing what they realize.
This is the way they did the R.
But Heidi thinks that guilt, well, that's the only two I'm sure.
Those are the big ones.
Anyway, they're going to show up that when you probably try to describe it, you're going to be in the R, you're going to be sure that that's going to come out to be flat.
It's only not finding right.
It's going to be 180 degrees wrong.
It's going to cover up what's really going on.
And moreover, that's why it's over.
It's not going to be a business department.
And why you have to do guilt first is because guilt is the clearest by the time of the interview is so hard for me to discontinue what where the the ontological right understanding goes down.
And they keep your eye on it.
You can beast being looking for it, what you would ask yourself.
What's the really wrong description?
And how is it 180 degrees?
What is the right description?
And how is it once you have the right description, you can understand that the other was the wrong description?
You'll see that so clearly in the guilt gap.
I'm going to explain it today.
And then, find the fault, you'll have to find our way to the point too.
Where are we?
So you remember that the formal and behavioral, by the way, I think when I talked about it, last I talked about it, didn't I really designate good?
You know, he was an answer.
But on 274, Sun Moon, because it's a move about formal indication, that the name of formal indication, which is a little bit off, the provisional sort of guess that you did, turns out to be a mighty.
If I were going further, it would like anyway, if I were doing it, I'm just saying he doesn't introduce God's body.
Because he says we're formally, here he does on page 274, we're going to formally indicate God's own as the being is being of nature first.
You see that already beginning of provision one.
But when we came to our, and we conferred back to it, when we came to our analysis of this video, it was look at our pre-market system, this interface, that's the provisional.
We designate it as the essence of diaspora.
This term is just formally indicated.
That means we don't really believe it yet.
So we're going to give it a try.
At least trace out what we want to talk about.
Formally indicates for God's art gives you the good units to be proof of God being itself.
You see, his problem his problem is he wants to tell you the right answer provision.
That's really the method we would require just to tell you the wrong answer.
The answer is always the answer would have to be something like the right answer.
Well, you should do that with God's mind.
But then that would make sense.
We got a serious problem there.
I don't know how to help it.
Because it would make it hard enough to understand the book without being given lateral stuff.
It's an issue for it.
But here's how it would go.
It would say, we want to talk about human beings in here, and we're going to provisionally call human beings rational animals.
And then we're going to discover that one of the people insufficient.
They're not rational at all, and they're really not animals at all.
All we're going to say is we're going to describe the structure of God of a being, and we want to know its nature.
And it's not impassive, and it isn't just a temple.
It's nature like plants and animals, and we're trying to find out what that is.
And then, of course, we'll find out there that's wrong.
But it would be so reducing the truth that I'm doing just to show you that there's a student realizing all the way that hermeneutic system works is found to be something which in its everyday manifestation, which is the only thing that God would describe, is bound to be not primordial, not authentic, not disclosing of what is, just followed from the bodies that is believed that everything you discover, what you discover important about God, but what is giving you the wrong answer?
I maybe about to get to reading my notes, that he's doing formally a pretty clear reason.
When I just don't believe in doing what I get done, and these even coming close to that bottom of the screen, fifteen lines up, all ontological investigations of such phenomena as real conscious today must start with what the everyday interpretation because Dawson has fallen as this kind of being.
The way Dasine gets interpreted is for the most part inauthentically oriented and doesn't be suggestive.
It doesn't all have formal indication.
It's just not using the term.
Or to Daseine, a primordial, appropriate ontological way of orienting questions were named clearly.
So you're going to but whatever we but whatever we speak as to the primordial ideas of the subject, then it's not like 30.
And it isn't as if being something yellow.
Even though it isn't we covered that up by calling the beings.
But if it is true, that if it isn't the case, that the long story about the long story about your anyway, Dawson has it the wrong story is always a motivated colour.
Then it's true that when you go get that home with the wrong thing, you've already got a clue or something that if something is revealed about the phenomenon, the way they say, and and why they do it, as you'll see.
And that's that paragraph is really telling you that this is going to be formally.
Maybe they're in the journal.
I once went through here and discovered about half the time later calls formally, something like ingredients that is there.
Now, it's like, you know, it's the same point again.
I'm going to read it.
He said everything we do.
He I'm just going to say not only is it wrong about God's mind or Prescard like say John Searle, that what would it be?
They're all kinds of wrong in ways of the provision in the Greek primordial.
It just occurs to me, well, of course, temporal value too.
Now, example, we've got a view of time as a sequence of moments which is measured by a clock.
It's not primordial.
It's it's way, way left behind to the primordial phenomena every day.
So again, he never said that, I don't think, because I don't know, but I never look, I wonder if he does anything like the provisional thing that he's doing the provisional.
I mean he's five, so I don't know where but he could be, I mean he could be, he could say it, but that's what he's doing.
So let's see, I'm going to read the first paragraph of 341.
This is my last method why I do both.
I'm stopping writing to get the grill because we have a solar I'm supposed to go regularly.
Behold, my word ready fun.
I can't resist getting there for I'm going to work with them.
Anyway, we will say the first whole paragraph on 341, we must first show how the only phenomenon with which the ordinary interpretation is infamiliarity, going back to the primordial meanings of all the causal consciousness, when they are understood in a way that is on ordinary understanding.
There's another one on the list.
Our ordinary understanding of the call of conscience follows.
Totally and thoughtfully, 100%, 190 degrees wrong.
Just to give you a clue about what that must mean.
Everyday people, us, think that conscience is some kind of voice that calls us and tells us what to do, gives us moral advice, told us when we've done something wrong.
All of that, that's all, you'll see the quotes in the lab, the voice of the one.
Real conscience doesn't say anything.
And it doesn't call you to do anything, and it doesn't expose you to do anything.
It's different.
And it's so pretty, real conscience, that of Redoff with this everyday story of what they are and when he violates them.
So when he's clearing that, that he's going to respond to you.
He's not going to find the ordinary interpretation.
He's going to be God is not an authority quote.
You must then show that the ordinary interpretation brings the limitations of the way God finds them.
That's the overday problem.
We inspire.
And since the law belongs to Carrot Health, you are showing by no means accidental.
That's what we have to cover up.
It's not right.
It's obvious.
That's the key that's not as but it's so accident that the fact is wrong in the way it's prescribed because of us something anxious negative and hard to understand and hard to live with the ordinary conception.
Well, let anybody who wants to say anything.
Everybody doesn't wait to find out where he's trying to wait for that for decades under the cycle of moral involvement.
Okay, let me think of it.
I think the answer to the question is here putting two things in the same.
Anything about the concept?
Basically, well, except it's it could be a moral it could be at least getting confusiness.
Because there is a strong and simple statement.
The guideline is basically a moral relativism.
If there's a culture which is not relative, which is through all guides, with all the rules with your Bible or whatever your culture is, telling you what about morality is and yes, why?
I haven't really answered too hard.
That's not even fun.
They even don't even want the difference between the good life and the bad life.
That's that's part of it.
There are no moral guidelines, no more rules, no sort of Kantian belief in economy or but it there is there are good guys and they have good lives.
It is paradoxical, but it's terrific, it's brilliant.
I think it's right.
I'll defend this.
Uh, you next to me, yeah.
I'm just trying to recall from the conclusion one discussion about the whole refining button the morals was arguing.
Would higher be considered as false morals?
Would be yes, and then again actually would be no.
In this part of these are very universal characteristics that guideline in all cultures.
And in profound ways to identify the good guys would plus principles or rules or human nature or anything to find a culture.
In that way, the weakened age be valuable or age be dunk.
Old people could be valuable or cultures can be bad, anything like that.
And in that way, the cultural relatives, that there are these structures of God, that any human being has a world and everything there is something like, you know, I forget a good blog and bad guys, the authentic ones and the inauthentic ones are going to be the same from the blackboard to those things.
There's no ground for anything we can find, and yet, by formal indication and working it on with who was basically, can help us distinguish between, yes, channel authenticity is perhaps what makes this book so high disadvantage of the gale-Christian position in our sense of the same thing about ethics and morality and so he's managed to save his money non-realistic, non-leveling.
He's trying to save a kind of way of having my moral judgment in a time in which we are in a certain way across relativistic realists.
And that's what makes it so important.
Okay.
At the close of vision one, he said something like that.
Heidegger wasn't saying that there is no supreme good or being, he's just leaving that open.
But is that deeply inclusive?
Did I say that?
Yes.
Really?
On the podcast.
I always do a describe this thing?
I think you were referring to it.
Say that again.
He said, I believe, if I'm right back, that Heidegger leaves open the question.
He's not saying distinctively that there is no God or Supreme Being or Absolute.
He's leaving that open for each individual to search themselves.
But isn't it deeply implicit throughout being a time that you can't have something like that because when you enter into anxiety, what's revealed to you is not a divine order or it's nothingness.
Yes, that's inherent to the situation of anxiety.
That's a good point.
I see what you mean.
Let's think about a supreme being who reveals to you the moral order and sometimes you actually die.
I don't know why he's believing him, Heidegger's, at least brains that I don't know what he wants to say, but he wants, he takes the stand to talk none of his business.
If that age is dead CL and not ASDCL, and nothing he can do to prove that there's no Supreme Being in no life after death, or that there is life after death.
And he isn't kind, he's no secular or naturalist kind of fundamentalist, and he's no Christian fundamentalist either.
That's all just Axis dead CL for him.
So that means that he needs it open.
Now your question is interesting.
And what about anxiety?
Doesn't anxiety reveal that you can't have that kind of grounding in the purity?
I think he does want to bring both these things.
I think he definitely wants to be somebody who says it's none of my interest in business or a view of religion and belief in the afterlife theory.
I'm going to tell you the structure of being on dead and so forth.
But he tells you anxiety is a ruin of any type.
That is, it was a fine boy, it's the best revealing, who is revealing experience, and anxiety was the experience of the groundless mind.
Well, let's see what other people are thinking about.
I think you're getting yourself into this lemon.
I mean, if we think about his word, all these structures, he's neutral with respect to authenticity and, you know, we can try and generate an ontological essay.
There would be one imperative to be what you are, to be authentic.
But he keeps saying over and over.
I agree with everything you say, but he's putting the argument one step further.
What about anxiety?
I would say the same.
It's like the temptation is to read all these categories, authenticity and authenticity.
One is sort of good, one is bad.
There's an implicit imperative towards loss.
But with all these structures, I think he's really useful perspective.
He's just going to tell you more primordial structures for surface structures.
And he keeps saying over and over, and there's no imperative to...
Well, I'm not convinced by that at all.
What about the being in the booth and the uncle?
I think even unless you do an esoteric reading in which you sort of practice his own language and sort of try and get behind in language, he keeps over and over.
He's not making any wrong claims about whether you have to live in the primordial structure to dress the...
I just don't recognize that Richard.
When you think about it, I think he's telling you exactly what it is to be authentic and authentic, isn's saved enough to go groundless.
I agree.
He's telling you what it is to be each.
I don't think he's generating any sense of the sort of moral imperatives that you and Eugene want to know.
He isn't.
I'm clear about that.
Telling you any specific thing you could lose in terms of your anxiety and design.
But there is a way to do it in which the authentic person does it, and you can tell the difference.
That's the crucial thing.
You can tell the difference, but I don't think he's saying you have to try to be authentic or inauthentic.
It's probably the wrong notice.
You're called the art.
But conscience is.
There's just possibilities that guidelines can get themselves into.
You either aren't.
I don't think there's any imperative that can be done.
There's no imperative at school's life.
But there's certainly no way to prove whether you're going to be authentic or inauthentic.
It's not up to your sort of willpower.
But there is something like an imperative.
Your conscience is not calling you and saying, well, you can be authentic or inauthentic.
But you, you know, your conscience is saying you've got to be authentic.
And the only way to avoid it is to cover up your conscience with the story we're about to hear.
If your conscience is giving you nice for your guidelines, it isn't.
And when you're authentic, this is why you're not recognizing the idea that any authentic or anything follows the idea about what you could do in these particular case.
But you're reading, so the only imperative I think you get in Heidinger is become yourself having learned it.
There's text.
Having learned it.
So he's going to tell you who you are in the guidelines, and the imperative is become it.
And the way you and Eugene are using it is telling you the reference design, authentic, inauthentic, and implicitly it's become the authentic person.
The other way of reading is just the same, these are the structures.
Um you're in one or the other.
And I still don't understand what to do with anxiety as a primordial uh disposedness.
He's supposed to show you something, what to show you something.
I think it's a possibility of being.
It's like these are all.
That's more than that.
It's more hungs be scientific.
But I don't think he's going to I don't think unless you read against his own language, not to be able to generate a comparative for his against the one.
Well, what you think that what do you think conscience is calling you to is not an imperative to be authentic and face up your anxiety instead of playing games.
This is what it's doing.
It's not clear, though, that anything's wrong in this.
I don't think he agrees with Pastella.
You shouldn't go out and cover up your wretchedness by playing billiards with hunting and dancing.
Eugenia has been involved in the selection cost of any of that.
You started with the same thing.
But he's saying that the policies have hung and haunting the problems when we're calling that hungry function.
That's interesting, but I do think he goes further.
I think I'm following him.
When he tells you that anxiety really experiences it, I think it's much worse than Eugenia.
Not only does he stop short of saying these things, he often says the exact opposite.
So it's the sort of reading you guys are offering.
Well, with authenticity and inauthenticity, he says it over and over.
Do not read this as an imperative, moral imperative to be authentic as a...
Don't read it as an ethics, doesn't it?
I don't think he ever says to be not an imperative.
There's not supposed to be any norms of weight on these structures, any of them.
And no normative weight on telling you that anxiety reveals things in a time.
I don't know if a privilege was.
Well, I don't get it.
I think you may be writing the books you should have written.
I'm not sure.
But the way him first talk that he brought it up, and then you wouldn't seem like you have to describe a moral evaluation to that.
But if you're in the groundlessness of anxiety, it seems like only from that point and in the groundlessness can is authentic and possibly possible.
Because if in this revealed experience, if what is seen is an absolute cross-cultural, a historic value that you must ascribe to, then how then authenticity is sort of laid out for you right there.
And then authenticity would kind of be following a roadmap, and it wouldn't be the owning of the self and sort of the individuals.
David, what this is a fascinating discussion, I just want to take on you can crack on it.
What you're really trying to interest me to watch when he's what I'm about to see, when he talks about guilt and conscience, and who is this call?
And what is Dazon free because we're in hell?
And what would he be doing the right thing about anything?
Does that have any concept?
These are the very questions that you're asking.
How normally a view and how to say death too, but death is something that's true that that's a great individual class do and do when it is in the building, we aren't able to see if we're looking for just what kind of any we think performance you want to say so he's just regarding your normality of the lack of imperative be authentic um i think that makes sense i think it would be difficult for heidegger to justify an imperative to be authentic like you might say that your conscience is there and it compels you to be authentic in one way or another but that's not an ethical imperative as well imperative any kind of that makes you do so even if there's no political imperative whatever that is where um even if it's not present explicitly in the evening program i think in certain respect that sort of imperative is present implicitly like for example when we see kindergarten influence on heidegger when he speaks of leveling and just looking at his language i mean i can't read the german but looking at the language in translation it seems as though heidegger had a certain present i guess towards level and seems to have perceived it himself on a non-philosophical unlike both as a negative thing and he seems to have his own ideas about it so um the impression i got anyway was that although heidegger wasn't willing to take the step and make an ethical imperative and say you should be authentic he did not seem happy about people being inauthentic in something else you know maybe i could take over what he said and put it this way that he thinks that there is a more or less primordial understanding than about non-loading levels and it covers up the true the more primordial understanding of what it is to be done.
That's already in the important term of opinion.
Then the discussion is evident because as neatly as what you could be doing, or any way imagining what you shouldn't be doing, follows from this idea that there is a work.
I guess I'm just pamping out on the hand now.
One thing at least follows.
Don't will, don't gossip, don't have a non-primordial understanding of reason because it belongs to the very healthy thing for doing what you get it right.
That is, don't cover it up.
And then we're still not getting any, you don't know how much normativity you get at.
There is none we are called to get that, that's the truth.
And we don't know yet what follows.
So again, we've got a few started this and a very interesting.
I'm going to throw one more thing out there.
Isn't normativity itself always in second sense?
Because if there was normal to autonomy and two cultures and to establish or having a set of beliefs, and I mean, isn't Dallas and I at Roth Bottom just playing normalist?
You didn't take all the kinds of, you know, what do you mean by norm?
There's no not going to be called cultural values or rules or virtues.
Those things could be called to make what it is that he does.
That is to take a stance on its own deity.
It looks like it's built in.
One does a long way to take a stand on it.
Maybe because other you're the kind of being that has to originally divergence and sweet and overall.
Or it's not that you're the kind of being that good?
It doesn't have any moral normative guideline, except that it better manifest its all these and required to sort of get right about the proof of Dai Line is.
And there is one all across all cultures.
It's a funny I'm just trying to give you this funny feeling that there's something normative going on, but it's nothing like rules, virtues, principles, practical justifications, and all that.
Something else that the name for it is ontological.
Yeah.
Well, um, being similar norms, of course, you can develop a darkest part of that, but it's not really just like what needs that because Gosman is an existential part of Daisy, also.
We are historically thrilling.
So in that situation, we are a situation where there are big norms and things we're calling to, and we can respond in some way or another.
So it's it's a particular there's a strange kind of normativity that we deal with, but it's not, but there's nothing but that's that sort of norm is not a constant norm or something that it does not even sort of erased here in our mind either that you should you're throwing in the culture where where they are.
So it seems well because this is if you're doing this long in a very interesting way.
I mean, you might say you're you're throwing into a culture and you don't do what the culture does tell you is the right thing to do and they're not right.
No, no, I mean it's not like a vertical it's it's also uh I mean it's just I guess I'm I'm thinking more of just the neoliberal that that people are kind of concerned about.
It's is is that Heidegger doesn't isn't a deal with nothing because you are you are born into a culture that you that you can take an authentic stance towards or a an inauthentic stance towards.
Yeah, I mean it's not it.
It's not in a risk of healing and virtue ethics or anything where you're still looking for whatever things are your culture or something.
But you're also not, we're not just completely free split.
I mean, it's a school year time crown, isn't that?
Well, I mean, well, I think, because I think the resolution and answer is compatible with doing all that in the background because that's what you're called is telling you these are good lights, do whatever you're you can be good in the way your culture makes it possible for human beings to be good.
I think that's what the guilt chapter was.
And then the guest chapter just blows that up the way anxiety goes in.
And so, no, that's why it did all the money.
The guilt chapter clearly tells you that the greatest thing you can do if you understand the call of conscience is respond in a unique way to each of these persuasions by being an expert in the values and ways of acting your guilt and conscience chapter.
He has the funny parent of never obeying the general rules that one does, but doing its own unique thing that can even look crazy for a while to the one.
But when you eventually come around to see that he is a terrific doo-who to the cultural things.
So but the phonemist uh we want Aristotle.
Aristotle said outside with any kind of norms of of uh thought that you could find in comics or in value ethics even, because uh that is he's outside it in the sense that they don't tell him what to do in a situation.
He just spontaneously, automatically does the appropriate thing at the appropriate time in the appropriate way.
That's fascinating.
He becomes a master of this culture.
But what the deaf ones is, in effect, okay, Aristotle, that's all correct about that.
But the interesting thing is Aristotle and the pharmaceutical, they equip the whole background of values and virtues and understanding of what a human being is and could be, and within that, the the pharmaceut is a master of it.
And thus, the thing that the part on death says, all grounded and if you think that there's a cultural sort of support for what you're doing, then you're a master of your culture, that's fine.
But you really aren't yet a full god of full design, this and the face of death, understanding even the very principles of their own culture is something Aristotle and the farmers don't.
I think that's what Heidi goes beyond whatever you think is doing and goes beyond what I think he's doing, or should be doing, and he's doing something more radically near the genius, Aristotelian, all the resolutions right, that's your point, do what you're called to be a master, because obviously the other time is no doubt, keep your eye open to the fruitful taste, which is what the run does, and responding to the initial having no way to justify He just says the inauthentic person responds to the general situation and the authentic person responds in a great way, without reflection, without justice, the uniquely appropriate age.
Yeah, can we spend some thoughts on those?
If it were to say that our sort of hard pairs come from our human one by culture, there's a very difficult person to explain by playing the like, you know, we got caught up, I think, about the screen old and I know and everything for sense, but you know, don't get that into the right thing.
I mean, that was what he had about constant sense.
You know, there's still a higher version of the one.
Yes, because if they could just say why they think it's the right thing to do, they're not the pharmacists.
That's the man of practical wisdom doesn't have a least handle.
He just is so good at understanding the deep meaning of his culture that he will deal with appropriately.
That's pretty radical.
I like that.
And a culture doesn't make any sense.
I mean, people who have, I don't know what you read, maybe Georgia is the closer.
The person who, I'll just tell you the volume on this part, the person who's understood this text, I don't think the Burst of English people understand it very well.
Whenever I read them, they seem to think that Aristotle is a pharm is built by what they're doing and and understands the the je something like the general situation.
Anyway, uh what Gourdru talk when he talks about the cultural virtuoso, the logic of facts, uh Bourdreur has an understanding a very very like all of them.
What he calls cultural virtuoso could do that if he does it by deeply accepting the whole culture.
I mean, Bourdruit generalizes and only this being when you get to have open source programmes, not what he's about.
You can have it say only the experience of the logic of death make you sort of even free of your whole cultural background.
It looks like it.
I hope that's wrong.
Yeah, that's Stephen.
But just a small point about self-formal indications with the badge.
We have to be careful though when you're talking about things like guilt of conscience.
Remember that they were formally indicated as being guilt of conscience.
You don't get to sort of remind the the normative or moral baggage attached to the phenomenon.
I feel that in the discussion of formative conversation with us.
Yes, and no, I mean, the you do leave the moral baggage of the door, so to speak, little by little.
I mean, I don't think we're disagreeing, but that's how formal indication works.
You have to start thinking that gold is that yellow stuff or the like or that lightening of those bright splashes and maybe quickly kind of examples that are easier that he is what he is warm.
You've got to start with things like that.
And but and in this case, you've got to start with a moral view about guilt, if there are things that are wrong and we've done them and done the wrong things are guilty and so forth.
But you're going to leave all that behind.
And that's sure.
But whether you've left anything that has any kind of normative significance behind, keep your eyes open.
I think no, well I'm not asking what I've just asked because I think that if you get the promises and fans that with somebody who's very right to get conscience and guilt, it's about that much knowing that it is significant.
No more and no less.
You can do the appropriate thing at the appropriate time in the appropriate way, but you can't say why it's appropriate because there's no answer to that.
It's just what somebody really understands the culture does.
And not everybody, but just this person in this situation does.
So there's some normativity in there, but it's just so sort of cleaned up.
That's what we're going to talk about next.
But I thought I could talk about it.
Yeah.
So the cultural virtuoso being the virtual cable sort of men's day thinking that I could talk about where you kind of reflected very deep fundamental way about being itself.
How we discover something.
Because the collective decision doesn't need anything.
No, he certainly doesn't need to do that.
He means that a culture virtual ethical person certainly is the most likely place to find one.
I think it hasn't been the black wars.
You ever write never went to school and certainly arts corrupted by philosophy.
That you don't need to you don't need to have that.
What you need is having driversion, what you need to become a cultural virtuoso is a dumb sense of anxiety and not just believe the norms that Rosanches tells you to cover up and here's the rules and rationality required and all that stuff.
I've got enough anxiety to fail to not accept, not believe that, not experience that.
The present thing happens too.
And then you've got to have this type of he doesn't talk about much, but you never have to.
Because there are lots of experience in the culture of not doing what the norm to be the general situation requires.
And sometimes it works very well, and everybody's happier afterwards disaster, and everybody hates you afterwards.
And if you have enough experiences like that, it takes them seriously.
You get more and more skilled at being, say, in a given way, Greek.
And the more skills you get, and the more of a mastery you get on the basis of a lot of trial and error that you take to heart, then you get to get from the column.
How do you do it?
Wouldn't that require comes from reflections?
Ah, ah, that's such a good question.
I argue what's going on.
It it can involve reflection, but it doesn't require.
This is how it looks.
I I wasn't going to I'm I'm here in a paper when I was going to tell you reading grants too.
But there's like this story about how you go from a novice for a master, so that's what I really thought.
He had to get the way I see it anyway.
What do you think you think?
Wouldn't it require oh yeah, reflect not on necessarily no rational getting down into these lines of issues about just proof that you ate the big scale, I didn't think about it.
But the question is, if you learn by making a mistake, feeling bad about it, two ways you can go for it.
You can make yourself do some kind of disputes.
You can look and you can try to figure out just what went wrong and make up your mind not to do it again.
The analogy of that is something like the golfer, the famous thing.
Yeah, Tiger Wood did when he took apart his whatever and went back and trained because he thought that he was doing certain things wrong, then he got worse, but after a while he got better than he ever was.
That's something like the form of meditated thinking.
You try to figure out what you did wrong, you feel bad about it, and you try to get clear about it, and you try to fix it.
But you can also just worry about it.
And the next time that you can decondition yourself to doing in the next situation what you did in the previous situation.
Or you can really just feel good about it.
Now, I have to bring me in.
I'm the only case I know of this, and my brother is skeptical.
But I think that's how I could be a good future.
That's why you have to have the faith for the line.
Because I always listen to the previous one, and what I am thinking is, wow, that really worked.
That was the right way to do it.
I understood it better.
They all understood it better.
Or I think, oh my God, he wasted 15 minutes going down the wrong track, and now they're more confused than I was when they started.
I'm confused too.
And then we can just, and I'm just conditioning myself to do that good thing again.
And I'm healing because it makes me feel good.
Do that.
Don't ever do that bad thing or then because they're going to go regret it was better.
And I don't think I ever analyze, or not very often, what did I do wrong to get me on that long track or to get me on that wrong track, and so forth.
So then I think that's a non-meditative, non-reflective way of getting to the autonomous.
It doesn't matter to Heidi how you get there, to want to get to a point in which you don't anymore or even understand why you do these things.
Oh, you just do it.
And that's the intuitive mastery of user.
And you can notice how cross-cultural that is, whether that's banmaster or verber, where that would be by who you study, the verber and the blow-through, or the astronomist being virtually like these people could be studied better than they are.
Anyway, yeah.
Relating to the idea that the authentic person can act without justification.
Is it that the authentic person acts entirely without justification?
Or that they sat down and thought that they could justify it, but they but they just don't.
I mean, I guess I understand that.
Going back to the idea that it doesn't make any sense that the moral person could act without a specific thing.
I think it's understandable, but it's very terrifying, I guess, that an authentic person simply does something totally unjustified.
That's right.
They can't explain it to you.
But it's just somehow very appropriate.
That's right.
And it is sort of terrifying, but that's how the is the the virtuoso can't tell that you or themselves why that was the appropriate thing to do.
If that specific thing was the appropriate thing to do.
In fact specific situation, they can't even generalize it or this thing that climbed in things you have to do.
So they're going to learn things and experience successes and failures in their behavior.
On the next crime area, what is sort of the same situation, it won't look like the same situation.
They won't do the same thing.
When you get really good, you can make a neural model of this.
There isn't any rules and representations.
It's got to do with neural networks and chaotic attractors.
They may not help some people.
It may help others.
You can make models of the brain which imply that there isn't any where people you can't give your reason.
You can't justify what you do if you're an expert in do it.
And that might be terrifying.
Yes, but is it appropriate?
Anyway, aren't there reasons to wish it's appropriate?
Theoretically, if there are reasons, can't you decide that there are not reasons why it's appropriate.
It's appropriate because that's what Fran might do and other ones will recognize it.
There are certainly some gross guidelines of why what's inappropriate.
And there are certainly for not appropriate meetings just people who are competent in proficient.
There are guidelines that you can give and reasons why you should why it's appropriate, for instance, that give people their condolences, give the relatives condolences when somebody dies, so forth.
But when it really gets to the crankshaft situation and and in a specific case of what you do and how you do it, you're not going to have any reasons at all.
Yes.
Really help out in thinking that understanding is not right, there's a know-how, not an explicit.
That's right, it's not.
They're kind of know-how.
Right, so if you express a reason, an assertion of why you did something, you can't possibly express all the nuance of the situation and the know-how so that an inauthentic person might understand.
Like sometimes it might be possible, but it's not necessarily.
You're more likely to be able to get another pharmaceutical understanding.
But even then, you may not.
I mean, all the other pharmacists in my picture take test masters will understand in the sense that you'll see that that was the appropriate thing to do.
And he'll say, well, yeah, that worked.
But that doesn't mean that now they've agreed on what the rule was or the analysis for.
All they agree is that if you play a million moves, just to have to play the visa and that's what it goes.
If you made a million chess moves, that'll look you like a very good move to make.
If anybody else is making chess moves, it'll look like it'll probably look good too like a good move to make, but they can't tell you why.
But yeah.
So practical morality becomes a very that's a funny way to put it.
That suggests that you use your towards which you want to get it or something.
Okay, you're right.
You're right.
Insofar as it's just like just like networking talk about human beings like stuff, you have to follow the rules and get that back and a computer has to.
I mean, and there's and there's no actual governing um you know, there's no mental political governing uh guidelines and inclusion for actions.
Um and that just as one can calculate um reasons for uh uh opening sprints and getting productive data.
You're making some point about about um where you're probably lost having red.
But they go ahead with this.
All you really need is to be able to get exactly and and there's no respect or possibly the mask attack weren't there.
So it's pretty much the same with the quality of the and moral.
People people were asked to you can they would postulate reasons for having done it, but they weren't actually part of this.
There were no decisions, there were no rules again, that's all to the truth.
And the reason you know they weren't part of surprising that there was no phenomenon large in memory, that's phenomenal memory of it, is that if you follow those rules, you won't get that expertise.
You may get that result in that situation, but the expertise were recognized as similar situations and very similar things, and there are no rules or even the really important rules.
Therefore, an effort to learn or a computer or a robot could never be something that even grasps an art.
Well that is that's what's so funny.
And I would say that the only people who lastly are rules or they can have expectations that many situations at all.
If so computers could do that, maybe you could do that.
Yeah, I don't think that's what morality is exactly, but they could never act they wouldn't be more experts.
Anyways, you you don't have to worry about that.
Uh uh so what are we doing?
Yeah, I'm I hear you part before.
I can either go back to problem or or I have all you said we want to study.
You've got a lot of clearing up the things that we're going to come up next time.
If there's no harm in that, I will now know that I can the last car, I I would love to start on the bills.
You can see how it works.
You're picking out signs.
You'd like to know the essence.
You all know right stuff like that, where you follow deal fast with good things.
Oh, okay.
And it has a much more of a connotation of owing something.
So when you want a debt, you are showing somebody a certain amount of money.
It's so magnetized.
It's it's not it's not the determinant you'll do is radically disinheriting it.
It's just it'll start this inner component in it.
It's a lot less.
If it starts with his words, so he does with the person who is who is somehow responsible for something and owns the deals and social work.
And I do as you do that why I know there are no very german to to be guilty of being responsible for a license.
That is you owe somebody's money, or you bought somebody's money.
You're somebody who's in those guilt is you're guilty when you're a ponderous sort of land and your conscience tells you your responsibility for it.
And you ought to understand.
Now, the next thing to talk about, some way, is a long way.
Commentary marvelously, don't misunderstand it.
Because what I say in the commentary is, well, it's not that you've done something wrong.
This is my question.
I understood that it wasn't in a way that I was.
Now, I want to say, well, what is guilt?
It's not having done something wrong, because that seems to be just the ordinary.
As you later said, don't do it.
That's what the one person who's done something wrong and you had this person.
He just played responsibly and picked up.
And I wanted to say, well, what does Heigris do?
It really does problem.
That's not guilt.
If that's the one, what is guilt?
And my answer I had tonight: guilt, yes, handsome history.
You know, we just know very well.
So let me go on without that.
The guilt is ideal lacking in some way.
If that's what one normally says and think, that in fact, guilt is some kind of, is the reverse of it.
That idea is a cover of something else which is ontologically guilty.
And the interesting thing about ontology, no, is that ontological guilt isn't a bad thing of things.
It isn't going to be black.
It isn't something you could face.
It's not something you can wrong.
It's not even.
And now here's my mistake.
I said, no, it's not something you did wrong.
Well, I said, well, you can't ever be clear about what you're doing.
You can't be losing the autonomous.
You can't take full responsibility for the lack of truth.
And that's something you're going to read a lot in what we're talking about when Heidegger says what ontological guilt is you don't get behind your throne about honesty and what you're doing and stupid about things.
It proves that Heidegger says what the state was to think that that's something wrong with you.
Heidi's things, that's fine.
That's just, in fact, that's good.
And guilt hasn't gotten anything to do with what's wrong with you.
The normal, the founding guilty, being loses and really do what he'll conscience for.
But the good thing, and the interesting thing is, that's just an ontological fact about people.
Everybody, all Daseins are all guilty, all equally guilty at all the time.
That's what's talking.
If you read this, read him in a point away.
He's guilty of a bad thing, and you get over it or have less of it, or some people have less of it.
There are two important points.
One is I just said, I'll say it again.
He thinks that everybody's, every Dasein is equally guilty, and pretty anything else is guilty because whatever the essence of guilty of when you've done the hormones, maybe just you found out what guilt is, but the structural feature of God's eyes, and every die's eye has itself, but though you're on the wrong track, I mean, guilt, that's what I was doing when the company students are thinking.
You can't be wrong with Dazine, and it has a certain structure.
They never get clear, ever get clear of what the world is doing.
You can never understand what you're doing, just like you can get clear about what it is that we need to do, that you can tell being in and you will do things for people.
Then you will have absolute guilt.
Basic structure, that there's lots of what you be able to be explicit about or basically.
That's the structural feature.
The second point is it's not only a fact that you all get one thing that there's something worthy, you know, basically.
Whatever we do, that's what Bruce is talking about.
I know identity because we don't choose it or give them a narrative.
That's why I'm going to be the reader, but I brought along.
He didn't have any non-lucidity.
You do function, playing the positive thinking.
We're in the world of art and in order to work with art.
The main sort of is backwards, and you never is reverse.
Every decision bases itself on something not nasty, something concealed and confused, something would never be a decision.
Now, why?
Because that's not certainly you don't understand it when I just read it.
What does it mean?
Clearer what it means, and the guy's discovered.
But when it amounts to it, you have to look at the other side of it.
Wasn't it so that you could justify what he does, you could recently clearly understand what he's done and justify the office the right thing.
What does that look like?
Well, Jeffy God said, when you break down together, that if you aren't competing on principles, then and you wanted to always do the right thing, you have to understand by some kind of principle why what you're doing was the right thing.
But then you have to understand that you would be in a kind of redress in which you would be in sort of principles maybe for justifying your first order principles and principles for your studying to justify.
But you are in a redress in which you never get to the self-justifying principles that you've got.
At least you believe in revelation.
So there has to be something which is not a problem.
But there's not explicit foreground, loosened reasons or principles.
Because, I mean, there's a better way to put it.
I mean, it's harder, but suppose you were able to loosenly and freely what you were doing.
Now, we've got this one problem: how you would ever justify your principles.
The more interesting one, maybe, how your choice would never make any difference.
It'd be a choice.
You probably know some of you.
This empirically has these free movements prominently one eating not to gamble anymore.
And the voice may have to be choices because no replay.
If decision-making is completely free, then it's everything to constantly up to new decisions and up to grab.
So somehow decisions have to be based on something which can't be justified principles that are justifying what we because there's always got to really make sense.
There has to be a background on which, insofar as you have any principles, gives you a sense of the justifying.
Whether that's revelation or what it has to be done with very high freedom in which when you do something, it doesn't just count as a very clear rooster decision we make for us.
So it's on the basis of how we should want to exploit it.
Now he's trying to find his ignorance.
That's all in this one hurting, which says, in a sense, if being guilty, it's a structure that works rules that positive people of God.
But if you can't get someone in its planet, to be that sentence has always been so interesting, every decision bases itself, that's the on the basis of it.
Basically, bases itself on well, let me decision based itself on something not that used to deploy.
Otherwise, it won't it won't get a grip on the way.
It's a bunch of redress, I think it will go into a seller.
So, what does this mean?
Somehow we all hold that.
Well, basically, and now we turn it thank goodness we do money between people.
I don't have it there either.
Well, I did not have it.
No more.
You feel some that's mainly.
That sounds rather good.
Do I hunt?
Yes, exactly.
Thank you.
Okay, so all of this we are involved in on the story.
And this is how we're going to find out where I'm going to be able to structure it.
One ontological view is when we've got it into new things with the ability to rule.
We find out where it is next to its eyes that it's a positive thing, and that's what we do here.
The threshold is being planned.
It's all about it on the basis of it.
Very about 320 or 300 times.
Uh, very near.
It is built, delivered over.
This is what it is to be built as structural.
As such, it's been just always an entity that does deliver.
It is existing with the basis of its ability to do.
Although it has a lot of it reposes in the way that it works down and going and how is the online entity into which it's been grown, the stuff which is the way the basis was done can never underline the exact basis is equal to it.
And yet, as existing, it must take over being the basis.
It be its own basis, with the ability to be a total of the visual voice, don't just be rewarded as a punchline.
It's being evasive, it's just growing about unconsciously lagged without responsibilities.
It never exists before this as this basically done now.
Thus, being evasive, one's almost being from the ground up, just not belongs to them doing anything as being self-being evasive is analyzing itself.
That is actually a constant.
You can never have become your own being who can what it is, that's what guilt really is.
Nothing to do with having done anything wrong, planting anything, bullying and things.
And it's not because you're falling order being your concept.
There's something wrong with us about autonomous.
No, it's not something wrong with us.
It's just the structure of a being that is on a basket and always has to be has a big dirt that has to always act on that basket.
And that's just like guilt.
It's not recognizable.
Nobody in their right mind is there.
No ordinary everyday person would understand what the world was talking about.
He said, Well, guilt, everybody's got it.
Everybody's got the same amount of it.
You don't want to get rid of it.
It's really a positive good thing.
But that's how it turns out.
If you think to be the opposite one, it turns out to be the opposite of what you would have brought.
That is, when you would have bought you something, it was so boiled.
You could do that stuff, but what's uncological is this structural.
Oh, yeah, fun.
And then the final result is that things are the color up this full resistance.
You can't take responsibility.
You have to take responsibility for it, even though you don't know why they do years.
That gives you the anxiety of your what I just described.
There's money, then you can see the last build was going on.
And why just want to why do people think it doesn't give you that one?
You don't need to be bought to one of it.
But all that is a color of it now, because it isn't a case of clarity rules.
But those things come in colour up where you live.
But those things are the full reception.
It's going to be all formatted.
There's always something theory of experience.
The real decision.
Okay, I think you I said