So Searle's course, which is dedicated to understanding the relation between mind and world in his philosophy of mind, and doing it by talking about representations, propositional representations in the mind, which represents the world.
That's exactly the view which Merilo-Ponty considers the Cartesian view that he's opposed to.
And it's important to have that because it's so neat that somebody should be defending in a very detailed and convincing way the view that Meriloponty is criticizing.
Meriloponty hasn't read Searle, naturally, but he's read Husserl, who has some commitments, surely, that Searle doesn't have, and Searle has some developments that Husserl doesn't have, but at the level that Merillo-Ponty is objecting, they would be very, very similar.
So, and I, and I will put it in the website, I have to explain this now, instead of making a reader of relevant papers, on the back of your syllabus, you see a whole bunch of relevant papers, I decided that I think it'll work to just have a virtual reader.
A virtual reader is a website, I give you the number at the bottom of that, in which I will put all the papers that I think would be helpful, really good papers by Merleau-Ponty.
Up to about two or three years ago, there weren't any.
But suddenly, there's a bunch of good ones around.
And I could add a paper I wrote putting up the Merleau-Ponty view against the Searle view.
How many of you had Philosophy of Mind?
Is it worth it?
Oh, yeah, a lot.
Okay, I'll put my Merlot-Ponty versus Searle paper on the virtual website.
And then in terms of Kant, Merle-Ponty is always criticizing what he calls an intellectualist account of what makes possible our experience of objects.
He's constantly talking about conditions of possibility.
And that's Kant.
And he is opposing that to what he calls conditions of existence.
And that's Heidi.
And he's, and it's going to just sound empty and mysterious to you now, but that's inevitable.
I mean, what it looks like to work out an intellectualist account, and you'll see him doing it for everything that he takes on.
He'll tell you how it would look to a Kantian or neo-Kantian, and he'll tell you how it would look to a human.
I'll come back to this, or you would get an empiricist account.
And then he'll give you his version.
And his version is always about what he calls conditions of existence.
It's about, one way to put it, is how what the enabling conditions are for what the possibility people are talking about.
And that always turns out to be what experience is like when you're involved in ongoing coping with things, as opposed to being detached and being a subject observing things.
I come back to all of these in a minute.
So Heidegger, against the representationalist view and against the conditions of the possibility view, has got a non-propositional, non-conceptual account of what he thinks of as our primordial openness to the world.
And that's what Merleafoni is interested in, too.
That's what he calls conditions of existence.
Now, all of this got suddenly more relevant by the fact that about, was it five years ago now, maybe a little more, Ms.
Dow John McDowell published a book called Mind and World.
How many have come across that in some philosophy course?
Not as many as I would have thought.
But it's mind and world is as near to a Merleau-Ponty-like account of perception as you could get, and still get it, from Merlot-Ponty's point of view, completely wrong.
That is, having described perception and the conditions that it must satisfy to connect us up with the world, and saying that we are open to the lay of the world thanks to perception, all Heidegger and Merle-Ponty-like sounding things, McDowell goes on to say, and the only way perception could do that is if it were conceptual all the way out.
Now, what exactly he means by that, I'm not sure I know.
But whatever it is, I'm sure that it's not what Merlot-Ponty wants to say.
Merle-Ponty wants to say, in the current jargon that's going around, that what he's discussing is a preconceptual, pre-linguistic relation between us and the world.
And perception is like that.
And you can't treat it as having, in some kind of jargon, propositional content.
And you can't think that when we perceive something, it's just like believing something, except that it's got some sensuous characteristic.
You know, it's totally different than thinking something, believing something, and inferring something.
And Merle-Ponty is going to try to explain how that is.
Whereas McDowell thinks somehow it has to be enough like believing and inferring so that you can base your beliefs and inferences on perception.
Interesting puzzle is going to turn up.
One of the interesting puzzles is to figure out how, even though perception isn't propositional and conceptual, we nonetheless can base our beliefs and our inferences on perception.
That's interesting.
That's basic.
That's one of the things you've got to keep in mind in the course.
It's not altogether clear that it isn't as if Mary LePonte's got this one figured out very well.
He knows that perception isn't like conception.
Sentience isn't like sapiens, as Brandon puts it.
He knows that.
And he knows that we're going to have to figure out how perception can ground thinking.
But he hasn't got anything to say about that.
He promised a book on the subject, and then he died before he wrote it.
And I don't think he could have written it because he had something like 20 years between the time he promised it and the time he died that he didn't write it.
But in the background, you've got to realize that he sort of owns that.
But even if he only got perception right and showed that it wasn't conceptual, that was a special mode of relating, or it isn't even relating.
It's a certain mode of our engagement with reality.
That would be a huge contribution.
And then it would be up to us, which is what I think is that the current interesting issue in philosophy that McDowell has run up against from one angle.
And how many come across Bob Brandon's book, Make It Explicit in some course?
These are the big heroes of Pittsburgh philosophy.
It's amazing how provincial philosophy is.
Anyway, it's a problem that people are beginning to worry about more and more, which is the relation of perception to thought.
And but it and before you can even worry about it, you've got to get perception right.
So you have to think of this course as doing that.
Now, it's interesting that this is just a kind of gossip aside, and this is an intellectual history that I find it I find it fascinating.
It's quite interesting that analytic philosophers have come up against this question of whether perception is conceptual or not.
And they come up with it because a philosopher at Oxford, Gareth Evans, was very interested in this issue.
And Gareth Evans is interested in this issue, partly because Charles Taylor was one of his teachers, who was very, very interested in this issue, because Charles Taylor's a Marilla-Ponty and through and through in analytic philosophical disguise.
And so that the idea that analytic philosophers are coming around now to have a question that Marilla Ponty had on his mind in 1945 is not an accident.
It just took sort of a long time to germinate in Oxford and in our tradition.
So I mentioned Charles Taylor because he's the first one I put on the list of background on the virtual website.
Taylor's got this sort of overall view of Marilla Ponty and why you think they're important.
And it's interesting to read it, though he never works it out in detail.
He's just but he's got but he is sort of and he would be the first to say so well he he said to me once that he was about to give up philosophy at Oxford.
He's bicultural.
He's Canadian French, but he also perfectly uh third English.
And he was at Oxford, he was a Rhodes scholar, and he said he was about to give up philosophy, it was so boring.
And then he came across Marillo-Ponty, and ever since then, he's been one of our most interesting philosophers.
So you might want to read the Charles Taylor thing on the virtual website.
And now, and the person, well, I'll say one more thing.
And another person you've never heard of, Daniel Totis, who's written a book called Body and the World, is the one who's gone furthest, sort of taking up the Merlot-Ponty line and going further with it.
He wrote this book in 64, and it's been as his PhD piece, but right now it's becoming very relevant.
So I put Totis' book on reserve in the philosophy, and he gives an account of perception that, well, when you read Merleau-Ponty, you'll see that though Merilloponte is all about the role of the body and perception, you never could find out by listening, by reading Merillo-Ponty what in the world having a body is like.
If you were a Martian reading Merlot-Ponty, you know that the body is something that we move around, and that it's very important that we move around, and that perception is intimately connected with the fact that we've got that we are embodied and moved around, but that's about it.
And Totis is trying to figure out sort of the role what the basic structure of the body, that it's got an up and a down, a right and a left, a front and a back, moves forward more easily than backward, and balances in a gravitational field.
All those important facts about the body, what role do they play in the way we perceive the world?
So eventually, after we've got Merlot-Ponte, if there's time at the end, I will read a chapter of TOTIS, but I will put it on your list there as something that as back in.
Where's my version of the witch?
I don't remember how soon I put it in, and maybe too soon.
Maybe I didn't put it in at all.
I'm happy to be too late.
Yeah, but it's not on my background reading.
So I think of it as background reading for the last week.
So we don't need to worry about it yet.
But that's where Merlot-Ponty was heading.
Okay, now it's the still a little bit more background, and then I get to the phenomenological method, which is where we should be starting.
Merloponty's relation to Husserl and Heidegger is something I mentioned.
Merleau-Ponty, for reasons that I don't know, wants to think of himself as a Husserlian, not a Heideggerian.
And he's going through contortions and distortions in the preface to the Phenomenology of Perception, trying to say that really he's the heir to what he calls the third period of Husserl, where Husserl became an existential.
Well, that's wrong.
It's nonsense.
Husserl never became existential.
And Merlopony was basing this all on unpublished manuscripts which he had read, which now that they are published, nobody can find some of the crucial sentences that Merlot-Ponty was basing this on.
So don't read the prefaces tomorrow with this.
Start where I find this one page, with the book itself.
Is it called preface?
It is, isn't it?
It's called preface, right?
That was obviously written later.
That was obviously written.
I think what's really happened, but this is, again, just intellectual gossip.
I think that in 1945, it was not politic to be a Heideggerian when Heidegger had turned out to be a Nazi and the French had just been liberated, whereas Husserl, a good Jewish philosopher, was a great patron to be the descendant of.
So I think he was just sort of covering up his Heidegger tracks and pulling out the Husserl resonances to get his book to be acceptable.
In any case, I don't think you need to read it.
And because he really agrees with Heidegger, not with Husserl.
Husserl has propositional representations, and that's what he doesn't agree with.
We got to go back to our experience of the world that is non-representational, non-propositional, pre-conceptual, pre-predicative, etc.
Sometimes pre-linguistic.
And he's got to go to Heidegger for that.
But when he does talk about Heidegger, I'll just read you one place to show you how strangely dismissive he is.
On the top of Roman numeral seven.
What?
That's very interesting.
I must be cracking up.
Is it true that there's no Roman numeral seven?
That it goes from six, oh, seven is here.
I see.
And eight is there.
Okay, seven just doesn't have a number on it.
But at the bottom of the first page of the preface, which is Roman numeral seven, he's talking about how phenomenology tries to give a direct description of our experience as it is.
That's fine for Husserl and Heidegger, without taking account of its psychological origin and the causal explanations which science, historian, and sociology may be able to provide.
And then, skipping a little, he says, one may try to do away, oh, well, he's talking about how Husserl seems to be saying that and yet not doing that.
And he says, one may try to do away with these contradictions by making a distinction between Husserl and Heidegger's phenomenology, which is the right thing to do, I think.
Yet the whole of Reinhard, being in time, springs from an indication given by Husserl, which amounts to no more than an explicit account of the natural world concept, the naturalist of Eltegrift, or the Leibnizfeld, the life world, which Husserl toward the end of his life identified as the central theme of phenomenology.
But the basic thing to see is that when Husserl talks about the life world, it's always from the point of view of a detached observer looking at objects.
The big switch in Heidegger that Merlot-Ponteen is taking up is that they want to describe human experience when you're most engaged, when you're in the flow, when you're actually coping with objects in the most skilled way.
It isn't even enough just to sort of observe an object while walking around it, which is the nearest Husserl ever got to an engaged attitude, is to describe what it's like to walk around a tube that he had on his desk.
No, you've got to actually, in Heidegger, be hammering.
In Merlot-Ponte, you've got to be perceiving the world and trying to get a better look at it all the time.
And that's the flipple from Husserl to Heidegger, which he knows is thought, but which he isn't going to tell you about.
So now let's go to the phenomenological method that he's got.
Husserl's phenomenological method is detached reflection on your experience while you're observing.
Now, Merilloponte's is to describe the world while you cope with it.
But I can't find him saying exactly that, but I'll give you a few references.
By the way, what I'm doing is telling you things from the preface that I think are important, because I don't think you should read it.
It would just confuse you.
But at the bottom of the first page, he says, I've read that, giving you a direct account of experience.
That means don't take what neuroscience tells you, don't take what physiology tells you, don't even take what common sense tells you.
You've got to go back and look.
And it's very hard to look.
So, and he says, I'll skip ahead, because now that I've said it, it's very hard to look.
Someplace he says, nothing can be harder than to describe experience.
Where is that?
On page 58.
Oh, well, it must be 58 in this one.
I think it is.
Then I have to tell you where it is in that one.
Yeah, oh dear.
I had it in this one.
That's so funny.
And now, why don't I have it here?
I just didn't type it in.
I don't think it's a good idea for me to spend time looking for it right now.
I'll just read it to you.
Nothing is more difficult than to know precisely what we see.
There is a natural intuition.
There is a natural intuition that is just seeing things, a sort of crypto mechanism, which we have to break in order to reach phenomenal beings.
Or again, a dialectic whereby perception hides itself from itself.
But although it is of the essence of consciousness to forget its own phenomena, thus enabling things to be constituted, this forgetfulness is not mere absence.
It's the absence of something which consciousness could bring into presence.
In other words, that's a stop with that.
So those of you who had the Heidegger will recognize this claim, which is that phenomenology deals with something which in Heidegger language withdraws or remains hidden so that you can have experience of objects.
But this is, though it withdraws and is hidden, it's not absolutely unconscious or unaccessible.
It's just hard to get at.
And the job of phenomenology is to get it.
Merlot-Ponty has, well, Heidegger's main way of getting it is breakdown.
So when equipment, like hammer, equipment to function well, you become aware of the world and a lot of the background that's involved in being able to use equipment.
Never mind that for those who haven't had Heidegger.
Merloponte's got an entirely different angle.
What he's got is the same structure, that there is something crucial in our experience, which has to be hidden and withdrawn for us to see things, but which under certain conditions we can notice and pay attention to anyway.
The example I used when I teach Heidier comes from Marillo-Ponty, is what went by.
Marilo-Ponty, I listened to Mariloponte's lectures at the College of Home for a long time ago.
And one of the interesting things he said was, and talked about, was the way the illumination in the room has to become invisible in the you don't notice its color, its brightness, or if you didn't have any lights, particular lights, you could just have general illumination.
The illumination is what you don't see in order for you to see the objects.
If the room was full of dust so that it was as if you could see the illumination, you couldn't see the objects.
So the way perception works, a lot of what makes it possible for theology, has to be done, so to speak, outside of your main focus.
And that's what he wants to talk about.
Now, how do you talk about that?
Well, you'll see he has at least three techniques, which he never just sort of risked, but I can try to risk them.
So he's got breakdown cases.
It's got to be breakdown cases.
There's got to be cases, because when perception is going just fine and you're all into it in a flow, you're not going to notice what makes it possible for you to perceive things.
The first thing he's got is lots of neural cases, which is something getting more and more popular.
He was way ahead of his time, I think, to be a philosopher who draws on all kinds of brain-injured people, stages of various to see what it's like when some one of our perceptual capacities is missing.
And then that helps you realize what this missing part is like by seeing what it'd be like to be somebody with a certain kind of brain injury.
There are lots of interesting cases, and you'll get them as you get them.
Yeah, just perfect.
You're now going to explain Rolapanti's methods for getting at, it's so hard to understand, to see personally see that what's really going on when you perceive all the background, the work that the phenomena are doing, like the color constancy and the brightness constancy and the stability.
Let's put it this way: seeing a stable figure here, me as a lecture, fixed, determinate, with properties, and so forth.
That's an amazing achievement.
Of course, it's a big achievement on the level of what the brain is doing, but that's not our business.
We can't deal with that.
We're not neuroscientists.
But it's an amazing achievement on the level of phenomenology.
You can actually get at it in various ways.
So it's what is with, how is it on 58?
Nothing words equivalent to know what we see.
Yeah, but then that turns out to mean not just the objects we see, but our experience of seeing them is one way to put it.
We've talked about that.
So because perception hides itself, that is, we see the objects, but what he I see why you're asking this, but he wants to say, yes, but the consciousness forgets its own phenomena, enabling things to be constituted.
And that means that there's something going on that enables us to see objects.
And we're conscious of that too, but only marginally.
What confused me was talking about what makes it an investigation of what makes it possible to include that.
Of course, that's why we said this from the investigation of what you saw along.
You don't see your real estate.
No, right.
Right.
So that.
Okay, I guess that's where one should say, not scientifically possible, not even logically possible, but this story about conditions of existence.
What experiences of objects makes it possible to make it possible for us to see stable objects, which, when we're looking at stable objects, we're not bringing attention to those theory.
It helps to go right on from that because you're not going to find that out directly by looking at these neuro gigs, although you will learn something by seeing what specific laps that people can have.
But one way you can see it directly, he thinks, is to see what artists do.
And particularly Cézanne, who thinks that Cézanne was actually sort of, I guess, the great phenomenologist of perception.
That Cézanne was able to paint a painting that slowed down and brought in all the factors that contribute to seeing an object of movie.
So that when you saw his painting, it wasn't like seeing a finished object made in the days of perspective and so forth.
It was as if an object was coming into being as you looked at the painting.
You'll never see Cézanne again once you had read this article.
Certainly, now I could spend hours in front of Cézanne and got one in my office.
But Meryloponte is trying to get what Cézanne saw.
And now that's something to read soon.
And that's, I'm going to have that on reserve.
I can't put that on the virtual website because it's in the book, Sense and Nonsense, which is, and you can take it out and Xerox it.
But there is an article there that Cézanne's doubt, in which he tries to show how Cézanne manages to describe our experiencing of objects instead of describing, or paint our experiencing of objects, instead of painting the objects as we finally see them, as finished.
He paints what Merlopony thinks is our objects coming into the kind of determinateness and stability that they have in our everyday, well, what we see in our everyday feeling.
He paints the, not, he doesn't paint the object and its properties, he paints our experience of, okay, that's the second thing.
And you might want to look at Cézanne's piece pretty soon because it's so good.
And finally, and this is something he never kind of thematized, but he's got a genius for slowing down our everyday perception so that he finds cases where it isn't exactly breakdown.
It's just that something is happening that makes perception difficult, so that you can see your perception at work, trying to get a grip on the objects.
I'll give you two examples, which will come across later in the book.
He wants to tell you that we're constantly trying to get what he calls a maximum grip on objects, where we will get the most clarity and the most detail and the most shape and so forth.
And you'll find yourself sort of struggling to get a maximum grip on your intellect or unit blackboard.
But he says, consider what you do when you're looking at a new painting in a museum.
Then you have to move around to try to get to the position where you get the optimal of detail and the optimal of the overall shape.
And moreover, you don't sort of move around willfully.
Your body moves you around.
You just find yourself either getting closer or getting further away, trying to get the best view you can of it.
And he wants you to see in that what you're doing all the time, only you're not noticing it because I think you're so good already at getting the best distance from people and doors and tables.
You've got to bring in some weird situation where, as in a museum, you've got some new kind of object and you haven't got a, your body hasn't already got a a skill for just going to the right place to get the best sight of it.
Okay, here's another one.
These will be more relevant to you when they come up in the context, but I do want you to just see that he keep your eye open for these wonderful moves.
He wants you to see that your perception is indeterminate.
And that means something like confused, ambiguous, unstable, and then you have to sort of find the right attitude or the right body set to get the clarity in it.
And his example is: you're walking along in, I think it probably Stockholm, where he doesn't say, but you're walking along someplace where the boats and the trees are all sort of mixed together.
And you come across something and it doesn't look right to you.
You can't quite figure out what it is.
And you're looking at it and looking at it and it's sort of unstable.
And then it clicks into place and you see that it's what you thought was a mishmash is a combination of some trees and some massive boats.
And that gets stabilized in there.
But you're supposed to be able to experience this unstable thing and this ability that we have to finally get a grip on it, whereby seeing a case in which it's bizarre enough so that our normal getting a grip on it gets slowed down and we can see it.
That's the kind of example that he's going to use to get you to see the kind of perceptual activity we've got.
I'll give you one more.
He talks, he wants to convince you that what you see is not what is projected on your retina.
And he has neat ways of doing that.
He says, well, in a movie where the movie camera just actually is like the retina, that is, on the film, you're going to get whatever it is that the optics puts there, an approaching train seems to get bigger and bigger at a great rate.
And that's because the camera hasn't got the ability to give the approaching train size constancy.
Whereas, another way to put the same thing, he talks about when you take a picture of somebody with their foot toward the camera, you've got this great big foot.
That's for the foreshortener.
When you're using your cell phone to take your own picture, you've got a great big nose.
That's because it doesn't have size constancy.
It really gives you what the kind of see you've got on your retina.
He's trying to convince you that you don't see the perceptual world the way the world is projected in your eye.
That's, and now I want to get to the next point.
That's a transition.
That if you thought that perception amounted to copying what you got on your eye, you would be making the, what he calls, you would be making the mistake of having of entertaining the constancy hypothesis.
He talks about that very early on.
Let me show you where.
On page seven of the old one, let's go to the new one, page eight.
I'm telling you this partly to avoid you getting into a confusion, which you'll bound to if you, on the middle of page eight, he says, physiology of perception begins by recognizing an anatomical path leading from a received through a definite transmitter to a recording station equally specialized.
The objective world being given, it is assumed, oh, sorry, being given, it is assumed that it passes on to the sense organs messages which must be registered and deciphered in such a way as to reproduce in us the original text.
Hence, we have, in principle, a point-by-point correspondence and constant connection between the stimulus and the elementary perception.
But this constancy hypothesis conflicts with the data of consciousness.
See, the constancy hypothesis says that there ought to be a constant relation between what's on your retina and what you see.
That would mean like the train getting bigger and bigger as it came towards you.
Or like the, well, there are lots of other cases, but that's enough.
The constancy hypothesis thinks that that's what you see, and then somehow the visual system has to interpret that as the object remaining in the phase of it.
It has to do something with this constancy data that you're getting from your sense organs to fill it in or fix it so that it looks a stable size per second.
And I want to, so the constancy hypothesis is a wrong view that leads you to think that somehow the job of the visual system and the job of perception is to compensate somehow for our direct experience of what is hitting.
our sense organs.
And he thinks that's wrong.
He's very influenced by Geschal psychology.
He thinks that we directly experience objects having constant size, even though the light is changing in color somewhat with constant color and so forth.
There are, and you'll hear lots about this in your reading Thursday.
There are perceptual constancies.
And our experience has, we have them directly.
We don't have to start with experience of what's on the retina and then somehow explain how it seems that things remain the same size or how we manage to conclude that they remain the same size as they approach us, that they really look the same size as they approach us.
Unless, of course, perception is broken down.
If something gets really far so close to us like this, then it might, then you don't know what size it is.
Or, as I like to look from airplanes, you may have done this.
You've seen that the houses and cars and everything look the size they look as you start to take off.
And then all of a sudden, I've never been able to catch exactly where and how it happens.
They look like little toy cars and little toy houses.
You've broken out of the perceptual constant, the size constancy thing.
And then you're getting really what's registering on your retina, little tiny cars and little tiny houses.
So, but now the thing I want you to notice is the constancy hypothesis is, he thinks, a mistake of assuming that we got the experience of what our sense organs pick up.
The constancy phenomena is his name for what he thinks is right.
That we see things as having constant color, shape, size, and so forth, even though we can pick them up, we pick them up in all sorts of incomplete and distorted ways.
I don't know.
It took me years not to get confused about that.
You've just got to remember, just bear in mind the constancy hypothesis is bad, and that constancy phenomena is the Gestalt's answer to the constancy hypothesis.
It tells you that the constant hypothesis says there's some kind of direct correlation between what the sense organs are picking up and your experience.
The constancy phenomena says, no, there isn't.
That you experience stable objects with stable sizes, not what your sense organs are picking up.
And, okay, he must take them.
Yeah.
So the reason I constantly see it, something that does follow you?
Exactly.
A camera has got the constancy hypothesis.
So let me give you another example.
He doesn't use this one, but he could.
You think that, well, he does say, notice that when you've been outside in what looks like normal light, and you come into, well, or you look in through the window.
Let's think of a snowy evening, and you look in through the window, and the room inside looks all yellow and orange.
And then when you get inside, then it looks like the room's got normal light, and outside it looks all bluish.
That's because the constancy story is the room that you are in, you see as having a constant normal color.
And but I made it more complicated for myself.
But when you look out of that room into some other outside, for instance, then you're outside of the constancy, like when you look at the tiny cars, and the fact that there's bluish light coming from out there makes it look bluish out there.
So constancies could break down.
But normally, you don't even notice that the color of the light is changing.
The constancy phenomena fixes it.
I forgot what I was, I made it more complicated.
My version is simple.
In the old days, when you had coat of color film and coat of chrome film, it said on the box, don't take pictures within an hour of sunset.
And why?
Because if you did, they all turned out to be all orangey.
Because you didn't notice that the light had changed, because your color constancy fixed it.
But the camera, again, I'm still talking to him, but you see the point, the camera hasn't got the color constancy.
I think by now sophisticated digital cameras do.
I think you can take a picture within an hour of sunset and it still looks normal.
But the old, old, just plain film was being just like the retina with a lens in front of it, and it exactly had the constancy, the constancy hypothesis was right about it.
But when you turn that into a story about your experience, the constancy hypothesis becomes wrong.
Because within the limits of the perceptual constants, you don't experience what's happening in your eye.
And that's what that distinction is trying to tell you.
Yeah?
Can you say anything more about what you mean when you say we experience constancy phenomena directly?
Because the idea that constancy can break down there's some kind of deviation happening at some level.
I think.
Okay.
What happens to the constants when the constancy?
I think these are all the right good questions.
Let's take Aladis first because I find that easier.
It seems to me that what happens when the constants break down is your experience of truth of the constancy hypothesis becomes true.
Your experience is directly correlated with the frequency of light and the size of the object as it is on your retina.
Is that because you're investing age toward the world?
Yes, it's like no, I don't think so.
Although I maybe have to think about that.
No, I don't think so.
I don't think so.
Let's just figure it out.
No, because when the sun gets low enough, you experience it orange.
I mean, even your constancy hypothesis is the story breaks down and you get, say, often, at least, say, half an hour before sunset, everything starts looking oranger.
Yeah, that's not because you're less engaged.
I see why you might think so from the airplane.
It looks like when you're not on the ground anymore dealing with these objects, but you're way up there contemplating them, your constancy story breaks down.
But I don't think that's right.
Because if you're just on the top of a building and not engaged with the cars on the street, the normal side of the building, not the Empire State Building, they don't go wrong.
It isn't a question of engaged, disengagement.
Well, don't add me another one yet.
I'm not going to add the word.
Okay, okay.
So I have a friend who's like, and I've never been bigger at hypothesis, right?
Like, you can see the exact colors, shading differences, and gradients as they move along, you know, shadows and stuff like that.
I could see that.
I think this is kind of like what we're talking about with the whole phenomenon versus hypothesis.
Like, you can see like the camera sees all the different actual light changes and color changes.
Or I'm just saying, like, what's the direct object of my perception?
Wait, yeah, you could do that.
This is related to the Seison Doubt article.
One thing you could do as an artist is see things as always breaking down the constants, as always from the point of view of the constancy hypothesis.
For instance, when Monet paints the Roulen Cathedral, I don't know if you've seen this, at all hours of the day, from morning till night, he paints it reddish and he paints it whitish and he paints it gray and so forth.
He's learned to see, like your artist friends, the color experience without constant.
That's what the impressionist would do.
But and that can you can do that.
Now that's you get into a very, very special detached attitude, not just any old detached attitude, because I can be passionate about this.
You've got to be trained to do it.
And then you can see it.
You can see what your sense are, what your eyes are picking up.
Right.
I guess what I was going to do is like, I don't think neither of us he can see by way of the constant phenomenon as well.
Like that's how he deals with the world.
He can, you know, kind of change it over.
That's right, of course, yeah.
So none of us are like less engaged or anything like that, but he has the ability to be able to see like the cameras can see.
Yeah, that's right.
And that's what the impressionists were trying to do.
And Cézanne said he didn't want to do that, that he wanted to think objects the way they really look, but not also the Renaissance people tried to think objects as they look, but they trained them as completely determinate perspective when he finished.
He wanted to explain how we experience objects in their coming to look.
Yeah, you'll see.
But let me s say something about Alda's question still.
I think it's good and I haven't answered it, which is, how does Merrill Pomosi think of this business of when the perceptual constant breaks down and you're left seeing why does that happen?
I don't know.
I don't think he knows.
I don't think the Gestaltists know.
I mean, the people who have an opinion about this are the Gestalt people.
They're the ones who got the constants and the notion that, of course, they also break down.
Does anybody know enough Gestalt psychology to tell me what their view of why they break down?
Yeah.
Wait, wait.
Okay.
Don't talk out there, please.
I can't hear you.
Go ahead.
It's not a question of mediation.
It's a question of fundamental change in the structure of structural virus.
So, what J.J.
Gibson would say, or even with the science stuff, what's changed is somehow the relationship of different objects and colors to each other.
So, the principle on the fiction science table that we're perceiving on the table when you're trying to look at the color of a cloud paper on a brown table is not a question of the change in constancy that you see have to do with changes in the structure of light, in the opposite array, it has to deal with the color of what are the invariants that are still invariant.
While there were some fundamental changes in mobility, previously invariant, it's not now variants.
That sounds, I see what you mean, sort of, but we have to talk about this because it's always been varying, and somehow we've been able to pick up the invariants.
I see what you're talking about here, Gibson.
And now there are no invariants for the perceptual system to pick up because the plane is too high or the light has gone too far in some direction.
And when we haven't got in the stimulus the kind of invariants that the Gestalt people understood we could pick up, then we have to fall back on what we got on the retina.
I think what Conis would say about that is, and I think his actually does his plane example: is that if human beings do not have bodies that were geared for perceiving from high altitudes looking down, that is not on normal, in terms of the background, you want to way of perceiving from the body's point of view, that's not something that's either a socially acquired way of perceiving that's complete model, nor is it an evolutionary denominator that human needs perceive.
There's certain ways you can stress these things out that in fact get these kind of breakdowns.
It's funny.
This is, I mean, do your own phenomenology the next time you get a plane trip, because it can't just be the angle.
Because for a while, while you're looking down, it's still okay.
Like it would look if you were on top of barrows looking down, you could definitely see the car as the normal size.
It's a combination, and that might make Gibson happy.
A certain combination of the looking down and the lack of detail maybe that you get from at a certain distance together will give it to you.
But anyway, the basic point is, I think they argue one should say that it's a job of psychologists to figure out what keeps the input, what invariants in the input make us able to see the constants.
And they can make experiments, which they do, where you change those and you lose the constants.
And I'm sure there must be books about this, but I don't know them.
But is that any help?
Well, I thought that you mentioned the constant phenomena was part of a motivation of the idea that active engagement or active coping of good violence is important.
But it now sounds as if there's no connection between active engagement and deep livering with the explanation of what we sometimes have constantly, sometimes doesn't.
So I wonder whether it is important.
Uh-huh.
I it seems that moving through the field, that's a Gibson-like thing, is important, which is different than whether you're moving through the field engaged or detached.
It's then you'd you'd be happy with that.
I mean move, wouldn't you?
Moving is the crucial thing.
Your attitude of whether you're engaged or detached doesn't seem to be the crucial factor.
So now it comes back to me.
Why am I making a fuss about engaged or detached?
And saying, you know, the husseral is detached, and then you get the wrong answer.
Let me switch to that.
I guess I put your question on hold.
There's too many questions.
Keep it.
You would start with it next time.
Okay, because I want to say something about this interesting issue about engaged and detached.
And the best way to see what's at stake is something like how to put it.
Well, I don't know where this is going to lead, but I'll have to start where I am and see where it leads.
I mean, the extremist, wrong-headed way of looking at this, is let's start with that, is to think that when you are introspecting in a completely detached this is where I sort of what I was going to say when I if I come across it in the course of the lecture is the the wrongest way to think about what phenomenology is is to think that it's the same kind of thing you get when you meditate because then you are totally aware of your experience.
And after all, that's what the phenomenologist ought to be, is aware of their experience.
And you discover amazing things that you don't have any stable self, there are not any stable objects, and so forth.
How anybody know Varela, Roche Evan Thompson book?
Well, that's an extremely interesting example of the total mistake in this direction.
Varela thinks that he's got, he's telling us what Meryl-Ponty should be doing.
And the real important empirical investigation about what a self is and what objects are and so forth is arrived at through meditation.
Well, that's completely wrong-headed.
From a Meryl-Ponty point of view, that may tell you something interesting about what happens to your brain when you detach it and detune it from the world, but it certainly doesn't tell you what it's like to experience having a self and having objects and coping with them.
Meryloponty thinks, I think, that there are just two long ways of trying to find out about our most basic experience.
One would be to be completely subjective and turn in and meditation, and whatever you found there wouldn't be illuminating about your normal engagement with the world.
The other would be, that's the subject side.
The object side would be just to stare at things and describe them.
That also, and that might be your impressionist story, that wouldn't tell you about your direct engagement with the world.
And why should you be concerned about your direct engagement with the world?
Because, and this is the crucial thing, it's on not only is it our normal position to be actively moving around, coping with things, but uh it's that which is the background of everything else I mean you can you can be subjective and you can be objective but always on the basis of your general experience of objects in the world that you have when you are dealing with them.
And I think really, I'm just trying to put this to extreme, I think I just want to give you a feel for this.
I think really, as somebody once said to me, the phenomenology of perception is really a book about sports.
Why is it a book about sports?
Because that really says if you want to understand people's relation to the world at its best, then you ought to look at what an athlete in flow is finding.
An athlete in flow isn't finding that they've got a subject itself with inner states that they can contemplate it in meditation.
And it isn't finding that there's some object over there opposite them which they can contemplate the properties of.
Whatever it is that an athlete in flow is experiencing, it's something that is not like subjects and not like objects.
But it's this business of being in the world where that hyphens, where you are totally engaged in the situation.
The way Merle Ponty puts it at one point is that Descartes has got us stuck with the two kinds of being ontology.
There's the being of subjects and their inner states, and there's the being of objects and their properties.
And we need a third kind of being.
And the third kind of being is really the being of athletes in flow, if you want to put it that way.
It's the being absorbed in dealing with the world.
And that's supposed to be us exercising our perceptual capacities at their best.
And that's why the phenomenologist wants to study that.
And why the phenomenologist has, so to speak, from the phenomenologist's point of view, the right to say that what you discover in meditation is like breakdown.
It's like detuning your television set and seeing a lot of static on the screen.
You can do it, and the static will tell you something about how television sets work and the pictures weren't real.
But it's a breakdown situation.
And the same as you just sit and stare at objects.
That's a breakdown situation.
If you want to understand what perception is like, you ought to understand what it's like when human beings are behaving at their optimal relation to the world.
And that's what it's going to do.
Now, I've got to stop.
Let me hear your question again.
I don't think I'm going to be able to answer it in one minute.
Okay.
Yeah, we directly, yeah, let me try.
Give me one more minute.
I've got the challenge.
He's asking you, why do I say we directly experience objects with color constancy, size constancy, and so forth?
Clearly, there's a lot of processing going on in the brain, and there's a lot going on, too, in the visual hoping.
Directly is meant, and this is the first approximation, directly is meant to be the opposite of that there is some kind of processing that intervenes between the experience of what is on your retina and the experience you have of the world.
You, I'm still, I'm not sure I can do this, let's see.
This isn't going to work, but I'll just say it.
If you want to describe again the phenomena of us at our best, if that's what your job is, as the phenomenologist's job is, then the fact that there's other, on the level of the brain, there's lots of processing going on, is not incompatible with the experience that I am just an open head turned towards the world.
What you want to get rid of is some kind of notion of sense data or representation or anything like that, on the basis of which you have to do some mental work in order to get the experience of the world.
There isn't any, of course the brain's doing lots of work, but there isn't any phenomena that on the basis of which you then produce this stable experience of the world.
This is a good transition because what you're going to read about now is the view of sensation and association and how, if you don't get this direct story, what it is that people try to propose that mediates between what the constancy hypothesis says they've got in their experience and what the result is.
And he's going to try to show, this is my last attempt, all these mediating stories don't work.
You've just got to leave it on the one level to the brain doing it however the brain does it, but on the phenomenological level, there's no story more basic than that you are opening your eyes and seeing directly stable objects with constant properties.
I don't that's more like a a promise than an argument.
But that's the best I can do.