Okay, so here so the basic point of the chapter is that normal people have this basically interconnected form of experience in which there is always something that they're dealing with or thinking about, but always on a horizon or a background of a lot of other stuff that they are not dealing with or thinking about, but is somehow available to them and they can develop these horizons in all sorts of directions.
So I made a list of some.
I'm sure there are more, but here's five.
Normal people have all these kinds of interconnected experience.
They know where the parts of their body are and how to get to them, like squatting mosquito or whatever, throwing your nose.
I'll tell you which of these Schneider has and which he doesn't have and why in a minute.
How then two, they know how things are grasped with one sense or one organ, one hand.
I don't know, is there a word that covers hands?
You don't grasp with your hand.
Anyway, they have a sense of how things are grasped and with one organ, one member of the body, or also with one sense organ and another, so they can see how something good sounds and so we'll talk a lot more about that pretty soon.
But already we understand that they can, an organist, for instance, can sit down at an organ in an hour and get a sense of how it's all functioned in a way that he can grasp it, even though the things are in different places and registers are different and so forth.
People have that intersensorial transposability and inter-graspable transposability.
And they also have a sense of where things that they normally deal with are, where things that they normally deal with are and how to get to them.
That's important because that extends our body space to new things like the blind man taking up a cane or the musician taking up the organ or any other instrument and so forth.
But beyond that, it extends it to our body space extends to all the sorts of things that we know how to get to, so that our finding a way around in the city gets taken over and inhabited by our body space, and our finding our way around in a house and on the campus and so forth.
All of these things that we normally deal with become extensions of body space.
And we can extend it to new places and new things as we acquire new skills.
And then, in a way that I didn't work out so much, and which he throws in every once in a while, we have the same thing on the level of thoughts.
We understand how our ideas are connected, how stories are connected, how conversations are connected, in a way in which, wherever you are in the story, you know what led up to it and what's coming after it roughly.
Where you are in a conversation, you're able to remember where you came from and where you're going.
And remember isn't even the right word.
The conversation just feels like it's already bringing with it the past meaning as part of the current meaning of what's being talked about, and it's setting up a future meaning, which isn't something you have to think about and project any more than you'd have to think about the back of the house as a future experience when you're looking at the front.
Keep that in mind always.
The back of the house is already on the horizon of the front.
The front looks like it looks the way it does because it has the back.
And the conversation is going the way it is because it came from someplace, it's going someplace.
So that's number four.
Number five, very abstractly too, we have the notion of numbers and that they are functionally related in terms of their meaning.
So you get this funny example about plus and minus five, five plus four minus five.
Schneider has to figure out that that is four.
Whereas we just look at it and think, well, the fives cancel out.
He adds it up and gets nine, and then he subtracts five.
Ah, well, you know, it's four.
I'm interested in that because in the days when I thought about computers and artificial intelligence, there was a logic program that was considered very good.
It was considered by people like Muell and Simon who were thinking that they were doing some kind of cognitive psychology to be thinking like we think.
And I looked at it and I discovered that what it had was things like that.
It would say it would do logic sort of this and then that too, and then he takes that right back again in some way, and then it has to figure all that out.
It can't just be that, I don't know, greater than and less than cancel each other out.
I can give you an example.
It was even simpler than that.
Yes, or I don't know.
Now, if I go back and look at my notes, they're very simple logical functions.
It's like adding five and subtracting five.
The computer had to go through the steps, even though you could see immediately that one of these things canceled out the other.
So, but we don't see it there.
And now those are the five.
And we all get better and better at doing this sort of thing by acquiring new bodily and mental skills that extend the range of our ability and our ability to get around.
By the way, I have to say it someplace, and I feel so strongly about it, but I'd better say it now before I forget.
When I say skills, you don't find the word skill in here ever.
And it's not the translator's fault exactly.
The French don't seem to have a good word for skill.
So maybe Olivia can help us.
The word is what Adidas, I think, gets translated habit here.
Habit's the wrong word.
Habits he, absolutely, that may be what it means in French, but it can't be what narrow continu means.
We say habits are rigid, sort of meaningless, context-independent something or others, like flickering the light switch when you go in the room whether the electricity has failed or not.
And this example of a habit on 165, which is the first place I found where the word comes in, is forming the habit of dancing.
Well, think about that.
Dancing isn't a habit.
You may have the habit of going dancing at six o'clock every Saturday or something, a routine and boring habit.
But dancing is a skill.
It's not like brushing your teeth, which even that is going to be a skill.
And it's crucial to everything that La Ponte says.
It is never means habit.
He always needs to.
And if you understand what happened in French or in English or in the translation that made this peculiar bad mood, I was going to say, the one place where he really needs a habit is a footnote to Berickson.
So you should mention that, but how could that ruin the whole chapter?
And here he is at the bottom, 165.
So then it means inactivity.
I see for Berkson too.
Well, the footnote on 165, he says, is Berickson, for example, thinks when he defines habit as the fossilized residue of a spiritual activity.
Now, that is a habit.
That's the light switch thing.
You once knew what it meant, but now the arm just goes up in a meaningless way.
But it is itself the congenital existence as well.
It is, I'll tell you, that when he's talking about acquiring new something or others, he's not acquiring new fossilized residues of spiritual activity.
Yeah.
All that.
That's what skills are.
You acquire a new skill, it's present, you can call on it any time, but it's adaptable, you can improve it, and uh yeah so forth.
It doesn't mean that you're just well I think I I mean all all I understand talking to you is that habit just doesn't mean the same thing to somebody in French as it does to to me.
I don't know whether there's something wrong with me or not.
Habit has got to be for us sort of routine, meaningless kind of activity.
We've got a word for what you can acquire, what gets sedimented in the body, what you can make richer and richer.
That's skill.
Now I suspect the French must have one word for this.
Yeah.
I did with my life switch story, but let me give you another.
You could have the habit of dancing to talk like him, but that wouldn't be.
I mean, make no sense.
Trying to explain to somebody who's taken up ballroom dancing that they've now acquired the habit of dancing.
That's ridiculous.
They've acquired the skill.
What the habit would be, just to give you an example, is you get boringly into the routine of going dancing every Saturday at nine.
That's a habit.
And you can acquire that too.
But it's different.
So a better example of that has nothing to do with skill and table.
I have the habit of reading for low finding people or going to sleep.
Yeah, yeah.
That's not a skill.
Nobody could say that that's a skill.
And and it's if you don't see the distinction between habit and skill, all this stuff toward the end.
From where that leaves talks about the habit of dancing and then he talks about the habit of the blind man using the sick and so forth and so forth, that's always skill.
These are m motor habits he talks about at the at one seventy five.
Those are motor skills of everywhere.
Yeah.
That's where we're that's where I'm reading this very minute, yeah.
Yes, that's right.
Every but that's not a habit.
That's a skill.
The habit of going dancing on Saturday night doesn't reside between perception and motion.
But that but the skill of dancing just resides between perception and motion.
Sure, habits all over these places.
It's all he says you've been analyzing motor habits.
And he says, and then he goes into the blind man and his stick.
The blind man might have a habit, just I keep repeating myself, that it's so important.
You just won't get it if you don't understand that this doesn't mean habit.
The blind man doesn't acquire the habit of using his stick when he goes out in the sense of a routine thinking that he would use it no matter what.
He acquires a skill of using his stick, meaning that he uses it to feel late at the end of it, and perception and action are tied together.
Why do you exist this?
I don't understand.
We've got a good word for this.
It's called skill in English.
Why not he's using this word?
Well, yeah, that I think is a question about the French.
What's the word in French?
I think you say.
Habito.
Oh, well, that's even worse.
Actually, it means feel more.
Is in French?
No, but now what the heck is that?
Yes, it means skill.
And our translator should have said skill.
Because habit means something else.
And habits in French, when I hear it, is more close to this routine or infinity.
Is it?
Okay, well, however, well j i it's so important that you should really go through in the book.
And I hope you're doing this because it makes a big difference to your understanding if the words go against your intuitions at every turn.
You should have written body schema everywhere where it says body image.
But you could finally sort of get away without that, I think, after a while.
That you just can't get away without canceling every time he talks about habit and putting in skill, or you just won't have any kind of intuition at all of what he's talking about.
Did you notice the funny place?
It might be interesting to look at the French.
But one place all of a sudden the translator is if he woke up, translates body schema by body schema.
I don't know what to make of that.
Then he goes right back to image again.
I don't know if you had a lot of coffee or something, but at the bottom of 164, the acquisition of a habit, that's already wrong.
The acquisition of a skill, that sentence demonstrates anything, as a rearrangement and renewal of the corporal schema.
That's amazing.
Presents great difficulties for traditional philosophers and so forth.
Okay.
That that's yep.
I know I'm not saying more.
If you can say it anyway.
Well, just a just a conceptual point.
In English, you know, it also and this now is going to happen to what does it start overlapping.
So it's not an entirely just translation is a well, I I mean I I'm not going to discuss it about, but I'll say one thing.
I think the fact that the disposition is overlaps both of them in some way doesn't convince me that habit and skill overlap at all.
I think they are totally separate from any to them.
The thought rate of eye, but I'm just challenged.
Think of an example of where something can is a wig where you can't tell whether we're talking about a habit or a skill.
I think in each case, think that's a skill.
I mean, do I have the habit of speaking?
I might have a habit of speaking, and you know, every time, I don't know, when the parrot comes into the room, I say something to it.
But the parrot may have a habit of speaking.
Linguistic patterns are habitual.
My linguistic practices are not habitual, I don't think.
I don't, it's up to you what you think about it.
I mean, my sense of that is my linguistic practices are a skill I've acquired.
But anyway, don't worry about it.
If there is some area where they may overlap, there's huge areas where they don't.
And Merlo-Ponty is writing about areas where they don't.
He's talking about motor skills you can acquire quite easy and skick, quite dancing, like finding your way around in your house, like whatever.
Okay, I had to put that aside in somewhere, because I think it's really important not to get confused by the translation.
Okay, now let's see.
So we can get better and better at acquiring new bodily and mental skills.
I thought I said no problem.
Now, just in your wrist, neither can do the first three.
He can know what his body is when he sweats a mosquito.
He can know he can grasp something with one hand or the other.
He can know where things normally are and how to get to them, like his own house.
What he can't do is take over new situations.
He can't enrich his world by learning new habits so that new things show up for him as something he can find and do.
This is on 155.
At the bottom.
Just as he, about eight lines in the bottom, just as he means by means of preparatory movements to be able to take a grip on his own body before performing movement, before performing movements when they're not mapped out ahead in a familiar situation.
Well, I'm trying to say somewhere that he couldn't acquire a new habit, but I don't think I'd want to go.
I think he can.
Maybe if he's a finished bad sentence, let me try.
Just as he needs by means of preparatory movements to be able to take a grip on his own body before performing movements.
When they're not mapped out in a familiar situation, yeah.
I mean, whenever he's in a new situation, this is only half of what I wanted your sentence to say.
But when he's in a new situation, we can just already convert into doing something that we haven't done before.
We can find our way to a new house, for instance, right off.
He can't do that.
He has to turn it all into completely kind of computer-like mental rule before he can learn it.
And he never turns it.
It never turns into a habit, I think, but that doesn't say that.
I mean, I think he's stuck with the familiar situations he's got.
New situations don't become.
But I'm not sure.
And nothing depends on it.
So I just thought it was that way.
I'll write a question mark here.
If anybody finds evidence how this is, let me know.
Okay, now, but the important thing is that he could do the first three, but he can't do the last ones, it seems.
That is, he can't understand numbers.
We did that as an example.
He can't understand stories.
He can't understand conversations.
He can't understand metaphors and so forth.
Those are all, those aren't body things.
Those are not sensory motor things.
And though he's got this sort of diminished sensory motor world, he's got an even more diminished sort of intellectual world where he's just like a computer who can only do these things, calculating together meaningless squiggle.
He knows what to do with the squiggle five and the squiggle four and the squiggle five and plus and minus, and he knows that when he can do those things, lo and behold, it comes out four.
But he doesn't know why or what that means or how to adapt it to other situations.
Okay, that's basic point of chapter.
That was the first thing.
Okay, we do the above things and to incorporate new meanings in new situations because we can see the meaning or significance of our movements and of our ideas.
Now, there's some way in which he lacks seeing the meaning or the significance of his movements and his thoughts.
Now, the more important thing is to skip him for a while and now follow out what Meryl Parni thinks we can do.
So our actions and our ideas call up other actions and ideas.
That's this horizon story.
I'm going to give you a bunch of pages what he's saying because I think it's important.
On 151, bottom, whereas in the patient, the meaning has to be brought in from elsewhere by an act of interpretation.
Conversely, in a normal person, the subject's intentions are immediately reflected in a perceptual field, polarizing it, and so forth and so forth.
A wave of significance.
Effortlessly setting up a wave of significance and so forth.
So in the patient, the perceptual field has lost its plasticity.
That's lost its horizons.
He says that lots of times.
The Bible 152, the translation of percept into movement is affected by the express means of language.
That's denial.
You have to think it out.
Whereas the normal subject penetrates into the object by perception, assimilating structure into instructions, and through his body, the object directly regulates his movements.
Now, the blind man's pain is a good extreme example of that, where you penetrate into the object and so forth.
But anything will do.
When you get to understand your coffee cup, then you've got one of these kinds of grips on it, and the coffee cup can regulate your movements.
That is, when you get ready to have coffee, the coffee cup can solicit your hand to go in the right place, in the right shape.
And if the handle happens to be hidden behind, it doesn't matter.
But your body knows the handle is there and just where it is and goes there.
But not magically in the sense that you knew that before you ever encountered your coffee cup.
But magically in Merlot-Fanti's sense, and you don't have to think that it's your coffee cup and it has a handle and the handle is on the back.
And when all that interpretation and thinking is done, then you could just, then you reach for it.
It's magically in the sense that in your world, once you've acquired the skill of drinking from your coffee cup, it all just happens automatically, spontaneously.
Maybe automatic if you have it routinely.
It happens spontaneously.
It could become automatic, but then it would, never mind.
It would have to be real rigid, and you would have to have the tough.
I think I couldn't tell you this.
This will sink back into a previous discussion I don't want to go into.
So 165.
Just collecting the quotes that are important.
Here's the blind man's stick at the bottom.
It's not an object for him, and its point becomes the area sensitive to them, the scope and radius and so forth, are all just taken up in here in his activity.
They've gone, as Meriloponchi sometimes says, I couldn't find it.
They get on the side of the object.
Sorry, they're on the side of the subject.
Maybe that's a bad way of talking.
Maybe he doesn't say it.
Maybe I just said it.
Because I don't want to call us a subject for him.
They are taken over by the body.
That's what he says.
And become part of the body space and become our access to the world with pain.
Or just become the layout of the world that we inhabit, to use his terms, learn to get around in a city and so forth.
So on 166, he's talking about, he's still kind of getting to see because in a movie, there's no quick comparison, he says, I like this, on 166, between the object's length and the stick.
And so the blind man doesn't have to do that.
Doesn't mean Merilopanchi kind of have to pass through the objective world, doesn't have to know where the object is in the objective world, where the stick is in the objective world, and what the stick therefore tells him about the object.
That is all gone.
He did have to start there.
Again, it's not magical.
He doesn't know, the blind man doesn't automatically have the stick, but he has to get it.
And when he gets it, then he doesn't have to think about it consciously.
He doesn't have to think about it unconsciously.
He doesn't even have to process it in a certain sense.
I mean, according to Nero Ponti, and it's really important.
The blind man does not have a bunch of, well, when the blind man starts with the stick, he has these thumping rubbers in the palm of his hand, or bumps, because he bumps along.
And he interprets that.
Remember the word interprets.
This is what he does when he hasn't got the skill.
He interprets the bumps in the palm of his hand as meaning there's a curve there.
That's what it is not to inhabit, not to bring it into your body, not to make it part of the horizons of your coping world.
But after a while, and this is the crucial thing, the bumps go away.
Now it's very important how you understand that.
If you think the bumps are still there in the palm of your hand and you feel them, and you interpret them, but it's all unconscious now and very fast, then you are getting it wrong, according to Baroque.
Anybody know Polanyi anymore?
The person who gets this sort of brilliantly wrong is Michael Polanyi in his book, The Tacit Dimension.
He does the cane story, and he says that at first you have to focus on the bumps in the palm of your hand, but later instead of being distal, that is the object of your attention, they become proximal.
They become so close to you that you don't really notice them anymore.
But I notice how I'm putting that.
They're still there.
You're still getting the not just the information about the pain, the pain in the palm of your hand, because you have to get that information.
But it's not coming to you perceptually anymore.
It's being processed outside of your mind altogether, according to the phenomenology of it, according to Merloponte.
We'll come back to this later.
But the important thing he wants to stress is you are not interpreting, you do not have a rule, he says this too, that relates the bumps in the palm of your hand to where the stick is.
When you've got the habit on the side of the body, the phenomena is that the stick has become part of you, it's transparent, you don't feel anything in the palm of your hand.
What you feel when you use the stick is the curve.
He says that it's with it.
But in fact, I've got a turn to it.
We've gone about this a long time.
Here we are on page 176, about 20 lines down.
Well, no, it's probably eight lines down.
It would appear in this case that the perception is always a reading off in the sensory data, that is the twitches in the palm of the hand, but constantly accelerating, operating ever with ever more attenuated signal.
That is sort of clearly an outer consciousness.
But habit does not consist in interpreting the pressures of the stick on the hand as an indication of certain habit again, here, of course, the skill of using the stick does not consist in interpreting the pressures of the stick on the hand as indications of certain positions of the stick, and these are signs of external objects.
It could relieve us of the necessity of doing so.
Now, you can still say, ah, but it's all going on unconsciously.
And all I think Merlot Fung Chi would say in response to that is, well, the burden of proof is on you to say that, but the nominology is that the stick is now just a part of my body.
And I don't have to, just as I don't have to understand the pressure on the palms on my feet to know how the floor is going, I don't have to understand the pressure on my hand to know how the curve is going.
So let's go on with that.
The pressures on the hand and the stick are no longer given.
That's the crucial line.
They are no longer perceived.
The stick is no longer an object perceived by the blind man, but an instrument with which he perceives.
It's the bodily auxiliary and so forth.
But the real object is not to give emphasized objection and invariant or set of perspectives, but something towards which the stick leads perspectives, which, according to perceptual experience, are not signs but aspects.
That's another way to put it.
Signs are what you have to interpret.
They're the perceptual given, which supposedly, and I think, well, which correctly says you have to be interpreted when you start to learn the stick.
But they stop being common and you stop interpreting when you get it stick.
Again, so they're not, it's now, what's the wrong view then?
It's called intellectualism, of course.
And intellectualism takes the world of, takes up these elements of impression and then interprets them by somehow, well, it could be that you did it by association, but that's such a looser view that it's dropped out by now.
We don't even hear about empiricism anymore.
But you still hear about the guy who thinks that there is an interpretation, a cognitive intention, in which the sensory data are grasped and put together by an intelligible core.
You see that?
He uses a word for that as concept.
For Husserl, who has this wrong view, according to Naro-Fonty, the word is no emo.
And the idea is that you've got some kind of rule in your mind or law which enables you to put these things together.
Let's go on.
Sodi.
It's a reference to Husserl, where he says they're taken up and put together by an intelligible core.
At this point, he's admitting that at least this stage of Husserl, he's admitted to the Hussar of an intellectual.
But this analysis distorts the sign and the meaning because it separates out by a process of objectification.
That's the place you should.
That's the prejudice of the world.
It has turned the stuff in the palm of your hand into objects, which you have to relate to the curve out there, which is an object.
So it's done, the sensations, which were pregnant with meaning, and the invariable core is not a law, but a thing.
What does that mean?
The sense content, which is already pregnant with demon, and the invariant core, is not a law.
Well, what's kind of tendencies here?
But this analysis distorts both the sign and the meaning.
We got that.
That sign being the twitch is misunderstood, and the meaning being some intellectual thing you bring to it, which is a misentive thing.
It separates out by a process of objectification of both the sense content, which is already pregnant with meaning, Narrow-Ponty says, but not the world of prejudice, and the invariant core, which is not a law, but a thing.
Ah, of course.
The law was being the rule, the concept, for putting it all together.
But there is no such invariant core.
That is just the curve or whatever it is that you're feeling at this point.
He feels the architecture between subject and world, active transcendental consciousness, the manner which carries it into the thing, intro world, that means that it's organs.
Okay.
Yeah.
So that's the first thing I wanted to say about horizons.
Where are we?
Yeah.
That should be a trouble you study.
No, it's only quote.
Which, but which one?
Because he goes back to the crazy.
Ah, things is true.
Ah, between.
Well, yes, I don't like that.
You're right.
Between subject and world, I didn't like.
Subject, I don't think it's the right thing to say.
Transcendent of consciousness, I don't like.
You're right.
That troubles me too.
I don't know why he wants to say that.
Yeah, that's right.
He shouldn't say that.
It troubles me.
Except that I got sort of like 30 lines on my side, and you've got one line on your side.
Otherwise, there's a problem.
The other line should 30 lines should trouble you.
We have to talk about that.
Okay, where are we?
176.
Let's see.
I just call up other actions and ideas.
Is that lying?
I don't know where I got off to this.
Yeah, okay, I did 171.
Then I did 165.
Yeah, there's a blind man slipping 166.
157.
Yeah, okay.
So Merrill-Ponte calls the movement side of this flexible adaptability where you stop having signs and interpreting them and just become open to the world.
That's motility.
That's what the chapter is about.
He uses the word motility, not all that much, though I thought I would point out, having said what goes on, that he calls it motility, the bottom of 158.
These move today should enable us to clearly understand motility as the basic intentionality.
Consciousness, aha, this is going to make Alva happy, but it doesn't make me unhappy.
You can see that.
At the top of 159, consciousness is in the first place not a matter of I think, but I can.
Exactly.
He never should say that.
That's a Husserl phrase.
He can't mean that, because on 167 or 161, 161, he's talking about what he should say, starting on 160.
A movement is learned when the body is understood, that is, when it is incorporated into its world.
To move one's body is to aim things through it.
That sounds like an I can, but goes on.
It is to allow oneself to respond to their call.
That's the right thing to say.
That's the Gestalt thing.
Yet it isn't I can do, it's that it draws me to do.
And it isn't drawing me in the sense of an I.
It's drawing the corporal schema, the one in me.
Remember, one experiences things.
There is a, and Heidegger talked about Mon side of the body.
It's one who perceives in me, not I.
And what it does is not put a aim on things, but be open to the call of things.
And uh I was just thinking, oh, yeah, I and I put on reserve uh a book called Ways of the Hand by uh David Sudnow, Learning to be a jazz musician.
And by the end of the book, I mentioned it, but I put it on reserve, he's very clear, thanks to me, I must say, because I had the manuscript, that he talked like Husserl.
He said, by the end of the book, my I know jazz and I reach for the right notes.
And I said, Why?
You're calling the book Ways of the Hand.
Why do you think that?
So you'll see that the end of the book is rewritten, in which he says, My hand knows jazz and reaches for the right notes.
That's the right thing to say.
Now, his hand is, in fact, he should say, I don't remember how far I've even into this, drawn to the right notes.
And that's very important.
It's just a, this is the sunny relation he has to Husserl.
And just when he shouldn't be taking up Husserl, he does for a minute.
It seems like he can keep the phrase, I can, so long as the I means by his human.
And I send them.
Well, and the can should, as long as we're clear that that's, and oh, I can respond, or I can be called, yeah, is this ultra.
Right, it is.
That's what I think if he did, as long as he changes the meaning it has for, for I think, for Usero, at least the meaning it has in ordinary English, to say I can is much too individual and much too active.
Well, you want it to be at least equally impersonal and passive.
You know, when you have a skill, you must be getting used to that.
That you are drawn in by the affordances.
That's what he agrees with at his feltist about.
Remember the arms of the heroes going out to the food in front of them.
Achilles doesn't say, I can reach for the grapes.
Achilles' arm just goes out and reaches for the grapes when Achilles is hungry.
That's better.
He responds to the call of the food in front of him.
Yeah, I agree.
Is it implied that there's an individual I as opposed to one can?
See, I want him to say one can.
And when he does say the body is, is one that perceives unique.
I don't think he should say I can.
And of course, Husserl does, because he thinks the transcendental ego does it, and that's an I.
Although Husserl once was far enough to see there was no ego, he brought it in later.
But at the same time, what you said the body didn't percept or what is the subject?
Yeah, I couldn't.
I mean, I agree.
That's what he says sometimes.
And sometimes he's very clear.
Well, yeah, but then how what he really means, and that is, I think we both agree, there is something like a body subject.
A body subject is me as an embodied moving organism in the world.
As long as you understand that, you're okay.
But when Descartes used subject, he thought of it as something separable from the world of harmony.
Well, I hope so.
But Hussle too?
Yeah.
Hmm.
There's no transcendental subject in there doing this that could have done it even if there was no world.
Yeah, but is that the last thing?
So speaking, in the last analysis, but let's not talk about it now.
I mean, I didn't until his death, Husserl thought, but in the last analysis, it was done by a transcendental subject.
I think Taylor Farming's paper says a lot on this topic, and I think their farming interprets Husserl as having this understanding of himself as being a secular totality that sticks together these subject-object qualities, and that's why it fails.
So, even though I think it was right in the Husserl says that there is this kind of unity, this unity is really just a high popularity.
Okay, well, let's read Taylor Carmen and see what you think.
Let me go back to this.
I promised I wouldn't go into discussions, and I can't resist.
So, why did I do that?
Because the ICAN came up and triggered my anti-Husserl reaction.
So, where were we?
Where's the ICAN?
Office 159.
I must have just read 159.
Yeah, I was.
Okay.
But again, if you're sort of warned how to hear it, you're all right.
I'm at the top of 161 now, where you're responding to the call.
And because it's all about what I said I would read you as it tells you what motility is.
Motility, then, is not, as it were, a handmaiden of consciousness, transporting the body to a point in space, of which we formed a representation beforehand.
In order that we may be able to move our body towards an object, the object must first of all exist for it.
Our body must not belong to the realm of the in itself, and so forth.
And then, skipping to the next paragraph, the body inhabits space and time.
And that's just the same point he's making over and over.
So, how do we do this?
That's the next question.
How do we inhabit space and time is with the body?
And the answer is: well, I'm setting things up, by the way, if you don't think this is really an answer, don't be upset.
I don't think it's really an answer either.
His answer seems to be: well, we do it because we have horizons.
In a way, that is an answer.
Phenomenologically, he's going to give you the basic phenomena in terms of this particular kind of phenomena that he's been describing: of inhabiting the world, inhabiting the body, taking up the cane, being able to do arithmetic.
All of those are examples of the kind of things we can do because, remember, I said there's always a lot on the horizon of what we're doing.
Now, I just want to show you places where he says that.
149 is a place where he says that a lot.
And it helps, I see, because there's two different meanings of subject here.
The body is the subject.
I don't like it.
But anyway, he's not a Kantian subject halfway down.
The Kantian subject posits a world.
But in order to be able to assert a truth, the actual subject must, in the first place, have a world and be in the world.
That is sustained around about it a system of meanings whose reciprocities, relationships, and involvements do not require to be made explicit in order to be exploited.
That's a very important thing.
One, it's telling you what the body schema is and does.
Two, it's telling you that it's done it on the level of these meanings that are just interrelated.
And I think it's important, though I can't tell you fully why I think yet it's important.
These involvements, the way the system of meanings, which is the body schema, works, do not require to be made explicit in order to be exploited.
Surely that's right.
I think he thinks, and I'm going to come back to that.
They don't even have to be implicit to be exploited.
To be implicit is a very, very bad intellectualist move, which is always to say, well, if you're not conscious of it, it's the same sort of thing, and you could be conscious of it.
I want to stress, and I'll come back to it again and again, that it's very important that the Vero-Ponte, this thing which he sometimes calls the synergistic system, the way all the parts of the body and all the parts of our familiar world are interrelated, is not something that you could make explicit.
It's not that, it's a kind of interrelatedness, which is what is sort of sui generous to the body.
And whenever you see implicit, you should reach for your pistol as far as I can see.
The latest one is Bob Brandon in his book, Making It Explicit.
But it's already, as Brandon is proud to say, in Hegel.
The intellectualist always claims that what they have finally been able to understand mentally must have been there all along, going on, and that they're just bringing it out.
And the happening is parade as you go by.
Now, what are they denouncing or defending?
Not very clear.
Does anybody know what that means?
It's very bad to have a parade all together denouncing and defending something they know they know very well.
A lot of people take a lot of trouble to tell it something.
Minority, I know.
They want to see more of minorities?
How can you tell?
Because that's a really angel.
Six-year-old you're underrepresenting them all right.
How long is this going to go on?
Why a long time?
Okay.
I've got to go on talking.
Time is short.
Close those windows.
Where are we?
What?
Can you educate most of the education?
Well, whatever it says, it's not what we're doing, so we better go on.
These acquired worlds, what am I looking at 149.
But I remember I said the ones that the horizons are not implicit, and they are certainly not explicit, and they're not implicit either.
I'll come back to that.
I think that's the most important thing to to to say, because as soon as you use the word implicit, unless you want to be an intellectualist, you will find yourself an intellectualist.
Because the implicit says always it couldn't be it could be thought.
And I think that the t the corporal schema can't be thought.
Strong thing.
I mean, that's the thing that you couldn't ever become aware of, but we had the total intercensorial way that everything sort of refers to everything else in some amazingly systematic way.
I think he thinks you cannot become aware of it.
But again, no talking here.
Okay, one remark.
This is always hopeless, right?
You're a wonderful straight person.
Yet that's to show that that's not what we do.
That's why he talks about it.
We don't do that.
We do not have to make analogies except when we understand them.
But again, they just express this intercensorial unity that just we can just see that the thing down there is the foot of the table.
Well, Schneider does it good.
And we can spell out the analogy sometimes.
It's such a wonderful analogy John Searle's written a whole article about.
I'm thinking of Sally as a block of ice.
Yeah, the metaphor.
But we can't spell that out.
And that's perfect for an answer to you.
I thank John for this because I think it's a narrow upon T-like point.
I mean, some metaphors we can spell out.
The table is supported by that thing, the way we're supported by our legs.
But John has this Sally is a block of ice.
And he goes through a whole article trying to spell out why we feel that that tells us something important about Sally.
She's not literally cold.
She's not literally hard, and so forth and so forth.
Anyway, I think narrow upon two things.
That some metaphors can be spelled out, that we don't do it that way, and that I don't, and I bet he thinks, or he should think, some metaphors can't be spelled out, but that's all right, because we don't implicitly do it that way anyway.
Okay, back to this.
I can't resist, but I'm doing pretty well now.
Okay?
Let's see now.
I'm at the bottom of 149.
Well, I said the actual subjects have these meanings and so forth, and they do not require to be made explicit in order to be exploited.
I want to say, and they can't be, and luckily they don't, because we couldn't.
And I haven't found that in him yet.
I'm just telling you that.
When I move about my house, I know without thinking about it.
And I think I want to add now, I want to read this, and I'm claiming that he says this, but I haven't found the passage yet to tell you, though.
You'll see it someday.
When I move about my house, I know without thinking about it.
And that means consciously or unconsciously, explicitly or implicitly, that's just not the kind of thing.
Know-how is not implicit know that.
So it goes through MI again.
I know without thinking about it that walking towards the bathroom means passing near the bathroom.
And he's spelling it out, that he's spelling it out in a way that's just sort of the tip of the iceberg, I believe he thinks.
That looking at the window means having the fireplace on my left.
And this small world each stress for each perception is immediately related in relation to a great number of possible coordinates.
Well, all I can say at this point is, if you're in the AI business, for instance, you think you could spell out all that we've got in this weird way, the relation of where everything is to everything else, in a kind of AI people would call a frame of my house.
I think that is just crazy.
And it's turned out to be impossible for the AI people in any way.
But I haven't claimed I proved it yet.
Keep your eyes open.
Does he think this could be spelled out, that it's implicitly comprehensible in mental terms?
Wouldn't that make him an intellectualist if he thought that?
It sure would.
And he's not an intellectualist, he says, so we've got to be, keep your eyes open.
So at the bottom, these acquired worlds, which confer upon my experience, the secondary meaning, I themselves carry colours out of a primary world, which is the basis of a primary meaning.
In the same way, there is a world of thoughts.
Oh, just giving you these parallels, the things that Schneider doesn're going to.
A world of thoughts or a set of names left by our initial positive people to enable us to rely on our concepts and acquire judgments as we might on things that are in front of us.
So our thoughts have the same structure as the perceptual things in front of us presented globally without there being any need for us to resynthesize them.
That's an important line, too.
Remember that.
Because everything is always already synthesized.
That's the whole regular parts.
Whenever you hear about synthesizing or resynthesizing, I think he doesn't think that we ever synthesize them.
That they are synthesized, all right.
That is, if synthesized means they have all these interconnected to each other.
There was never a time when they had to be synthesized or resyncrified, which doesn't mean that sometimes you can acquire a new skill, like you using a blind man's painting, in which you will have to do the synthesizing.
You will have to get the bunks in the palm of your hand related to the curve.
But when you really got this pain in hand, then you nothing is synthesizing anything.
I mean, your mind isn't doing it consciously, your mind isn't doing it unconsciously.
Before the end of the time, I'm going to try to find the brain isn't doing it either.
It does not done.
But the only reason you could believe in synthesis is if you made the crazy pain the money and believe that there were all these little parts to synthesize in the first place.
That's what makes you an intellectualist.
If you believe that there are elements, then you believe that somehow they must be synthesized into this historic whole, then you are going to have a story about the synthesis.
It's going to be a concept that enables you to do it or something like that.
If you're a gestaltist and think the whole is prior to the parts, and the whole is just given both the perceptual holes, which we're just born with, some of them, some of them we learn, cultural holes we pick up by imitation, but we pick them up as a whole.
We never have to go through the elements unless it's some weird special thing like the wine ends.
I think behold.
But now let's see.
So I don't have to do this.
There we are, 150.
Yeah?
Well, I said that, but I would say exactly.
You can always, and this is, I think, the illusion of the intellectualist.
I keep going to say, this is what I believe Merlot Function says.
Keep your eyes open.
You'll find him saying it somewhere.
If he doesn't say that he's an intellectualist, then he knows very well he's not an intellectualist.
But on this point, I want to say, what fools intellectualists say is that you can always sort of do the tip of the iceberg.
You can start telling the stuff you know about the house.
You mustn't think that that didn't fall like that all the way down implicitly.
That's just what you can, on reflection, sort of turn it into, not make it out of.
And now in AI, you see this in the common sense knowledge problem.
You can make a lot of your common sense knowledge explicit.
There are these wonderful examples from the one that when they're dead you stay the dead.
Or John Searle, George Bush wears underwear.
And then they're then disposed to think, not, gee, all my common sense knowledge is like that, but there is so much common sense knowledge we would never be able to get it all spelled out like that.
But I added one, you can't whistle and chew gum at the same time.
That's true, too.
You can spell that out.
But try spelling it all out, and the answer is going to be: I think there isn't any such thing as that total common sense knowledge list of all the common sense things you know.
And there isn't any list of how you go around your house, and the bathroom is related to the living room, and the living room is related to the kitchen, either.
And it's an illusion, which is a very interesting illusion that you get, because you can spell out some of it.
You assume it must be the two forces that make somebody intellectualist, I think.
One, the thing that Al is saying, you can start spelling out some of it, Nero-Ponty just did, and you could spell out some metaphors, as she just did, and that you think then it must be like that all the way down.
But why do you think it must be like that all the way down?
Because you think it needs to be explained how you get these relations to other things.
How do you know that this movement will be related to this perception?
How do you know that the living, when the living room is on your right, the kitchen is on your left?
And that must be somewhere in you.
Okay, I'm going to say now what I was going to say at the end, but this is what's really on my mind today, so I might as well say it now.
The real crunch thing that you're going to ask, and it could have been more dramatic to say it to me.
I'll have to say it.
The thing you're going to have to keep asking Nero-Ponty is: how are you finally going to explain all this stuff about horizon without finally becoming an intellectualist on some level and saying it's something that the mind is able to do?
Or becoming an intellectualist on another level and saying it's something the brain does just like the mind but sort of out of touch with the mind and I think that you don't if you that's what's going to drive you the intellectualism you're going to think that you need a mental explanation of it you're going to think you need to find the rules you think you're going to think you need to be able to do implicitly what you could make explicit or that it's done unconsciously or it's done by the brain and I'm going to say no you don't need any of that and if you did need that you would be forced to be an intellectualist as everybody has been up to Marilyn Clanty yeah is it time for questions and answers then what do you think I was hoping to go on because people have too many questions a criticism is I guess his position is really demonstrated in this chapter though that at some level there must be some sort of synthesis going on with some sort of inversive knowledge because you can knock out parts of the brain and you lose just parts of the perceptual content so there are parts of the brain you can knock out and you lose and actually categories of rooms or categories of building so that's always the counter argument to what you're saying that no at no level there's no synthesis going on we can't explain okay what's forcing people into intellectualism that's interesting I don't I had never thought of that aspect that argument before I'm not impressed I mean I think Marilyn Quanti is going to say that these are artifacts of taking up parts, breakdown parts of the brain and so forth.
And if these concepts, say, rooms, started in isolation, we wouldn't be able to use them to understand rooms.
It's only when they're part of this higher order synergistic system.
They always have to fit in this hole.
But that would be the right move to make if you were going to make an intellectualist move and try to say that.
But I think you really got to believe, I'll come back to this at the end, I mean, that the brain has a certain kind of top-down holism, and we don't know much about it.
What 11 or 12 billion neurons can do, we don't know much about anyway.
I think it's late, is it up to 12, I think it's up to 12 billion neurons with 10,000 connections on each.
It's going to talk all the time.
And we have no clue what it does.
But you can imagine that what it does is top-down.
That's what Walter Freeman's got supposed evidence for.
And it doesn't do it by analyzing anything of anything.
It's important to just tell yourself that that could happen.
Because as soon as you have the idea that the brain could be doing it in a way which has nothing to do with how we move our minds, then that liberates you.
I'm getting, I am saying what I was going to say at the end.
That liberates you to have to take the phenomena at face value.
That is, it's only if you think that there's got to be an explanation of the felt top-down holism, of which there aren't any elements, and elements are only the result of the prejudice of the world.
If you think that that can't be the bottom line, there must be an explanation, then you're driven to intellectualism.
And you're driven to say, and I was going to say this at the beginning, Nero-Ponty talks about horizons, he talks about the being in the world, he talks about existence, he talks about maximum grip.
That's all very well, Nero-Ponty.
You've got the best phenomenology in the world, you could say to him.
But you can't explain how that works.
And then the intellectual said, I've got an explanation of how it works.
And the associationist said, I've got an explanation of how it works.
What is Merloponte supposed to say?
He's supposed to say, I don't need an explanation of how it works.
The brain does something.
Physical stuff comes in, and the physical brain does something.
And then I've got a world.
And the world is already holistic, and my body is already synergistic, and they already fit together.
And I'm giving you a description of that.
And there's no reason why there has to be anything more basic than that description.
That's very important to keep in mind.
Yeah, now, okay, James, and then Rick.
Well, it just seems like if what you're worried about is reduction, reductions or something like that, and that's fine.
But that's not to say that there's no brain story, there's no explanation at the brain level.
It's just that there's a different explanation, a sort of content level.
Well, yes, but I'm not sure.
There's no reason why they can't work together.
Yes, but the question is how they work together, right?
There could be a kind of intellectualist cognitivist brain level working with an intellectualist cognitive phenomenological level.
That would be, Merloponty, wrong.
Okay, that would be wrong.
Or there could be, and I'm claiming this is what Merloponty thinks there is, a dynamical system story to be told about the brain, where the brain is, in some holistic way, putting all this together, and all the component parts are being coordinated with each other within the brain, and there are tractors in the brain which are not ever come about, have any rules or elements in them.
And that is correlated with the phenomena, namely, that he's describing.
So, should this be a brain story?
That's what I want to say.
If you deny a brain story, that is much too magical for anybody to believe nowadays.
It doesn't have to be a brain story that is correlative with or conceptualism or intellectualism.
That sort of base the question.
And if there is this holistic brain story, then Nero Ponte doesn't owe you any explanation of how the stuff he's describing works.
And at least you can get the feel for this.
The stuff he's describing works because the phenomenal world and the body are the way they are.
Now, what there is underlying is a brain doing something and a body doing something, which is correlated with, which, and I probably didn't, and you can say in Searle's terms, caused by all this stuff that Nero Ponte is talking about, it's going to be caused by and realized in the brain, that you don't want to get from that any claim that you need to, that there's something nearly descriptive about the phenomenology.
Because I just want you to get the feeling.
How can I put it this way?
There are only two levels of explanation that you need, not three.
And the intellectualist slips in a third one.
That's the cognitivist have always done this.
The bottom level is the brain does it somehow we haven't a clue.
Or if we do, it's a Walker Freeman-like holistic clue.
And we know that the phenomenon is like this.
From that, we have Narrow-Pon T.
But there should be underlying this concepts, rules, features, categories, any of that stuff that we use sometimes when we understand things, sometimes it's unnecessary.
There's no have to be a third level between the neural level and the phenomenological level that explains the phenomenological level.
They're just in different levels of description.
They're correlated, but you can't get beneath the phenomenological level to another mental level.
That's the point.
You can get from there to the brain level, which we don't understand.
Well, if you did understand the brain level, it might show that you don't need the mental level.
The mental level by which I mean some operations, some rules, some noema in social language, some categories in common language, which are like making a whole framework together.
It's not to be put together.
It's not to be synthesized.
Okay, that was the end.
But I was supposed to let people talk, yeah.
If I answer you to describe the way I first house we live in, can you do it?
Hello.
Is that because the house and the world is so simple?
Because you stored information about the house.
Because I stored information about the house.
Well, that's the intellectualist illusion.
I mean, that that you can sometimes operate like a representational system.
There's no doubt if you can draw conclusions, you can have memories like the house, in which there are elements, I presume.
Although probably Merrill Punky would say, well, I've got more like a field for the house would have been I could fit a few wounds in, but whatever.
The fact that you can do mental stuff sometimes can't be an argument for you are always doing that sort of stuff whenever you are an intelligent being presenting intelligence.
So the objection is not to be weakened to write that for the legal representation.
No.
It's that there be an explanatory level of the phenomenological level with which the whole thing is redone in terms of the fremented representations, resynthesized, in a bad way of talking.
But the only trouble is to think that there's something going on beneath the holistic compound story.
The story of Star Garden is a kind of sound is that many of the capacities that you have have themselves in for an ancient theoretic structure.
That is to say, they're driven by certain patterns of syntheticity.
So for example, you understand the words of signal producing your words of this knowledge.
I don't agree with that.
Yeah, I understand.
This is the compositional story.
Well, so you're excited to work some words and more exciting rules showing the word words of combination.
And of course, we shouldn't get off too much in this.
But then the Mero-Pantian says, okay, there is grammar may have some compositional structure.
Why not?
But it's not at all clear that semantics and its meaning does.
And it's pretty clear that pragmatics, how language actually functions when people talk to each other, doesn't have that structure, at least phenomenologically, clearly doesn't have that structure.
Why should we think that because you know grammar is compositional and has a physical cognitive structure, we should think the whole thing does.
But it challenges to accept that certain aspects of the holistic field could be thought about as computational.
I think that's right.
Then why doesn't it wisdom?
Well, I mean, for one thing, it doesn't seem right, but I mean, why not?
Because we've got arguments for the computation, compositional story of the parameter.
But if we had arguments about that there was a schema underlying my ability to walk, which put together elements into a coherent pattern, we believe it.
But we don't.
But you know that the final number of muscles in the body is finding the forms unless there's still in very precise ways given different forces exhibiting on them.
That's why it's hyper-engineers and basically to walk.
That's how you do it.
That's right.
You're explicit.
And basically, but isn't mother nature just the energy engineer to perform certain things you have to conscious access?
Well, Alan is saying just what he should say, and he was the one I was, you know, thinking a while I talked.
But I want to say, sure, the brain has to take account of this physical thing, which is the body of bones and sinews, and it has to learn how to do it so that it doesn't fall over in a gravitational field and all that.
And it does it.
But why we should think that it does it by rules or by concept or by anything, that it we don't have a clue as to what the brain does when it does it, but we know this much.
We don't experience bones having to be in the right relation to tendons, having to be in the right relation to gravitational fields.
We experience this holistic, synergistic system.
And why suppose that when the brain does it for us, it does it the way we do it when we're thinking about things and learning new skills?
I mean, that's the crucial question.
It's always reading back down into the brain's way of doing it, our way of doing it.
And I think Malopanti is resisting that.
Okay, now, Rick, yeah.
I just wanted to tie in what you were saying to Schneider.
I think that's a natural question to ask, you know, in this whole chapter is why even talk about Schneider?
Why not just tell us what's normally going on in normal people?
And I think what might be up his sleeve is precisely this kind of philosophical scientific point where we want to get clear on these top-down explanations.
And when we look at Schneider, the mistake is not to see the holistic nature of what's going on with Schneider.
So it's a little bit about the same thing.
Because it was so perfect until then, I've been terrific.
It's not that we don't see the holistic thing going on with Schneider.
We don't see that Heidegger, that Schneider hasn't got the holistic thing going on.
Yeah, well, right, right.
And so we're not applying this holistic.
Yeah.
He has no horizons.
He has no significance.
He has no synergistic system for his body.
And you're absolutely right.
I think that's a terrific thing to say.
When we do Schneider, we're supposed to see what it would be like for us to be like a computer and do everything like an intellectualist.
He's a caricature of him.
Yes, he's a kind of caricature of cognitivism and intellectualism because he does have to figure out where his body is over the time.
He's not a complete caricature because he can swat a mosquito.
But when he's trying to figure out where...
That's how he's a caricature of empiricism.
Okay, good.
Yes, he has a reflex art.
And sometimes he's a caricature of intellectualism when he tries to find out where his hand is in objective space and his head is in objective space and then gets his hand in object.
That's like the hand-eye robot that was being built at MIT when I was there.
They never managed to make it work.
It couldn't have so many degrees of freedom that it needed to go through to find its objective hand and then bring it over in objective space to something else and so forth.
And Schneider is like that.
Schneider is like a kind of cognitivism.
Yeah.
And so it seems like perhaps part of introducing the Gelvin Goldstein Schneider's government is that the mistake is the fact that they think you can build up an understanding of a whole normal person from a distorted Schneider, which is a valid method.
Maybe.
Maybe you're going too far.
I mean, that would be interesting to do, but I think Merylopunty doesn't go that far.
Maybe he does.
He talks about the being in the world.
You know how Schneider just doesn't kind of.
That's right, but that's a slightly different point.
I think the point is to see what it would be like not to have holistic being in the world and how that would be like intellectualism.
And then we see that we've got something that Schneider hasn't got.
He doesn't, I think, try, although it'd be interesting to try, to see if you could, how you couldn't, how you could try to build up what we've got out of what Schneider's got and how you couldn't.
I think that's what Gelden Goldstein attempts to do and why they're so peculiarly it's not just they're they're wrong in a deep methodological scientific way so that's why we have a long discussion about scientific human reduction and and it's this new understanding of science that's equal is the new understanding of our beaming the behavioral dimension which he thinks is supported by Schneider so he that's right he thinks Schneider is actually the scientific support for this new dimension of being this third he or Gel Goldstein Merloponte and so Gel and Goldstein's mistake is that they don't quite recognize that let me try to put it back to you because we're so close to getting something important right because this doesn't sound right to me yet I mean what Gelden Goldstein think is and you sort of said this you should be able to put Schneider together in a way that was like us and so you just you put more abstract attitude in and or abstract movement and more movement and and you get it all together right Schneider could be would be like us but he's lost it and and Merlopony wants to say no no you can't put these pieces together to be like us but Schneider has lost cannot be understood in terms of the pieces okay we agree about that and that's right so and uh and Del Goldstein seems to think they've got the two elements namely that concrete motion and abstract motion out of which you could build a normal person if you put them together in the right way that somehow in Schneider they've fallen apart and this is just my way of trying to get clear on the question why in the heck I lost Schneider in the first place okay and the answer is because when you have and not this what we just said that's only part of it mostly it's typical of Merloponte you look at the dysfunctional breakdown cases to see something that we got which is absolutely crucial but is so transparent like water to the fish and so ungraspable in intellectualist terms that we wouldn't see it except to see what it looks like when some when Schneider hasn't got it.
That leads him to talk about what we have got.
That's the great lines go back on this because I want to I'll let me go on a little bit.
I skip a bit about horizons here, but I want to say because get his diagnosis of all this, the Ashtaltists understand that Schneider lacks something, that narrow Ponte has a better understanding, a more holistic understanding than they've got.
And they only get as far as our experience has horizons.
That the Gestaltists know.
Everything we do is done on a background of other things we're not doing.
And everything we do can become a figure, and then something else will be, everything in the background could be made into a figure, and then something else will be put in the background.
That's not big enough for what we need.
What we really want to think is that why does all our experience have horizons?
Because we're involved in coping, and that's called existence.
I want to run through all these quotings that my old kind has left.
And so you'll see how the argument goes and how it looks like an explanation, but it isn't, and it isn't supposed to be.
So there's this stuff on 140 about a deeper intentionality at the bottom, which we saw already.
That's called exhibit.
And that's what Neider lacks, the bottom of 140.
We read it last time, that there is it's concrete and abstract movement, but and then it looks like there's only in itself existence and for itself existence, but then in the footnote, there's a deeper intentionality, which others have called existence.
That's Heidegger.
And that's the third term in the next footnote between the psychic and the physiological.
And we're always led to that.
We call it existence.
Well, that gets us a little further.
We realize that existence is all tied up with the intentional arc, which normal subjects have.
Well, but he calls it the bottom of 152, sort of badly, a subject-object dialogue, a drawing together by the subject of the meanings of use through the object and so forth.
And he's talking about all that, and it's lacking in Schneider's taste.
But when he finally gets down to what he wants to call it, he calls it an intentional arc, remember?
Now, where is that?
I just missed 150.
I got the wrong market.
Oh, there it is.
I've got it.
It should be 150.
I mean, that's not the first, the only place, but that's the one we want right now.
The bottom of 150, he says, the world with its two stages of sedimentation and spontaneity is at the core of consciousness.
And it is in the light of the leveling down of the world, which is so sustained in this Schneider's problem.
What Schneider leveled down is the intentional arc.
I guess I said this in 20 different places in 20 different ways.
Well, 157.
Yeah, that's the main one, which we looked at last time, but it's very, very important.
What he calls the intentional arc is the way our experience is constantly feeding out into the world, remember.
So that it projects around itself about 10 lines down, the life of consciousness, cognitive life, perceptual life, and this intentional arc is always there.
But then he says it projects around itself, which is bad.
We don't want to say that, our past, our future, and so forth.
Or whether, and now he gets it right, it results in our being situated in all these respects.
It is the intentional art, that is, we don't project it around us, live just in it.
It's not a searchlight, remember, he says, that we have and we want to think is that we are in, always think of the feedback thing.
We're in a world which is already full of meaning, always already full of meaning.
We never get a meaningful hand.
But if we act in and then we enrich with more and more meaning, and then it shows up.
And so, or whether which results in our being situated in all these look better.
It is this intentional art which brings about the unity of the senses, of intelligence, of sensibility, and motility.
It's that which goes limp in Schneider.
Schneider hasn't got it.
Now, the next question is: and the intentional art is the same as being in the world.
That should be obvious, being already in the world.
And on 141, he says, I've been right there in two ways of relating to the object, two types of being in the world.
We've seen that a lot.
So now we've seen it's level on 150.
We've got the leveling down of the world.
It goes limp.
And now, why does it go limp in Schneider?
I just want to show you that there are a whole lot of sort of explaining questions that don't really explain anything.
But it turns out because it lacks the power to sustain it.
Or the middle of 155.
But patient's being, his power of existence, is what his illness is taking.
So existing turns out to be a kind of energy, as he calls it in the Phantom Limb chapter, an energy that you have to open up a world if you're healthy, and this power can go weak if you're ill, and then your world collapses.
The middle of 1506: future and past are shrunk in extension of the present.
He's lost our power of looking according to the temporal vector.
Well, now we've got this magical power hidden.
That doesn't really explain anything.
You just renamed the problem.
So, well, what is this power?
Well, it's a tendency toward basic COVID.
I mean, all of these things are just names for the same thing, I think.
They're not really explaining anything.
But I hope I've tried to convince you that you don't have anything to explain.
So I've done that one.
It's called, it's something, it's a momentum called existence, he calls it.
A momentum.
So you've got these energy, these dynamic terms.
It's an energy, it's a power, it's a momentum.
Existence is all at about five lines down in 159.
Now, here's an important point I'm still getting.
Insects already have this momentum of existence.
Remember, if you tie up one leg, they go struggling on to do things at another leg.
What do we have that insects don't have?
Well, we have the intentional arc.
What's the difference?
Insects just have a fixed world.
Our world is constantly enriched by what we learn.
That's very important.
In AI, that's the difference between the animats that they've now got at MIT that Rodney Brooks is making, which already would be said to have existence, maybe, that they don't learn.
Their world doesn't change.
And that's very important.
We've got that, and the higher animals have it.
But then the next question becomes: and why do we have it?
Well, it's because, and now you're beginning to sound familiar, although you're not really learning anything new, it's because we have a tendency to get a maximum grip on the world.
This is on 177.
And so let's look at that.
It's a very important paragraph.
Penlines from the bottom.
I'm going to read it fast.
Whether a system of motor or perceptual powers, our body is not an object or an IP.
It's a group of lived through means which move toward equilibrium.
And our natural powers come together in a richer media.
And then it's skipping a little.
So, and we re-shuffle these elements into an equilibrium.
Now, why am I making a fuss about that?
Because this talk about getting toward a maximum richness, getting more rich, getting equilibrium, all that finally is maximum grip talk.
So the whole thing bottoms out if you ask, well, why do we want to cope?
Well, we want to cope finally in order to get the richest grip, which gives us an equilibrium with the world.
And that's the bottom line.
Now, I can say quickly, because I said it early, and if you say that you haven't explained anything, Maryland, you've just gone from wider and wider things, from the horizon to existence, to being in the world, to coping with everything, to finally trying to get an optimal grip on everything, the biggest thing.
What does that explain?
How do we do that?
And I think the answer is supposed to be: there's nothing we can explain.
I mean, something is going on in the brain, and we get a world in which we can and do that.
And all we can know is to do is describe the world in which we can and do that.
What you don't want to do is give an account, that's the intellectualist story, of some mental operations which enable us to do it.
Because if you get the right feeling of the holistic bound story, then there couldn't be any mental operations that enable us to do it.
And that's where we can stop.
Okay.