I will comment the text or follow the way Moroboti develops his arguments.
And I'll try to show that it might have an this chapter might have an interest.
And I think for this the first sentence is very important, the one that I have uh you have it.
Yeah.
And this first sentence says, our constant aim is to elucidate the primary function whereby we bring into existence for ourselves or take a whole event, state the object or the instrument, and to describe the body as the place where this appropriation occurs.
So this we have to have in mind for the whole to understand the whole chapter, because the thing is globally stating, Miraboti's aim in the whole the whole first part of the book on the body is to show that as you put it somewhat metaphorically close to the time there's what we call the the current or the flow of existence that runs this means exist that runs through the body and what this means is that you wouldn't have to think of the body as being only say the regulated by biological functions or as being only the place where a sensory motor integrity could be at work.
The body encompasses all these different layers, including what Meropote calls explicitly in this chapter, sensual perception.
So the thing is this chapter is interesting.
The the third and I think the main reason why this chapter is important is that it helps us understand what Meropoti means by body, which could be a fuse.
The thing is, and it will turn out, and this is one of the big big issues that Meropotimus brings forward, there's one identical in some way, meaning for the term body that's similar throughout all these layers.
So the body is that which endorses all these dimensions of existence.
And the thing is, as Meloboti explains it in the preface, in a very important paragraph, the question is what is existence or how does it work?
And existence is the way that things come to exist for us.
So our existence is the way that we articulate, we organize, we give a form, similar expressions, to the world that's around us.
The existence of man or the human being, what is it?
It's made of what we call operative intentionality.
Yeah.
In yours, it's page twenty.
Operative intentionality described stands for the fact that when we have behaviors or conduct in the world, we organize it in such in such a way.
And thus, certain parts of the world come to have some meaning for us.
But what he states in the preface, and we need all this to what he says in the preface is that his own meaning of intentionality is proper.
Definition of the concept implies the body, which means that the intentionality is not enough, I think.
His intentionality is not to be conceived of as something that starts from representation that then are the cause or the motivations for a behavior.
What we experience when we're in the world is that we're being motivated by the world.
This is what it means when he says the disembodied subject is a part of the system of the world itself.
We're just articulating the world and all these he has.
What this means is that it's not as if meanings or representations were in the head motivating what we're doing, is that if you have this situation A that you experience as motivating a behavior that leads our conduct that gives this situation B.
So this is what, I mean, this is very important to have in mind since Miraboti positively says at the end of the second part, the last of the second part of the book is that everything relies on time and on the flow of time.
And so in the time science, it goes even as far as to say that the operative intentionality is that which we experience as relating or as motivating the passage of time itself.
So that by which our behavior has the unity of time.
So this is and the last part of this framework that you have to have in mind is that, as I just said, it's not as if the operative intentionality was starting from mental representations.
We can only act following the operative intentionality because we are embodied in the world.
We come back to the body.
This is the end of this sort of sketch of the body that I wanted to go.
So we cannot act in the world without the body, and the body is that by which we are being receptive to the stimulations that come from the world.
It means that without the body there could be no subject, because we couldn't be subjectively, intentionally behaving.
And on this, with this framework, with the help of it, we can understand, I think, why this chapter is interesting, because if you see what Melobotti states in the first, very first paragraph of BitCapter, the body and stateful being, Melobotti clearly says that the existence of something for me, the way I articulate the world, this very functioning sort of existence can be understood as well if we consider, and this is the last sentence, yeah, let us try to see how a thing or a being begins to exist for us through desire or love, and we shall thereby come to understand better how things and beings can exist in general.
It's the last sentence of the first paragraph.
But I mean that nobody's clearly integrating, replacing sexuality within the framework of operating that by which things come to exist for us.
And as we will see, this existing other things for us find operatives as being mediated by the body, as he says in the first sentence, direct.
This by the body as the place where this appropriation of only comes to have a meaning for me thanks to the body.
And this happens because the body is the perceiving subject.
So the meaning of perception and the meaning of the term perception and of the term body are clearly related.
And I also want to express the fact that in every dimension of existence, they are related.
This is why we will not get for the specificity of the sexual perception within the framework of the existence that encompasses all these dimensions.
And to do this, we start, as usual, you remember what Sean said when he gave his lecture on the thing.
To do this, he begins by stressing the fact that there are two positions that you wouldn't want to follow because they don't respect this embodiment framework.
And as usual, these positions are the accuracy.
And even the end with the first one and the paragraphs are very long in this chapter, particularly long.
But the first one and a half page, just following the very short first paragraph, deals with these two positions and how they're wrong, using, once again, Schneider, quotation from Georg and Dolstein.
Very briefly stated because I don't want to spend too much time on this because it's how I want to describe the imperialist and Schneider's case, but what we should be more interested in are his conclusions.
The thing is, in sense, you can't conceive of what we would come to call the erotic life as being only related to anatomical or organic processing, which would be the empiricist account.
Everything that happens in sexual life would be more or less elaborated reflexive.
That this part of the body reacts because of this or this stimulation.
This would be the empiricist account.
And the intellectualist or mentalist account of this would be that there's the experience of pleasure, but there's nothing to be said about it until it becomes shut through.
It's the second sentence of the second paragraph.
Shut through with intelligence.
That it would mean that to be the mind that would have to give a content to the experiences of pleasure and pain, mostly pleasure, hopefully, and hence that it would mean that there are no specific sexual stimulations.
Of course, presented this way, it can seem to be observed, but that the positions between which he wants to have his own, the third way, the way of existence.
So, this intellectual position position is, well, he's saying about force identences from the beginning.
Apart from the experience of pleasure and pain, of which there's nothing to be said, the subject stands out by his power of representation and affectivity is not recognized as a distinctive form of consciousness.
I think that if one conceives of affective life that is behaving in as having its meaning only thanks to the work of the intellect, then you can't say that sexual behaviors are in themselves or correspond to a certain dimension or as Malaposa puts it original dimension of life.
Even better maybe.
Okay, so obviously this way, this way of dealing with perception, sexual perception, that is sexual behavior, will satisfy Malawi because he wants to stress, on the contrary, that affective life is some original mode of consciousness.
Well that's a very good example of a sentence that one would have to understand the right way.
It doesn't mean that the consciousness is constituting in an intellectual way the sexual life, otherwise you would be having the intellectualist account for it.
Human consciousness means that that's the way we consciously live, experience sexuality.
But it doesn't mean that we have to have representations.
So then he goes on in describing what happens to Schneider, which I won't I won't develop very well.
But the thing is, because it's stressing the fact that these two approaches are incomplete, what I'm interested in is the conclusion.
So it the sentence that begins with with cosmology brings to light.
So for you, it would be 180, I think.
182.
180 in the sort of regular.
I don't see why it is.
Okay, guys.
Yeah.
When it says pathology, and this is how he just kind of puts forward his approach of it, giving a solution of this dialectical dilemma.
Pathology brings to light somewhere between automatic response and representation.
A vital zone in which the sexual possibilities of the patient are elaborated in the same way as we saw above, as are his motor, perceptual, and even intellectual possibilities.
There must be, immunating sexual life, some function which ensures its emergence that the normal extension of sexuality must rest on internal powers of the organism.
There must be an eros or a little which breathes life into an original world, gives sexual value or meaning to external stimuli and outlines for each subject the use he shall make of his object.
But gives that, as Maroboni may clearly say it a few lines after, that sexuality as being an original dimension of life is as such related to what Melobomsky calls the intentional arc.
He says it at the very end of this huge paragraph, the last sentence, we discover both that sexual life is one more form of original intentionality and also brings to the view to view vital origins of perception, motility and representation by basing all these processes on an intentional arc, which gives way in the patient, and which it means it's not working for Schneider, and which in the normal subject and those experienced with its degree of vitality and freedom.
So what Mercosur wants to express two things at the same time in this in this paragraph, is that you have to consider sexuality as being one of the dimensions, but nevertheless as being original.
Even though you have to relate it to this flow or current of experience is to relate it to what Melbourne said, that the sentence that I read previously when he says that you have to consider that activity as an original mode of consciousness.
So well, concretely, what would it mean?
It would mean that when you're say, to use to use what he says about Schneider, when you're facing a woman and when you're Schneider, so when you have heterosexual orientations, then it would you could suppose that Schneider should be experiencing immediately a certain type of stimulation that would prescribe, or that he would feel prescribing him, describing him, some sort of behavior.
And this immediately, the fact that it should be obvious that this kind of sexual behavior is called for by the situation.
This this would be the original thing.
It would mean that in certain types of situations, the the sexual dimension of life is experienced as being the only way you could live in certain.
You don't even think about what you're going to do.
It calls for what what what certain powers or or certain attitudes of the subject.
So it would have to elaborate it.
So or visual means medium and basic?
Yeah.
Are there other original?
Yeah of original.
Yeah, well, how the other examples?
Yeah, all those, yeah, that's right.
What the biological, the perceptual, sensory motor perception, for example.
And that's it?
Or there one?
Are there three originals and then?
Are they not original?
Well, actually, no, it isn't.
Because if you if you if you see what he's I I think the thing is he the the formulations he gives of the intention this is limited to how many dimensions the intentional arc has.
Basically you can see that the formulation he gives of them slightly changed.
But I think you see here it's uh at the very beginning of the third paragraph he talks about the whole active and cognitive being as being two other sectors of life along with say sexual.
So I think that the original dimensions are the ones that that go along with the intentional arc.
For instance, just to try and get clearer, why you do things moving?
Is it the same central kind of a thing?
Like is moving original something or other that Mirabel Hunting wouldn't just isn't talking about or or it is not what disqualifies it.
Well I I I think it it would be disqualified uh as a as a sort of original well.
In a way, I mean he doesn't he he doesn't and I think this is one of the reasons why he's been criticized so much by analytical philosophy is that he he doesn't systematize everything he says sort of so he would he's not making lists on the time, right?
But so I would say maybe no because well at first sight, so to speak, maybe not because uh it's not uh in mood it's not as obvious as in say sexual perception or uh sensory motor regular perception that the body comes in the first place.
So so the um the the metaphor in Mike is is that oh I have it, I have it for you one is that these um is a copy, the sensor copy is itself the source of movement.
Yeah, source of the origin of those things.
What's the origin for regional or originary?
Yes, that's correct, yes.
But I I I wanted to say originary, but he doesn't say it.
But well anyway original and originary have the same meaning for him.
It means both all the time.
I think um we need to make a distinction between this sort of but uh it's adversarial is a behavior.
So that's to make a distinction.
It's the same.
Okay.
You act when you perceive intelligible.
Um you did say the bodies first.
So um he said that we've been talking about pre-personal existence and like non-discrimination and everything.
And so I think there is like the basic level that's like references saying the course, but then through action we in Domino would write new arguman significance and what we can just even give our personal existence, like the sensor conspiracysteria and like individual actuality, but um that's all based on our bodily functions, which are so um then more path no no no no no no you require meaning well like it's it's I mean it's not really an important distinction but it's not the way information it's so let me please okay go ahead I mean I don't know because this is what he has to ask you he talks about later he said um I can close my eyes by down this is the blood culture and repeat okay but why does he say that?
Because he has to know.
This is what we've all been like arguing.
Yes, but it has a precise meaning in this chapter.
So you have to understand.
But I don't know the issue.
The thing is otherwise you just you just end up picking parts from here and there and you don't understand why he talks about this or why he mentioned it at this very moment.
And the thing is that it's uh as Berkele put it once, the book itself is a biggest out because you can you can it's like Screen Loza's ethics.
You can find connections between all the chapters.
So we're not going to tell each one of these patterns individually so but I'm not sure everyone understood what you meant.
Well I know I hope so.
Certainly.
It's connected but I will come back to this later.
So yes the the original dimensions of existence are the ways are I mean basically they correspond to the different types of meaning that you but meaning.
And I met with this qualifying moment.
So because meaning is the way you interact with the world, right?
It's not it the world is the way you're opening up the world, but it's not a way of giving and it yeah, because well it's not embodied.
And it doesn't seem to well it does seem to be embodied.
I I'm not sure.
Yeah, because because uh in the second part, for example, that of course the world the world appears different to you when you depress yeah in a way that but maybe means something different because I think that maybe I don't also say that and maybe he says this somewhere that I don't have in mind yet, but maybe you would s he would say that the being depressed is a sort of is should rather be conceived of as a sort of withdrawal from the world.
You're not that present to the world anymore.
Let me try something which would be interesting.
It's too global.
That always takes some situation for some particular object or person to give meaning to.
You think just everything at any time.
Even the sexual, which is a whole dimensional whole atmosphere, he says, doesn't make everything sexual, not the trees, for instance.
But when you depress, everything is depressed.
Yeah, yeah.
So yeah, this this withdrawal from the world goes goes along with a sort of confusion or yeah, yeah, that's the right thing.
Yeah.
I know he was involved.
Let me just say this quick on faster.
But you would think that there's no such thing as sort of a mood neutral for that very reason it seems to be a different sort of candidate than the ones on these lists, which are not only in the background, but always pick out something or other in the foreground as what's particularly significant or meaningful.
That's right, but on the same hand, the whole end of the chapter deals with what neuropathy calls ambiguity.
So it's the fact that all these dimensions are always present together, but there's one that's being put forward.
Go ahead.
No, it's deeply related to what we're discussing.
Yeah, but yeah, but it wasn't a different problem than the one I was talking about, which is the in a movie.
Yeah, that's right.
Whatever.
These things, I think it's getting clearer.
These original something or others are original forms of intentionality.
I mean, they're directed at something specific and under some aspect in a way that you're specific.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
So, yes, and this particular way of experiencing meanings that you experience are in the world and that your experience calls for some particular action is, for example, described in a very concrete way by Nerval C.
So, this would be for you something just a few lines after what I've been reading.
In the case of the normal subject, in the case of the normal subject, the body is not perceived really as any object.
This, and I come to the question that I have, this objective perception has within it a more intimate perception.
The physical body is suspended by sexual schema, which is strictly individual, emphasizing the emerging areas, outlining the sexual figuratively, and eliciting the gestures of the masculine body, which is itself integrated into this emotional totality.
Those are all with your question.
Because you have these different dimensions of body interact interaction with the world.
But obviously, if you can't even perceive the things, you can perceive your measure the woman that's in front of you.
So it means that obviously there's a basic level that, well, we've been discussing this in the discussion groups, so that's partly where the question that's been raised came from.
So of course there's a basic level that calls pre-personal that he mostly deals within the theme chapter.
I won't give all the references all the time because otherwise I'll just be so but I can send and this level in is the this is the purely sensory motor pre-personal meaning doesn't have yet any human significance.
At this very level, it's at this very level you wouldn't or there would be no difference between say the a sexual a potential sexual partner and a chair, for example.
So that's which means it's it's fairly an abstracted level.
So this means that as well this level is the first, because you need to perceive and I mean what why does he talk about this mostly in the theme chapter?
It's because it corresponds and as well also in the chapter of the sensory experience, the first of the second part, because it corresponds to the to the to the qualia of the traditions, but sense sense second or very qualities, that's colors and brightness of sound and our colour, and the perceptual consensus.
So, this pre-personal level is concerned with medium.
It's it's a certain basic user device that's the minimal one, and it's the condition of the object.
And actually, it's of course he just doesn't want to discuss this because he discussed the biological level, because to him, and I won't go into this very discussion for example, but to him, the biological level alone cannot characterize perception.
In perception, in human perception, I have to give, but in human perception, even the per-personal level already has one fundamental dimension.
It's that when you perceive something, and even just as having this or that shape, and this or that color and brightness, to describe the thing you're perceiving, you would have to relate it to all of the context, to the whole context that surrounds it.
So, it would mean that you always perceive things as being in the world, precisely, with this lighting and everything.
So, now I go back to what towards everything Sean has been discussing.
So, there's this global dimension.
It means that you can perceive the thing from themselves, apart from your biological needs.
This was just to say that the very first level of human, the pure tends to perception, and not the biological, because it could be too much laid in by the needs.
And we as humans can separate ourselves from our needs and just look at what's around us.
So, that's basically what he means.
And that's why it's the perceptual level, that's the first level of human experience.
But it's pre-personal.
It means that when you're during your life, you're not always experiencing explicitly human or person, sorry, you're not experiencing always personal, that would be erotic, for example, dimensions of the way.
You can be concentrating on this language.
But still, I'm not discussing this more now because it's a completely different issue, but you have to know that he puts forward this pre-personal level.
And it's very important to you because what he just said is that the visible body is suspended by a sexual schema, which is pretty individual.
So it means that, and also here he says that this visible body is suspended.
So you might want to think of the erotic dimension as being under in some way, as being under, say, the purely perceptual sensory motor qualities of the things.
Well, actually, considering this visory schema, this personal dimension, you'd rather say, and this corresponds to what I will say in the rest of the book, that this erotic dimension supervenes on top of I'm still confused as to the distinction between pre-personal and a personal level.
I assume that you also get a personal level.
Yeah, of course.
What what is the personal level?
What makes the personal level personal and brings it out of the pre-p well it's okay, so how well the thing is okay th if if we discuss this we have to enter a new business but but then the thing is that um you can never experience the pre-personal level alone.
You can concentrate on the perception that you can have.
You remember what how the new one was when when John was discussing this, but well basically the thing is you can concentrate, so you can sort of you can abstract from the the human features of the situation, that looks that would say the practical features of the situation, and you can uh you can just concentrate on this level, the level of the student equalities and the perceptual consensus.
And this would be the the pre-personal level.
So the the things have no human meaning for you, basically.
They're not like tools.
It's without human sense, but it has a sense because what sense you ultimately needs for neural concept is the fact it's it's the dependence of the part between themselves.
The fact that they depend on the whole.
And there's and that's why I discussed well very badly, I agree with that, but that's why I mentioned the the dependence of say one and the equality to all the others, it's precisely because they depend on each other.
The color that you see depends on the lighting and everything.
So there's there's a the there's a pre-personal meaning or sense.
And these big complications with that kind of holism for the works for the animals too.
The the the lighting level, presumably they also have yeah well so you wanted to have again to to have the discussion that we had again.
I still believe animals have the equipment in totality is of course human, but with chairs and stuff.
But are you saying is Merloponcy saying according to you that animals are just zapped into some kind of affordances which don't have any global they can concentrate on them.
The dimension that always comes forward in their well and actually I and he says in the lectures on nature actually that you would have to well he doesn't that he's not primarily an ecologist so he will assert that but still that you might want to include the low developed monkeys to this to the to the sort of maybe to the human level but the thing is that yeah he says remember the text we've been discussing at the end of the first chapter of the first part he says that the animals are always in a particular world so they're they're absolutely they're drawn towards this world by immediate immediately biological concerns and that we humans can uh just sort of reflect on this uh pre-personal level and concentrate on it and that's what we say the based on the first sorry isn't it associated the pre-infusion with the secondary quality consultancy level um accountable ways of thinking more yeah well sensory qualities bel belong to the natural world from local but it's not but there's also this primary quality right yeah that corresponds to the perceptual consistency that i mentioned.
So I don't understand what the the the the what the well but what?
Um so the idea that that the pre-imparsonal level gives us is a secondary position or something like that.
You know secondary of theory that would be yeah.
Well it seems a thing like gives us primary policies as well.
Yeah, like the constancy.
Um what uh what's distinctive in what's distinctive in the pre-personal level about secondary modeling, how distinctive?
I couldn't answer.
I think we probably got something different by secondary, right?
Yes, I said well I said that this is what the philosophical tradition has called secondary qualities.
So it's not the shapes saying of the objects but their colors and everything so that that all the and the bright the the color and the brightness and uh what's related to the fact that we have the I called it this way because Meropovi separates them.
He talks about these secondary policies in the chapter on it's in your translation it's probably sensory experience, the first experience.
Sense experience, the first the second part.
And then you have the perceptual constancy that your screen and the short find the same.
So this is what what I would relate it to, but I think I need to add somewhere now.
But I just said the opposite for that it was including perceptual constancies and the shapes and the weight of the of the objects and size and all and those.
Yeah, yeah, the constancy.
I can hear you.
More brightness.
So the three personal level, the basic value.
Not all the significance between because precisely there's a significance that's purely sensory motor and perceptual.
That's the way things depend on each other.
When you perceive their shape and colors and everything.
Right, okay, yeah, because you see we can never provide those in the pre-versimal abstract from your your practical concerns and concentrate on this very pre-personal level.
This is a task you're doing.
So when you're copying and inflow and everything, you're never experiencing this this level alone.
Because what what the what motivates your action is so think of the personal level.
That's the task you're accomplishing.
Yes.
Otherwise you'll just yeah, otherwise you'll be bumping in the tables when you want to to do something else.
This wouldn't be taking into account the perceptual consensus and everything.
No, no, no, but other people have been having friends I think.
So but now I have to go for that.
Sound people.
The other people are in line.
So you have to wait now.
I guess I just wanted to clarify, hearing what you said about pre-personal fear in relation to these other categories, why original or originary?
Because you you can have a genuine experience, immediate genuine experience of a situation that's directly that which uh of a situation uh in which the dimension that's the most pregnant in it is the sexual.
But based on what you said, um that's only possible because of the sort of better perceptual levels, right?
That's what the pre-personality.
That's what gives everything.
It's that which human or personal significance relies on.
It's not the same.
Because if you say this, in some way, you would end up saying that the sexual perception is not original or original in some way.
So that's what Maraboti wants to stress by saying this.
He wouldn't deny that if you meet your girlfriend, whatever, you're not, it's not a backbone part of your experience, the fact that, well, she has a body and this body as being also physical and not only an analytical object, has dimensions that might not change suddenly.
So, but I mean, it's very what you have to have in mind is what he wants to stress at that very moment.
And the thing is that there has to be a way to account for the specificity of the sexual experience, even though it draws on the situation.
Okay, so that's what, because well, you have to know that I won't give you the cause, because precisely what Marbotti says is that you won't want to think of it in terms of causes.
You won't describe what's happening without presupposing the fact that there are causes located here and there.
You know, it's the it's the thing that causes are located to the it's a dinner uh yeah in the first sentence of the second IRF he says he opposes and this is not a big topic in the history of philosophy that I won't have time to get into, but he opposes explanation and understanding.
And explanation is when you give causes for events, and understanding is something else, which can be intellectualist, purely conceptual, and so, or different from that.
And the account that he's proposing is a different kind of understanding from what's happening.
So he says that you can't give the cause of what's happening because you would just have to say, well, he's been wounded here in his brain and stuff I'm not competing for.
But this is what he says.
Everything Snyder has comes from a wound that's in the occipital novel sphere.
I don't know.
No, no, but the thing is, so well he look precisely what Don Bonzi wants to say is that the best way to account for it for the difference between Snyder and us is the fact that he lacks this very sexual perception or the sexual intentionality, precisely, because he can't, he says he can't, because, I mean, think of the task of grasping something, the task comes to fulfillment when you grasp the graph.
And the thing is, he says that for Schneider, the intentionality is not fulfilled because he doesn't come to satisfaction.
So what he does when he's with a woman, what he says in the same paragraph is that you can't describe his behavior as something that's, or his conduct, as something that seems to be unified by the perspective of satisfaction.
So this is so and this this the this lack of meaning, sexual meaning in his behavior is that by which that that which that what uh is watched, right?
Uh to say that he lacks this very level.
That's that so his aim is to to give to to to to wonder whether you can separate these layers so so they're useful to to state they're useful to to understand what he lacks in uh in an existential in this situation would you say that Schneider then is only operating at the personal level, he never you don't belong to the personal level inside well we talked about problems of the creepers somewhere yeah because you can barely see actually yeah yeah so it's uneasy to want to put part what you were saying um in relation to original intentionality so specifically I think in answer to the question which you you said in your own words like on the top of one eighty one that Schneider was a patient but has disappeared from the patient is his power of projecting before himself the sexual world yeah and so yeah this is what I was heading towards before there was a forest of hands raising yeah so so there's in the parallel of his argument here in the sexual dimension to the intellectual dimension and then I guess the biological and the perceptual dimension and it's it's precisely this very peculiar problem of Schneider that he can't well project himself into a situation he can't imagine you know he's not open to all the other possible situations that we're open to.
In a way you could say that he he has his capacity to organize the world and to give meaning to it is just unbent, whereas our intentional art is is more bent.
So that basically means that his behavior has less dynamic dynamism into it.
And so that, you know, he says in the in the chapter when he discusses Schneider's case, the third in the first part, he says that on motility, he says that when you say it's thick or ill, I don't know what his his impairment or disability ends up as disorganizing his experience.
So it would mean that the world is not as articulated for him as for us, but also that the dimensions themselves come to be blurred in some way.
Yeah, well he says there's a structural difference, so he even says that on one line.
The structure is is the world as being articulated and the fact that this articulation has different layers.
So since it's the the power that he lost, so specifically the power of rejection.
So that's the case then seems to account for the fact that he can't learn things, I guess.
I mean, I'm I'm kind of wondering if if Schneider could learn things in a way that when you learn a skill, that kind of more significant system comes out.
So it seems like he's stuck with what he's already learned.
And so he can or he he still has the kind of motor intentionality like making the wallet.
Because he's not learning to make a wallet.
He's already got it.
I think you would have to consider I think you would have to consider operative intentionality as primarily a learning process.
Well, I wouldn't consider it as primarily a learning process, but a necessary condition for being gave a bit of clients.
Yeah, but it's not the same.
So I mean you you could use it to characterize the the the maybe the the learning impairment that he has, but you wouldn't you wouldn't want to start from the learning possibilities that he may have to characterize the protein that was only I was trying to make sense of the fact that you can so make wallets yeah but but it could probably be by following uh instructions that that that are not oriented toward the production as a wallet but this isn't transactual so this is in consequence wouldn't that better word in impersonal language oh maybe that's pre-personal but but the thing is no no well what do you say impersonal?
Well I don't think so because I if you say impersonal I'm having two lectures actually because I hope we can do paragraphs and there's dates and it has to be important.
No no no I have sorry I have to think.
No, you have to say pre-personal because the thing is and this helps me maybe clarify or maybe blurring for the people that I've lost already I have not is that he talks at least three times he talks about living men, living human beings as being he says knowing organisms and this he goes he deals with this also in the lectures on nature in the very pulse.
When he says that that the peculiarity of the human animal is that he has logos so this capacity to articulate the meanings of the world and to concentrate to focus say on the even people.
But why is it important that it's a pre-personal?
Because because of the things.
It's well first of all it's the condition you have to I mean what you says is that you're always always doing so you you're always in your experience drawn by some human motivations.
He's being very clear about this.
And this is why he says for example with in the chat on the thing when he talks about the picture that you come to have the best vantage point on and blah blah blah.
Well you're in the museum and the task you're performing is that you want to have the best vantage point on the picture.
So even when you concentrate on purely sensory motor, you're doing something.
It's it's a very peculiar way of having a task.
Why is that?
It's because you want to you you're in the in the attitude of knowledge.
You want to have the knowledge of how it works for an unbodied subject to perceive something.
So you're performing a specific knowing or efficiency, whatever, capricorn.
Second, it's that and this task relies on the fact that we humans can try to spell out as painters and the earlier between phenomenology and painting, we can try to spell out the world as it is in a purely natural way.
But this purely natural way is only natural to us.
The way it's being articulated only has an influence because we have this body that's and we have five senses and blah blah blah.
So the thing is that even this very pre-personal dimension is I mean you can only have access to it when you're performing a personal task.
And it's the condition of our having an experience that's always laden with personal uh motivations.
I think you misunderstand the the the pause of my present.
The way to terrify pre-personal was with respect to a level of abstraction of the object to which we are directing.
So you're not you're not looking at the fact that that's money, you're just looking at straight things colored.
You're not thinking about that as money.
You're abstracting away from the things that are in there by the impersonally existing.
Yeah, well if you if this is a way to that's what I was putting impersonal maybe I carried it for one week and simply should have tells me where you're putting.
Yeah, like well, that's important.
Yeah, sure.
Yeah, the thing is that I think you want to stress the fact that you can't say the fact that we even seven experiences of the world in general, that you can just we can just focus on the purely perceptual dimensions of our experience and by animals, because we're not going to be thrown by these.
But the problem about the creed is that the death that's the death based on the temporality.
So if you think that this is one of our genes discussions, you don't really see the left-handed greenness, and then you impose the knowledge that it's money.
Or the ball has a sexual object.
So I was trying to find words.
No, no, I couldn't.
Five words, maybe I'm just going to ask you this.
The reason I think that pre-personal is probably better than impersonal is it sounds like a necessary condition uh for the rest of the levels because you have to have a pre-personal level.
Impersonal sounds logically separate.
Yeah, thanks.
Yeah, I have to read the inside.
Yeah.
I think this is an undergraduate class.
Are you the other graduate?
Well, no, but like I mean one of them between other undergraduates both once, and you spoke one.
Yeah, I was going to say the same thing in general.
The impersonal, I think, Alva, is you just deal with people in an impersonal way, like in a bank or something.
That's in the personal dimension and in brackets.
And this is supposed to be foundational.
It's supposed to be something that happens before the personal and the universal get into the act, which is the smaller change saying is about well, but then to be less.
Okay, so this this big pre-personal discussion anyway, I think it, well, what we started with was the fact that even though there was this necessary condition being the pre-personal level of the perception of the body as a thing, then sexual perception is a necessary condition, is this pre-personal level, but still it's an original form of experience in itself.
So this is the thing that's being the most important in the second term.
So I will try tweaking the third one before it stops, but I'm pretty late.
So the thing is now, even though this very the dimension of say, if you have better words for this, I don't I will call the level of perception purely sensitive motor perception, the level of pure perception.
Big will you and me and it is very important, this level of perception of natural features of the things.
Okay, this is the condition, but then there's a level of sexual perception.
And the thing is that now it becomes a bit more tricky because what they want to say is that within within the different personal dimensions, not at this level of the perception of the faith and everything, but so, in at the very level of the personal thing that we do, that's the knowing and the acting, beginning of the third paragraph.
It's in the first step.
The knowing and the active and sexuality.
The beginning of the third paragraph, he says, he says that sexuality is not an autonomous cycle, it has internal links through the whole active and cognitive being.
These three sectors of behavior displaying but a single typical structure and standing in a relationship to each other as reciprocal expression.
And so, this is well, I'll give another lecture because to explain the chapter for itself, sort of we deal with this and especially the fact that the precursor level is a condition of personal life, but then within personal life, that's that I've read.
Very important because this is what Maropot is going to be discussing until the end of the chapter.
It's that the existence at a personal level since it always implies all the personal has one structure that you can find in them.
So, there's, and this is this is why he's starting global relationship between them.
That's because obviously he wants to discuss the attacks that have been made against psychoanalysis, which is the name, it's the main strategic, one of the main strategic purposes that he has in this chapter.
This is the fact, the very well-known fact that psychoanalysis has been reproached with reducing human life in general to what you do in bed.
Right?
Actually, what he wants able to discuss is the fact that it, well, first of all, you have to understand what sexuality is and how it can be related to existence in general, and the fact that stating that you cannot separate sexuality from the rest of personal behavior doesn't mean that you can reduce personal existence to sexual behaviors.
Why?
Because this would mean that when you're trying to understand the mathematical, you're not having the genuine experience of the original experience of trying to solve it.
This is unauthentic, you might want to say, which would mean that this is a...
Well, I can't say secondary now, so I have to find something else, but anyway, that this isn't an original dimension of experience.
And so this is the point that Normuti will be trying to make and to discuss in the rest of the chapter, is that this very peculiar relation between all the dimensions of personal, purely personal life, the human life that supervenes on top of the physical properties.
And what's the relation between what you do in life in general, how you behave with people?
Maybe more easily related to the very sexual context.
So the thing is, what he will now try to find, what he will now try to say, is that he will try to explain how there can be and what would be the fact that there's only what he calls one existential structure.
That is, there's one, the personal life, and it's at the personal level that you can make differences between the existences of different human beings, you know, their temper, everything.
They all reflect, they're all parts of one existential structure that expresses itself all the dimensions of the but stating and stating that sexuality I believe this because that's the that's what I will discuss first I it's the fact that saying this and saying that you cannot that sexuality is an irreducible dimension as personal life doesn't mean that you have to reduce the others the other dimensions to say the only questions no but I understand very important sense about the single typical structure you can it's a single existential structure yeah because I I'm happy that he gets a problem yeah well yes yes because well actually he says he says that there's only one existential attitude and then and what and what does it mean I mean this is a two-part question okay suppose it is a single existential structure which I'm sure is what we really say what is this thing not to be mysterious I would say it's movement for an absolute gray but if that isn't what it is then I want to know what what it is well the the thing is it allows for well that's that's the that's what the rest of the chapter is explaining but I have to wait okay good um I'm trying to to to get a very short answer to your question, if possible no okay well we'll have to answer these with how we know that okay so now so this is the this is what we're heading towards now.
So it's very important to have in mind even this first sentence, does sexuality is not an autonomous cycle?
Because this is this is what we'll be discussing all along.
So but and well, to begin answering your question, but the thing is that what uh you see when he quotes Freud uh there's there's a word in italics italics, I don't know.
For you it could it could be page one hundred eighty three just just after uh the sentence of the sexuality not being an autonomous cycle.
In fact that in this I'll go faster on this on this paragraph.
Well he says just before this exotic consciousness whatever the theoretical declarations of Freud may have during psychoanalytical research is in fact led to an explanation of man, but in terms of his sexual substructure as if this would be the primary layer and you have to have this this substructure in mind because at the very end of the chapter he he discusses in in a very long footnote he discusses the the sort of bad understanding that you would have uh of psychoanalysis and he compares it with with what Marx said.
So have this substructural approach in mind as something he wants to criticize.
So it's a discovery in sexuality of relations and attitudes which have previously been held to reside in consciousness.
So, this what what does it mean?
It means that it's it's a way to stress uh his commitment to the third way or to the way of existence.
It's that the relations between these three do not come because there's a single subject, single mental intellectual subject that would be the identical subject in these dimensions.
There's something else or the common existential structure that they have doesn't simply come from the fact that there's a single consciousness experiencing these dimensions.
There's something more, not very surprisingly, I would say, is the fact that the subject that experiences all these personal dimensions is an environment.
So, the thing is, the way of existence will help us understand why is crucial to understand the fact that there is one existential structure common to all the personal dimensions.
So, that's what I was also having towards when I said that one of the aims of the chapter is to understand what male body means by body.
The fact that there's in it there's a very basic identical meaning present throughout the book, hopefully because that's what he's trying to stress, the fact that perception is embodied interaction.
So, what I'll be trying to explain next time is how the body plays a role in defining the exist the existence of all the dimensions of life, including sexuality.
Because you might want to think that you might you might want to stick to this, say, reductionist uh sub-structural view, relating to which sexuality is the is the bottom of the rest of life, meaning that the rest of life should be reduced to sexuality because when you're say researching on your mass awards you'd be more detached from your body than you are when you're in bed with someone but this is not true from the rule there's an there's an identical meaning of the body that's present in this experience because the attitude the general existential attitude that you have can only be understood thanks to the way you behave in say and by the it's it's only you want to say something more can I say okay I'll say like a problem for next time because I I disagree completely with your reading and this single typical structure it doesn't say existential structure but I wish it did but the single tendical structure isn't maximum clear I take that that it's something sexual I mean the sense films and the sexuality isn't an anonymous cycle it's something like the single typical structure in all of these things the single typical I think it's now what it doesn't say single to be a sexual structure no but it doesn't say existential structure and in the context talk about context I mean it's in the scope of talking about sexuality would you might want to say that there's something typical of thinking of acting of all these things which is their sexual dimension and that's what we're going to talk about that's what it looks like it says now that doesn't make me either because it's a sexuality is not an economist cycle and then he said internally with the whole active and cognitive being and then he said these three factors there's only mention two and the cognitive so the first must be sexual are guided by uh the three players.
This is why he says this is what we stop on.
This is why he says that there's a common existential attitude to all these dimensions.
I would recall sexuality.
No, no, no, no.
There's something deeper than what than only sexual conduct.
It means that you can't only refer to sexual conduct to understand what people are doing in life in general.
There's something that's the common dimensions of all.
Yes.
Okay.
And my only question is if the depends on the mentality of people.
It turns out it sounds very anti-structured.
Okay.