I to go back and talk more about attention.
It was too easy, I thought, that how clear I was and how quickly I got through the part on attention, and then I realized that I had sort of misread a whole chunk of it.
Not that I'm taking back anything, but there's a piece of it that I just didn't put in.
The easy part, just to remind you where we are, was to say that the intellectualist uses the idea of attention in this double way, uses attention to break down the result.
Remember from Erloponte, always the whole determines what counts as the part, but you can, by focusing attention on the parts, make them come out of the hole and then see the line for the molar layer illusion is equal, or the moons or two as the same size on the horizon as in between it.
So you could use attention to take apart the whole and find elements, which more or less I suspect correspond to what's on your retina.
Where did they come from?
They're not elements that were implicit in the whole.
He's very clear about that.
The whole determines the parts, but when you break down the whole, there is something.
Well, I presume that's where the constancy hypothesis may be right, that if you take an analytic enough attitude, like a painter or an introspectionist, you can actually see something that roughly corresponds to what you're getting on your sense organs.
That's certainly a misleading and wrong-headed way of using attention, unless you're a painter.
And it has a further, it wouldn't be misleading just like that, because there's nothing wrong with breaking down your perception and finding these elements.
The second half is the brainer that makes it evil, and that is that you think of attention as a searchlight, that is not being, as he calls it, being neutral, not adding or taking away anything.
And if you it's just like noticing.
When I notice something, I don't do anything to what I've noticed, at least not in a normal sort of noticing.
But this kind of attention, this special kind of isolating analytic attention, is not neutral.
It's not like a searchlight.
It doesn't reveal what was already there.
Just in saying that, it produces something new, namely what these elements would look like if they didn't get their whole meaning in the song.
So you break down the Moller-Liar illusion and get two equal lines.
But in your normal perception, you see them as unequal.
And it takes a lot of effort.
I don't think we could do it.
I think you probably have to be a painter or an imperfectionist to get the ends of the Moller-Liar illusion.
You know what I'm talking about.
Try to see, of course, I'm not going to draw it fair enough to make it count.
But I mean, try to see those ends gone and the lines are equal.
Maybe they are, maybe they aren't.
Probably they aren't.
I'm not trying to convince you.
Anyway, so it's when you think that attention reveals what was there all along, that you make the experience error, you take it that what you're seeing is what's there in the determinate world, or you make the sensory core error, the same error, just described with different motivations.
The sensory core error, you think that what you've got when you've done this analytic kind of reflecting is what was there all along.
And then, of course, you ask yourself the question: well, how does experience build up?
How are the elements, which are what you really see, and the experience of objects which seem to be holes with determining their parts and so forth.
Well, then you give an associationist story if you're an empiricist, or you give an intellectual story, which we haven't gotten to, we were just getting there, if you are intellectualist.
But now I realize that there's another thing going on.
So let me just start with a quote that I just mentioned.
So on 32, he's telling you that all the ways that you can make a perception break down.
And then he says, I just want to remind you that Merrill-Ponte often isn't saying what he thinks.
He says on about five lines down on 32, inattentive perception contains nothing more, and indeed nothing other than the attentive kind.
That's not his view.
That's the neutral searchlight view of attention.
That says that when, well, and it's putting them in the language of the uh intellectualist, the intellectualist thinks that attentive perception, focusing on deconceptual, decontextualizing and focusing on the elements, is real attention.
And our ordinary way of being in the world and paying attention to things isn't real attention.
That's inattentive attention.
So inattentive attention is what we've got when we focus on something and bring out the details of it.
We talked about that last time.
When you you focus on the some aspect and make it more of a figure and put something that you were paying attention to into the background.
That's ordinary attention.
That's inattentive attention from the point of view of the intellectualist who thinks attentive attention is isolating the element from Gustav and also thinks inattentive perception contains nothing more and nothing other than the attentive kind, meaning that the everyday kind of attention, which they think of as not real attention, is only what real attention, that is analytic attention, reveals.
But that's a weird sense.
I thought I would just try to make sense of it for you.
It's saying the same thing I said.
He's got so many different words of talking about attention in his own words and in the words of the other.
Yeah, okay, one more time.
But there's everyday attention.
That's not what he's talking about.
There is but everyday attention is called by the sensually poor people, the analytic people, the intellectually, inattentive attention.
Because the everyday attention isn't paying attention to what the analytic person thinks you could be paying attention to with real attention.
What is real attention?
It's isolating what you're looking at from the context and breaking down the whole.
And then this same person who thinks that everyday attention is what he calls inattentive attention, he thinks that that is really what you see and what you see when you pay careful attention, which is analytic attention.
And that's just the neutral spotlight idea of attention.
So inattentive perception, everyday paying attention, contains nothing more and indeed nothing other than the attentive kind.
That is, it's always really just what the analytic element-finding attention gives you.
Only, that's why they call it inattentive.
You just don't pay enough attention to notice that.
If you really paid attention, you'd see what painters see when they paint when Monet paints the cadilla of Rouen about five different times a day and sees it as an entirely different looking something or other with different colors and everything.
Or you see it, what introspectionist psychologists do, they are really paying attention.
But when you are not really paying attention, your experience is nonetheless what they say it is, and they have the right to tell you that you're wrong because they're really paying attention and you are not.
You get it, yeah?
So until you get to be able to pay attention like that, like an introspectionist psychologist who can see just the thing and not the context, you get so you need to pay attention to the lines and not the end, you aren't really paying attention.
That's why you don't see that.
But that's there all along.
The sensory core is really your experience of two equal lines with little things on the end.
And if you pay careful analytic attention, that's what you see.
That's packed in that one funny sentence as a way of reviewing.
If you haven't got it, it doesn't matter.
I mean, if the idea is important, you could if you take time, you could sort of do that you could translate that sentence into what I've been saying if you want to.
The sentence is on 32.
I just picked it out of the way to summarize and show you how weird it all is.
Inattentive, about five lines down.
Inattentive perception contains nothing more and indeed nothing other than the attentive.
I hope that after all I just said that could be a good exam question and you could answer it.
You could explain what that sentence means.
It's just a funny, condensed way of saying the story we've been saying so far.
Oh, thanks.
Good.
Okay, yes, it's good if somebody who has the older version says the other page number, that would be helpful.
Sometimes I have the other page number, but I don't know if I had that one.
Yeah, I did.
Okay.
Now so now attention's not a search light.
It breaks down the perceptual field.
It's not revealing by carefully paying attention what's been there all along.
It's not neutral and so forth.
That's he's saying it again on 33.
I don't know, you'll have to find it because I don't have the other page number in here.
But I wanted to read the end of the paragraph.
You can find it because it's right before a new paragraph that begins against this conception.
So it says, perceptual consciousness is confused with the exact forms of thought of thought.
Is it that one?
No, I just say it again, there's no reason why.
Attention creates nothing.
But I guess I'm reading it because I want you to realize we're inside the, that's not Merlot-Ponte's view that attention creates nothing.
He's talking from within the intellectualist, where perceptual consciousness is confused and so forth and doesn't get it, doesn't get it right.
In spite of the intentions of intellectualism, the two doctrines then, that is, empiricism and idealism and intellectualism, have this idea in common that attention creates nothing, since a world of impressions in itself or a universe of determining thoughts are equally independent of the action of the mind.
That is, we are just finding out what's there.
Okay, that's where we were last time.
But now we go on, and very strange things are happening.
We ask, well, these are all bad stories about attention.
What is attention really?
What is its positive function?
And I think there are two.
And last time I was talking about one of them and did it, sort of, and that is, it's this enriching function where you sort of zoom in on something and explore it.
That's on, again, because I when I sometimes I have the old page numbers, but sometimes I don't.
I'm now going to, but now I get worried.
I'm not going to try to do it if you find it.
I want to read where just another version of this enriching talk is a paragraph that begins, now attention, about halfway down.
The miracle of consciousness consists in its bringing to life through attention phenomena which re-establish the unity of the object.
Whoa!
No.
I mean, that's no, in the sense I shouldn't be reading that yet.
Wait a minute.
Now let's look at my notes.
That's what I want to talk about next.
So where is interesting?
I think I just wrote something wrong here.
Don't worry about it.
What I, this enriching function is the way that your attention is drawn to something because you're interested in it or looking for it.
And then you respond by making the unpacking the horizon.
And I talked about how that year ago.
Sorry, is that what I'm looking for?
Go ahead, where?
Well, the one with the paragraph is now thinking.
Yeah.
Well, interesting, interesting.
I got to look at that because I decided maybe that that's one of the places where he's doing something different than I thought.
Let me that's why I stopped when I started reading it.
Let's read it and find out.
So pay attention is not merely further to elucidate pre-existing data.
It's to bring out a new articulation of them by taking them as figures.
They are performed only as preformed only as horizons.
They constitute a really new region of the total world.
No, oddly enough, that is exactly not any the same thing.
That's why my notes confuse me.
There are two different things going on.
The positive use of perception is to bring out something as figure on a background.
That's why this is so confusing and misleading.
What I read last time on page 78 of this, with the view right at the beginning of the chapter, Experience and Objective Thought, if you look, that's where, I'll just leave you to see an object is to have it on the fringe of consciousness, or to see an effect, turn on the horizon and open it up, become anchored in it, and so forth, exploring it.
And you close up the background where you were and make it into a figure, and you plunge into it and so forth.
All that is well expressed in the, by the way, and maybe I'll go a little further than I did last time.
I don't think I said this.
He has this great difference between this kind of positive role of attention, of bringing out what was on the horizon.
When he says it doesn't happen in movies, he has this brilliant idea to every once in a while, compare what he's talking about to movies, because movies don't have figure ground characteristics.
And a film is like the retina.
It's just got some determinant something on it.
So he'll say later that when a train comes at you in a movie, it looks like it gets bigger and bigger very fast because the movie is just registering the size of the projection through the lens onto the film of the train.
And it's very different than our normal experience of trains.
Well, here he's saying that when you, and this is really quite amazing, I'm going to read this.
When in a film the camera is trained on an object and moves nearer to give a close-up, we can remember that we're being shown the ashtray or the actor's hand.
We do not actually identify it because the screen has no horizon.
I'm now on page 78 of the book you guys all have, I hope, about 15 lines from the bottom.
And that's the story.
If we sort of focus in on the ashtray and make it the center of our attention, this is our kind of attention, and put the previous theme, let's say, of the person smoking, into the background.
And so we understand that in our if that happened in our experience, we'd have the ashtray on the margin and we'd zoom in on it in the sense of bring it out of the margin into the focus.
But the camera, I mean, I don't know what would happen if the camera zoomed in on it.
He doesn't have zooms.
It'd be interesting to figure that out.
I don't want to do it in front of you.
We wouldn't be doing what we're doing.
Even if it zoomed in on the ashtray, you'd have to figure out that that's the ashtray which was there in the picture before, but not at all something you were noticing on the horizon.
You wouldn't, you have to associate with it.
How does he put it?
You have to figure out.
You have to remember that there was an ashtray there, and now that on the edge of the picture, and you have to figure out that it's the same ashtray that you now see in a close-up, yeah, zooming in once.
You now see in the close-up, a cigarette being put out.
That you could figure that out how movies work.
But that's not the way we experience it.
Okay, so all that's supposed to be one kind of positive function, what I'm calling enriching it or having your attention drawn to something or unpacking it, as he talks about it sometimes.
Now, but there's another one.
There are really two functions.
Go back to 31.
You know, a quick way to give you a hint that this is coming.
31 is way back at the beginning of the attention chapter in the second paragraph.
He just says, in very brief, about 10 lines down, in order to relate it to the life of consciousness, one has to show how a perception awakens attention and kind of how attention develops and enriches it.
Now, that I misread, I misannounced.
That doesn't tell you what I'm about to tell you, but I'm going to show you.
There's two senses in which it develops and enriches you.
We just talked about the one, by focusing on the ashtray on the margin and burrowing into it, taking it up as your whole interest.
But there's another sense, totally different of enriching it, which is now what we have to look at.
And this is what I haven't realized ever.
That's why I spend time on it now because I started teaching it to myself.
It also has, and I'm amazed that he brings this in because he doesn't develop it and he doesn't prepare you for it.
It's got the positive job of opening up the conceptual world in which we see everything as determinate figures, so that we see determinate objects with properties.
That's another role of attention, a positive, important role of attention, such that you can pay attention to this lecture.
Not, I mean, there are three ways you can pay attention to it, really.
You can pay attention to it as trying to see it like an impression, break it down into its visual element.
You can pay attention to it by getting really interested in it and sort of burrowing in on it and unfolding it.
Or you can observe it as an object, a stable object with a certain shape and size, an object with qualities.
And it's important to be able to do that.
And it's something we do.
And it's something that he has so little to say about that when he does, you don't even notice that.
And that's why, I want to talk about this for a minute.
And maybe it comes up more often in this book than I realize.
Right now, I'm on page 33 of him talking about, well, I don't know yet because my notes are so confused because I just was getting used to this.
33.
The first, the full paragraph.
Against this conception of an inactive subjects, the analysis of attention by the psychologists, that's the Gashalt people, acquires the value of a self-discovery and the criticism of the constancy hypothesis that develops into a criticism of the dogmatic belief in the world seen as a reality in itself by empiricists and as the imminent of knowledge by intellectualists.
Attention, first of all, this is the crucial sentence that woke me up.
Attention, first of all, presupposes a transformation of the mental field, a new way for consciousness to be present to its objects.
Now, I've always thought, yeah, breaking down the gestalt.
But no, this is something that is a good way.
Attention is the way we have the experience of the presence of stable objects.
Now, on that one sentence alone, you could never base a lecture or get very interested.
But it goes on for a while.
The middle of page 34, the next page.
And what he's going to tell you, I have to prepare you because it's always so obscure.
Attention here stands for what I call detached observation something.
There's really two kinds of detached observation.
I said last time, once or two times ago, impressionist painters have it.
They have it in this breakdown, the whole way.
But there's another kind of detached observation.
I'm just hoping.
Just look at the lectern.
Look at the stable characteristics it's got.
Don't break it down into elementary impressions, but don't get involved in it and cope with it and make it transparent like it is for me, just something supporting papers which I don't even see.
Just study it.
And that's when you get a certain form of detachment.
Really, just objectively paying attention is what he's talking about.
And he says it in the middle of the page: the active attention can localize or objectify this invariant factor like the characteristics he's got a very complicated brain injured face but I don't talk about that that objectify this invariant factor because it has stepped back notice that that's the interesting thing step back from the changes of appearance attention therefore as a general and formal activity doesn't exist there is in each case a certain liberty to be acquired a certain mental faith to make the most of it it remains to bring to light the object of attention itself there is literally a question of creation boy lots of strange things are happening here you step back you actually bring to light something about the object but this is not like the sensory core theory carried up to the level of objects it isn't as if you see the object as it really it isn't if you really understand perception it isn't that you think you see the objects as it just is you see that you have created a new way of organizing your experience in which stable objects will now appear to you that's this creation it's not here's a good way to put it it never occurred to me that the first the bad attention then when I say bad I don't mean it's you it's you shouldn't ever be an impressionist or a stale psychologist but the misleading kind of impress attention is a destruption of something.
It's a destruction of a global whole into its elements.
This kind of attention is the creation of something.
It's the creation of the everyday stable substances with properties that we normally experience and which we think are just there all along and that we are just open minds that open heads that see them.
But he wants to give you a story about how you manage to stabilize your experience into this new form in which I think you could say, and this is where the core of that figure comes in, everything is free.
You manage to make qualities and the taste and everything determinate.
And then, you'll hear more about this later, you get the retroactive illusion that you're just an empty head turned towards a completely determinate world.
Whereas in fact, you have to compose the text before.
You want to decompose it.
You want to decompose it into the figure of ground objects whose involved with and have all kinds of characteristics like attractive and repulsive and they're tending towards, I guess, draw you to get a better and better grip on them.
The whole Merlopante is really interesting.
Our involved perception of the significance of things as we cope with them.
That's one way we compose the world into significant, useful affordances, to use the gate.
And now we're talking of another way we compose the world, into stable objects which we're able to contemplate and look at the determinant characteristics of and develop a science about and so forth.
And oddly enough, that's what he's talking about here.
I mean, I really bet on it.
Partly because it's a new kind of creation that you get when you step back.
Notice that.
I'm not going to say, I'm making a fuss about that because it isn't stepping back that gives you affordances.
You've got affordances when you're about to go out the door and the floor and the floor affords support when you're hungry and the food affords eating and you find your arm going out to the food.
That's the level that Meropony is interested in.
That's the absorbed phenomenon.
But, lo and behold, you can, and he's better say this, step back somehow and see objects that don't afford anything, that are just stable substances with properties.
And that's what he's talking about, I swear.
Okay.
But the pretty suspect.
The changes of appearance.
Well, good, good, okay.
I'll buy that.
Like something which you think is only achieved through a different kind of thing.
Okay, I'll buy that.
I need a better place.
I'll look for a better place.
I think we'll find one.
Because the reason that happens is because he's doing this, he's in terms of the brain-injured people who can't get a distance from their sensory field of experience.
And so it keeps shifting whenever they shift their attention.
And this gets you some way of stepping back.
And I guess, let me see if I can find that you said the opposite.
Really?
Wow.
Tell me.
Did you go back further into the beginning of that paragraph?
Yeah.
He says, attention, first of all, he starts with the transformation of the mental field.
A new way to consciousness is present to its object.
And the example he gives is rotating position on his own body.
I know, that's why I say it's misleading, or I think misleading, that he comes in that context.
I was trying to take it out of that context.
But let's go back to 33.
Remember this is this business now?
Wait a minute, I don't want to say against the anastic subject.
You think of it, especially in your body where you engage more.
Yeah, but this guy, but this is this brain-injured person who doesn't have the normal relation.
We've got to find a place outside of that.
But until we do, I haven't made my point.
So let me try to find a place where I can.
Well, I mean, it sort of cuts both ways on 33.
He says about six lines down.
He says, attention, first of all, presupposes a transformation of the mental field, a new way for consciousness to be present to its objects.
Now, that's what we're trying to understand.
What is this new way?
And now let's see if on 35, the paragraph that begins now, attention, I want to say I think this is now I want to claim that this is the kind of attention I'm going to talk about now that gives us very low odds.
Now, attention has to be conceived on the model of the primary axis.
Secondary attention, which would be limited to equality.
Knowledge already gained once more identifies with an axis with actual existing.
Now, I don't know what that means, but I'm not going to try to stop the patent.
I'm done.
To pay attention is not merely further to elucidate pre-existing data, it's to bring about a new articulation of them by taking them as figures.
They are translated, are performed only as preformed only as arises.
They constitute in reality new things in the total world.
It's precisely the original structure which they introduce that brings about the identity of the object before and after the act of attention.
Now, I think that's got to do with getting these qualities.
Once the color quality is acquired, and only by means of it do the previous data appear as preparations of this quality.
Once you go forth, now I'm still looking for what it is.
Skipping down, the miracle of consciousness consists in its bringing to light, through attention, phenomena which re-establish the unity of the object in a new dimension at the very moment they destroy it.
This attention is neither an association of images nor the return of the self of thought already in control of its objects, that's empiricism or echoism, but the active constitution of the new object makes the explicit and articulate what was until then presented as no more than indeterminate arises.
Well, I don't know yet.
You can see why I well, I'll get anyway.
You can see why it's confusing.
Which object is he going to be talking about?
He could be saying, well, aha.
Now I'll tell you why I think this, man, I'll let him talk.
If you were talking about the kinds of objects that you've got when you are responding to affordances, which is, is he talking about how thanks to the way the body works, we can see affordances, floors that we walk on and food that we eat, and it just calls to us and we respond?
Or is he talking about the way we see objects when we're seeing them as subconclusive properties?
Well, I think what I thought this morning, and I certainly not read you get it up, is that attention must have to do with seeing objects as objects.
You're not attending to things when your arm goes out to them to eat them, or when you walk out the door and the floor affords stepping.
You wouldn't put the discovery of affordances in the chapter on attention.
Affordances are exactly what show up for you when you've got your mind on getting to work.
The floor with its affording walking doesn't get your attention.
When I'm lently, the last thing that has my attention is the electron and its properties.
But I think, and so the question I asked myself this morning was, why is he bringing them this far under attention, since I've always thought he was only interested in affordances?
Okay?
I think what he wants to emphasize is that attention is like there's tens of types of attention.
I'm trying to get that.
It's just happening all the time.
And I think what he wants to say is that, you know, he said here, the first operation of attention is that you're creating for itself a feel.
So it's a phenomenal feel that he wants to get at.
And then there's this phenomenon.
So that's why he, I think that's why he mentions this particular case of the of that person you're being figuring bigger, right?
Because there you're getting the the kind of sensations without the field, because the purpose we have stuff.
Okay, good.
But when you do create the field, then it looks like it's a question of stepping back and creating something new with advanced, you think that's all the coping story.
No, no, but you don't have that.
You're in the field.
That's the point.
That happened.
You're the field when you're coping.
You're my feeling when you're natural higher to get observations.
Okay, and why would attention be necessary to create a field?
Why would you call that attention?
A lot of people want to talk about him talk.
I'm sorry.
I've been filled up.
You weren't saying something a while back, right?
Okay, I imagine.
Oh, well, I was maybe a dose of intentionality with the representation.
Intentionality.
Well, I don't want to talk about that.
No people are looking for the mask.
No, I don't think that's working about.
No, I don't think that is that's that although I can see why you say that because when if if you were giving our us a giving a description of objects somehow independent of our purposes and so forth, then maybe but now that only makes me would make me confused.
Right.
More of a question about how you might think about this.
If you think about the process by which you become capable of skillful coping, from applying example learning to swim, there's a point in the process of becoming capable of thematize or attend to the aspect of something like how to breathe.
Yeah, that's how you have to do it.
Right.
And it seems like that there is some continuum there between the way you focus in on the actual kind of techniques of using the body, and then gradually over time begins to fade into the background and make constitute kind of the phenomenal field of same activity.
Maybe.
I mean, I don't want to do it in terms of coping skill if I can help it because he's talking about proceeding right now.
And in proceeding you don't start with the rules and the features.
Now don't let me that doesn't make me happy either.
I'm sorry.
I just got to figure that out I got to suckle this through on my own.
Yeah.
I know he goes into the learning to see colors.
And that but I don't think the learning to see colors is the crucial thing here.
Let me find my quotes and then you guys can come back with your quotes.
I want to why do I think this?
Where is my list?
Okay, I'm 34 and 35 of the figures quote.
I want to say it creates an experience of the objective perceptual world, 362.
If this doesn't fit this, I'm in bad trouble.
So let me see.
This is the paragraph again.
Well, it's right before the paragraph that begins.
Intellectualism sets out.
So now I'm going to read this and see whether whether it helped me or not.
If God reflections makes us put the world of the exact back into the cradle of consciousness and ask how the very idea of a world of exact truth is possible.
This is in this attention set.
And that seems to fit what I want to say.
And look for its first appearance in consciousness.
When I look quite freely and naturally, the various parts of the field interact and motivate the enormous moon on the horizon.
And then he goes back to the beginning part of the experience.
But let's consciousness must be faced with its own unreflected light and things and awaken to its own history, which it has been forgetting.
Such is the true part of that philosophical the true part that philosophical reflection has to play and to arrive at a true theory of attention.
Now, I read that to say the true theory of attention has got to explain how we get from the holistic stuff like the moon on the horizon to a world in which there is determinate exact food.
What's this idea of the world of exact truth becoming possible within the moon?
He just wants to clarify how we get the prejudice of determinate gaining.
There's something to it.
Right.
Attention seems to have something to do with it.
I think the beginning of the wonderful thing.
Yes, where are the questions?
Now attention has to be conceived on the model of the primary act.
Then secondary attention, which would be limited to recalling knowledge already gained, would want more identifying, identifying with acquisition.
So paying attention is not merely vertical, we say pre-existing data.
It is to bring all of the articulation.
So I mean, that's your quote.
I just want, I just think that he wants to say that there is the attention of our coping, which creates a phenomenal field.
And then that within this field, a transformation can happen when I make a scientific observation.
Okay, but that doesn't just any old observation.
It doesn't have to be.
I observe this thing here that has these properties.
The objective that he wants to get at.
And so now he feels like, aha, now we can account for how you got the idea of the prejudice of determining being defined.
That's right.
I think we're saying the same thing.
What he needs to explain is why we think that there's this objective world that has these betterly determinate properties when the perceptual world never has complete determinate properties.
And he wants to attribute that to a certain kind of attention.
That's what I'm saying.
Well, it's the result of, yes, of a certain kind of attention to see fatal determinate objects, which then we inevitably, that's another piece of the argument, make the mistake of thinking we're there all along and explain why we saw them.
And then if you throw in the experience error, you try to explain perception and attention from the objective right.
And you can't do that.
Then you give up.
But at least what I'm trying to see here is, and I think it's here, is he has to have a story about why we do see objects with determinant properties.
And I think he's putting it in here in the attention chapter rightly, because we do have a way of paying attention to things which turns them into objects.
And he needs that to explain why people overlook the area the level that he's really interested in.
And what's the level he's really interested in is affordances, you remember.
Where our normal way of perceiving is not to look at things, observe them as objects, but to cope with them and and and respond to their solicitations.
That's right.
Yeah, but he doesn't talk about affordances or solicitations.
What he's focusing on here is the whole tension between the determinate and the indeterminate.
And kind of the perception and the point of exploration creates the determinate.
Right.
And it creates it now, we want to say, in sort of two stages.
I mean, the one stage is where the child finally creates the colors, and the next stage is where grown-ups see the objects with qualities and secondary properties, I think.
Yeah.
I think there's also an interesting connection with the criticism of intellectualism and empiricism that kind of clung a little bit earlier, where he says that empiricism cannot see that we need to know what we're looking for, otherwise we wouldn't be looking for it.
And intellectualism fails to see that we need to be ignorant.
So the idea being that there is something right that they're both sort of going after with these stable determinate objects, but what they don't see is that, as with affordances, something needs to be constituted in a way.
So I think he's sort of acknowledging, like you said, that there is this determinate object that we need to take account of, but really it all leads back to what he's going to say is more.
Yeah, he wants to explain, remember, both be empiricists with their impressions, and if we ever get there, the intellectualist who also has the same view that there is some determinant something or others which we have to put together and give meaning to.
And then we have to explain where they got this idea.
And then he's got this two-fold story.
Well, they've got this idea because we have a kind of attention which makes objects appear to be completely stable and determinate with fixed qualities.
And then because we can do that, we assume that, again, it's the searchlight idea.
But when we do that, we assume, well, it's been like that all along, and we're just finally seeing that all it really is, basically, is this world of determinate objects.
And now he wants to say, no, that's not how it is.
That's something we've, quote, created, better to say, composed.
It's one of the ways that we can organize that our one of the ways that our experience organizes itself.
By the way, let me say something about that.
It's always, to be put not in the terms of us, you know, synthesizing it or constituting it or anything like that.
It's always on the side of experience.
There are two ways that our experience organizes itself.
When we're involved, it organizes itself into affordances.
And when we take a more detached attitude and step back from our ongoing activity, it organizes itself into substances with properties.
And then we read back, this is what you were just saying, as if that was all along there, substances with properties.
And that's the experience error.
And that leaves you only with two possibilities: the empiricist story or the intellectualist story.
How did this stuff that were just substances with properties ever get to be perceptual objects?
Don't think about that for a moment.
Yeah, let me go on.
Maybe because I want to cover more.
The algorithm fake up in a few minutes ago.
I could wait till lunch.
Okay, let me see now where we are.
So there's an objective world, and let me just give my own text.
Let me just have one comment.
Let me just create something and give some more.
Not my full time, it's my whole time.
I think really right.
The distinction that matters here is between the determinant and the indeterminate that I've experienced now.
Whereas the contrast between the facts when you engage is really not in thought.
And the reason why that matters is so much otherwise when I look, when I give my focused attention to the left gentleman, the fellow behind it is out of focus.
I can turn my attention to him and now he's in focus.
When he's in focus, this becomes background.
And that's the military contest because it is that sort of creative process of making out there.
All along, if you're asking me, what am I seeing?
I don't think of myself as seeing a blurred room.
I think of myself as seeing a personally determined room.
Yeah, that's what he's going to be most interested in.
But that alone wouldn't get you, what if we call it the world of the completely determinate world of science, this quote I was reading on 35, the idea of a world of exact truth.
You've got to go one step beyond the way you can bring the background out of this figure on some background or change it and make that figure background on some other for some other figure.
You've got to be able to go beyond that.
And then you can go to the point of just seeing an isolated thing and in all of its determinatives.
Well, I just don't want to get stuck on that.
One last thing.
That that explanation is in the right direction, but hasn't gone far enough to explain what Mary LeBlanc is trying to get at.
Have I said that or you're saying that?
Are you suggesting that?
Yeah, I'm saying I agree with Alva that the context here and with Rick is to explain how it is that we get the illusion that there is a completely determinate world of impressions or whatever.
And the end the answer's got to be that it's us or even that's not what I want to say.
It's the way experience organizes itself that if we pay attention a certain way, we get determinate objects and that that's and then it looks like that must have been there all along.
That's the always research light error.
And but it's all in the interest of explaining why we've got the problem that empiricists and intellectualists are trying to solve.
Now I'm going to go on to the problem that intellectuals are trying to solve.
I have to go back to the drawing board and see if I can find more evidence for what I'm saying.
But I haven't given it up.
I just feel I have a right not to be convinced.
So now let me see where I am.
Okay, we're ready for judgment, which starts on 37 in this book.
And the paragraph that begins at the top of 37, intellectualism, intellectualism set out, it is true to discover.
32.
Do you want to explain motives?
I've got motivation.
I was going to skip it, but see if I want to do it.
Is this time I would say motivate in five?
Yeah, I think it's going to because it's going to come up again later a lot at the end of the chapter.
Let's wait until we get there.
I I could I think we should jump to this or we won't have any new material on our, you have to think about it.
Okay.
The the judgment is going to fill in what sensation lacks to make perception of objects possible.
That's an italic in the beginning.
And that's pretty straightforward, and that's the whole story.
And there's all kinds of variations of it.
There has to be some kind of given, some kind of, in Kant language, given to the intuition, that is some kind of passively received, meaningless data.
And then the mind, and this is the why they're intellectualists, has to put some kind of organization on that.
It doesn't just organize by association.
It organizes by being brought under, to talk like Kant, categories.
That is, if you want to bring it more sort of down to the lectern, to see the lectern, I've got to see, and then I have a whole complicated, Kant would call it an empirical concept.
My teacher, C.I.
Lewis, called it a meaning in mind.
The meaning of this thing is that if I put books on it, it will support them.
If I look at the other side, it'll have another side.
If I turn the light up a certain way, the color will change a certain way.
You've got a whole mental construct that you put on the basic minimal meaningless experience, and then you could experience it as something or other.
And it doesn't matter here whether it's an electron that affords putting papers on or electron that's got certain properties.
The whole thing is to get any kind of perceptual object out of the basic stuff.
Now, I want to just sort of fill you in to how sort of manifold this is.
I mean, the basic stuff could be something like sense impressions, that they need to be organized by these categories or needings in mind.
What C.I.
Lewis thought the basic stuff was was indubitable data like seeming to see electron.
And the seeming to see electron had to be filled out by, if I do such and such, I'll seem to see the other side.
And if I put pages on it, I'll see they will seem to be supported.
And he did it all in terms of seeming because he wanted to, he was still believing that there had to be an indubitable given.
And then there's Husserl.
Husserl got himself into the very interesting position, very sensible and logical, that if order is going to be put in by the mind, what's it going to start with that needs to be ordered?
Well, Kant had this mysterious notion of a synopsis, which was wired with synthesis, which gave you the minimal spatial tenfold ordered something of it.
But Lewis, but Husserl doesn't have that.
He gets the notion of what he calls hyletic data, which is completely unstructured matter, perceptual matter, which you have to get the right mental set concept to, he says, no ema, to bring it under.
And there's lots of sort of Husserl in the background in this chapter, probably, at least the intellectualist as Merrill-Pontee is most sort of trying to overthrow it.
I'll give you an example from Husserl because it sort of helps.
What would it be like to have this minimal data?
Well, my favorite example is think of what happens if you think physically as if you're about to get a glass of milk and you get instead a swallow of water.
Then it isn't as if you simply switch over and say, oh, milk, I thought it was going to be water.
You get this sort of experience in which you just don't know what is happening to you or what's in your mouth.
And then you switch from the mental, from imposing on it the noema or the concept milk to imposing on it the concept water and it all falls into place.
But in that moment with the highlighting data and the highlighted data, there's nothing you can say about it except it sets boundary conditions.
It won't accept being taken to be milk if it's water.
And it won't accept to be water data.
And it won't accept to be taken as water data if it's milk data.
There is some boundary on what you can take things as.
If any structure that you give, that's your mind putting on the structure.
That's what Husserl calls constitution.
And that's the intellectualist view.
I want to say one more thing because I know Alva's concerned about this.
Hussar an entire, the book is very confusing because it uses the word constitution when it's talking about the intellectualist, and then it means imposing the meaning on the matter, whatever you think the matter is.
And when Merrill-Ponty uses it, it means the self-organizing of experience.
So it constitutes itself into a figure on his ground.
And it's very misleading.
If you've got to always ask yourself, is this Constitution being done?
Well, there are two levels to that.
If the Constitution is being done by the mind, you've certainly got an intellectualist.
If the Constitution is being done by the body, then you have a complicated question exactly what that amounts to.
What sort of understanding does the body have that it brings to bear on the data?
Because it could just be, like in C.I.
Lewis, what you're bringing to bear is if I move such and such, then such and such, and if I move such and such, then such and such, that would still be intellectual from a narrow-ponty point of view.
You only have a right to say from a narrow-ponty point of view that experience constitutes itself as such and such.
And it turns out that's correlative with the body.
We'll get to that.
But I think it's important at this stage just to pay attention.
I'm going to give you, I'm always trying to give you guidelines for not getting lost.
Here's the Constitution guideline.
And there's a whole lot of talk about Constitution at one place.
Okay, so on 46, which is in the middle of nowhere, I'm afraid, for a few other people, maybe I've got it in my notes in whatever form.
Well, I'm just going to read it.
He's talking about analytic reflection breaks the world in itself.
Breaks the world in itself, 38.
He says it constitutes it through the working of consciousness.
But this constituting consciousness, instead of being directly apprehended, is built in such a way as to make possible the idea and so forth and so forth.
Constituting consciousness is the intellectualist account.
But here, on page 44, and this is so confusing, Herr's going to do his story and use Constitution, about 15 lines from the bottom of 44 for me.
We shall have only an abstract essence of consciousness as long as we refrain from following the actual movement by which it resumes its own operations at every instant, focusing and concentrating them on an indefinable object, gradually passing from seeing to knowing and achieving the unity of its own life.
We shall not reach this constitutive dimension if we replace the plenary unity of consciousness by a complete transparent subject and so forth and so forth.
There he's ready.
This does two jobs.
I think it tells you that he wants to go from, you can go to seeing and then to knowing, and that's the two things we were talking about.
And both of them are constitutive in his sense, self-organizing.
But at the bottom, he starts talking about the other kind of constitution.
Let's see, let me just go on.
The intellectual process of self-discovery doesn't penetrate as far as this living nucleus of perception, because it's looking for the conditions which make it possible, without which it would not exist, instead of uncovering the operation which brings it into reality whereby it's constituted.
Now that's still self-organizing.
Let's see if I can find a constitution which is with him.
Well, he talks about on the previous page, about 15 lines down, the domain of the constituted and not of the constituting mind.
When he talks about constituting the mind, then he's not talking about the way the experience achieves its own unity, organizes itself.
He's talking about the way the mind imposes order.
Now, let me go back because it would be good.
So the intellectualist is talking about the way the mind imposes order, and that could be order on sense data, it could be order on meaning, it could be order on philotic data, but whatever it is, it's some stuff, it's some kind of order which exists independent of this stuff and which is imposed on the stuff and puts it together.
And the mental one is the one we want to focus on, because the sense in which the body might or might not do that is too complicated for us yet.
So, now I want to see where we are.
Well, I like this passage.
Remember, this is why I keep saying it's an antinome, the intellectualist and the empiricist, right after the italics about judgment is what sensation acts.
It adds to what sensational acts makes perception possible.
He goes on a little bit later.
Analysis is dominated by the empiricist notion, which, however, is accepted only as the boundary of consciousness and serves merely to throw into a leap a power of coordination of which it is itself the antithesis.
That is, the power of coordination is this mental power.
And the power of just association is the other.
Intellectualism thrives on a refutation of empiricism.
Analytic reflection makes its position firm by carrying to their logical conclusions the realist and empiricist thesis and validating their opposite by showing their absurdity.
So, that's that's so now we're going to get these people who are going to reduce to absurdity the idea that we can get any that blind intuition, as he puts it in the next paragraph, could ever get you anywhere.
But you've got to have a concept.
And that judgment is applying these concepts to the given, whatever the stuff is that you're supposed to be organizing.
And then perception becomes, as he says, this is before that big footnote.
Perception becomes an interpretation of the signs that our senses provide in accordance with a body's visionalized, a hypothesis that the mind evolves to explain impressions to itself.
And judgment explains the excess of perception over the retinal impression.
All of this is just the same point.
Another way to put it, and we're now down to about 15 lines on 39, this is what the intellectualist does.
We, the intellectualists, construct perception instead of revealing its distinctive working.
We miss the we, just very, the user, but it's not him and us.
We miss once more the basic operation which infuses meaning, sans, that's significance, into the sensible, and which is taken for granted by any logical mediation or any psychological causality.
Logical mediation is intellectualist.
Causality is associations.
And psychology now doesn't mean Gestalt psychology.
It means behaviors.
Whenever you see psychology, you must be getting good at this, I hope.
You could have to ask yourself: are these the people who don't understand anything, or are these the Gestaltists who understand it almost completely?
So, and now let's see.
So, something given and has to be interpreted.
And the one other point I want to get across today is the way you have to understand very clearly that the Mero-Ponty, getting interpreted doesn't mean having some mental belief about what's going on.
Getting, sorry, no, that was very wrong.
Getting interpreted sounds like there's something about which you have a belief or an interpretation.
Mero-Ponty wants to say it's built into the way things look themselves, what affordances they have, for instance.
He's talking at the bottom of 39 at the beginning of the paragraph against a large cardboard box.
If you look at a large cardboard box, which actually weighs as much as a small one, it will look heavier.
You will say that it feels heavier to your hand, and intellectualism can't say that.
And then he's got lots of examples of how that works.
And I just wanted to give you sort of my own kind of example, so you have this in mind as you read it.
Because the way to see that this intellectualism is wrong is to see this intellectualism has to presuppose something which it then interprets, and then you have some kind of meaningful experience.
And what Mero-Monty wants to say is that it's not an interpretation.
Things look different depending on what you are coping with them as.
Yeah, what let me just give you two examples.
I mean, if you he he thinks, and I think it's right, that if you look at a house from the front and you think it's a house, it looks thick.
Remember I've said this several times already, that you can go in through the front door and so forth.
And if you think that it's a facade, it looks flat and like you can't go in through the front door.
Now, what I'm adding to that, having said that lots of times, there's no percept, there's no impression, there's no data that stays the same and gets two different interpretations.
That's the view that he's trying to refute.
And I think that's the clearest way to refute it.
He's trying with the box example, there's nothing like the blank interpretation of the box as just a box, and then you interpret it as heavy or light.
No, it looks heavy or it looks light.
Now, I don't know if you believe this about the houses, but I'll tell you how I came to believe it.
I mean, I remember the day that I was switched out of seeing a C.I.
Lewis follower who would have said, well, it's got some particular look, and that, and then you interpret it as a facade, or you interpret it as a house, but your interpretation doesn't change how it looks.
Your interpretation just changes whether you take it to be a facade or a house.
Now Fonte wants to say, no, what you take it to be changes how it looks.
And that's, in fact, you could say, once you're in sort of in a certain involved way, the way it looks determines what you take it to be.
So that when you're on a movie set, all of the things look flat and you therefore take them to be facades.
And when you're on the street, all the things look like houses that you could walk into.
So you take them to be houses, how they look.
Here's what happened to me.
It's sort of a crazy story.
I was going down Telegraph Avenue in Berkeley when I first came to Berkeley way back in 68, and I saw what I took to be a beautiful woman in front of me, and I just walked faster to see how she looked from the other side, how she said she was looking so nice from the back with long hair and all that.
And what I found was when I got around that this beautiful woman was a man with a beard and a mustache.
And this was a shock.
And then, that was totally uninteresting, I fell behind again.
And now that didn't look anymore like the back of the beautiful woman.
That looked like the back of a man.
And there wasn't any determinate impression which I had interpreted in two different ways.
That's when I saw that Lewis was wrong, and when I saw that Marilo Funty had a very important point that we had to pay more attention to.
And you can make up interesting stories, which I think are important.
How did the back look here?
Well, I don't remember Marilyn Funcy talking about this, but I worry about this.
I think it's because the shoulders now look important to me, maybe more than the hips, and stuff like that.
You can make it, you could, what stands out is significant.
So, with the house, I think, if it's a facade, you'll see the sort of blank glitters on the windows.
Whereas if you think it's a house, you'll think you see the furniture inside the windows.
You'll pay attention either to the glitter or to the furniture, depending on whether you think it's a facade or the house.
So, it isn't magical.
It looks different.
It isn't as if you just interpreted it that way.
And that's okay.
Now, having said that, we want to get back to so there isn't a given that gets interpreted.
That's where we are.
We're at the top of 39.
It's not, perception is a hypothesis which explains the impression.
Because I'm just going to repeat my point once more, because I think it's so important.
There is no neutral impression that is there both in the back of the man and in the back of the woman, or in the facade in the house.
You know, it can't be that we are interpreting this, our mind is taking this impression two different ways.
It can't even be, I think, but again, I say this is a difficult question that I'm not ready to talk about yet, that you can't even understand what he means by the body as something that manages to take this impression in two different ways.
Because he thinks that if you think there's any impression at all that gets interpreted by the mind or the body, you've already made the mistake.
So, but he's interested in the intellectualist view.
He hasn't really thought about it, I think, but I think it's a great thing to try to think about.
When you bring in, how you bring in the body will make a big difference in this.
But I'll do that later.
Let me see now.
I want to do the 39 we just did 40 at the bottom of 39, the back the cardboard box story.
Okay, we've done that.
And now we're going to go on to, well, I just like this phrase at the next page.
He says we have to apprehend an imminent sense in the sensible before judgment begins.
That's just another way of saying it's not a neutral impression that gets judged one way or another by being brought under one concept or another.
There's already a meaning, and that's rock-bottom.
You don't go, you can't get behind that.
Now let's see, there's another one I wanted to show you.
Okay, at the top of 45, I don't know how I'm going to tell you how to get to that one.
No footnotes either.
I don't know, maybe you'll find it.
It's right back when I talked about constituted, where I said that it's self-organized.
Right after that, right after where I read that there's the operations which bring things into reality whereby it's constituted.
Well, constituted now means, if the Christ I was reading, remember, organized by itself, not given a meaning.
This is the anti-intellectual view.
In actual perception, that's his view.
Taken at its origin before any word is uttered, the sign offered to sense and the signification are not even theoretically separable.
That is, you cannot carve out anything in common between the back of the girl and the back of the guy, between the house and the facade.
You can't find the part that needs to be interpreted and the part that's the interpretation.
That's his basic view, and he just keeps hammering away at it.
I don't know if I need to tell you anything more, just because I think I got 30 minutes left.
Well, I was going to tell you some things, maybe I will, about what not to pay too much attention to.
Let's try that.
I'll tell you things for the last three minutes to help you with your reading.
There is all the sort of criticism of Gestalt's psychology at the end, about five pages in from the end, when intellectualism took over the naturalistic notion of sensation.
This is a paragraph.
It begins with that long footnote on Descartes, which I said you didn't have to read.
Remember, I said you didn't have to read the whole Descartes thing, which goes from 48 to 53.
And at the top of 53, you really ought to start reading again, but not with the kind of concentration.
It gets, because what he's doing, he says, conversely now that psychology discards the notion of sensation and so forth and brings it and has a criticism of the conflict hypothesis.
Of course, that's Gestalt's psychology.
Then he has a lot of criticism to give of Gestalt's psychology.
And that's something, since you don't know Gestalt's psychology, you don't, I don't think you have to worry about it.
And it's got to do with whether they whether they believe too much in causality and too much in the real world, whether they're looking for a causal basis of the Gestalt phenomena.
So you can skip clear up to the end.
Do you think they can read that?
I think it's very important to see that Miliponi's not basically defelled psychology.
Okay.
And that his criticism doesn't have, well, basically that metaphysical consequence that will come out later.
Granted, it will come out later.
Rick is right about that.
But read it in a way, don't get too worried about it.
I mean, I agree about that, because you must not know Gisela psychology.
You can't.
Oh, you don't do heard this.
Well, yeah, he knows a lot about Gisela psychology.
He's got a vested interest in this.
He's got stock in Genfelt psychology.
And I think that the Geshell psychologist shouldn't do anything wrong.
They've just been granted stresses because of naturalism.
Yeah, but so is Gibson, for instance.
Well, no, Gibson's a thing.
Okay, well, yeah, but Gibson is what the development psychologist should have been.
Right.
And that's a little nice thing to be saying, but they should have been by suffering out what they got off.
Yeah, oh, yeah, but Gibson's a naturalist anyway, though.
No?
Woo!
I'm going to talk about that.
First doctor of the book.
Okay, never mind.
Let me go back to reading you one thing at the bottom of 56, which is three pages from the end of the section, which you now, according to Rick, and I think I will go along with him.
You could be.
Let me just tell you, by the way, remember that did I tell you not to read 36 to 39?
Or did not not to read it, but that it wasn't gifted to the list.
Another place where it's not Meryl-Ponty talking to a lot of it.
Let me tell you that.
In the middle of 36, it's where he starts with if the moon on the horizon still so forcibly brings out.
That's about 20 lines there, which cutting it switches into the not his view of the picture.
And I want you to say, yeah, and all of 37, 38, and 39, up to the bottom of 39, up to the large cardboard box, is him getting inside of and explaining the intellectualist position.
So you should read it for sure, but you shouldn't think that it's his position.
That's very important.
And one more thing about that, and then I'm going to go on.
I told you that you could skip 43 to 44.
Not being him really begins on 42.
Starting with the paragraph, it is true that at the bottom of 42 to the middle of 44, where it says negative power, that's not him.
I was told by so many people that it was helpful to tell you this that I figured I'd better go on telling them.
And now, I guess, yeah, time is up.
I wanted to do that.
And now we're going to go on and do the phenomenal field for, where are we?
We're supposed to, you're supposed to read up to 59 today, and that's where I got it.
And now we're going to go on and look at the part called the phenomenal field for next time.
The reading is pretty short.
You need a short reading now.
Okay.