So so ex I I would like to to find out if if brain science uh can can can shed some light on what's going on in this in this very brief episode uh where we move away in the elevator to the right distance now I focus on a few aspects within neuroscience a few perspectives the neural basis of skills utilization behaviour performance monitoring actually I've been mentioning this all before so I won't go through the list again very briefly there's a whole body of literature on the neural basis of skills sometimes it goes on the name of procedural memory or system memory the most important thing to know is that there is a widely distributed network of brain activity involved in executing a skill and from neuroscience it becomes quite clear which areas of the brain are particularly involved in this type of skillful motor action.
I've written down the most important areas, I won't go through the list now.
One question that isn't answered by these people working on the neural basis of skills is how all these deep areas that show up in imaging or in lesion studies, how actually this the activity of all these areas is being coordinated for the realization of some tasks.
And in order to understand how that may be the case, it's useful to study the literature on self-organization and functional integration or neurodynamics, where they do have a story about how functional integration can occur.
And one of the most important hypothesis at the moment is that it's translated global phase synchronization that makes it possible for areas to be integrated and to generate behavior at the global level.
So far for the skills, now I will pay attention to utilization behavior, but starting from first there's some parts or some descriptions from Melo Ponty about know-how and what we could call affordances.
So as you all know he describes some concrete situations of know-how like the woman with the feather on her head making sure that it doesn't break or the people in the desert immediately knowing where to go when they want to go home.
When you look for it you find something somewhere in phenomenology of behavior of perception.
Often it's important that this type of action occurs freely rapidly and it doesn't come from nowhere.
The body unifies many capacities, capacities attuned to certain parts of the world, you can say.
There is a direct link between the organism's capacities and what I perceive the possibilities for action in the environment.
However, one of the limitations, as you know, is that Melo-Ponty's descriptions leave some some quite some mystery.
Sometimes he speaks about how metric a real is.
Neuroscience doesn't, of course, immediately shed light on this, but indirectly I think it helps to get a better feeling for what's going on.
So what would be accordances in Mel Ponty's pre-Gibsonian descriptions?
The subject, I put here the craftsman, but actually it's about Snyder, but in this situation, I think Meloponty is also trying to describe a normal concrete feeling with the world.
So I put there the craftsman or it should be the wallet nail, each wallet maker.
When put in front of his status needle and familiar tasks, he doesn't need to look for his hands or his fingers because they are potentialities already mobilized by the perception of scissors or needle.
The central end of those intentional threats which link him to the object given is the piece of leather to be cut up, it's a lining to be stood.
Now another place is Meloton T often stresses that in familiar environments we do not deliberate with reactive movements, a possibility for action.
Or as he said, if the body starts towards objects to be grasped, objects speak to the body subject, objects invite our reactions.
Objects are already look attractive or repulsive before you perceive your objective qualities.
He speaks of being called by a situation if you do some work.
One way I like to think of the portion rule is as an integrated system where the open situation can ask for some kind of work and elicit the necessary movement by some sort of remote retraction as an electromagnet.
So from other competitive descriptions, it's quite clear that familiar objects do not even feel cold but move you or do something with you.
Then there is this pathology called utilization behavior.
It was described in the 1980s by Lamit, a neurologist from Perl.
His patients had patients with utilization behavior in general have acquired labial fungal lesion, but it is part of the brain.
Often acquired after a stroke, that can also be other causes.
These patients tend to grasp and use objects, familiar objects, when they see them.
So I could grasp and use this thing.
Yeah, that's playing with it, but it's not familiar for me.
But a patient may be attracted by this type of object if it is familiar to him.
They even use it when they are told not to do it.
And it's important that they disregard part of the situational context.
I'll come back to that later.
Finally, about the pathology, it's a trenching pathology.
If they recover, because often of course they don't and they die, but if they recover it's transient and it occurs after a period of akinetic mutism, which basically means that they are without initiative and don't speak their mood, being without initiative.
Characteristics of utilization, it occurs spontaneously.
These patients disregard personal concerns.
So with personal concerns or also situational concerns, I mean their needs or interests or preferences.
They also disregard social context or social norms.
And the behavior is normally instrumentally correct.
So here you see a picture of one of the next patients.
One example would be a patient seeing a pair of glasses laying on the table, putting it on.
Well, nothing is wrong with his eyes.
Then he's disregarding his personal concerns.
Another thing that can go wrong is grasping the pair of glasses from the experimenter.
That would be disregarding social context.
And something that often also occurs is in this case, they keep on using so here the patient puts on two pairs of glasses, which is also again disregarding personal concerns because one pair of glasses should be another.
Note that instrumentally correct Euroce means that the movement is fluent and technically adequate.
It doesn't put the glasses on the top of his head or on his shoulder or try to put it on upside down or just scratch the pair of glasses.
It's a normal movement and such a movement is often in neuroscience called a complex movement.
It's called a rectified sequence.
So examples of eucalyptizing behavior would be taking pen and paper to write when they are laid down in the room where you are.
Eating from an apple, like these patients are often tested while doing neuropsychological, other neuropsychological tests.
And then there may be all kinds of objects in the room and one of them may be the experiment with apple and the patient can grasp and use this apple eat it.
Another old example is the patient being in the house of Lamit.
The neurologist being shown to the house on the writing in the bathroom sees the shaper and uses it.
Another example from the same case is the patient starting to undress well on seeing a bed, but not his own death.
And it could also be that that patient takes the first means of transportation instead of the one that goes to the right direction.
So, to summarize the main characteristics, behavior is instrumentally adequate, personally and socially inadequate.
It's called a rective complex action sequence.
It's triggered by objects in the environment, triggered when they perceive it, when they perceive the object.
Their lived experience is that the object orders the patient to use it.
And importantly, they are not aware of the inappropriateness of what they are doing.
And of course, we are not so much surprised that they don't have an explicit intention before they act because we don't have an explicit intention before we sit down in a chair either.
But for neuroscientists, I like to remember that it's not so strange that there's no intention beforehand.
So, what we can learn from utilization behavior is that familiar objects have some impact on this at the subpersonal level.
There may be a link with miracle-piece descriptions of object affectiveness.
Moreover, our everyday behavior is very well attuned to the complexities of the context.
And there is a medial frontal system in the brain that seems to contribute to this attorney.
Then, something about the lesions.
Now, if you're not interested in neuroscience, then you may forget the areas, but for the people that are, I do want to mention it.
The most common lesions of utilization behavior are generally bilateral lesions of the medial control cortex, ACC, pre-SMA, SMA, and often also it's connected to cortical structures like Cardassinucleus.
And two cases are known of anterior and medial euclid.
Here, a picture of the medial frontal lobe.
So you look at, imagine the brain is scratched like this.
You look at the medial side, at one of the sides.
Then, I don't have a pointer, but when you see all the dots in the right picture there, that's the part of the grain that often gets damaged in patients with utilization behavior.
The areas there are the pre-SMA and the anterior singlet, the dorsal part of the anterior singlet.
Another word for the area that comes back later in the presentation is muscle singlet zone, RCZ, that means the red part in the top left picture.
Again, it overlaps ACC, dorsal ACC, and pre-SMA.
Remember also that these areas, this is a picture of areas involved in performance monitoring.
And the same regions that are lesions with utilization behavior are also lesions.
No, the regions that are lesions by patiagnosis with utilization behavior are the same regions that are normally involved in uh performance monitoring.
Okay, so there is a new basis of performance monitoring where you where you see all the all the dots.
Uh these are um uh studies that um that investigated performance monitoring for aspect of performance monitoring.
Don't mention there are there.
Um these um these studies point out that uh uh an important part of the brain for performance monitoring is this this region.
So each one of the stars is somebody's region.
Now is one study on performance monitoring.
Yeah, so it's uh it's a a review of many articles uh that study performance monitoring.
And I just use this picture for utilization data to show which part of the brain is involved there.
And moreover, because later on I will be talking about performance monitoring in the sustainable mode of the brain for hostile singlets on ACP.
But at the moment the the latest articles on utilization behavior they they tend to focus or think out of a different frame of thinking.
This is a model by Gary Goldberg from 1985 where two systems are being distinguished, the medial premotor system and the lateral premotor system.
The green lines here point to areas of the lateral premotor system and the red lines areas of the medial premotor system.
One area of the media with medial premotor system which is not clear is the ACC.
And also the distinction between SMA and pre-SMA wasn't made at that time.
The hypothesis of the people working on utilization behavior, so these are normally neurologists doing review work, the hypothesis is that there's a loss of inhibition and more specifically there is an imbalance between the medial pre-motor systems and the lateral pre-motor system.
The lesion in the medial system is the cause of this imbalance.
And they tend to speak of a loss of internally driven motor control.
And they also note that normally the medial system functions upstream and controls the lateral one.
Going back to this picture, you see that both the green, so the lateral system projects on the motor cortex and the medial system projects on the motor cortex.
So when the medial, the red corner is lesion, the green gets dissignated.
That's the picture in the crystal.
But it's not very clear what they mean with this internally driven motor control, which should be endogenous and self-regul regulated that gets generated there in the medial pre-motor system.
And one way to investigate this further is by asking why aren't our everyday automatic actions, immediate actions, normally in line with our concerns and why are they contextually adequate normally?
And what are the neural mechanisms involved?
And another question which I find very interesting and which is neglected in the literature, almost neglected in the literature in the visitation behavior, is how can it be that these patients are not aware that they do something inappropriate when they press somebody else's cup of coffee?
You can confound them with their behavior and then they won't they they don't care that they did it and they are not bothered that they did it.
But you can you can convince them that they did something which is uh which is not uh appropriate.
So it's not that they that they cannot be made to realize, but it's just that at the moment when the act doesn't play any role whether it's uh it's uh appropriate or not.
We have to discontent.
That's the point, because they're in the room and the bed is ready to get into when they are you said something they feel or they say they're ordered to do it by the object.
Yeah, that's not when you ask them, so why do you do it?
They said the object ordered me to do it, but this should be more seen, I think, as a rationalization and that it's really precisely that they hear a voice uh from from the object they're hearing.
It could be a kind of description of a tendency that it's feel they feel bad there and they feel discontented there and they put the bed looks like they're the bat they feel good over there and contented over there.
But they they don't they don't experience this uh this inappropriateness or uh they don't experience that something is wrong.
They just I think the best way to to understand it is by just seeing it as as some attraction that that occurs and that they that they do experience.
Uh but then when asked to describe it they say the object ordered me.
But uh one problem with this literature is that the the the phenomenological part is often not so well described because neurologists tend to think of uh people like machines often, not all of them, but some of them do.
So uh it's uh it's a bit neglected.
This sounds I don't know this is open questions for us, but I'm saying that's why this sounds very similar to act syndrome and it seems an argument for avoidances, but it argues against loner intentionality actually.
What's missing is rationality and that they can't be lowly behavior at all.
And it seems like when you combine at a free or some personal level those avoidances, it seems at a personal level you have the ability to make a judgment as to the appropriate okay.
Why would it be that?
Yeah, it's it it would be being restored by personality of pure classes as well, I think.
And then I don't like the word in this in this context, but it's um the way to think of it I think is to to remember that no how if I can call uh you're sitting down in a chair an automatic action, but only when I realize that it's controlled in a sense you can stop it.
It's not you uh doing something weirdly you if you would like to you can you can you can stop.
So um uh it refiner in a very limited sense of having control of what to do.
In all action.
For example, suppose they're about to sit in a chair and you say, Don't sit in that chair, the chair is broken.
Now the way Jennifer thinks of it, they just can't stop, they just go on anyway.
And the way I understood it, well sure they wouldn't stop.
They're not autonomous.
They are they the the chair won't look comfortable anymore and they won't it won't order them anymore.
No, but when when they are told not to use the objects, they they do continue using it.
But um it may be um when you tell them to stop um I w I wouldn't know how they would trip.
I wouldn't know.
It's it's not as fair.
It's something that the importance of the good person having dormitivity goes that since the fast open relativity comes in.
You pointed out that the guy doesn't flash on the topic of the test and without thinking honestly and legalizing them in a probably and cannot position instead of styling another way.
But then what makes them I mean reason comes in at a certain time.
It doesn't sound like there's an argument for mono intentionality when the appropriate person sees a badge and thinks about it.
He doesn't have or he doesn't think they would well no, I I mean what's the argument that that you know um bad behavior is right.
I don't think there's a there isn't a the reason of that I don't have an argument, but I think it doesn't think from from your own technology and from oils, I think there's no thinking over it going on.
Uh perhaps it is this this uh perhaps in our case this performance monitoring system but then it's again a loss.
So that you do have some some some control intensive ones in point of if you don't think about it.
Partly in my thoughts, you benefit from the same point, but I think it's sort of it's a valid objection that there isn't a sort of correct uh argument for that disposition.
But one thing in favor of it is um is that it has a lot of understanding of the subject is not alternative of what actually would be the body setting if we engage in the motoring technology.
But one thing that I find this demonstrates uh raises the question of the relation between um tasks in motoring technology.
Because one way of understanding utilization behavior is that you know part of the reason why I don't just grab her coffee is that I'm engaged in a task right now and the task is to drive off maybe work this one to the slide or if you're walking or talking part of the utilization behavior maybe the monitoring and finding out is a a lack of or disruptions of whatever it is that enables us to be caught up in tasks.
Yeah precisely this is correct and ever uh the task is being neglected.
But the task are new situational concerns and so personal needs and tasks and has um preferences and and incorporated social norms.
Well I mean I just think this is connected to a discussion we've been having all semester because what I think what the these um people who have the lesions, what the results suggest is that there's really two levels of normativity involved with affordances.
There's the um norm of how to deal with the objects, you know, to eat the apple as opposed to you know your army or something.
Um and uh then there's another norm of win.
And it seems to me that uh that win norm is um much richer and more complex and uh really goes beyond the sort of barely perceptual um in a way.
And so um this does as Rick was just suggesting I think um bear on this question of when you're fully des describing uh affordance related behavior and perception and things like that.
In normal behavior in normal behavior, do you need to include something of that personal level?
I think so yes.
And so this this instrumental correct use as I call it which is one one level of normativity isn't sufficient.
There should also be uh something more which is the um a broader type of of normativity and takes account of um yeah uh the the so the the social uh conventions for example.
But I guess the question is do you think that's a distinctively perceptual norm?
I don't care about perceptual norms, it's just a norm in action.
I don't know if it's distinctively per perceptual.
I think perception and action cannot be just cannot be uh separated in this type of behavior.
Well let me put it this way.
Uh does a normal subject, when they see the bed as something that could be lied down in, do they see it as something that's not to be lied down in now?
Um that's a phenomenological question, I think.
Um I think they just don't lie down in it.
I don't think they experience it.
I don't think they experience normally a bed as not to be laying down in.
Only perhaps when someone tells them go laying down in the bed, but normally it just doesn't occur to them to lay down when the situation isn't appropriate.
I think that the normal people don't think about a bed for something to lie down in.
Well, I was asking whether they see it that way.
They don't see lying that way.
It depends on the situation if your music is comes up as something in which you look at that normal right now, but these bases.
They only see it.
So when a normal person is tired of spend time, they'll have a relation to the bed, but that orders they don't go to it.
And the utilization of the person is just like the normal person, except that the relationship objects isn't sensitive to the problems behind that.
Yeah.
You receive that, you don't think that.
So then you should that's true that you speak from brain studies that show something happening in those medial areas for the normal.
When the normal is engaged in the expert task or the task appropriate.
The performance monitoring system, for example, should should sell a different and there may be a very small chance that the people working on neural performance monitoring in Instagram are going to do experiments.
I really hope they will, but it's part of Shelby.
Okay.
So a bit more of the neuroscience part.
So the part of the brain damaged by these patients is the mediofrontal lobe.
This part of the brain is involved in motor planning and attention, in conflict and conflict monitoring and error monitoring.
The people working on that topic of monitoring, performance monitoring, there seems to be now quite some convergence of opinions that the medial frontal lobe should be seen as a general performance monitoring victim involved from various types of actions and that it monitors in relation to what they call anticipated rewards.
This is a notion that comes from reinforcement learning.
I'll come back to that later.
For the moment it's important to know that this part of the brain that's missing in these patients is seen as the interface of cognition, motivation, autonomic arousal and motor control.
And that projections from this area, there are motor neurons projecting to other motor areas in the brain.
One thing that I would like to call your attention to is that this part of the brain is also involved in pain fun in pain functions.
It um you can see it as like monitoring pain and it it responds to the uh affected distress of pain.
So another part of the brain is involved in more the sensory components of pain, but this part um uh has something to do with uh the unpleasantness uh experienced well in pain.
Um and I want to tell a bit about that now because um this may be an explanation why these patients are not um aware of the inappropriateness of their actions.
Um so the the um this dorsal ACT activity there is related to the felt unpleasantness of physical pain.
And recently it has been shown that uh that it's also uh active uh and plays an important role in the um experience of social pain.
And an example of that uh would be the experience of distress that you can experience when you are excluded from a social group.
And these uh Eisenberger and Lieberman, they did an experiment, an imaging experiment, um, where they put uh a person in a scanner and told him that they would be playing a game with other persons in two other people in two other scanners.
Um and um uh on the left you see uh a drawing of the first episodes of playing this game.
It's a virtual bulb tossing game, as they call it.
And so it occurred that the players are towing to each other and also charing to the small handwriter on the bottom, which is the the the the person that is actually being scanned.
Um and then in the second uh condition, uh at the beginning, this this uh person gets well the legal and he's uh excluded.
And then what these uh uh experiments did was trying to um uh to to locate the the the the correlate the activity in the brain um of the difference between these situations, which activity was um uh measured in the dorsal ACT again.
Uh and uh they correlated with uh a questionnaire about the experience distress that these people uh experience while being excluded.
And there's quite a strong correlation between uh this activity in the anterior singlet and this uh experience distress.
And the the experiment suggests that this may be uh the the experience of the social uh unpleasantness of pain.
Um this is just the first study on this topic, so it's not it has been replicated with just anything.
Um but what it suggests is that um the the area that gets lesion in these patients um can be seen as as an alarm system uh and perhaps also as an as a first responder of title first aid.
So there's this monitoring going on there uh which detects that things are going worse than than expected.
Uh then when when this happens at the same time uh it other areas of the brain are being engaged.
Uh but moreover there's also um uh this this self-unpleasantness uh that alerts the organism as a whole, or that may alert the organism as a whole.
This is not such a defect, it's just suggested.
Um and at the same time, this area, due to its motor capacities, also has the ability to give a first online reaction to what's going wrong to contribute to making a correct effect.
I think I skip this one.
And you can ask after the next two slides.
Unless there's very let me do one question that we have personal, you can either have any utilization.
Like I forget what he's done when he's making the wallets.
Is it that you just stick them in a wallet making a room and you'll use the wallet?
He was very good at making wallets.
Actually, his performance was not normal, but almost normal.
And well.
It wasn't compulsive.
No, it wasn't that.
It wasn't more like an approach to something.
No, there are people elsewhere.
So I guess my question is what exactly makes nothing utilization behavior.
So it usually case that you have normal, you put them in a room and you just start making wallets.
Where they put the patient in and let him make technological tests.
And at the same time, there's this object on them.
If he puts on the head, then they just score the occurrences of this behavior and then they also score if it's just throwing around if they're doing it like this, or if it's really normal sequence or something.
How far from much of the legalization they go?
So let's say you sit down as a green peers.
You show him a piano and he just starts playing data doing work.
Or is it that he just goes and lists up the talk to the piano?
I mean, how far is he playing to the fashion stuff?
One of the, again, one of the problems with the symbol needle, but it there's many and not many open questions.
But I suspect it would be always going.
I didn't do mine and just opening piano, it was certainly that same, but I couldn't say how you thought the slightly just opened the piano.
Since people can play the piano or at least the saxophone, so I read it in their sleep, then it looks like you're able to do a lot, even though you're you've lost the higher monitoring stuff.
Well, I was looking at the ballerina that's stuck in parallel and sockets.
How uncontrollable is I guess this is a bit of a spare situation because there's no visual cube to create a yeah maybe there's a lot of music.
I think the music may behavior in case of the Callerina, but this is disk activation, I mean it doesn't make much sense.
How much time has I made them go on?
You have a seven minutes.
Okay, so I'm afraid I won't have time to go into both freedom.
But anyway, I will just finish working again.
Yeah, no, but I will I will finish this one because I think it's important to speak about reinforcement learning and anticipation.
Partly because you write about reinforcement learning, excluding reinforcement learning in your articles on maximum grid and for example in the one on that team Cambridge campaign.
So anticipation, first a bit from medical T and then some more on neural aspects of anticipation.
So Medical T writes somewhere at a very important presence actually.
We are brought to the recognition of something which is an anticipation of or arrived at the objective, which means your aim.
And it is ensured by the body itself as a motor power, a motor project, radius and work, a motor intentionality.
Now in many places in phenomenology of perception, you see anticipation playing an important role.
It's very unsurprising because as I said in the beginning, when you acquire a skill, you acquire the ideas to anticipate.
There's also a neural basis of anticipation and the core of it is shown in this, no, not the core, but one of the core systems involved is shown in this video.
So on top, the green, no, let me first explain the experiment.
There has been done many experiments with monkeys and with humans where they which is a simple uh stimulus response uh uh um uh experiment where they um show a light and then um later on they they give the juice after a fixed uh period of time.
And in the early learning stages, which is on top of the in the green, when the light is greater than here, then um nothing happens in the part of the brain that is involved in uh or that yeah that contributes to amphication, which is the uh uh the the upper part of the brainstem, the uh dopaminatic midbrain.
Um these these graphs show activity in that part of the brain.
When there is a light flashed, nothing happens, but then when there is a reward delivered, in this case the juice, you see this this phasic increase in uh the dopaminatic activity.
Uh the this juice arrives uh unexpectedly and then the monkey or the human uh brain um activity in that area uh reacts to it after the arrival of this what they call rewards, in this case juice.
But the interesting thing is that with learning um you don't have to wait.
The the reaction of the of this part of the brain doesn't wait until the uh juice is being delivered, but anticipates its delivery.
So then when the light is being flashed, when the light is being flashed, there is already a basic increase in this uh dopaminatic activity.
Um and uh that's not even the late training stage, the blue uh figure here.
So um there is what they call back propagation.
The the uh the the flashing of the light already um makes uh triggers the reaction that normally would have been only there at the moment of arrival of the of the juice or the reward.
Then the lower figure is um when um when the lights flash, but then at the moment that uh you've learned to expect the uh the juice being delivered, there is no juice coming.
So um they call delayed reward because it's given later.
And then at that time there is this uh this activity again.
So there is um the light flashes, you expect the juice to come, but it doesn't come.
Um at that moment there is uh what they call negative reward prediction error.
Uh and next one when the juice is delivered, there is another um another response and increasing the dolphinetic activity.
This is important because this this type of activity um contributes to um to reinforcement learning and uh contributes to building a a system that is able to anticipate um yeah, to build a system that is able to anticipate rewards.
And not any rewards actually, basic to any anticipated action.
Um so this this system is called oh actually no, this this what we've seen so far about the the passive uh just sitting there and getting the juice uh are not um situation.
There is a more active situation where they have people uh choosing uh responses, which is called extra critic reinforcement learning.
Uh which is the paradigm coming from control theory and uh animal decision making.
Schulz is a neurophenologist working on this.
The idea is that with learning the system becomes able to anticipate future rewards.
The interesting thing for it is that there's no need for any goal representation here.
And that's because one part of the brain, what's called the adaptive critic, learns to predict future rewards and the other part of the brain, the actor, learns to select better and better actions.
It's being trained by the critic and it responds not only to the stimulus being given but also to the activation at a certain moment in the brain.
So it takes the current activation of the brain into account when it selects an action.
I'll skip this one.
There's increasing neurobiological plausibility for this type of learning to occur in the brain.
So it's even more useful, I think, to read this with this article on reinforcement learning and maximum grift.
Recently an fMRI study has been able to dissociate these two roles in the human brains before it had been done already in apes or monkeys.
And it becomes more and more clear that the dopamine protections from the midbrain play an uh an important uh computational role uh in anticipation uh or anticipatory behavior.
Um so what's the effect of this this phasic increase uh in dopamine that we've seen in the colorful picture before?
Actually, it occurs within about 100 milliseconds, so one tenth or two tenths of a second, very rapidly, rapidly enough to guide online behavior of the organism in the complex and uncertain environment.
And they tend to describe it as follows.
Doppler increases the likelihood that an action, a valuable action for the organism gets chosen now because this impact is immediate, but also in the future because of the learning.
There's also a theory on performance monitoring that includes this work on the neural weight of rewards by Schultz.
And they say that this area that gets damaged in utilization behavior, and that's involved in performance monitoring, shows that it receives these dopaminatic projections.
And when things go worse than expected, a basic cause in mid-brain dopaminatic activity triggers something which they call error-related negativity or O shit potential.
It's seen in in between experiments, it's just like the the same spot that you've that you've seen before in the colourful uh picture, it's a certain area.
Um, what's the singleton, uh as they call it?
Um it's like it's like the alarm signal that we've seen before.
It engages other uh areas uh perhaps or for top down control later on.
But more importantly, there's also something happened uh something happening immediately.
So there's some immediate uh adjustment to the situation.
Something goes seems to go wrong, something goes worse than expected.
Um this is the this is the moment that that it may be adequate to select another uh possibility for action.
Are you saying that that's directly disconcerting?
No, I'm not I'm not I I hope it will be related in some way to direct to this because in the end I try to figure out what will be the mechanisms underlying it.
Um but you cannot say it is direct to discontent.
No, no, of course it might be.
And interesting is that so it's the same type of area and it may be that this this experience of unpleasantness or so the the pain you say you feel when you when you experience something going wrong you can call it pain, the displeasantness of it, that that when this this area gets damaged often with point to the documentariatic signal arriving doesn't occur.
But it's at the moment it's just open and so this part of the brain is involved in value-based action selection as they call it.
So guiding decisions about which actions are worth doing based on the expected value.
We take into account the future and this is possible thanks to the critic activity that we've seen before.
And it's interesting that the value-based action selection occurs not in just any situation, but in situations that seem to fit everyday activity very well, namely free choice situations, which can be distinguished from situations where an experimenter tells you what to do.
And moreover, there's activity there when immediate action is required.
So it's online directly after a change in expectations like you would correct your behavior online immediately when your copy slips out of your hand.
Now going back to utilization behavior, so now we've seen all this about performance monitoring and the important learning.
Can we say more about what may be the mechanism underlying utilization behavior?
So the area that's used as virtual HTTP and PSMA, such a lesion may increase the likelihood of the selection of an inappropriate possibility for action.
The impaired monitoring because of the lesion may lead also to less corrective action being taken.
And as the same area is also involved in the unpleasantness experience with an error or with social pain, lesion there may lead to the absence of an awareness of and if that is the case, then you would expect because of the relation between physical pain and social pain, you would expect patients with utilization behavior to have some attenuated unpleasantness experience of physical pain.
So that would be a a way to test uh test this.
I I'm going back to Sanskrit's actual question while you were involved.
So skeptic might say that you're purchasing non-deliberation and non-judgment at the personal level by just shifting them all down to the quite personal level.
You've got mountains, you've got boundaries, you've got volumes, you've got volumes, you've got deciders.
So are you really giving a possible non-judgmental effect?
Stop giving give a quick answer, really.
Okay.
A way to account for that would be and by means of the the the the critic role that that that um that is able to do all this that should be able to do all this without uh uh taking uh without referring to explicit goals and explicit deliberation.
So that would be the way to go uh like like Professor Greyfus did in his article on reimportant learning.
The actocritic models would be the way to