We're going to go being going on to freedom, but I want to go back to temporality.
Freedom is sort of a freebie in the sense that we don't really need it to understand the rest of the book.
Whereas, of course, as disorganized as ever, the book should have ended with temporality and put freedom before temporality, because it keeps promising that temporality is going to be the big final aha where it all fits together.
And then you get temporality, and then he met Gard in a cafe and they had a big fight about freedom.
So you get another chapter on freedom, which is a very interesting chapter.
I definitely want to get to it today.
I think it's one of the most understandable and original of all the chapters.
But there's this funny situation about temporality we have to talk about first.
I can't decide whether it shows that I'm very smart or very stupid.
But what happened was that I complained and complained that there was no place in the temporality chapter where he talked about what he should be talking about, which is my world prior, sorry, the world prior to my world.
And in the same way, it should be the present prior to my presence.
There ought to be a shared present on which I am open and from a perspective.
And there wasn't any in that chapter.
And remember, I said therefore it's the most confused chapter I've ever seen because sort of 95% talks about my present and in the last paragraph it mentioned the present.
Well, as I say, either he's stupid or brilliant or just memory, he does talk about the present.
He talks about it in two very important places.
He talks about it, of course, not in the time chapter, that would be asking too much.
But in the freedom chapter and in the thing in the natural world chapter, the piece of temporality that's crucial to the whole time chapter, there it is.
So I'm going to talk about it.
I would be so pleased that I had sort of invented it, except, of course, I read the book before, and I probably just remembered it.
But in any case, whatever, we've got to talk about it.
First, reminding you of the problem that we're supposed to be talking about.
That is, he's talking about on 483 in the first paragraph, which you need to think for transposing it.
He talks about my field of presence in the widest sense.
And you don't know what he's talking about there, but it seems to be very much mine because he goes on and talks in the paragraph about my present and my life and so forth.
And then, about two-thirds of the way down, he gets to mentioning the field of presence, just in the passing, everything causes me to revert to the field of presence as the primary experience and so forth.
So, and I just find it all utterly confusing.
And on four, I'm not going to go into this much, but to remind you of the problem.
So, on 490, he's talking about two-thirds of the way down, that one single explosion or thrust, which is subjectivity itself.
We must understand time as the subject and the subject as time.
Well, that all makes it come back, seemingly to me again.
And so that every, it's as if I said last time, and I still believe it, it's as if in this chapter he has one foot in Husserl, which is always about my subjectivity and my present and my time, and occasional glimpse of Heidegger, which is always about openness through the shared world and shared time.
And it doesn't, it goes on flipping mostly back and forth till the end of 503, on 503.
And then you get about halfway down that paragraph.
The two temporalities are not mutually exclusive, as our two consciousnesses, because each one knows itself by projecting itself into the present where they interleave.
So now it looks like something like there are two different temporalities, two different streams of time, in inner sense, you would have to say, that project themselves into the shared world, and there they intervene.
They interleave.
That's not good enough.
I mean, that still seems to give the priority to the subject, which then projects this time, and then you put together out of it a shared time.
That would be Husserl's view.
That would be Sartre's view.
That shouldn't be Merrill-Conte's view.
And then he gets it more together as my living present.
That's still my, opens up on a past, which I nevertheless am no longer living, and on the future I no longer live and never will.
My living experience, that's this streaming inner something.
And perhaps never will.
I can also open to the temporalities outside my living experience, inside and outside mine.
And V.
It's just crazy, and acquire and acquire a social horizon as if I could be a living, living present first, then get a horizon.
And then, and then so that you get a collective history which my private existence takes up and carries forward.
And I wrote in the margin, what happened to nature time?
And then he quickly, the solution of all problems of transcendence is to be thought in the thickness of the pre-objective present in which we find our bodily being, our social being, and the pre-existence of the world.
Well, that is nature time, but he doesn't say so.
And that's as far.
And so we have to go look for it.
Olivier helped me by saying, you messed up last time.
The natural time you're looking for is in the book.
And I said, I missed it.
I have to go back and read the time chapter more carefully.
And he said, no, it isn't in a time chapter.
That would be asking too much.
It's in the freedom chapter.
Okay, so we'll go to the freedom chapter on 525, starting really at the bottom of 424.
What?
524.
Sorry.
And now, there's a whole different story about time.
It's about 10 lines up.
There is therefore no occasion to ask ourselves why the thinking subject or consciousness perceives itself as a man or as an incarnate or historical subject, nor must we treat this apperception as a second order operation which somehow performs starting from its absolute existence.
Somehow, I don't know what that means.
And now comes this weird new thing.
The absolute flow.
That's going to turn out to be nature time.
It could have been my own most private time.
And if that's what it is in historical time time consciousness, but it isn't here.
The absolute flow takes shape beneath its own gaze as a consciousness, a man, incarnate subject, because it is a field of presence to itself, to others, and to the world.
So now it's looking like, at least what I'm going to say is, you better sort of expect him to say sooner or later, that there's going to be a field of presence, and I'm going to be a perspective on it.
And so let's go on and because this presence throws itself into the natural and cultural world from which it arrives at an understanding of itself, we must not envisage this flux as absolute contact with oneself and density with no internal fault, but as a being which is in pursuit of itself outside.
Now this is getting what you want.
If the subject makes a constant and at all times peculiar choice of himself, one know why his experience always ties up with itself and presents him with objects in definite historical places.
So this is not his view.
We have why we have a general notion of time valid through all times, why finding the experience of etherebus links up with that of others.
You better not be starting to be a subject.
You keep talking about Sarter or Husserl there.
Okay.
But it is, but it is the question of itself which must be the question itself must be questioned.
What is the question?
How does my private, inner, subjective, temporal experience connect up with the world so that there's continuity in the world, connect up with others who are temporal?
That's the wrong question.
Well, what is given?
And now we finally get what we want.
It is not one fragment of time followed by another, one individual flux then another.
There is a taking up of each subjectivity by itself and of subjectivities by each other in the generality of a single nature.
Now, he was getting close in this intertwining of subjectivity, but now the intertwining of subjectivity doesn't seem to be what sort of you get at as second order when you find out how my subjectivity links to yours.
No, there's something behind it all.
A general nature, the cohesion of an intersubjective life and a world.
The present mediates between the four itself and the four others, between individuality and generality.
And then skipping one sentence because he doesn't do anything there.
It just free lines from the bottom.
I am an intersubjective field.
That's what you want to be.
I mean, that's what you want him to say.
That would mean I am an openness on the world.
I am an intersubjective field, not despite my body and historical situation, but on the contrary, by being this body in this situation, and through them, all the rest.
Well, it's still a little hard to get, but I take it through them meaning being a perspective on the shared nature time.
Well, if that was all we had to go on, I must say we wouldn't know for sure what to think.
But there is more to go on.
At the middle of 426, he talks about a little above the middle, the notion, oh, yeah, five for correcting, but I thought 526.
The notion of a generalized or natural time, he's going to say, we have seen that there is no natural time if we understand the time of things without subjectivity.
Remember, that's the beginning of the time chapter.
But if you try to have a time laid out without any subjectivity, then you would just have sort of a blocked universe of, it wouldn't make any sense.
There'd be no temporality and no way to get into it.
But we don't want, there won't be no natural.
And that he agrees with Heidegger.
There is no natural time, if that means time without some involvement of Dasein or whatever we are in it.
Because Heidegger thinks, and I think Nero Ponty thinks, there wouldn't be any now, and there wouldn't be any earlier and later, except insofar as we bring the now into something like a universe in which without us there would just be a succession of states, that there wouldn't be any now state.
And that's what Heidegger calls the time-free movements of nature.
He's got a fuel about this.
But I think Aeroponte has a similar view.
Nature by itself doesn't have temporality because it doesn't have now and earlier and later.
On the other hand, it isn't that we sort of out of our inner streaming experience constitute temporality either.
I mean, it's the usual thing.
We have to link up with our subjectivity and unlock this natural time.
And there wouldn't be any natural time until we unlocked it.
And when we don't make it up, we do unlock it.
We get in sync with something that's happening in nature, this usual story, this are boot-given.
And when we get in sync with it in the right way, we then experience a natural time which is shared, when our body's human, which is impersonal and in that sense shared, gets in sync with this natural something or other, then we get a shared nature, time, of which we then all have, which we then all have perspectives on.
So he doesn't want the generalized notion.
There's no natural time if we understand the time of things without subjectivity.
There is, however, at least a generalized time.
That's what we're trying to understand.
And about 15 lines from the bottom of 526.
As long as we place an opposition with no mediator before itself and the inn itself, start and so forth, and fail to perceive between ourselves and the world this natural foreshadowing of a subjectivity, this pre-personal time which rests upon itself, acts in the sustaining the upsurge of time.
So there is a pre-personal time which rests, which is somehow there, and then we, by getting in sync with it, make it into the upsurge of time which we experience, I guess.
I mean, I'm giving you the clearest passages.
It makes it sound, just if that's any help.
How many have had contacts with asking and forgetting?
Well, it's as if there's something which in itself isn't temporal.
And then there's us and our way of getting in touch with it, which makes for their being a shared time.
Whoever talks about this has got to get a shared time out of it somehow, because we, as Heider says, we all say the same now.
This gets to be a mystery in personal thought.
And it sounded like a mystery when you talk about my presence.
Why is my presence going to be like the same present as your presence?
So there's got to be something in nature which is general and something in us which is general which gets together with that something in nature and produces this impersonal shared nature time.
And then I'm going to keep saying that's the present.
That nature time has a constantly shifting presence.
And it's shifting, so this unboxing thing I don't want to go back to, so that what's in the future gets nearer and nearer, and then it recedes into the past further and further.
That's the field of presence that we all open on.
Okay, let me see.
Let me just make sure I've got every quote that I can find that will help.
Oh, no, there's still another whole bunch of quotes.
So let me look.
Now we're really going to go to Did We Do Thor and He Dead.
Yeah.
Now, now for more on the subject, bring into page 385, where he talked about it already when he got to the end of the thing in the natural world.
And he talked about it, I guess, a little clearer, about six lines down in 385.
The natural world is the horizon of all horizons, the style of all possible styles, which guarantees for my experience a given, not a will unity, a given, not a will unity, underlying all the disruptions of my personal historical life.
Its counterpart within me is the given, general, and pre-personal existence of my sensory functions, in which we have discovered the definition of the body.
So there's this business again.
In me is this pre-personal something, and out there is the natural world.
And together, they produce this shared experience of time.
At the bottom of 385, my last attempt almost to tell you what it's about.
No, 386.
Oh my gosh, that can.
My perceptual field.
Now, what can my perceptual field mean at this point?
Well, it's got to mean my point of view, this shared, impersonal, natural time.
And it looks out that way.
My perceptual field with its spatial horizons, I am present to my surroundings.
I coexist with all the other landscapes stretched out beyond it.
And all these perspectives together form a single temporal wave.
That's the unboxing and boxing thing of the world's instance.
So my perceptual field connects me up with the temporal wave, which is this woo-shin presence that's coming through and constantly shifting at a whole thing so that the present keeps changing and taking up the future.
That's got to be the world.
So through my perceptual field with its temporal horizons, I'm present to my present, to all perceiving past and future.
Well, it isn't going to get us any more than we've already got.
But it's getting clearer, I guess, I mean, at least I hope so, that there is a my perceptual field and a my present, but it's not basic one.
It's the opening on the natural time, the general, the pre-personal.
That's got to be the basic one.
Just keep saying to yourself, as far as I can tell, the slogan that either you're going to have my world prior to the world, then you've got SARS and first of all, or you're going to have the world prior to my world, and then you're going to get either in Verlo upon T.
And the same thing has got to be true of time.
So you're going to get either my stream of inner experiences as prior to a shared, objective, public, temporal world where we interweave them and constitute the shared one.
Or you're going to get an a shared, natural, general, temporal shifting field.
And then you're going to have to get some story about how my subjective perspective sort of scans that in.
But then it'll be the world prior to my world.
Now, there are uh there's of course and I want to say I got to be careful something.
There's no the temporal world though prior to my perspective on it.
The right thing to say is that we are open heads.
We turn toward a fair natural temporality from a perspective.
We have our own life, our own history, and so forth.
And that's what he wants, that's what he should be saying.
I just let me just I go get two more quotes.
Now maybe one.
Okay, this is the final one, 387.
I just saw what I was looking for earlier and couldn't find, so let me put it in where it goes.
Remember the first thing I read to you said something in the widest sense, and I didn't know what the widest sense was, and I have question mark in the market.
You don't know that.
What's the first thing I read to you?
That's my field of the 43, of course.
483, my field of the presence in the 483.
Okay, you're section 483?
In your book, in my book.
48.
487.
Oh, yeah, you're right.
Okay, you're right.
That's where it is.
Yeah.
So the top in my field of presence in the widest sense.
Now, what is that?
Well, it's related to 387, the time in the widest sense.
You could sort of get them together because otherwise, that phrase, he thinks you remember that phrase, because he presumably wrote that chapter the day before he wrote this chapter.
We don't remember that.
I was looking for it.
I dimly remembered it.
So, because otherwise, who knows what time the lightest could be.
Okay, so time in the widest sense, that is the order of presence in the widest sense.
What?
Well, I mean, one of them says the field of presence in the widest sense, right?
I'm 483.
But I'm now on 387.
I think they're related.
I think they're the same.
Time in the widest sense.
Time in the widest sense, that is the order of coexistence as well as that of succession, is a setting to which one can gain access.
See, this is now this idea I want.
The public time, which we have access to from a perspective.
It's the coexistence is a setting to which one, that is, an individual, can gain access and which this individual can understand only by occupying a situation and by grasping it in its entirety through the horizons of that situation.
So you've got a situation, your situation has horizons, and that gives you the grasp you get on the totality of this shared time, which is, I think, what he calls nature time, general time, impersonal time, and all that.
I think that's all I could say about it.
I mean, if anybody wants to say anything about it, go ahead.
I don't have any more to say about it.
Yeah.
Which book then?
Of the new magician.
The new one.
How you managed to make yours stay open?
What's it?
279?
279.
Okay, great.
Let's see.
Look at all.
The page down, it says perception is always in the vote of the impersonal one.
Yeah?
It's not a personal action, even enabling me to do a question of this to my life.
Person who, in sensory exploration, gives a past to the present and directing towards the future is not myself as an October subject, but myself insofar as I am a body and able to look.
Yeah, that's as far as that is the essence of time.
Yeah.
There would be no present, that is today, no sensible role because thickness and the gospel of richness, the perception in Hegel's words did not retain a past in the depth of the present, so that contraval.
That past with that depth.
So he specifically says perception is always in the vote of the impersonal one.
Where does he say that?
He says that in the first sentence I read.
Always in the motive.
Okay, and that's temporality too.
It's a motive and the personal one.
No hope.
I'm trying to see if there's any more because this is another piece of the time story.
I didn't know he was around.
I'm going to put it in here.
Okay, so we get it also in 279.
And does it, because I'm always hoping he'll say clearly that the way that I have a perspective on this general share of impersonal nature time, he never sort of doesn't say it, but he never denies it, but he never says it in so many words.
Okay, I put together the best I could.
Anybody else want to say anything about it?
I'm ready to go on.
Yeah, Albert.
Just keep going.
Your presentation, I was puzzled about the role of the size of this is always funny, and I'd like to know if you agree with them.
Because that one said, I was thinking about what you said earlier about the pre-personal perception of saying tree's color.
The pre-personal perception of the tree's color is not supposed to depend on users of the world.
So why should the pre-personal perception of time in anyone's kind of interception world?
And then, of course, the answer is that it doesn't.
But that which is perceived, experienced pre-personally in a temporal fashion, must also be that very same thing which is accessible interpersonally.
Just as that which is perceived as the color of the tree must be available to another perspective as well.
That's good, that's good, that's right.
Just as the thing is always experienced from somebody's perspective or other, but it's the shared thing that we all have perspectives on.
So time is always experienced from somebody's situation or other, but it's the shared thing that we all have percept the shared time that we all have perspectives on.
That's what you're saying.
Right, but I think to be consistent, he doesn't want to be able to do that in some sense, my experience of time to anything that is other people.
No, did I say that?
No.
No language they worry.
That's what he was saying.
So I was just trying to.
I wasn't going to challenge it.
He's doing Steve.
I thought it wasn't great.
Okay.
I thought it was my.
I stunned.
Okay.
Before you said though, I was saying one thing about that just repeat in my own term, in my own words.
Yeah, just that we don't make up the shared time by interweaving the personal times any more than we make up the shared thing by interweaving the perspectives on it.
I'm just repeating the same point.
And that's why I think it's bad for him to talk about interweaving.
That makes it sound too much like that I have to construct the shared thing out of the perspective.
Maybe not.
But I mean, at least if anybody thinks that, he shouldn't be saying anything like that.
Okay, now.
Well, he does.
I think the end of the passage sounds very worried and like that.
When he favorably decides Husserl and the self-constitution of your time.
He does not favorably decide against him exposively.
Well, let's go.
Where are we?
See, in my book, there's just this passage I'm thinking of, views at the bottom of page 240, because in your book, it was involved in knowing.
Oh, well, maybe he.
It will be by thinking about time, explaining how it exists only for subjectivity.
Since without the value, the past would itself be no longer featuring yourself to be not yet.
So being in the time.
And however, that you can study that God or refer with Husserl to a self-constitutional time.
Okay, well, I don't understand where he's writing in order to protect the tendency.
And they're like, well, that's that's possible.
But to begin with, a lot has got to do with the notion of subjectivity, whether there could be a shared pre-personal, non-individual, non-private kind of subjectivity.
Because he does, we don't don't think that I'm saying that you could have time without subjectivity.
Remember, he's very clear at the beginning of the time chapter.
Dependent objective, there is no such thing as purely objective time.
So the question is, what sort of subjectivity?
What does he mean by subjectivity?
And there must be several.
And something like my individual private subjectivity would be one possible thing.
My perspective on the world would be, I think, the right notion, one of the right notions of subjectivity.
And then this shared nature thing, which we all produce together by our shared body set to deal with things, that still got subjectivity in it, but now it's not talked about from the point of view of each individual perspective, but as a kind of co-production of human beings in nature.
That's the good one.
That's what I think he calls nature time.
I mean, nature time tends to be your time and my time, and it better not be something that we sort of constitute out of our individual times.
It ought to be this co-production of bodies with all of our bodies with this universal unlocking schema produced, co-produced along with whatever there is, this group being out there, nature time.
But it's got subjectivity in it.
That's right.
He's clear about that.
And so is Heidegger.
So is Husserl.
The question is, what sort of subjectivity?
I think in Husserl, it's this private inner streaming kind of experience of time, which is the subjectivity.
I think in Marilo-Ponte, it's supposed to be the shared, well, that's the complicated one.
The pre-personal, general, natural time seen always from some perspective, experienced always.
All I want to keep saying, and now I'm going to stop this, is you've got to keep your eye on the phenomenon.
Isn't that how it is?
Don't we all experience ourselves as empty heads turned toward the present from each of us from our own experiencing of the present, from our own perspective, but it's one shared time that we all feel we open onto.
Yeah, with.
Okay, well, when I speak of the phenomenon, it seems like if we all died, the Earth would have been here way back when.
You know, if Earth was here before we were all born, now we died.
That things are going to keep on going, and that part of it's fine is that the plants exist in time, that they grow and that you know.
And it would have happened whether we were ever around or not.
Yeah, and it all just happens in time.
So that's, you know, I think the phenomenon I see advanced in nature.
Are you agreeing or disagreeing with Marillo-Pontino and with me?
That means two different things.
Well, first, I'm just trying to stick to the phenomenon.
Okay.
Second, sort of in response to something that you said of any during Berlin, you talk about like a brute eating or something like this.
And this is precisely why I used them as being a kind of transformer.
Oh, Scott, I thought that's what you were having.
That's fine.
Remember, that's the subject.
This will come back for sure in the last meeting where I said we could devote the whole time to what kind of idealist he is or isn't, and time will bring it, of course, all back, but not now.
Yeah, I sort of...
Let's not talk.
I mean, I said Brood Being, which is, by the way, not a phrase from this book, but a phrase from the next book, The Visible and the Invisible, the book that he was writing and never finished.
But Broot Being is sort of always surrounding this group in the background, so to speak, because it's that whatever it is that we have to unlock in order to get a world and we have inherited.
Behind it, it helps me to think of him as a kind of evolutionary epistemologist.
I don't know if that occurs to anybody else or not, and he wouldn't like it because, of course, that would suggest being much too much of a realist.
But it does look like whatever it is and our body schema for coping with it, which is innate and which has always been in human beings and will always be not only human beings, but all higher primates.
And it works to unlock the world.
But you wonder why in the world do we all have this?
And why in the world does it work to unlock the world?
Well, you can't help thinking it better.
It's evolved to do just that.
And I don't, Merlot Ponty wouldn't say it, but if it helps you to think about it, to think about it that way, it helps me.
I mean, that makes it so much less of a mystery that we all share, us and the primates and the pre-linguistic children and so forth, a general, impersonal body schema that enables us to perceive objects with stable properties and perceive time as pattern and so forth, get a grip on space and so forth.
All the stuff he talks about is somehow supposed to be the way nature is.
Well, I don't know what nature is before we get a grip on it, but whatever it is, that what nature is, is the sort of thing that this kind of schema can get a grip on.
And this sort of schema is there because it can get a grip on nature.
I don't think even Nero Ponty would want to deny that.
It's just that saying, and thank goodness and why not, and evolution, I don't think he wants to talk about that.
Yeah, no.
If he said, yeah, I don't want to challenge the shared time thing, but it's just that the experience of time was the moment that I have any kind of perception on that time is when I have a mistake between my I have respect for receiving the shared schema, either when it passes very slowly or it's good.
I mean, these are the moments that I have any knowledge about the phenomenon of the market.
I think some of you could write an interesting paper on that.
So I wonder if Michael was kind of what it doesn't want to do.
I think that's a terrific question.
And I have an answer which I've given, I think, once or twice already, but it always looks different in different contexts.
I think that when there's a kind of breakdown, then you have a different experience of time and you experience the inner time as your own temporal perspective which can be in or out of sync with other people's time and with nature time and it looks like that must be and this is the crucial move, the basic one, that inner stream of time, and it must look like this other one, this shared one, is some kind of construction out of it.
That's how it certainly looks to Dart.
I would say that's how it certainly looks to visceral but then if Olivier were here, he would probably say no.
But in any case, and what is Mario-Ponty supposed to say to that?
What would I say to that?
That's this issue about whether your experience is transformed when you have a breakdown and reflect on it.
And it's supposed to be the idea that then you experience yourself as having private experiences, as having your unique temporal inner flow and so forth.
And then the question really becomes the issue: is that the way it was when everything was going right and you were coping?
And then the answer is, well, no.
But then, did you discover that that was what was going on when you were supposedly all shared in this transparent coping in this shared world?
Well, as soon as you say yes, if that's a discovery of what was really going on all along, then my world is prior to the world, and my time is prior to nature time, and so forth.
So you've got to say, if you're a Mario-Ponty or a Heideggerian, that kind of reflection, which produces an ego and a self and a stream of innerness and all that, isn't a discovery, it's a production.
It's the way that shared time is transformed when you reflect on it, which is usually either doing philosophy or having a breakdown, or maybe the other thing.
But anyway, so then that's the deep, deep issue.
And his, and in remembering the answer to the coquetoe, he's got to say, and he does in effect, that the I think can come to uh accompany every representation, as Kant says.
But you can't read that back and say that there is an I think that's constituting and accompanying every representation anyway.
In fact, you've got to deny it.
But that's a great place to stop.
You have a new quote or something?
But I think Ralph Ponty would say that you experience this phenomenon of shared time whenever you run into something that's familiar.
Whenever you turn the doorknob, this is based on your path and habits of turning the doorknob.
I mean, I think that's what he means by experiencing the phenomenon of time.
That's not quite what I think.
I mean, not that I disagree with it.
But that happens too.
But no, no, no, they're going to we can't plunge back in.
I just let's stop while we're ahead.
Or if we're not ahead, if we're going to stop anyway.
Well, happy reflection on the fucking paper.
I can't say more.
And I don't want to say more, because freedom, we've got now time, very little time for freedom.
And it's important because it's so good.
It's such an interesting chapter.
You can do it sort of on your own, it's so good.
And you can do it probably after you've written your paper, since I doubt if anybody's going to be writing their paper.
Anybody writing on the freedom chapter?
So, okay.
But still, we should talk about the freedom chapter.
To begin with, just curious, and I won't be upset if I thought if you tell, just tell me the truth.
How many have already read the freedom chapter?
Okay, the really interesting question is, how many realize that the first uh four pages are not a marvel pong tea?
Or did you get suckered into it, as one always does?
Okay, the first convincing four pages starting from four from five oh four to the middle of five oh seven will start.
And it's the claim that consciousness is a pure nothingness and gives whatever meaning anything has to anything.
And it therefore follows necessarily.
Tartan patrol Husserl, as having this notion of this meaning-giving consciousness, radicalizes it to pure nothingness and pure freedom.
and then says that whatever meaning anything has is up to the individual.
Then you get this amazingly pure kind of freedom in which you can, everything gets its significance according to you.
Therefore, there can be no causal action on you from the outside because you'll have to give to whatever has any causal effect on you, whatever meaning it has.
I forget whether it starts here or somewhere where he talks about the people who give to their athletic activity the chance to enjoy the nature and to enjoy hard work, and the other people who think it's like him, the nerds who think that it's sweaty and unpleasant, and why would anybody ever go out and hike around in the outdoors?
And the answer is, you create a kind of outdoors which is exhilarating and good if you give it that meaning, and you create a kind of outdoors which is depressing and bad for your health if you give it that kind of meaning, and it's all up to you.
That's the first chunk.
And on 506, he's talking about that, then total freedom to give meaning to everything.
And then the next three pages, starting on 507, he rebukes Sartre by not yet by giving you his view, not at all.
He just takes Sartre to the limit and shows how crazy it is.
That starts the middle of 507, where he starts to say, if you believe Thark's view, you end up believing all sorts of crazy things, and that you can completely determine the meaning of the world for you.
And that goes to the bottom of 508, I think.
I mean, since Meryl-Ponty isn't telling us, we don't know.
But I think his view starts three lines from the bottom in the middle of the page.
We shall soon see that.
We as him and us.
Versus Thart.
He's now sort of taken Thark to the limit.
And now he's going to go on his version.
We shall soon see that we have indeed always the power to interrupt.
That's the proven start.
That's the freedom part.
Sartre's got a point that Merlopony never wants to take back.
That you can radically change your life.
It used to be in the little town where I come from that there would always be these alcoholics who would one day or the next would become born again Christian and completely un-alcoholic.
That just goes, and that's Sartrean freedom.
And that really exists.
But Merloponty is going to say again and again that that's always done on a background and so forth and so forth.
And that's sort of not the way to think about our normal kind of freedom.
So he says we shall soon see that we have indeed always the power to interrupt.
That he's never going to deny.
But it implies, in any case, the power to begin.
But there would be no severance unless freedom had taken up its abode somewhere.
I mean, you can't stop being an alcoholic unless you are an alcoholic.
And how did you get to be that?
And now freedom's taking up its abode somewhere and prepared to move it.
Unless there are cycles of behavior, open situations requiring a certain completion and capable of constituting a background to either confirmatory or transformatory decision, we never experience freedom.
So, and then he's off criticizing Sartre again, about ten lines down, as J.P.
Sartre himself observes, which is very funny because he almost never names Sartre.
He always usually says one can object.
It might be said, I don't know what game those two are playing with each other.
You realize this book comes out, I think, two years after being in nothingness.
So it's just every, it's in every philosopher's mind that already what Sartre said, and this is to take it as assumed that you all know Sartre code, and Merrill LePonty is finally getting his turn.
And so the big argument in this chapter is the blurred ideas that the limit on our freedom, there's a threefold limit on our freedom.
There's the shape of my body.
Well, maybe there's four if you want to cut it off then.
The shape and size and power of my body limits my freedom.
The way my perceptual system works, my own past as a sedimented background, and I think the most interesting part is about the power of the background.
My own past as a sedimented background limits my freedom.
And my own past as the history of my, he's got my class that you could say, my culture.
Let's just say that they're all this, I mean, being a Westerner, being an American, being in the working class, but all this shared stuff limits my freedom.
And in most of the cases, we're free also to break out of it.
But we can't break out of the first two.
So I ought to make a distinction, which I haven't in my notes.
The first two are the body-determined ones, literally bodies.
Certain mountains are going to be impossible to climb, he says, and certain passes you can get through, and certain passes you can't, because you've got a body of a certain size, and you've only got a certain amount of energy, and so forth.
That's not something you can fix.
And this wonderful example, Anthony Carpenter on the bottom of 5'11, you know, the way your perceptual system works is not something that your freedom can explode or totally transform or even mess with.
And those are those dots at the bottom.
The Gestalt figures is the way the visual system works.
And all the freedom in the world, you can't make those dots group any other way than in those set of seven or whatever it is fixed, I guess, fixed, group.
That's a wonderful, elegant, just brilliant refutation of Sartre because you ought to be able to just freely give them the meaning two sets of three groups.
I mean, I mean, yes, you could group them.
You could group them, you know, you could, in theory, you could move them around any way you want, group them any way you want, but your visual system won't.
And that's, so there are two body ones, the size and shape of your body and the way your perceptual system works.
And then there are two background ones, your personal history and the personal history of your culture.
Those aren't up for grabs in freedom, in the way that Sartre thinks.
Okay, now we can look at that in detail because it's all me.
So, what's the point here?
Starts at the bottom of 507, about the middle of 507, the start of his own critique.
And that's where the result, however, of the first inflection would appear to rule it out all.
No, that's the eternal critique.
And now, in 508, he starts in film, no, those and field consequences are few.
509 or so, we'll take my notes here.
His own positive view doesn't begin until 510.
At the very end of reduction out of Sword and Last Sartre, he tells you his view at the end of that long paragraph, about 15 lines from the end of the paragraph, the middle of 510.
By defining ourselves as a universal power of Zindgel, we should be used to that now, meaning giving.
That's Sartre.
We have reverted to the method of the thing without which, with the analytic reflection of a traditional type, seeks the conditions of possibility without concerning itself with the conditions of reality.
I read that partly because I said he had this distinction, which he uses a lot, that he never makes blame between the conditions of existence, or sorry, the conditions of possibility, which are sort of abstract logical analyses, and the conditions of existence, where conditions of existence, he calls it here conditions of reality.
I remember it as conditions of existence.
I don't remember whether that's because the translation is different or because the words are different, but call it either one.
There's something going on, which is not just the logical possibilities, but which make possible whatever it is, sorry, make possible, which word, somebody gave me a good word.
Enabling, yeah, which the enabling conditions.
The conditions of reality, the conditions of existence, the enabling conditions are what he thinks he's providing against sort of analytic philosophers and analytic phenomenologists like Christroll and Sark, who think that you shouldn't really worry about the actual phenomena, but just tell somebody about the logical possibilities.
So Sartre's arguments about freedom are extremely logical.
If you're a pure consciousness, if everything you experience has to be organized by you as a meaning giver, then, and then comes all these wonderful possible necessary possibilities, so to speak.
It all follows necessarily from a certain conception of consciousness, which Sark claims is just obvious, I guess, that we give it to you.
And he's going to say, no, if you look at the phenomena, you'll see something different.
You'll see the enabling conditions.
So I'm back to 510.
We must therefore resume the analysis of the Zen Gablung and show how it can be both centrifugal and centrifugal.
That is, how I can both give meaning to the world, and the world can give meaning to my life.
That I'm both this source of freedom and the receiver of these absolute limitations, body and history kind.
So, since it has been established that there is no freedom without a field, now has he established that?
I don't remember.
Mostly he's established it by being on SART and going to what happens.
Ah, yeah, well, here's a way to say how he establishes it.
And this has got to do with the background story.
He doesn't have much to say, by the way.
It's so devastating that you can say it with the dots and the climbing of mountains in a paragraph, and it's over.
I mean, Sartre just really can't explain that.
But he's much more interested in the history.
Now, why can there be no freedom without a field?
Well, I forget where it is in here.
But I think it's in here.
Sartre has the, well, actually, this is some other factor he talks about.
Sartre has, I remember now, it's in the Coventry chapter.
I mentioned it in class.
Sartre has a review about this person who has this adolescent crisis and then gives it a certain meaning, and then it turns out that they become a monk, and then it turns out that that was the wrong me, and so forth.
It looks like in Sartre, it's just up to you to give your life whatever meaning it just occurs to you suddenly to give it.
And now, I don't know if it's in here, but a better example is the gambler example.
Okay, well, it's something very good for him to talk about, and I don't know where he talks about it, but he must.
But anyway, Sartre has this great example, and I'll tell you because he shows you what Sarkrean total freedom looks like and why Meryl-Parnio Party thinks it's not freedom at all.
A gambler decides one evening that he's not going to gamble anymore, and he freely decides that.
The fact that he's been a gambler up to then all his life is irrelevant.
And he can do that.
That's like being born again and giving up drinking.
So he gives up gambling one night.
And the next night when he faces the gambling table, what has he got?
Well, he's pure freedom.
He's free to either give the previous decision the meaning, boy, was I drunk or crazy then, I'm going back to gambling, or the meaning, yeah, didn't I decide last night not to gamble?
Well, then I won't gamble.
But he's totally open.
He hasn't really decided anything.
Because at every moment, it's all up for grabs again.
When you've got that kind of total freedom, then there's no, it makes no difference.
It's only if the act of not gambling, and now I'm telling you more of what Narrow Party's story would be, is something which he, one, already is motivated to by something in the background.
If his wife doesn't like it or he's dumb things, some things, reality forcing you to give it up, and that you've repeated it enough, that may be sort of like dieting.
You can decide one day that you're not going to eat any goodies, and the next day, his goodies are so good, and maybe we should start God made you then, but not just yet.
Paraphrasing Augustine, who says, God made me give up sex, but not just yet.
But in any case, you can do that, but unless and you undermine it.
But or you can repeat your resolution, which is already based on some background, until it becomes part of the background.
And you are a dieter, or you are a non-gambler, or a teetotaler and stuff.
And then that that's because it becomes sedimented in your history.
I'm just telling you the story of the chapter rather than reading short.
When it's sedimented in your history, it then becomes, and this is very interesting, View, not that you couldn't possibly go back to gambling or eating the goodies and so forth, but it becomes less and less probable the more it becomes the background.
And so he thinks that you've got to introduce a notion of probability into your notion of freedom.
And then he gives a whole Sartrean story again.
I better keep up with where we are because it's suddenly become start again.
On 512, let me see where we are.
511.
Well, yeah, we should do these things right.
511 is where he talks in the middle of the page about our natural self.
And the natural self is the body.
And it can't climb the mountains that are too big and so forth.
The Alps can't be molehills for me, as he puts it.
And that's because, and I can't help reading this, below the middle of 511, because I have hands and feet.
The only place in the book where you know that the human body has hands and feet.
You don't ever know much more about the human body than that.
I think maybe someplace you find out, yeah, you do, if they have a face, because if you see the face upside down, it looks all weird.
But it's important to know that the body from Arila Clancy is so, he's making progress over everybody in the history of philosophy who didn't talk about the body at all, except as an object.
But boy, has he's got a long way to go to talk about the body and its front and back, up and down, balancing in a gravitational field, moving more easily forward than backward.
All that plays a crucial role in perception, but he doesn't know it.
I'm getting you a quick blurb for TOTUS's book, which I mentioned before, Body and World.
I mean, the great step forward of TOTUS is to try to describe the body in the philosophy so that, and show that, that the body having the structure it has is more than just what Berlopony says the body is, which is an I can.
It's the ability to move around and organize things according to the body schema.
But the body schema hasn't got a front and a back and an up and a down and hands and feet.
It's just this shared way we have of coping.
So, but if you go beyond that, you could have a whole story about how the structure of the body gives you the way we have state, the way we have time, the way we have objects.
You're going to read it.
You have to read it on your own.
So, yeah, we've got some hands and feet, which is quite amazing.
And then there's the docs from Gustav psychology.
And you can't change the glue.
And then you get back to Sartre on 512.
We should get used to this because he gives you signals.
The second sentence of the paragraph that begins: it is true not only of an impersonal of an impersonal, but, and in all abstract functions, such as there is something, so never mind.
Now, about present evaluations.
And now we're going to get the story about whether it's fun or not to backpack into the woods.
But it has been presentedly remarked that Sartre.
The pain and fatigue depend on causes.
It's up to me what the causes are.
That goes down to the line 15, roughly on 513.
And that gets us to the probable, which is by a jump.
Since freedom does not tolerate on 513 now, any motive in its past, my habitual being in the world, is each moment precarious and so forth.
But it now comes, and from Sartre's point of view, no matter how much, and freedom can blow your past sky high.
And remember, I keep wanting to say it can.
But, and remember, that's the teetotaler example.
It can.
However, having built our life, and now he gives an example, upon an inferiority complex which has been operating for 20 years, it's not probable we shall change.
Okay, well, that's a funny example for reasons I don't have too much.
I don't have time to fill in too much.
He's got, I'll mention it.
We should have said something more like, not the extreme pain of an inferiority complex, but something simple, like, having dieted for years, I'm not likely to take the chocolate clear that comes by in front of me.
And certainly, people, alcoholic anonymous people, don't take a drink every once in a while.
And that's because the more it gets sedimented into the background, and we'll get to that in a while, the more these things don't show up as tempting anymore, or they show up as unpleasant and so forth.
And that's going to help you and win your freedom.
But he's got a whole theory, and that's good and right, and that's the right phenomenology of the normal way your past goes in front of you and determines what it makes sense for you to do, determines it's too strong, makes it probable.
Well, organize what it makes sense for you to do, like eat every goody that comes around or refuse everyone.
But it doesn't take away your freedom, but it makes it improbable that you're going to eat the next goody you've done so long because it doesn't look tempting any.
But you put on a bat or something.
That's the way it stands.
But then the inferiority complex is a really different story.
He's got a whole theory of psychotherapy in here and psychopathology.
And I'm going to s say about two words about it and then you can read it on the website if you don't have time.
I've written a paper on it, which I think is the definitive word on the subject, probably because it's the only word on the subject.
But he's got a whole view about transforms Freudian depth psychology with Marlow Country and breadth psychology.
That is, the idea that your background can become so pervasive that it determines your sense of reality completely.
And then you will get something like, take this example, this inferiority complex person who thinks that all of life is about who's the inferior and who's superior and knows that they're always on the losing end of that.
Or it could be the opposite.
I just saw a French movie yesterday.
Look at me.
Anybody's seen it yet?
There's this Frenchman, typically a Frenchman, who has got this sort of superiority complex, that only he that he knows everything and everybody ought to pay attention to him and that only his problems are really worth thinking and worrying about and so forth.
Anyway, you could have that, but let's stick to the inferiority person.
I mean, if it becomes your whole sense of reality, you're going to be stuck with it all your life.
But because there's no way to see that there are any other possibilities.
It looks like that's just how the world is.
And it's a question of that whether you're in school, it's a question of that whether you're in love, it's a question of that.
Everything turns into a struggle between who's superior and who's inferior.
But if there is any little marginal other things in there still, like maybe at least in, I don't know, computer games or something, you really can hold your own or beat everybody.
What happens in therapy is, that was a funny example, wouldn't work.
But I mean, if in your inner subjective relations there are bits of non-inferiority and superiority, then in therapy, you can gradually, by small deflections, he puts it, the therapist can get you to see that this isn't the only way to relate to everything.
And then bring more and more of your freedom back by emphasizing the part of the background that keeps it from looking like this is just the way everything is.
It just shows up that way and get you out of it.
He's got a whole beautiful story about that, which I'm not going to talk about, but we have to skip now from the inferiority and the background here kind of is placed in some sense.
Absolutely.
You just said that made that up.
That's absolutely right.
Exactly.
What's not accessible to you and representable to you isn't some idea, some representation which has gone into the unconsciousness, sending out messages by way of symbols in a Freudian way.
What's inaccessible to you and controlling your life and ruining it is the background.
That's what I mean by breadth psychology as opposed to death psychology.
Yeah.
And he's got it worked out.
He's got a theory of repression, a theory of France, and everything.
It's all scattered through the book.
You just have to pull it together.
Yeah.
There's another way of getting at the international art that we talked about in reference to Freud.
Absolutely.
And sort of all these things are in there.
I'll say them all right now because time might run out before I have a chance to say them.
He's got the same story that he tells about psychopathology.
He also gives, that's his adaptation of Freud.
Then he does an adaptation of Marx in which he does the same sort of thing, in which your class as a worker isn't something that you know and represent, and you have to be brought together with the other workers who know it and represent it and start a revolution.
And it also isn't something that you just don't know either.
You experience it all the time.
He has a list, a sort of touching list of what it's like to be a worker.
These were the big deal in France at the time.
Everybody had to be sort of out Marxist and everybody else.
And where is it?
You know, the upper left-hand side of the page, I saw.
It doesn't mean, okay, you depend on others and you haven't got as much money as you need and you have no future and so forth and so forth.
Anyway, you have this background and it isn't as if you are aware of it, which could be the intellectualist view.
It isn't as if it's just a historical, sort of not historical, a kind of an economic fact about you, that you don't have enough money and that you can be fired and hired and so forth and so forth.
It's neither.
It's a background style of life.
He introduces the notion of style very effectively.
The the inferiority complex is a kind of style that gets sedimented in your life, and being a worker is a kind of style that gets sedimented in your life.
And you what makes a revolution, and then he's got a whole story about revolution, which would be sort of like what it would be to be sure to be a worker, would be to become bit by bit aware of this and aware that you share it with other people and become a a member of the proletariat.
You're not a member of the proletariat just by thinking you are, and you're not a member of the proletariat by having a certain salary, which is the objective thing.
You're a member of the proletariat when you come to identify yourself as a member of the proletariat, which you can't just freely and arbitrarily do, which is what's our thought.
It takes a lot of effort in therapy or in Marxism to get this background, which looks like reality, and thus into the foreground so that you can little by little overcome it.
So so uh sort of Marxist activism is a kind of therapy to the working class.
Uh so now let me see where we are.
Um could I keep jumping ahead?
Gringam and the problem did that.
We didn't probably switched we got rid of, we did, we did all that.
I don't know.
Where was the where was the I got sidetracked, I'm not sidetracked, it jumped ahead when we got to the the inferiority problem.
517.
513.
Okay, so let me get, okay, yeah, there we are.
Uh-huh, okay, yes.
Okay, yeah, the style is what is there in the background determining what it makes sense to do and what it doesn't make sense to do.
And that style in the background, either shared or in my own, I mean, they're both, I said, is what he's going to talk about, is a way that the background governs what you do.
I want to add a new note in here.
Governs what you do.
It doesn't empiricist cause you to do it.
And it isn't intellectualist.
It isn't something you believe, and therefore because you believe it, you do it.
Having an inferiority complex doesn't cause you to behave in a cringing, inferior way toward everybody.
And it isn't that you believe that you're inferior.
It's something that is the atmosphere of your life, as he puts it.
And it's something that's in your body, in your cringing attitude, and in your not looking people in the eye, and then you're already getting ready to be put down and so forth.
And that way the world shows up for you as you being inferior.
That's the way your background determines, again, what it makes sense for you to do, and thereby governs what you do.
Not in a causal way and not in a belief intellectualist way, but in this governing kind of causality.
And that's what makes it probable.
The governing causality is what makes it probable.
Because in the world, certain things make sense to you and other things don't, whether you're a worker or having a pure complex or dieting or whatever, that determines, not determines, governs what you do.
And governing is a probabilistic notion because you could break out of it, but you normally don't.
Yeah.
Ah, I don't think so.
It's time for a list.
It's close.
I've got a list here.
I'll patent you.
About four kinds of causality.
There's, so I'm here here.
I think he's got these different kinds of causality.
There's linear, physical, third-person causality.
It's Fumian constant conjunction.
It's Kant's, whatever it is, according to a rule, necessary succession according to a rule.
It's medieval.
It was a diffusion of power and capacity to natural kinds.
All of that, I think, he would, that's just, I think he probably calls it linear causality, though I didn't find a place.
Anybody know Carlhan?
I think third-person causality.
Third-person causality.
And it's the kind of causality of the in itself, of course.
It's physical causality.
That's not his contribution.
He has nothing.
Good, good.
Walter Freeman must have taken it over from there.
And Walter talks always about the wrong way of thinking about causality as linear causality.
Okay.
Then there's mental causation, first-person causation.
That's what Searle is interested in.
How my deciding to lift my arms can cause me, or my willing to lift my arm can cause my arm to go up.
That doesn't that's not linear physical causality, although it might it's grounded in it somehow.
But that's that's first person causality.
Now, neither of those, of course, is what Merlot-Ponty is interested in.
Now, then there's lived-body causality.
That's got to do with the third kind of being that we are, neither minds nor objects.
It has to do with responding to the solicitations of affordances.
It's the way my affordances cause me to act, which is not a physical kind and not an intellectual kind.
And I think that's what we should call the motivational one.
And motivation, I want to try to distinguish motivation from intentional art, so I think they sort of probably swap over into each other.
You could distinguish it.
If you make the way the lived body and the perceptual system are tending toward equilibrium and so forth, and how unstable the stalls tend towards stability, and how binocular images in your eye, in your vision, tend to be overlapped so you see depth.
And then when he talks about that, he describes all that in terms of motivation.
So it's not just responding to affordances, though that is part of motivation.
It's responding to all of the Stahl tensions that you have in your experience because you have the the perceptual system you you have.
And I think, yeah, okay.
I think that's probably the third kind of being, that is not first person causality nor linear causality, but this kind of motivational causality.
But there's another one, fourth one, circular causality.
He calls it dialectical causality, I think.
That's what I want to keep for the intentional art and the background governing.
The background governs people by way of having, so to speak, what was once something that they actually consciously did or decided or whatever, which they repeat enough until it becomes so transparent to them that it's like the light in the room.
That is, it's the background in terms of which they see whatever they do see.
And then things show up for them as making a certain sort of sense.
Their actions get into the very organization of their perceptual field.
So some things look attractive and others don't.
And that, of course, solicits certain actions from them.
And that's where it looks like motivational.
I mean, but I want to make the emphasis on the circularness.
That, when you act on it, you contribute to it.
So the more you act and make choices that you would be, the more that becomes part of the background, then the more that further inclines you to make these kinds of choices.
And that further becomes part of the background.
So that your past experience and your past choices aren't there as your explicit memories aren't acceptable anymore, but they show up to you, so to speak, in the way your world looks to what it makes sense to do and what it doesn't make sense to do, what's attractive and what's repulsive and so forth.
Which again solicits action-that's the circularity of it.
So, the background governs activity.
And that's I think that's his big contribution really in this environment.
Now, yeah, yeah, good.
We got four minutes.
I don't want to start.
I mean, that's really the bottom line for this chapter, so go ahead.
Just a third one, you know, significant source.
I don't, I'm not that sure.
But the language of psychotic and centrifugal is just like used to contrast abstract and concrete movements and trust and smartly categorize it in terms of in abstract backgrounds, where it's concrete and you can see a sort of slight background.
It's a bit interesting that not only Marxism and psychoanalysis are sort of formed now in the curve of the student.
If he enjoyed that, but now cartologies learned in them.
That's interesting, yeah.
I'm sure that he thinks about it that way.
I'm just going to say one more thing about the background, if I can.
The insight, which I haven't made clear enough yet, is that the way your background limits your freedom, I haven't been saying it, but not clearly enough, is it's because you don't see it.
I mean, what Sartre has to tell you is how you can change any particular thing that you can think about.
You can do something else.
That's first-person causality, and so forth.
What what governs you is precisely what you don't see and don't even take for granted, but is just there the way the back the the lighting in the room is when it's gone to zero, so to speak, and you don't see it because all you see is the colors.
But that's that's what it really interests Merloboni, and how you can get back your freedom by taking up little bits of the background and fixing it is what interests him, I think, and what his big insight is.
To sort of say how things can go in and out of the background and thereby go from the kind of first person causality to governing causality and back.
Yes.
A while back we had one example of level of sunlight and path and how once coming upon that evolved and that's what kind of sunlight.
How would according to his kind of perspective on Sarge Peter, how would he how would Sarge you would experience the dilemma?
Ah Sartre can't take account of it at all I think he would say.
It's that's a question of motivational stuff.
I mean it isn't wasn't up to him to seek Sartre I mean it would just be a joke sort of it's part of the perceptual uh limits on our freedom that we can't just see anything anywhere we please.
I mean Sartre would think so.
I mean Sartre thinks that I remember in that somewhere he says you could you can experience yourself as having one eye in the middle of your forehead or your arms turned into snakes.
You're free to do that.
Of course, they'll lock you up if you do that because they'll say you're schizophrenic.
But that's just their way of thinking about the kind of absolute freedom people have.
And so he's consistent.
I mean, I suppose he would say you can just think you're walking on the patches of sunlight till you fall, and then you can think that you didn't really fall.
And you can get any meaning to anything.
Sartre's clear about that.
I mean, Sartre couldn't deny the phenomenon that's experienced actually.
Wouldn't just freedom.
So what you're saying is for Sartre, bad faith begins to the point of misperception.
Good, you had mentioned bad faith.
That's the right thing to say.
I don't know.
Wouldn't you say that bad faith begins upon reflection on the misperception?
So the bad faith would begin when you deny that you had this misperception.
I think they're deeper kind of bad faith.
I think Sartre would say that bad faith is really in a perceptual level conformism.
You just don't want to be locked up, so you're going to not exercise your freedom to have one eye in the middle of their forehead and their arms turning into snakes.
And that's just, and it's bad faith in that it would be, you know, you could, dimly you know it, and you know how upsetting it would be to be radically free like that.
That's what, that's what gives you anguish, according to Sartre.
So you'd accept the normal way of looking at things.
Only, instead of this being the generality of the body and perception, this is just the normal cover-up.
And you abrogate your freedom and go along with it.
Sartre's going to have to say that.
It's interesting to bring it up.
About all this criticism from Harold Ponte, Sartre's going to have to say, you're just describing bad faith, you're just describing conformism, you could have done it otherwise, but you don't want to admit you could have done it otherwise.
And how does Sartre know that?
Because you, as a free, meaning-giving consciousness, Husserl, if Husserl is right, then you are absolutely free to give anything any meaning and any cause any meaning.
And if you don't, that's your bad faith.
That's not a very satisfactory answer.
I mean, even Sartre gave it up later after reading the time, gave up this notion of radical freedom.
It just won't work.
Okay, we should stop at that.
Now, where are we?
Oh, yeah, next time, Eric is going to tell us about the neuro basis of affordances, in effect.
And then the last time we're going to talk about idealism and realism.
I wonder if we should reverse that.
Wait a second.
Do you care whether you do it this next time or the last time?
I think you were going to hear that the whole schedule isn't here.
I see if I miss.
Well, that's their problem.
Let me discuss this for a second.
For those of you writing papers about idealism and realism, it would be better to put that before Eric.
I think I will put it on the website.
Tell your friends.
If they miss it, that's their problem.
They should be here today.
But it makes it how many would prefer to go do idealism and realism next and then Eric after that?
Nobody cares.
How many prefer to do Eric as planned in the program now and freedom next?
I guess.
What?
No, well, I want you to do what is helpful to people.
Let's do that one more time.
Some professor out there been in his class didn't afford.
Yeah, okay.
So does anybody have any strong feelings about this one or the other?
If not, we'll do it the way we plan to do it.
Okay, we're going to do it the way we plan to do it.
Erica's next time.