In the book you've got, on 497, he says clearly he's not an idealist or a realist.
And just to get that out of the way, so that that doesn't, I mean, so that that only says that there's a certain kind of realist he isn't and a certain kind of idealist he isn't, and we still have to figure out what in the world he is.
But let's read that at the bottom of 497.
We were once concerned, that is, in the structure of comportment, with gaining an understanding of the relationship between consciousness and nature, between the inner and the outer.
Or again, the problem was to link the idealist perspective, according to which nothing exists except as an object of consciousness.
He doesn't hold that view.
He does not hold the view that nothing exists except as an object of consciousness.
He's going to get rid of that.
And the realist perspective, according to which consciousness are introduced into the stuff of the objective world and of events in themselves.
Well, that's, I think, means that he doesn't, he's not a reductionist either.
When he says, realist in that way of talking, he means try to explain consciousness in terms of objective events in the objective world.
So he's not going to say that everything that exists exists only in so far as we in our consciousness exist and constitute it in some way, a view that one might think would be viscerals, and visceral defenders aren't here to defend visceral today, so I think it is lycerals.
And he's not going to be what lots and lots of people are now, a kind of reductionist who thinks, like John Searle, I believe, that in the end, all there is is finally physical particles batting around, and we've got to explain everything in terms of them, consciousness, meaning, et cetera.
He's not going to be that kind of reductive realist either.
Now, what he is is really interesting and complicated.
And so here's my story.
There are going to be four different levels of description.
And so the first one is the world as we perceive it.
That's this indeterminate perceptual person.
That's the world as we perceive it is indeterminate.
It's always got horizons.
It's always given to me from some perspective.
That already, I have a quote for that, but I think I've even read that quote once.
And in a way, he holds that that's the richest of all experience.
All whatever there is, that's the richest there is.
And perhaps he should have held that that's sort of what is ultimately real.
I wish he had.
I mean, I think it would be interesting because we were so close to what Rick calls the rich world ontology.
Namely, that the world is very, very rich, and one of the most rich aspects of whatever that being you have to say or something is very rich, and one of the richest takes on it is ours, and we get a lot of the truth of it.
But that isn't what it says.
We'll get there.
Yeah, there's one word.
Yeah, that's right.
I think that this world with its objects, which have always got more about them than we can ever fully discover, which have always gotten deterministic, but nonetheless have a structure, and we can explore it.
And there are people and bodies and trees and cars and desks and all that.
I wish he had just said that's what's ultimately real, period, and then gone on to just to talk about that he doesn't say that.
He does think that it's there is this perceiving that we do, and then he perceives everything from a perspective.
Maybe I will read that because that's sort of as far as he goes towards this endeavor realism of rich world of realism.
So that's, I don't think you need to even find it, but I read it once before.
The world is the field of experience, and we are nothing but a view on the world.
That's 406 is the middle of the page.
472.
Okay, on 472 here.
That can tell you where it is on the page.
That's about 15 lines from the bottom of Forest.
But then, I mean, that's just where you start.
But things get much more complicated.
Then, well, then there is our perceiving, our view on the world, always perspectival and unfinished and open.
And then number two is there is the perceptual world.
That's different than the world as we perceive it.
That's the shared world on which I've got a perspective and you've got a perspective.
And that world has inexhaustible details.
And then, you know, in your book, you'll still 451.
Now, 451 in this book.
In this one.
Yeah, I mean, the reason you'll see, I'm assuming things broke down and I couldn't have time to do all the copying, but right here at the beginning, I was still able to look in here.
So on 451, which is the end of a paragraph, the last 15 lines of a paragraph where you say there's a where it begins, our body.
It gets to go 15 lines before that paragraph.
451 on in the old ones.
No, sorry.
451 in the in sorry, in in ours.
And now Halv is looking for it.
Well, I'm going to go on.
Yeah.
Okay, so I'm going to read those 15 lines on 451 in ours.
I have had the experience of a real triangle.
And because as a physical thing, it necessarily has within itself everything that has ever been able, that it has ever been able or ever will be able to display.
So now it looks like it's part of the way the physical thing shows up in the perceptual world is that it's experienced at least as having within itself all these determinate characteristics.
Then he goes on, unless the perceived thing, see, it's the perceived thing, has for good and ever implanted within us the ideal notion of a being, which is what it is, there would be no phenomenon of being.
So there is a, this is very strange, but it looks like there is, in the world that we perceive, we can't help seeing it as having all these characteristics and completely determinate.
It's a good thing he says that, because I swear I do.
I mean, I think the desk has got all of its details completely determinate.
I think it would be wacky to think otherwise, that it somehow gets determinate when you go around and look for it.
None of us want to say that.
But I'm not quite sure of the status of this claim.
But it looks like it's the crypto mechanism, which is not a bad thing.
I could tell.
The crypto mechanism is the way we are led to extrapolate the way the perceptual world is perceived by us, indeterminate, etc., to the way our experience of the world is indeterminate.
We extrapolate that to a shared perceptual world of objects which are completely determinate.
That gives us our understanding of being, which I think is equivalent to this thing he says every once in a while, the in itself for us.
And we actually experience the in itself.
And it's, and that gives us our understanding that there are being, where being means everything is either this has this property or that property, and all of its properties are in.
That's what it is for something to be to have and so forth.
We really got that.
And but, and now we go on, somehow it's going to turn out that that doesn't obviously capture the next thing, which is the natural world.
Because the natural world doesn't have this characteristic of having all its properties in and so forth.
Or maybe it does.
I mean, I'm telling you what I think.
I can't quite figure out.
Does the natural world, as he's using the term, have meaning?
Well, let's talk about the natural world.
The natural world turns out to be absolutely other.
But before we get to that, let me just, it's such a weird thing.
I do want to read you some quotes.
And now, Alga, they'll be in your book, because here's where my references for mind give out for a while.
Okay, the first opens up a natural world starting on 24.
And it's very important to see that the natural world is not the same as the world dealt with by science.
We'll get that.
At the bottom of 28 for you, Paul.
We have to discover the natural world, too, and its mode of existence, which is not to be confused with that of a scientific object.
Okay, so let's find out about that natural world.
So there's lots to be said about it.
For instance, and this is another, this is now 330 in your book, Alva.
About 29 down.
330, 385.
385 in our book.
Okay, that's this mysterious thing which I read about six lines down.
The natural world is the horizon of all horizons, the style of all possible styles, which guarantees to my experience a given.
Not a willed unity, a given, not a willed unity underlying all the disruptions of my personal life.
Its counterpart within me is the given, general, and pre-personal existence of my sensory functions in which we discovered the definition of the body.
That's one of these crucial statements.
So what does it look like?
Well, it looks like the natural world is a horizonal thing.
So that would look like it's correlative with my body.
It's got a style and so forth.
Now I sort of sigh because it's hard for me to figure out how to reconcile that with the notion that the natural world is the absolute other.
I don't understand how the absolute other has a horizon, but let's read about the absolute other, but that's really very important is not being an idealist.
If there's an absolute other, it would seem to be even more absolute than a horizon.
A horizon is always relative to me.
It can't be an absolute other.
I mean, somehow, I hope this is coherent, but I must confess I don't see how to put it all together.
And that's what I want you all to help do as soon as I get laid out here.
Where are we?
I want to look at 432.
Yours.
I think that is fine devotion.
Okay.
I'm going to go over here also, so I know what I'm talking about over here.
432.
The paragraph that begins, our replies.
And it says, at the bottom of that paragraph that begins, our replies, what is true taking one thing with another, is that there is a nature, which is not that of science, but that which perception presents to me.
Okay.
Now, and that's, but how that's supposed to be absolutely other is not clear to me.
Where did you say that?
Absolutely other?
Oh, yeah, the absolute other is on 325 of yours.
Didn't I give the code up to ours?
I think that's 379.
Okay, then let me find that over here.
Not quite.
Okay, let's see now.
What did I say?
I was, I'm getting 325.
Okay, and that's 379.
Eight lines down there.
Eight lines down on 379.
389.
38.
Ah, that's why we can't find it.
Okay, yes.
Eight lines, yeah, something like that.
So that we open uh we open ourselves to that is open himself to an absolute other, which he is making ready in the depths of his being.
Okay.
Now, that's for the...
Are you going to 325?
Okay?
I can't find it on 325.
Okay, let me go to the 33.
Oh, you said two is on 226, actually.
I see.
Well, they're there a little confused.
But and let's go right on close to that.
It's 328 in yours.
I'll find it in a minute in ours.
It says it's 325.
Okay.
Let me go over here.
If anybody finds more about the absolute other.
Well, it's not, it's another, it's not neither like a horizon quite, nor like the absolute other.
It's it's on 328 of yours, about 15 lines from the top.
And what did you say it was going to be in mine?
Um 328 is 3.
This is a strange thing here.
Back to the horizons and the styles and so forth, about six lines down.
The style is a certain manner of dealing with situations and skipping down about until 50 lines down.
I experience the unity of the world as I recognize the style.
You know, that's not altogether, that's not wrong.
It's not actually in that.
I do not for the moment, I think.
But I find this one somewhere, but I do not for the moment doubt that in themselves things have become possible and compossible because for the very short, I'm in communication with one being and one owner, a vast individual from which my own experiences are taken and which presents on the horizon of my life.
You don't find out.
Nobody understands where that is.
What?
In the old one, it's on 328.
Oh, it is.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Here it is at the bottom of 382.
A vast individual, about six lines from the bottom, exists at the horizon of my life and so forth.
Okay, so I'm just trying to say there's this horizon story, and the world is this ultimate horizon, this individual on the horizon of my life, and somehow it's also absolutely other.
It's experienced as independent of human beings, as being completely determinate.
It's experienced as having being in his language.
It's experienced as the in itself for us.
Now, you could find that on 293, which is on 341.
Okay, and now I'll tell you where it is on the page.
For you.
Oh, it's a famous one.
We've read it before.
I'm just calling your attention to it.
It's in the middle of your page 293, and it's here wherever the Place de la Concorde is.
Help me find it.
The paragraph begins in the same way.
Oh, yeah, here we are, the middle of 342.
I walk across the Place de la Concorde and find of myself and so forth and so forth.
And then you see the surface of the stone and the play of lights and entirely without history.
And the greedy circles and so forth.
My total perception is not composed of analytic perceptions that capable of dissolving them.
My body, through my habits, ensures my insertion into the human world, does so only by projecting me in the first place into the natural world.
And now the funny, interesting thing, which can always be discerned underlying the other, as a canvas underlies the picture.
So that's this natural world of being, and it obviously is supposed to be absolutely, and maybe these two jobs are not incompatible.
I mean, it would be there somehow, whether I was around or not.
That's the sense in which I think it's absolutely other.
But it also shows up in my experience as this ultimate horizon, this greedy surfaces and mountains and stuff, underlying my evaluation and my experiences.
That's what he wants to say.
That the puzzle keeps coming back, and I'm sorry if you're confused, but I'm confused.
That the follow-ups are how much of this natural world structure is there independent of us, and how much of the natural world structure is a co-production correlative with our bodily.
He seems to want to say both.
There is a natural world independent of us, which is correlative with our bodily capacities to organize it.
Can you make sense of that?
I was going to ask a question that seems the way about the crypto mechanism, something that we just can't help seeing the world as it is.
The crypto mechanism experiences good.
I mean, yeah, that's how there is an in-excel for us.
But that's not the natural world.
That's the way we have to perceive the shared perceptual world.
But underlying the shared perceptual world is the natural world.
And the question I'm asking is: the perceptual world already, this is what you're saying, has to be experienced as having being, of having determinant properties, even though our way of perceiving it never does.
That's what I said earlier.
But underlying the perceptual world with its determinant properties, which are clearly relative to us, in the sense that we're the ones who see the colors and the shapes and so forth, there is a natural world which is absolutely other and which, and this is the crucial question, it has whatever character it has, presumably, whether we were around or not.
But then, let me say what's cousining so you won't get lost.
The story he thinks there is this nature independent of us, and we have to get in the right relation to it to unlock it so that we can have experience of this perceptual world.
The question is, how much structure does he think that nature in itself this absolute other has and how much of its structure that it is a structure disclosed by our activity and how much of this structure is constituted by our bodily way of organizing.
I can't tell.
If you have passages that can, we're going to have to look at.
The constitution issue, I think he clearly says settlement.
Of course, but I mean that's does it that begs the question because what I want to know, because there is a world that's absolutely other, a natural world, and we don't constitute it.
But how much of the structure of that natural world do we constitute?
That is spatial, that is temporal, that is objective with colors and sizes.
I think he thinks that's all relative to us and our body schema.
He says that we're injected into the natural world because of our habit, those needs are still.
And so we're injected into it because of certain capacities we have to encounter it.
And that's the sort of unlock it thing.
But the question, I'll give you quotes.
I mean, I wish he would say, and I tried to say this and make up an evolutionary kind of story, that there really is a world of the kind of space and time we experience, and that's independent of us, and then we have this capacity in our body to unlock that, to disclose that, and so forth.
But I think when the tips are down, he thinks that all the structure of the natural world is contributed by our body schema.
We could quotes, which would leave the natural world there as boundary conditions.
That is, we can't just organize it any old way.
That's the truth that you're asking, Asher.
And the fact that we can't just organize it any old way, however, doesn't say that we find a structure, and it's this, this very world of perception.
This natural world, which is absolutely other, set conditions such that one of the ways it can be organized is by our body thema.
But that's not its structure.
That's one of the ways that it can be organized, is the way I read it.
What do you think?
I'm just asking you the question.
What do you mean by structure of the world?
Do you mean a structure that can be articulated?
Oh, no, no, no.
I haven't got to be able to step down the line.
This is the natural world.
He says specifically, it's not the world that science studies.
Well, not explanatory.
No, the natural world can only be hymatized by making sense of it as perceptual objects.
This is the constitution, or sometimes he says the recomposition, I mean, once, of the natural world, as if it had already this structure, and then we have to recompose it and give it this structure.
That's an interesting possible view to hold.
But so, I mean, all I can say is it looks sometimes like he thinks it's just boundary conditions.
When structure, one way of getting to think of it is our bodily way, and that gives us this world.
But that's not what's really there, because if there were no human beings, then the boundary conditions wouldn't be sorted into this experience.
That's one thing.
So the boundary conditions that you get in sync with and you compose this world, organize it, and it works.
Or the boundary conditions already have a lot of structure, and all you have to do is get that structure, which you happen to be happily in sync with given the body schema, and then you disclose this very world or recompose the way the world really is, the natural world.
And I guess those are the two views.
I mean, has it got the structure we find in it, or is it the boundary conditions, the absolute other, that just sets a limit on what you can find?
Yeah, James.
That's what he said.
Good, good, good question.
I'm not sure I believe it.
But the perceptual world is we understand it as full of significance relative to our interests and purposes.
And the natural world, this gritty stone in the philosophical Congo, is sort of like the secondary and primary qualities, only that would be a very bad way of thinking about it because, for instance, shape and size are part of the we disclose.
All that there is is a kind of stony stuff that we can get at when we take it away all of the part of the perceptual world which is historical, cultural, and relative to yeah, social, cultural, and significant.
That you take that away, you get the natural world so the natural world of the size there should be the absolute the one and the sensory world of the size should be possible no no no no I'm sorry no that's not what I meant to say no the the one already has in it significance history fedimented history and culture and the one reveals this world which is full of what what it affords to any kind of but that couldn't be the absolute other so what is the absolute other well the absolute other seems to be what's left if you take away everything that's relevant to history culture meaning and so forth and there's going to still be something there which is what you see in this passage when you see the the where are we then let's read this some more a natural non-human space he's talking about so you walk across the plastic concord you are engaged by a yellow green surface and there's no longer even a stone there that's too much of our interpretation the play of light upon an indefinite substance and this is and this my body projects who through my habits ensures an insertion into the human world and it not only projects me in the first place my total perception isn't not compounded as such analytical perceptions, but capable of dissolving into them.
And my body, which through my habits ensures my insertion into the human world, does so only by projecting me in the first place into the natural world, which can always be discerned underlying the other, as a kind canvas underlies the picture and makes it appear insubstantial.
Let's see if we can get any more.
A little toward the bottom of our page, one human spaces present themselves as built on the basis of natural space and so forth.
And maybe the top of 343, about 15 lines down, he's talking about the natural world again in 94, is it is so foreshadowed by the horizons of possible objectification and it frees me from every particular setting only because it ties me to the world of nature or the in itself, which includes them all.
Now I saw a hand up.
That's the yeah, Eric.
You didn't sell, did anybody speech about the inner self first?
Is this in itself?
I would have thought so.
Okay, I think so.
The in-itself, well, wait a minute, wait a minute.
No.
Well, I don't know.
I'll tell you the two things that I go into my mind.
When he talks about the being as this completely determinate, which perception gives us if you extrapolate it, I don't think that's the absolute other.
I think that's the shared perceptual world as completely determinate.
This, the very classroom and so forth, that's what you get when you extrapolate all of this to determine it being.
But that wouldn't be the natural world, which doesn't have all these properties of being death and and so forth.
That's further underlying.
And it's got to be a kind of anti-idealism, just to keep all of my cards on the table, because it has at least got this property of being the boundary condition, some kind of absolute other, which sets a limit on what you can compose it as or organize it.
Even if all the organization of it is finally up to us, we just couldn't organize it any old way.
And we can't organize it simply by consciously trying.
There's something in us, namely this shared body feeling.
And there's something there, independent of us and our bodies feeling.
And you get them together.
That's the natural world.
And when you put them together, you get this, namely a perceptual world full of meaning and significance and historical and so forth.
And a sense that there's something that underlies it, which I think, I think about which you could probably say nothing.
I mean, I don't know how far he gets with his gritty yellow surface and so forth.
I think finally he gets rid of that too, not even a stone and so forth.
It's, by the way, like Sardin Nausda, I mean, he starts taking back all the human relative characteristics of the world until you get to the whatever that underlies it all, about which I think he can say nothing finally.
What is it?
Finally says, it's not even a stone, but the play of light upon an indefinite substance.
The indefinite substance is this absolute other, is the boundary conditions, is what keeps it from being idealism, because we have to build our perceptual world on the conditions provided by that insubstantial, that indefinite substance.
That's right.
Maybe I should go on to the fourth.
But I'll come back to this one.
This is the hardest one.
I can understand that, I think I can understand, as I said, the way we perceive the world, the shared perceptual world, the natural world is the one I don't get.
I'm giving you all the variations.
And now I can go on to the last one, which is the scientific universe.
Can I do that?
Well, okay, I was going to offer an account, but I'll do it.
Well, I certainly don't want to leave this.
I think an important passage is my book, which is 380, but you're connected with the things about the.
Oh, yeah, okay.
He said a lot of things there that suggests maybe he thinks that in our experience of the pebble as a pebble, there is also almost the experience of it as a kind of play of light.
Speaking of the possible equipment, my gaze knows the significance of a certain patch of light in a certain context.
It understands philosophy to light expresses more general terms to the logic of the world to which my body in its environment conforms.
So the point is that, um here's what I propose: that the perceptual world and the natural world are actually the same thing, and that there is some level of sort of indeterminate perceptual degree that requires that through skills, through the skills, which are which are based out of your body, you can make the mere play of mind into something which is intrinsically there and has hidden parts and notes more than you can see, and that's that's the natural world.
So he's also done the natural world underlying, what he says in that other message on 1993, is that the natural world underlies the human world, not exceptional the human world, as of as canvas underlies the picture.
But of course, the canvas is well, but only present there's one.
Well, there's a really syndrome.
Well, I don't know about that.
I think maybe that carries out the analogy, Hodge, but I'm not sure.
That's interesting.
We try that in my look on 380.
Let's see what happens to in the light of that.
Let's start at the bottom of 379.
I just want you to not make a mistake.
Yet we reject the idealism involved in the synthetic view because it just it because it too distorts our lived through relationships to things.
Insofar as the perceiving subject synthesizes the percept, he has to dominate and grasp it through a material perception to organize and lead together from the inside the aspects of the thing.
That means that perception ceases.
This is his view now, to be inherent in the individual subject and so forth.
And the thing loses its transparency.
And this is how he's not an idealist.
You have to be.
And now skipping a little.
The perceiving subject must, without relinquishing his place and his point of view, and in the opacity of sensation, reach out towards things to which he has in advance no key.
If anything, he sort of has the key to unlock it, but he doesn't have it in consciously or anything, but it's in the body schema, I think, for which he nevertheless carries within himself a project and open himself to the absolute other, which he is making ready in the depths of his being.
That is, he's alerting the body schema, which is the way the anyone, the impersonal organization in him, is going to take up this and organize the world.
Now, let me see if I can help connect with Albert.
So you perceive a pebble and you understand all of its sort of perceptual properties when you do that.
Let's go to the bottom.
Expressed in more general terms, there is a logic of the world to which my body in its entirety conforms.
I take it that must be the natural world.
Is that what one would think?
I mean, that's the thing you're unlocking.
But the moral I'm seeing from this is that there isn't isn't natural and the perceptual world understanding.
And I I'm not concerned.
So th that's that's that's probably what I think as thanks to I know if you tension the natural world and the perspective of the world are the same.
Well, let me go on.
I I mean if that would solve it, that would be great.
There is a logic of the something world, whether they whether whichever it is or or the same, which my body conforms and through which things of interior significance become possible for us, insofar as it is capable of synergy, my body knows the significance of the totality of my experience of this or that color added or subtracted and so forth and so forth.
To have a body that has a universal setting, a scheme of all types of perceptual unfolded, and of all those intersensorial correspondences which lie beyond the segment of the world which are actually perceived.
The thing is therefore not actually given, it is internally taken up, reconstituted, I wanted to get to that, an experienced by us insofar as it's bound up with the world.
The basic structures of which we carry with us, of which it is merely one of many possible, bound up with the constants experienced by us, so far as it's bound up with our world, the basic structures of which we carry with us, and of which it is merely one of many possible concrete forms.
Well, the point is, maybe there's a difference that distinctly can be drawn from the perceptual world and the natural world, but it's not one which bears on the ideals of rivals and contrast.
So maybe you want to say the perceptual world is sort of the shape and color, and the natural world is the sort of whole bigness of the whole nature of the thing.
But in both cases, the shape and color, no less than the oak trees of the thing, are only available to us thanks to available to us.
That would be to say that when we do unlock them, we really find out what was there all along.
I mean, there are the structures not relative to us in our body.
Even if we were here gone and our body was gone, there would still be these trees and so forth.
I don't know, but I fear not.
Let me see.
Let me go one more sentence.
I'll go part of our living experience is transcendent in relation to our life because the human body with its habits, which weave around it, a human environment, has running through it a movement towards the world itself.
See, I think there's a distinction between this human environment and the world itself.
I would have thought the human environment was this fair perceptual world, and the world itself is the underlying whatever, which is.
Well, let me let's anyway, somebody had a hand up.
I'm ready to hear some other people.
I didn't see a hand up.
Where?
You've got a pretty good question.
Well, right off the nebula quote, which I know you're not.
No, well, I don't mean I don't care where it is.
You could get these two together so that.
I have no 525 502 breaks into the temporality child.
Okay, got it.
It says what is true, taking one thing with another, is that there is a nature, not even two that is a natural world.
Which is not that in the sciences, it's not in the universe, but that which perception presents to me.
Yes.
And I'm trying to link this to what Nicozon says even possibly presented to us as well.
Well, I was trying to say that the perceptual world, I'm kind of agreeing with Bala, that is the same as the natural world.
But the perceptual world is a different aspect of describing the world.
It's the world insofar as we deal with it with our perceptions.
It the perceptual world views the natural world as we deal with our perceptions.
And that's and it's and the perceptual world there has to be something that exceeds the perceptual world that is uh we can't get to.
I mean it may ground the perceptual world, but it goes beyond perceptual realms.
And that's the perceptual world.
The passage where Reading Bird goes on actually talks about the natural world.
Let's find it.
Calling that, where were we then?
Well, I would have thought so too, but but there's now a consensus which would certainly help.
And so if we want all these things to fit together, I'd be happy anyway they do, that there is the absolute other, there's the horizon of all horizons, there's the well, these are all names for something, there's the perceptual world, there's the natural world, there's uh that's and how to fit all that together and uh is the question.
You can make a important distinction about accessing this natural world and then talking about one world rather than another.
You know, I think for him, you know, we the perceptual world comes first for us in terms of trying to explain the body explaining the phenomena and trying to access these phenomena that like ourselves and bodies are names.
In order for us to understand this, we have to stick to the phenomenon, think to this perceptual world.
But that's not to say that there isn't a a natural world that you can kind of think of without you know perception dealing with it.
I mean it's but it's not even not about accessing the natural world because we can only access the due to the perceptual world, but there it's not to say that there's not this natural world that we can kind of conceive of.
And the natural world isn't even like stones.
I mean, it isn't just, it isn't nature in the sense of the trees and the stones, because the stone gets cancelled out in that passage I read.
And there's something even more minimally structured in our intricate terms.
And that's what puzzles me.
Well, is when you start describing it, you bring in all these other things.
That's right.
I think we can't describe it.
I mean, I'll keep my position just so you can contrast it with Alva's and maybe what Martin is going to say in a minute.
I have a feeling.
But my position is you can't describe it.
It's just what sets these boundary conditions.
Anything you say about it or see in it is already something you see because we've got, you've got, we all share a certain body schema which organizes the world into perceptual objects and so forth.
But I'm holding this just in order for you to be able to shoot it down.
I don't have any particular love of this position.
By the way, what it would be, just so you can see the position I feel driven into, would be very close to Kantian.
There would be a kind of thing in itself about which you couldn't say anything except that it's the ground of the phenomena, of our shared world, sets the limits on our shared world, keeps us from being able to make it this world any way we please.
And we get in sync with it thanks to, and now the difference between Kant and Nelloponte, we get in sync with it in Kant thanks to the categories which we have in our transcendental consciousness, which enables us to make a shared phenomenal world out of the impingement from the thing in itself, which sets these limits.
And Nelloponty, in this reading, I've driven to is saying, well, it isn't the categories in the mind that enables us to organize the thing in itself about which we can say nothing.
It's the shared body schema which enables us to organize that about which we can say nothing.
And the natural world seems when it's the absolute other, anyway, seems to need to be like that.
But when the natural world is something, and this is what I think Elvis picked up on and so forth, the horizon of horizons, when the natural world already seems to be full of meaning and relative to us, then it doesn't sound constant.
Then it sounds like we ought to be able to describe this horizon of horizons.
But how we would earlier so far I'd be, well, I was saying this because natural world hidden behind, appears in these perceptions we have.
Okay, it appears.
I've been saying that's what's some limitations or boundaries that you think.
Right.
But exactly.
Then we must machine it.
So let me just say that I.
So I don't know who he's saying as you be, but it's corresponding to what Alvin is.
He knows better.
But I want to just prove how I do it.
So there's when we are, when we take this over, thanks to our body schema and reconstitute it, or as he says at some point, recompose it, it's there's how we find the structure.
I mean, that's, and that is the structure of it, which we find.
And so far, I've been trying to say.
Uh i in what does that mean?
Well, that you can't say more than that.
I mean okay, that is the structure I see that a being like us finds in it.
And well, that would be the rich world view.
I like that.
I mean that would be that there's other points the being might find other things in it, but we I really found a structure in it.
If we've gotten in sync with it and organized it, it isn't as if it's it's ineffable.
One of the ways it's equivalent is with one.
And that's what you're saying.
Well, but the reason why I said it was to make it difficult, because the console happens the world somehow is hidden behind their appearances.
Okay, good.
It says that the natural world is the dreamer of intrasensory hypervisions.
So you can definitely in terms of some kind of sensory regularities.
And then he usually says that that's not to follow cause.
Okay, where are you?
It's very much the same way we believe your motivation is on creating one.
Okay, well that sounds important.
I suppose.
Where could I start?
It's the bottom of three eighty for us, I guess.
Well, when if you go if you go, this is those breaks to the most here.
Okay, well let me get up to the break and say okay to everybody's this is I read the reconstituted part.
That's about fifteen lines from the top of three hundred eighty one.
Maybe we should read somebody else's voice here because it starts studying journalism.
Well, not going to be excluded then in the next part, Joe.
They're right up there but before the break.
Not to the break.
I'm going to read up to the break.
Everybody read up to the break.
Animal behavior and all that.
And it looks, I mean, this leads to the quote on 385, which we looked at.
This makes the natural world the horizon of all horizons.
And that seems to make it what Alva and Martin are saying.
But we didn't just say, I don't understand how that could be called the absolute other.
That's the other, that's the thing that bothers me, because horizon is relative to us.
I just don't understand.
The horizon of horizons must be relative to us, too.
The very concept of horizon is relative to us.
And therefore, absolute other is what threw me off.
Maybe there are just two conflicting tensions, or maybe I'm disposed to not believe in the absolute other.
Maybe it's the only, the seemingly absolute other or something.
Or maybe it's we try to get the boundary conditions back in, saying that we are sort of this other would be there whether we unlocked it or not, and it's what's sort of forcing us to overdiscose it and reconstitute it this way.
And we experience in it a kind of receptivity to some order which we don't compose but recompose, and that order is absolutely other, the order that we take up and recompose.
I don't know.
I mean, that's, you want to say, you look like you want to say something?
I have a couple things.
Let's just go back to what we've been talking about it.
I always interpreted the horizon to be the condition of the possibility of our perception.
And to me, it seems like the other beggars just be like these structures of non-perception.
Oh, I think horizon by its sort of the metaphor of horizon.
You can only have horizon relative to somebody who's sort of in the middle and of it, and it shapes their around them.
I can't, I mean, how something that was, and this could be both, and I'm trying to keep both, the natural world could be the perceptual world and understood as a horizon, but also understood somehow as what sort of governs and limits the way we make sense of it.
Okay, and then you have to say, and you've got two choices.
Then it becomes either sort of ineffable and you're, or you say, and it governs the way we perceive it because of the way it is.
And the way it is is what we find out when we get our body schema and perceive it.
And there isn't any sort of X.
And it would be that way whether we unlocked it or not.
I mean, I recomposed it or not.
I mean, it's got a structure all of its own.
I like that.
I wish he, and maybe he is.
Maybe he's that much of a realist.
Yeah, well, he does that often.
That's what's causing a problem.
You put the cradle of all meaning directional in all directions here.
On page 500 of our books, you could be four lines down.
Okay.
Hence, we've discovered.
Oh, hence, we discovered that the world as a cradle of meaningless direction, the ground of all thinking.
How do we find the world?
And I know that realism idealism is talking maybe like empiricist realism and concept idealism, but it's still the same point that we've been talking about as the world just being the same into an actual and perceptual world.
I mean, are the points we've been trying to make?
Well, if something which is the horizon of our life, we're back to that again in the primordial unity of our experiences.
That sounds like the perceptual world, but it doesn't sound like an absolute other, the horizon of our life and the unity of our experiences.
It is no longer the visible control of a constituting thought, so forth and so forth.
Okay, let me stop.
But we'll have to put the last time.
I don't know.
Just one suggestion, and this is really a speculation here.
In the passage that we just read, he talks about animal behavior as directed to a natural setting and as encountering the resistance.
And then he talks about human behavior over the world.
Maybe something about centers of resistance, of Egypt, is what gives you the notion of an absolute other, because there's a way in which we're talking about vision, that if there's an animal, and Zoom said, you're worried about the cleanup that's going to eat you, or the cliff you're going to fall off of, or the hold of your barriers.
I like that.
I like that, there's got to be something that we and animals all have to sort of come up against, which we can enlarge as a shared perceptual world with its ultimate horizon.
Let's try to break some of rates are the idea of the natural world with the absolute other?
The absolute other is the absolute resistance.
I'm taking that over, right, if that's what I meant.
I thought you were doing is whatever it is that we and the animals all come up against as something that limits us, and not just in a negative way, but to what Martin says, but provides us the opportunity on the basis in which we can respond and make order and so forth, maybe that's the absolute other understood.
I guess not just a bad kind of resistance, but it's affordances too.
I mean, resisting and affording to us and to animals, that's the bottom level.
And then there's this world perceptual shared cultural human world that we get when we deal with that.
I'm going to have to see what you're going to find.
Heidegger and the original world are only a parent very greatly different.
He says the world worlds, every single one for all the earth adjusts into or exposes itself more than anything more.
I think that's probably a very useful thing to say, except I suspect nobody here will have any help.
Anybody who's know about Earth.
How many?
Yeah, well, if you knew what Heidegger meant by Earth and the origin of the work of art, which is, I think, equally mysterious, I mean, I think I'm afraid it explains the obscure by the more obscure.
You see that it's exactly the same thing.
They struggle, the Earth struggles with world would be like in Merlot-Ponte.
The natural world struggles with the perceptual world.
Okay, I want to take the last five minutes to do the fourth level.
I'd feel very bad if I didn't get beyond this level.
And so let me do it.
The objective universe.
Now, there are two sort of parts under that.
The objective universe is something that the human sciences and the neurosciences presuppose.
We're going to try to find a general statement.
The objective universe is what science is trying to describe and get the structure of.
It's completely determinate.
Presumably, it's got elementary particles in it and they're obeying causal laws and so forth.
Now, Merloponty then, this divides into two parts.
Merloponty thinks that, first, you can't explain consciousness and perception and significance in terms of the natural universe.
And that's what's wrong with the human sciences who try to, as people could repress or forget perception, and then empiricism will try to give you a story in the human sciences and so on, intellectualism, which tries to find some objective, independent elements and laws in terms of which to explain everything.
And then neuroscience does it on another level, tries to get an account of the brain, which explains significance, holism, indeterminacy, consciousness, and everything.
And Merloponty has the sensible view, I think, that that's just, we couldn't believe that.
That's reductionism.
The idea that you can explain consciousness and significance and the holism of the way of the perceptual world in terms of any elements, the empiricist elements, the intellectualist elements, the physicist elements.
And I think he sort of would hold like Tom Nagel, whom I mentioned, there is just no third-person account possible of this meaningful, first-personal way of experiencing the world that we've got.
But I think, and now comes the last move I want to make, I think he feels that he needs a stronger argument than that.
That just sounds dogmatic.
There's Nagel versus Searle.
And there's probably another whole list of people you could put on Nagel's side, and a whole list of people you could put on Searle's side.
One of them says to then explain it all in terms of the particles and laws finally.
That's all there really finally is, is what physics tells us there is.
That's the objective universe.
And the other side says, no, the objective universe is somehow, for some reason or other, incapable of explaining everything.
Now, I think that that's right, but there's a wrong way of trying to defend it.
I think Mero-Ponty feels he needs an argument why it's that the physical universe is incapable of defending us, of explaining our world and our kind of experience.
And then I think he makes the absolutely wrong move that Searle sees he makes and blames him for, but I don't think he should have made it.
And I don't, and where Searle thinks this is what any phenomenologist is going to make, that is the wrong move.
I think you don't have to make it.
But the wrong move is to say, well, science is really some kind of abstraction.
It's not getting at.
I mean, it's not getting at what there really is in the universe.
So naturally, it can't explain significance and consciousness and so forth.
At 468, in ours now at the top, he's been.
I don't know what the right way is saying that science is limited and can't explain meaning and significance.
I think probably the thing to say is we don't know yet whether it can or not.
We haven't got an argument that's convincing.
But the argument that's not convincing is that you can, where is it, 468?
We are led by as much as the realist believes the subject of eternity with the morality.
He's saying, there, that's not very helpful.
You can't believe in, maybe it's visible, but that wasn't, that wasn't very interesting.
Let's try this.
458.
No, I don't know what I meant here.
But let me tell you, natural science, he says, is an abstraction from the natural world.
He says this on 351.
What?
Let me get your book.
3.409.
Let's look.
Yeah, right.
And this is this important Magel-like quote on the middle of 409.
I don't know where the abstraction is, but how significance and intentionality could come to dwell in molecular edifices or cells can never be made comprehensible.
And here, and here Cartesianism is right.
And then, skipping down, the body as a tentacle structure or an agglomeration of tissues is formed by a process of impoverishment.
That's a very important line.
You can hear that two ways.
One way, it's absolutely right.
You've got to leave out a lot of what there is to say about the body to describe the physical body as a machine with tissues and so forth.
But there's nothing wrong with that.
It's only when you use the idea that science is a very impoverished version of the rich world and the scientific objective body is a very thin impoverishment of the lived body, when you use that to argue that somehow you couldn't from these elements explain the richer stuff.
It depends on how you hear this impoverishment.
If you hear it, yes, you leave out a lot, and what you finally get is Cartesian space and particles and laws.
That's right, but nothing follows from that about what you can explain.
Or, except that you've got a lot of explaining to do because you've left out meaning and significance and the body schema and all that, and that may well be impossible to explain.
But you can't claim just because science has found this minimal level of description that it couldn't explain it.
But that's what he concludes.
That's the trouble.
This is where I think he goes wrong.
On 391 of your book, what?
455.
I'm going to go very fast over this if you guys need time to write.
He just becomes, I mean, the next move, besides saying science is an impoverishment, is to say science is just a social construction.
At that point, you've gone beyond saying that it's a very thin objective universe that science talks about, which doesn't prove what you can and can't explain.
to there really isn't any universe that science is talking about.
It's a construction.
That's what he says, and that's where he just goes wrong.
He has a strong argument, all right, but I don't see why we should believe it at the top of 455.
He says, prosaic and scientific utterance is a cultural entity which at the same time lays claim to translated truth related to nature in itself.
Now we know that this is not the case.
But modern criticism of the sciences has clearly shown the constructive element in them.
Well, that's to make what Searle calls it as confusion between epistemology and ontology.
That's to say that the way we know about scientific entities, which of course depends on language and lots of scientific, that that's somehow intrinsic to what the scientific entities are, that they are constructions.
Whereas all you want to say, if you want to be through to the phenomena and so forth, all you have a right to say that's the way to put it, is that if it weren't for our language and our scientific practices, we couldn't have access to the entities that science discovers.
Now, maybe it's true that what we get access to is really not discovered, but somehow constituted by this access.
But it doesn't follow from the fact that you need science and laboratory practices to talk about electrons and nebula, that electrons and nebuli are cultural products.
That's what he finally says of this outrageous passage on wherever it is that I always get upset about at the end of the time chapter, 502.
where he talks about Laplace's nebula, about two-thirds stem, is not behind us, but is in front of us in the cultural world.
And I guess I've got to stop here because let me just see if I...
Yeah, so I think that he is an idealist about scientific entities.
There's no doubt about it.
He thinks they're constructed.
And he thinks that if we weren't here, there couldn't be any electrons and galaxies and so forth.
I think that's just wrong.
But that's not the interesting issue.
He could fix that.
What we really want to know is the stuff we spend most of the time discussing, what this natural world is, and how it's independent of us, and how he's neither an idealist nor a realist about the perceptual natural world.
I've got to stop with that.
Okay.