Okay, now, the punchline of the sense experience chapter, after you've gone through a lot of discussion of whether the senses are all completely the same or completely different, and that's all this talk about whether blind people do or do not experience objects the way people who see them experience it.
That's not the point, really.
The point is sort of the opposite.
He finally comes around to saying, well, though all the senses are different, sort of, in that they give you the world from a different aspect, they are not different in the sense that what you see of an object, its color, say, is unrelated to its shape and its what it's made of and everything.
In fact, what you get is the intersensorial unity of the object.
It's given to you as having a color and shape and texture and made out of material and everything all at once.
And that's because we've got this intersensorial unity of the body.
And when we perceive something, we don't perceive it with each sense.
That's just the way it looks.
If you think about the stimulus error, or that is, of course, something different is coming into the eye, than it's coming into the ear, than it's coming into the hand.
But that's, but when we actually experience an object, it's our whole body actively experiencing the whole object.
That's why I want to read this because I think that's important.
And that's on 262, let's hope.
The middle of the page.
Sensory experience is unstable and alien to natural perception, which we get feed with our whole body.
Sensory experience means seeing as separated from hearing, as separated from touching.
That's not what's natural.
What's natural is what we do when we perceive the whole object with our whole body, all at once, opening on the world of interacting senses.
That's the moral of it.
Like that, the sensible quality, the experience of the separate senses is gained only when one assumes a particular, highly particularized attitude, and this won't help us in understanding what's going on when we normally perceive that important.
Now, if I could just figure out why the other important, because I want a quote way back near the beginning, I think.
Although maybe it's, maybe it really isn't.
Yeah.
Why are you, what a surprise I.
Okay, on 376, it's way in the same in the natural world.
And it's only a sentence, but I does such a good job there at the bottom of 376, where he says, this sums up this intersensorial thing.
It is impossible completely to describe the color of the carpet without saying that it's a carpet made of wool.
Remember, that's the woolly blue story.
And without implying in this color a certain tactile value, a certain weight, a certain resilience to sound, and so forth.
That's the intersensorial claim.
And that leads him to talk about synesthesia.
And what he was going to claim about synesthesia is, which is this experience that we have, which you can see colors and hear sounds and so forth.
You get it under mescaline, you get it under sort of the brain problems.
But he says on 266, this interesting claim, which sort of follows from his view, that synesthesia, the middle of the page, synesthetic perception is the rule.
That is, we normally are able, on 266, that I, at the middle of the page, nor are these exceptional phenomena.
Synesthetic experience is the rule, and we are aware of it only because, unaware of it, only because scientific knowledge shifts the center of gravity of experience, and then we have to unlearn and so forth that we pay attention to our bodily organization and think of how the difference between the physics of how you see and how you hear, for instance.
But the claim that synesthesia is normal, I mentioned this in the past.
I don't know how it is in your life.
I don't think I experience it.
But the people who now do research on synesthesia say lots of people do, and they can go out and find plenty of subjects, and most people don't talk about it because they think there's something wrong with them, or they're weird.
They don't want to talk about how they see colors.
How many of these see sounds or hear colors and so forth?
Is it?
I don't understand why anybody would be afraid to say so.
It wouldn't show you a crazy.
It would just show that Merylo-Ponte is right.
Anyway, now nobody.
Well, you in dreams.
Ah, dreams don't count, I guess.
I mean, I know that these people do it really just in the everyday world.
That's right.
Well, those are the people that they particularly study, because they're very easy to study, and you can do funny things like spell the word red, R-E-D, in letters that are always green to a synesthe and see what happens to them and so forth.
Anyway, it would be nice if Merylophanti were right, that we all see like this.
I think probably some painters certainly see like it.
Anyway, that's all I want to say about that so far.
Yeah, okay.
Now, the last thing I'm going to talk about, being specific, and then I want to talk about his general conclusion, that was his story about binocular vision is really interesting and has sort of lots of little morals of the whole way he does things packed into it.
This starts on 268.
And I've got it all marked up because everything he's saying here seems to be interesting.
Now, what is going on with binocular vision?
What's he talking about?
He's talking about the fact that just to sort of demonstrate it, you can demonstrate it to yourself, if I'm looking at you and my finger is here, I see two fingers, but I see just one of you all, or I can focus on my finger with a little effort, and then you get to be two and blurry.
That's just because we see with two eyes, and if you focus those two eyes on the finger, then you get the image on the retinas, two retinas of you guys won't line upright.
And if I get the image to line up right for you guys, it won't line up right for my finger.
But he's got a whole account of that, which is very interesting.
He wants, he, or the, the, the, the, the thing he wants to show, let me just say it in my own terms, is that there is the crucial thing, I think, for him is to show that, is to claim that if you start by seeing two things, and you do sometimes because you start out focused wrong, too much onto something near or far, then they come together, but not just instantly, he says, which they would do if it was just a question of calculating what was on each retina and lining it up.
Probably they come together instantly in a digital camera, which just looks for the edges and lines them up.
But they take a while to come together for us, and that shows that it's not just a mental operation, and it isn't just a causal operation either, he thinks.
There's some things that are sort of just going on outside of any relation to our existential involvement.
He thinks that it's only when you make an effort and focus your attention, either I try to see you all clearly, or I try to see my finger clearly, when I do that, I can pull the disparate two images together.
And when I pull them together, they don't just superimpose, they disappear into the object, which then looks like it's solid, and these two images just look like ghosts.
So now I'll read you things.
All of that is interesting enough.
So this is not 268, he starts talking about this, about five lines down.
Now, though perception brings together our sensory experiences into a single world, it does not do so in the way that scientific collegation gathers together objects, but in a way that binocular vision grasps one soul option.
Let us describe carefully this synthesis.
Notice the synthesis has been quotes.
And he does sometimes talk about what he's interested in is synthesis.
But it's a very tricky notion because it's usually an intellectualist kind of notion in which there are elements and the mind somehow puts them together, in King Kant's say.
But when he does use synthesis, he means the sort of how the experience self-organizes.
And this is the case of that.
You try hard to see, say, whatever it is you're looking at.
And when you do, then the experience, somewhat sluggishly but obediently, self-organizes.
That's what he's interested in.
So he goes on.
When I fix a gaze on a remote thing, I have a double image of the objects nearby.
Then you can transfer to objects nearby and so forth.
This is what I just did.
We must not at any point say that the synthesis consists in thinking of them together as images of one object.
It's when we're dealing with a mental act or an apperception, that's what it is.
You thought to occur as soon as I notice the identity of the two images, whereas I have to wait much longer for the unity to appear and so forth.
Until the moment when correct focusing does away with the images, that is, the two ghost-like things.
The single object is not a certain way of thinking, the two images cease to be given the moment it appears.
All that sounds right.
And then, from 269, he gives his usual analysis of it.
Now, I think it's just important.
It's always important to keep your eye on what he's always going to talk about.
And it's always got to do with equilibrium, balance, maximum grip, and tension.
That whole picture, which I'm going to give you lots of quotes about in a little while, so don't worry about it yet.
But that's always there, sort of governing what he says.
And as Eric pointed out to me, and I wanted to say this to you, I don't think I said it last time, as advice for how to read it, did I say this?
If you go to the end of these hard chapters and read the last few paragraphs, usually, you find that that's the punchline, that it's got to do with gaining a maximum grip, getting a balance, lowering a tension, and so forth.
And then you can sort of find your way through these hard chapters by knowing that all of these ways he's heading there are either wrong ways because they ignore it, or hints at somebody who's got a clue about it but hasn't figured it out completely, like the Dishal people who have a notion of balance and unbalance and tension, but don't have it in a properly existentialist way.
Because to make it really existential, you have to add, I'm always trying to get a grip.
And that trying part, not consciously trying, my body is always trying.
Something in me is always trying to get an optimal grip.
That's the way I think I got Olivier's agreement on this one, that he really goes beyond Husserl.
Olivier and I disagree about a lot how much this is like Husserl.
And there's a whole industry trying to decide how much Merlot is like Husserl, partly because he's got lots of claims about that.
But the thing that he considers, I think, his original idea, and which is the underlying idea of all these analyses, is this business of we are constantly, or the body is, or one in me, is trying to get a grip on the world, to find their way about in the world, to talk like TOTI, to find themselves in the world, to talk like TOTUS.
And that's that usually shows up at the end of every chapter.
And you'll see it does in this too.
But now let's see, the next thing is going to 269 after we start hearing about this.
It will, unless he he introduces the notion of in unbalance here at the bottom, it will be replied that unless the eyes are focused, these two groupings cannot be superimposed on each other, nor give rise to a vision of anything.
And in this sense, their presence alone creates a state of unbalance.
And that's sort of on the right track.
And because he says, isn't admitting what we're trying to show?
That the sight of a single object is not a simple outcome of focusing the eyes.
Now comes this, it is anticipated in the very act of focusing.
Or that has been stated, that the focusing of the gaze is a prospective activity.
For my gaze to alight on near objects and to focus my eyes on them, we must experience double vision as an unbalance.
That's always the crucial thing.
Some kind of something that isn't right and is pulling you to get it right.
Even the masks and the ships are, remember, like a storm on the horizon, unstable and make you uneasy until you get to them, they pull you into getting the right picture of them, which is stable and the masks and the trees separate out.
It's always that.
So there is this unbalance.
But it'll go on because everything in here is mixed.
That's going on at the bottom.
Not balanced, or because an imperfect vision tends toward the single object, is toward the release of tension and the completion of vision.
The top of 270, I think.
Now, I have to say at some point, and I'll say it here, he doesn't talk here about motivation, but it's a very important idea of his, which, and it's very hard to figure out what it means because I don't think he ever tells you just outright.
But this is a case of motivation.
It's whenever there's a tension that's pulling you to get a better grip, then that motivates you.
Not in the sense that you say to yourself, gee, it would be nice to have a better grip.
But motivation is his name for this being drawn to the optimal, which I'll talk more about in a minute again.
And it's supposed to be neither causal nor it's neither empiricist nor intellectual.
The way this tension pulls you to get the two images together and see an object isn't that you're caused by some third-person process in the brain, or I mean, there is some third-person process in the brain, all right, and it underlies it, all right, but it has to do what it does by underlying something which is an experience of deviation from a norm, to put it another way.
And you're being pulled toward the norm.
That's not mere causal, and it's certainly supposed to be not mental, not intellectual.
It isn't as if there is some reason such you can deduce, or you don't anyway, that this image is enough like that image, that I should superimpose them.
It's this ground-level narrow pony, and Sean Kelly will talk about this too, that the experience has always got this thing, that in order to have perceptual experience, you've got to be sensitive to these norms and deviations from the norms.
And you mean, again, your body's human.
Okay, I'm going to go on, because I always have the same point over and over.
How about 12 lines or 15 down on 270?
We pass from double vision to the single object, not through an inspection of the mind, see that's being intellectualist, but when the two eyes cease to function each on its own account and are used in a single organ for one single day, it is not the epistemological subject who brings about the synthesis, but the body, when it escapes from dispersion, pulls itself together and tends by all means in its power towards one single goal of activity.
And when one single intention is formed in it through the phenomenon of synergy, well, namely, again, it's being pulled toward this single goal.
And the single goal, I'll read you quotes, but is always maximal grip.
Getting the most, we'll see a quote in a minute, the richest and the best form and the most sort of coming out the way you expected it.
Experience.
Don't even bother to write that down yet because I'll show you the clear place where he finally says it.
But on 270, we've got that, we've got, and then he says intentionality.
After our discussion last time, or the last two times, I'm trying to figure out what he means by intentionality.
So down toward the bottom, about 10 lines in the bottom of 270.
What is meant by saying that this intentionality is not a thought is it does not come into being through the transparency of any consciousness.
It takes for granted all the latent knowledge of itself and my knowledge, knowledge of itself that my body possesses.
Well, I think I keep wanting to say intentionality is tied up with something like motivation.
It's not something you're trying to do.
I mean, you've got to separate it from Thorough-like intentionality, where you have a goal and you represent this goal and then you do something to achieve the goal.
That's a kind of intentionality, too.
And that's sort of close to what it is for human beings to have intentions.
And so Thurow talks about prior intentions and intentions in action when he describes that.
But this is some, there is a kind of teleology.
There is this tendency toward this optimal.
But it's not something that any, any, that is anybody's intention.
And it isn't clear what the goal is until you get it.
It isn't like I have a goal of going and getting ice cream and I know exactly what I want, how many scoops and what flavor and all that.
You don't know what you want.
You just want the tension to go away.
And you don't even want that.
Your body wants the tension to go away.
And when the tension goes away, you will have the optimal grip and you will see a stable object with stable properties and stable size, stable distance, and all the things that this calculus fout.
So there's a kind of intentionality that's not thought, not representational to talk like Thurley.
And it's got, now that's the first point.
The second point is, this paragraph interests me because of the talk about latent knowledge.
What sort of latent knowledge?
Well, it's again this self-normativeness of the body knowing that it doesn't feel good this way.
There would be a better way to see it instead of two hands, all blurry, one clear hand, and so forth.
The body knows that there would be a better way to see it.
It doesn't have to know what the better way is, and it doesn't know it.
in a knowledge source.
It senses that this is good enough, there is a better, and it senses which direction will make it better.
It's always, I can see it better from, I could see it better from over there.
I feel that if only I was over there, I could get a better grip on it, get a better look at it, and so forth.
That's bottom line.
That's important because it's related to what Alda talks about.
It's too bad he isn't here, but we talk about it.
It's not behind his back because we talk about it all the time.
And he has this important idea that we have in our body an understanding of if I do such and such, such and such will happen, so that my experience of the mind knowing this as a table involves, not intellectually, but a whole bodily understanding of all the ways I could move correlated with what I would then experience.
And I think Merloponte thinks that's not wrong, but it leaves out this important pull toward an optimal.
It's the normative part that he would say is missing from that description.
And for Merloponte, the normative part is the important part.
Namely, it isn't just that if I do this, I'll see that.
And if I do this, I'll see that.
And if I do this, I'll see the table from here.
And if I do that, I'll see it from the bottom.
It's that if I'm seeing a table like that, I feel that there's a kind of tension that I could get a better look at it from here, and maybe even a better look at it from here.
There's, and perhaps this is the optimum, that that feeling is crucial.
It doesn't get represented in a bunch of rules for if I do this, then that.
It can't be represented because it's about what feels better, not just the correlation between perception and action.
Yeah, Rick.
So how does the actual task that you're engaged in that or wasn't pulling you?
Because, you know, there is an animal advantage the way you presented it.
I think isn't right, that it is complete.
Well, you know, if you want to change this.
Good example.
Yes.
Right.
Okay.
Fascinating.
This is something we discussed yesterday, some of us, and it's good for Rick for bringing it up.
I can say certain things that are clear, and then there's something I'm not clear about, and I think we disagree about.
But what Rick has said is obviously true, that it's relative to your task, and that your optimal grip depends on what you're looking for.
However, and I don't think Rick disagrees, there is a level in which the body schema is trying to get an optimal somehow more basic than this past relative thing, which is just there is perceptually the best way to look at it, and you will have at this level of description a feeling that you're not getting it right if you don't get it better that way.
Now, that could come in conflict with your, and that's what one does.
The one thing, the anonymous bodied schema has its own idea, so to speak, idea, its own sense of what's optimal, and its own sense of tension and deviation when you don't get that.
And it's the same for all of us, and it doesn't have to do with our purposes.
And now, sort of on top of that, and sort of overriding that, can be the purposes that he certainly has.
I have to find a quote that I was going to use much later in the lecture, but since you brought it up, I think we should find it now.
There's a place where he specifically talks about how what he's describing takes place on this MON1 neutral basis.
Maybe somebody will know where that is.
Maybe not.
Yeah, yeah, you got that?
It's in our reading for, I think, like next time.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, we already read it, but it's coming up again, though, I think.
But it comes up, of course, everything comes up again and again.
250 is one place where he says that.
250?
I'm not sure he's getting it.
Yeah, no, there's one place where he says it so clearly.
What I'm interested in, there's a, because I had this discussion that we had yesterday in mind, a place where he clearly separates the kind of personal historical optimal from this universal body optimal.
And I have to find it.
Yeah.
A different place.
I believe so.
I'm not sure I remember the one cushion.
Where will it tell me again where that was?
I found 250.
350.
250.
I don't think I was back reading on 250.
No, that's fine, but I don't think that's it.
Maybe, let me look.
No, no, it's another one.
A little clearer on this issue.
Well, if I just go on, which I will do, we will find it, because I have it listed as one of the quotes I wanted to read on the time comes.
Okay, let's wait.
Where are we now?
So on 270, we've got this one cushion.
The, well, what is one 50?
Pulls itself together, intentionality and issues like that.
And then on 271, still reading things I think are very important, the top of the page.
Herein lies the distinction between the perceptual synthesis and the intellectual synthesis.
On passing from double to normal vision, I'm not simply aware of seeing with my two eyes the same object.
I am aware of progressing toward the object itself and finally enjoying its concrete presence.
That's, you see, that's this normative thing.
That's not just getting the sensory motor coordination.
It's seeing that you've got the best and on some level best, on this basic level best, I think, view.
I haven't claimed to have answered Rick's objection yet.
We'll come across, and if we don't, there's no answer, but it's a possible paper topic.
And to balance out what the relation is between the impersonal body schema that's just doing this job of getting a grip on objects, which is the same for everybody who has a body like ours, and how this is related to individuals with their own interests, desires, and purposes getting a grip on things like the bubblegum is something very unclear, I think, in Malafonte.
But I don't think it's terribly, I mean, all you have to do is just try to get the phenomena right.
It's true, both.
Only I think my reading makes it a lot more important than more basic, this general one.
And my feeling is that the book, being about perception, is trying to make this level, if common level, more important than basic.
Yeah.
Can you say precisely why it's supposed to be important?
I mean, is the idea that is the worry that are taking our personal projects and stuff like that into account?
No, no, no, I see a good point.
No, it's just the only reason it's important to separate them out is because you want to be clear as to what the decisive factor is.
And if experiencing a solid object which is present to you in the flesh, so to speak, fully given with what you're trying to explain, then all you need is the universal body schema story to explain it, the one perceives in me.
And if you bring in personal things, it isn't that you do anything wrong, you sort of muddy the argument.
And the basic issue in this book is how we perceive objects as rich and present.
It isn't sort of how, what particular features interest us and so forth.
That's my feeling.
I think both of Eric and OJ disagree.
Eric got there first, yeah.
I think it's not fair to say that this book is primarily about intentional perception.
Oh, of course.
Of course.
Sure, you can.
I mean, not you can't deny that the individual is acting with concern, but you could claim, and I think Merrill Kanji does claim, and I want to claim, you can separate out a part of the action, which is the same for everybody, and all you need is that when you're trying to talk about why the object is rich and present and self-sufficient and opaque and has hypothetically, and what's the other word?
I forget, but we're going to get there.
All that typical Merrill Kanzi talk, what it is to be an object of perception, I think you can talk about that, and of course you have to bring in action because it's drawing you to move in such a way as to get the grip.
But you don't have to bring in the fact that an individual person is acting.
That you can just bracket out.
That's all I want to say.
You don't think it's such a measure here that the difference between the animal level and the human level is precisely the basic individuality of the animal.
But, I mean, I mean, this is just a kind of non-secret mean that you bring even the individual part.
No, well, I would get rid of culture, too.
Well, Calibrity.
Yes, well, he does, and he doesn't.
I mean, I mean, right, it isn't the only space you live in.
But if you want to understand, give it what you want to understand what it is to be a perceptual object, you know.
But then you're shifting back to the fact that there's the perceptual rules and everything.
But you say that he's only talking about this.
Oh, no, I don't say he's only talking about this.
Okay.
This is the most important part.
Which is the one I'm talking about.
Yes, yes.
And to understand the way humans behave and everything, which is the different perspectives.
You don't mean I suppose.
That we're agreeing, right?
Or I mean not agreeing.
Later, or even to do that?
Even to talk about the level at which there is solid.
We can talk about pictures.
No, you don't give the whole picture.
I mean, the question is somehow hard to focus.
I mean, the question is: can you do a story that is a partial picture, but is not modified by adding on the next one?
It isn't as if the shared we all see it the same way changes by culture.
They all see objects as solid, as present, as having a kind of thisness and a fullness.
That's the affair and the astheity that we talked about.
That's just totally cross-cultural.
Probably animals have it too, but we can't.
You know, you're good.
You can.
Right, though.
Leads to.
It's all we're having, just a discussion of sort of method.
And there are two ways it leads to.
Leads to it in such a way that it feeds back, it modifies in some basic way the perceptual level, or leads to it in the sense that once you've got the kind of beings that we are, you not only see objects this way, but you see them symbolically and you can see them as yours and so forth.
And I don't think we disagree.
That doesn't change the good.
Good.
That doesn't change the natural.
Okay, it's very important on a certain way.
We're trying to understand what a whole human experience in a human world is.
And that we're not disagreeing.
But I think that the really important contribution of Merila-Ponty, it's the most original and probably most important to him, is the level that I keep trying to stress.
And that's fine.
I mean, I don't think we've got much disagreement there yet.
So, I think you like your position and read as the question.
Okay.
Would your view be that the body schema has this kind of natural level and then a cultural level like violence?
So the vibe.
And so one question I have is that it seems like part of the one that perceives in the other cultural one that has a sense of the appropriate distance to stand.
That's true.
So you would say that it's part of the body schema.
That is part of the one that perceives it.
That's right.
But it's a cultural part of the violation and not a natural level.
Yes, and to put it in the funny slogan of Merilo-Panti, it has a history because I learned to stand that way in this culture.
And there's this other one that has a prehistory which is always already given.
That's the natural one.
It's really innate.
But he doesn't like to terminate.
I don't know why, or maybe he hasn't got it.
But he says things like, it has a history that was never present, meaning that's what all of us have, and that's it.
And then, I agree with you, we have, each of us, by way of our culture and also by way of our family and also by way of our personal thing, our own history, which, thanks to the intentional arc, will show up in the objects.
So, some objects are frightening to you that are sweet for me, and vice versa, and that's going to show up in our world, too.
And that's fine.
I guess we're agreeing about that.
You were right.
I'm glad you did.
And that is my position.
And he has this distinction between the history that never was present and what we really got through our history.
Yeah.
So, what would you say about this?
I mean, when we're in the engaged attitude, are our concerns being sort of at the forefront of...
At the forefront.
I don't know what to say.
I don't know, because I can't tell what that means.
I wouldn't be surprised they're at the forefront.
I'll take that metaphor.
And I think what he's interested in is the background.
They're only possible with these things to be in the forefront because we do this impersonal constituting, if you want, well, I don't like that language, no, this impersonal organizing or experiencing of stable, perceptual, solid, present objects in the background, because it's done physically and all the time.
It's just on the background.
No, because you can focus on the background while within it.
I mean, now we've got two problems.
I don't want to talk about both of them.
I mean, the kind of reflection that's involved here is doubly weird.
I say that.
And you see in every once in a while things are radical kind of reflection because it doesn't, it tries to describe the world when we're not reflecting, when we're engaged, fully immersed in what we're doing.
And then you've got two funny problems.
I mean, you've got to describe it without somehow capture this background body set that's doing all this, the body schema, and describe how that works.
And he does it with metaphors like I've been using, the thickness, the richness, the full of objects, and so forth.
And then you can also capture, if you're interested in human freedom, for instance, the last chapter of the book, which we're going to read, then you want to understand how the world appears to workers as opposed to capitalists.
Oh, but back to hotels, okay.
I don't want to think about that.
Ah, okay.
I saw another hand.
Eric?
I think this last point about Freeman makes me sure you do.
But you just mustn't think.
And another philosophical position would be, and there are people who certainly strongly believe this, that either, I mean, there's several, that given our history and our culture, it permeates and changes perception all the way down.
That's some kind of view.
I mean, I don't know who holds that view, but I've got lots of people do.
Really?
Do you think it overrides and changes our perception of objects?
Yes, which is why my mother has holy water in her refrigerator from Blourge, France, and appears to her in a radically different exploit.
Well, it's sacred water.
Yes, but it's got obscenity and acidity.
It's solid, it's present, it teaches properties, it's got a size, it's got a distance, and blah, blah, blah.
If you were in the same boat, those shoulder regressed in the same way.
Yeah, and if I told her, by the way, that was important.
I said cross-border.
Okay?
So when they're waiting, what do you mean by the same thing?
Yeah, so, well, but the difference between calling it a natural has this understanding of an understanding of being.
So everything we understand is we we can't understand it as being a creation of God.
Now is that why that our understanding of everything.
Okay, but the question is, I don't want to go further with this, but I'm just going to say, the question is, du in what way does it look look does it look different when it you see it as a creation of God?
And that's a tricky question.
I mean, that's another possible paper topic, because there's some way that it looks exactly as it looks to the the primitives and to the in pre-linguistic children, and another sense in which it doesn't.
By the way, one more point about this.
No, no, no.
I don't want to talk more about this.
Well, okay, both James have been a second.
The really more, the place where this issue becomes clearest, and I don't know if it's really discussed in this book or not.
I can't think of any place where it is, is whether when you get language, it radically transforms perception all the way down.
There are people certainly who believe this.
Lots of people.
Yeah, but not in this book, right?
Yeah, I think later Merle Ponte does.
I'm not sure he should.
It's funny.
Heidegger does too, after being in time, think that language transforms our experience all the way down.
Some important issue there, one way that just so you realize this is an interesting issue, is is our perception like the animals?
And there are people who are very much convinced that our perception is not like the animals because we have language.
A puzzle for such people, it seems to me, is what two-year-old children are supposed to be like when they're perceiving just prior to language.
Because when it seems to me pretty strange to say that these children are just like animals until they get language and then their perception is radically transformed it.
It might be true.
There's certain people who believe it.
I don't know how you can find out.
Okay, James.
Okay.
Um, you said you're starting to conversations about language what kind of bridge concepts do you have?
It just depends on what we're trying to explain.
So the more common the explanatum, the more the more people who you share the same the same kind of experience we're trying to explain, the more the guys can appeal to Dasman or one's task and one's uh I'm sure some of you don't know that's German for the one.
He says one perceives the meaning.
You're getting it from Heidegger and Heidegger rights or you're speaking German.
Oh, the is Gasman.
Go ahead.
So the more the more common the exploratory experience we're trying to explain is, the more we're going to appeal to the one to the task of the one, and the more particular it is, the more we're going to appeal to the features of the individual.
It doesn't matter if the features of the individual, the task of the individual, do infect the experience all the way down.
Depending on the level of commonality we're trying to explain, the more...
I know I don't like that.
I mean, I don't think that's, I think that's makes it just relevant to our interest whether we if the language affects our experience all the way down.
And I want to say, no, it's a substantive question whether it does or not.
And it is, and no matter how interested you are in how much language affects our perceptions, you can hold the view that children, pre-linguistic and us, see things exactly the same way.
So, yeah, but the language fits to work out something like that.
That's basically all of the aims of the individual and so on in trying to characterize.
Yeah.
I could see that.
Language is the hardest.
And I guess I want to say that if you think language affects it, then of course you think that the individual and the style of the culture affect your perception of an object.
And if you think language doesn't, then I think you also think that your personal interest in your culture don't.
I don't think language is all that special about it, about this big issue.
But I don't want to spend more time on this issue because that wasn't what I came to talk about.
Though it's an issue that ought to come up sometime, and now it has.
In fact, it keeps coming up.
So I'm going to go back to where I was because it's fascinating exactly what I want to talk about on page 271.
It's when he gets all these gets onto the notion of presence with this side of Merlot Fonti, it makes our perception like children and animals prominent.
So starting right at the top, herein lies the distinction between the perceptual synthesis and the intellectual.
On passing from double to normal vision, I'm not simply aware of seeing with my two eyes the same object.
I'm aware of progressing towards the object itself and enjoying its concrete presence.
Presence is a big deal word in Merlot Fonti.
It's not just any old thing.
Remember, it's got to do with the way the back of the house is already present.
We have a front of the girl or the guy.
When you see objects, you don't just see surfaces or data.
You see the whole thing.
But here's what he does, his obstiety and the affinity of it.
So let's read it a little further down.
The 50-month sound, the binocular object in which the synthesis occurs, absorbs the monocular image, and which in this new light finally recognize themselves as appearances of that object.
My set of experiences is presented as a concordant whole, and the synthesis takes place not insofar as they all express the same invariant.
That's the intellectual handy and the identity of the object.
That's again more interesting intellectualists.
They all come under the same concept, but in that they are collected together by the last of their number in the expirity of a thing.
That means when they come together, then what is really, what is experienced is really there as sort of taper needs ghosts back into it.
And the expirity means distance.
The distance is, of course, never reached.
That would be the pure distance of the thing.
Then you have to sort of take in every aspect of it from everywhere.
Each aspect of the thing which falls to our perception is still only an invictation to proceed beyond, still only a momentary halt in the perceptual process.
I wanted to mention that because that's very interesting.
Because it sounds always like the perceptual process is reaching equilibrium, is somehow getting someplace and stopping.
And most of the time he does talk that way.
You get an imbalance which you finally balance, a tension which finally goes away.
And yet, it's clear that there's something wrong with that way of talking, too, because you've never sort of arrived at now you've seen the object so completely that there's nothing more to see and or one because you switched to some other object but two because there's always more to see about any object that's its richness so he wants to say both that there's a tension toward equilibrium, that that isn't ever uh final.
And I don't know quite how to say that right, and I don't know I don't think he knows how to say that.
There seems to be, I mean, I picture of it something like this, that we're tending toward an optimal grip on this object, but then some other purpose or some other object attracts our attention, and before we've ever even finished getting a grip on this one, we're already off getting a grip on that one.
And we certainly and so that we don't so that though there's a tension and you are always moving in the direction of reducing it, I don't think it's important to know that you arrive at the equilibrium of the zero tension of the total balance.
I mean, it's always there as the goal that explains the way your perception is organized.
But I don't think it's something you have to arrive at, yeah?
The goal is important, you zoom in on it and you can keep feedback all the time.
It's really interesting.
You just go and buy a microscope and then you get it.
So I think the way to put it is the norm aspect, which is absolutely crucial, is that you are always trying to get a better grip.
That is, and in a certain sense, therefore, you could say you're always trying to get an or tending toward an optimal grip.
But I don't think that you need to think of it as what you are actually doing is arriving at an optimal grip, or that if you fail to arrive at an optimal grip, you have somehow not perceived.
The thing is, as long as you're moving toward a better, clearer, richer grip, that's all you need to explain all the phenomena that he's trying to explain.
I don't think the arriving at...
Nope, that's wrong.
Some of the experiences he wants to explain require an optimal grip.
Help me remember that when we get to the notion, when we get to depth, and the distance, that is, or depth is anything.
There you need an optimal.
And size, you need an optimal.
Huh.
Interesting.
I'll just tell you what I'm thinking.
The size an object is, perceived as being, is the size which it appears to have when you have an optimal grip on it, he says, I believe.
And the distance an object seems to be is experienced as how far it's from what it's like to experience the object optimal.
So I guess I believe, and I'm going to, that's the two chapters I want to explain today, or at least by next time, that the depth story and size constancy story assume that you actually get, not that you always have a maximum grip, but somehow the experience that you have when you do have an object, plays a crucial role in your experience of what it is to have a certain size and to be a certain distance.
Rich, were you onto this already?
Yeah, why?
What?
Because.
I don't talk about what?
Oh, I see the task.
No, I don't want to talk about the task.
That's why you're running into this problem.
So, the quantum special example of equilibrium that William T gives is when you're engaged in the task, you're looking at a painting.
And there, you want to get a maximum grip of behaving, not as having microscopic properties that you would look at through a black microscope, but as a work of art in the museum where there's certain lighting, and then that's what's pulling you.
So, you are being pulled, and there is this maximum grip stories to be told, but all that is the field vendor that's not for trying to accomplish.
And that's why, you know, when I want to find an object inside, you know, a fork instead of the knife or speaking in a dark kitchen, once I get the knife, I maximally grip it, and then I move on to the other task.
And it's not like I don't believe that knife.
Once I have the knife, can I go on and I can't do that?
I disagree with you about this.
I think I've seen you and the chair and the book, all task-free, so to speak.
And then some of them I have a task.
Oh, I like reading the book.
But the chair, I got no task at all, but it's got its CAD and it's the Eddie and CAD.
And I think, and when I look out, there goes a police car.
I got no interest whatsoever in that police car that I perceive it.
And I just don't want to deny disagreement.
Well, the disagreement is again, boy, we're stuck on this one.
That whether there's this basic level that you can describe in a task-free, language-free, culture-free way or not.
Because in French differently, he says that when you cross the concourse design barriers, when you're crossing us in fact, there's a girl who can always stop this task and just concentrate off your what's on the wall, and then you do it for the predictions of the world to do your so I think Santa's saying the opposite of what you're saying.
So you don't always have a task, which does like you always have a task.
Well, then you don't have it.
But I mean, and now when when you suspend it do you reveal a more fundamental well but I think you could suspend it and reveal thereby a fundamental thing that the one is the one is doing in you through your body schema whether you've got a task or not.
But it's each other.
No, no, it's never the whole picture.
It's a methodological point.
I think the bike would be sense of our getting a maximum grip on anything without involving that somehow in the parents.
Yes, all the time.
Yeah.
I mean, absolutely.
I mean, every tree I see when I walk down the street out there and so forth, unless my task is what?
Oh, you are maximally gripping them.
I think all of them.
Or at least, no, I think you're not.
Of course not.
But what you are experiencing due to them as attention away and in the experience of them is a sense of what it would be like to get in a better look at them and not task, but just in them there is a tendency to pull you to what would give you a best look at them independent of the task.
For example, all the noises that are going on.
Now you're you want to get a maximum group of blind voices when I understand them.
Yeah.
And just as there is the bell ring and also, you know, going by or something like that you're trying to pay attention to all these things.
And if you're asked to change them, and then you do make an effort to get an active movement.
That's why you're turning your face and listening.
You're not turning your head down and listening to the bell.
You turn in your base and you know basically.
I'm not sure, I mean, it's a task.
I mean, I think he thinks that there are things that attract your attention, and it could be that the bells attract your attention, in which case you then sort of pay attention and zoom in on them.
Uh whether you have to have a task of whether paying attention and zooming in on an object that's drawing your attention is your task.
Boy, is this uninteresting something?
If you didn't you weren't guided by the task, then you would be pulled in an infinite number of directions, trying to get a mask and river everything at the same time.
No, no, why shouldn't something pull you rather than others?
Because this has to be my point of this has to be what it pulls you for a long time.
But the bell could pull me just by being noisy or why being a distraction of your past.
But when Google is noise to boosters, you will get a different path.
Well, it could destroy my past.
Okay, how about beautiful?
I mean, well, considering the guy's telegraphed object, when you see it as a beautiful woman, that's relative to certain interests.
I can't deny that.
That's the basic level of seeing a solid object there, I think.
Yeah, I think that there's a basic level of seeing a solid object, on top of which there is the attractiveness of the object, whether God created the object, whether, you know, whether I'm threatened by the object, whether it reminds me of my mother, and all this of course.
But that doesn't deny that there could be something I share with animals and one-year-old infants.
Yeah.
It just means you want that.
You're talking about sea hounds.
It's never your attention.
Something that we're explaining is the sense of all the time.
And it's not even like a particular task.
Like the task is not always.
But do you think there always is a task?
But there always involving a team retention.
Let me get this in the pot.
Well, I'm there.
Being in the world, being in the world in Heidegger is a personal task.
I think in Merlot Quantity, he's clear, animals have it.
Insects.
How much?
I mean, the existence is always trying to get a grip.
And if that's a task, then everybody's always got a task.
But it's not personal.
I won't talk about it anymore.
I'm just going to tell you everybody's going to tell me how I blew this lecture, but it'll be all your fault because I'm trying to go on.
So I'm going to go on.
Okay, let's see now.
3712.
I did the, I just did that.
I'm going to, well, that one thing, I did the obscenity.
Let's do the essay of it.
A little further down.
The obscenity of the thing is unchallengeable presence and the perpetual absence into which it withdraws are two inseparable aspects of transcendence.
I mean, that's the thing.
Okay, I see now that I can leave this one for Sean, because the whole issue of the thing in the natural world is where he's going to try to tell you the level at which your personal tasks and your personal history and so forth are not what's at stake.
And then you can see whether you believe it or not.
Okay, I'm going on to the general conclusion of this chapter, which is always the big deal thing that's going to bring in optimal grip and all that.
Being in the world at the top of 272, this is again where I started, seeming like five minutes ago, at the top of where I was saying how the body as a unified system, that's the body schema, the impersonal unified system is geared into dealing with the world as unified.
So he says the sight of sounds, the hearing of colors, we're back in synergistic stuff, comes about in the same way as the unity of the gaze to the two eyes.
That's getting the two images together.
Insofar as my body is not a collection of adjectives and organs, but a synergistic system, all the functions of which are exercised and linked together in the general action of being in the world.
That's, I mean, that's sort of the slogan, or one of the slogans that comes out of this chapter.
The other one, I think, is in 279.
Oh, that's the one I'm looking for.
Book, I have lots of blood today.
No wonder I put these things into it.
Two-thirds of the way down in 279.
Perception is always in the mode of the impersonal one.
See, we haven't totally wasted our time because now you can see how hard it is to understand what that's claiming and how important it is to understand what that's claiming.
The issue is sort of when he says it's always in the mode of the impersonal one, I presume he's got to mean, we all agree at least, underlying whatever personal task and so forth and so forth, there is this mode of the impersonal one, unchanged by language and your tasks and your understanding of being and your culture.
That's what I read this passage to say.
So let me read it.
Perception is always in the mode of the impersonal one.
It's not a personal act enabling me to give a significance to my life.
The person who, in sensory exploration, gives a past to the present and directs it towards the future is not myself as an autonomous subject, but myself insofar as I have a body and am able to look, rather than being a genuine history, perception ratifies and renews us as a prehistory.
That's the quote I was looking for.
Now, that's the level that he wants to describe.
And my claim is, and I get to have the last word on this one, is that he wants to describe that level in this book anyway, as independent of what levels get laid on top of it, personal levels, historical levels, past levels, linguistic levels.
And it's something I think at this level that we share with animals and pre-linguistic children.
It's any entity that has a body enough like ours will see objects enough like ours because there will be the same impersonal one in their body schema.
Now, that might be wrong, but that's fine if I'm wrong.
Then you guys have got something you can write about and think about and challenge me on.
I'm going to go on, okay?
Well, we're finally to the space chapter.
Luckily, we have Thursday also.
And here's the past things I was looking for.
Bit by bit, I find what I put in here.
Things not Merloponte.
I knew I had a list.
We're not big lists.
I only found two so far.
But something to warn you about as you go into this chapter.
It stopped now in the space chapter.
It stopped being Merrill-Ponte about two, four, six lines from the bottom of the first page of it, 283.
Kant tried.
And it's not, usually, it's hard.
You need me to warn you, because it just sort of goes off the rails without him even without him even telling you who he's talking about.
But Kant is what he's talking about.
And Kant's field space, until about 15 lines from the bottom of 284, where it says, and according to Kant himself, of all knowledge connected with space, and of that.
Now Merle Panchi comes in and says, it's true that we are faced with the alternative either of perceiving things in space or conceiving in so-and-so.
And is it true?
Wait, wait, is it true?
No, yeah, he's questioning it.
I see.
Yeah.
I walk like let's say.
Kant has been saying that.
But now he's answering Kant and saying, is it true that we're faced with the alternative of perceiving things in space?
Or if we reflect and try to discover the significance of our experience, of conceiving space is the invisible system governing the acts of unification performed by a constituted mind.
All that's critiqued with a recent talk, and you don't need to know.
Does not the experience of space provide a basis for its unity by means of an entirely different kind of synthesis?
Again, that's a synthesis in quotes, if you think that Kant's the big geosynthesizer.
But he's saying Kant has his idea of synthesis.
We can call it a synthesis if we want, but there's a whole different way of experiencing space than this idea that Kant has, that you either experience things in it or you have what he calls the pure form of intuition, which is the global grasp of something called space.
Just don't think about Kant.
Go on.
Say, all now I'm going to read my stuff for a minute.
All the arguments in the space chapter, and maybe in the whole book, depend on the organisms seeking not just a good grit, but a best one.
Ooh, I was contradicting myself for a while.
At least, so I think I'll take out this in the whole book.
But I think the arguments in this chapter depend on the organism seeking not just a good grip, but the best one.
And the chapter shows how important the idea of maximum grip is for narrow function.
It's necessary for us to be able to achieve a maximum grip, not just tend toward it, achieve it.
In order to experience things as having a certain size, being a certain distance, and moving.
That's pretty serious, I mean.
And I think that's the claim.
That that's what I'm going to get to show you more next time.
First, I'm just going to give you some maximum grip quotes to keep in mind as you read this and try to decide sort of what a maximum grip is and whether you have to have it in order to have size, distance, and motion.
And I guess I have to add orientation.
I'll tell you in a minute, or next time, why I think orientation is a special code.
But before we break up, I have to tell you what to worry about in the orientation.
Maybe we could read something first.
From 177, the end of the synthesis of one's own body.
We read it already, but I think we have to read it again now.
And notice this is one of those places where the punchline is right at the end, about 15 lines from the end.
Whether a system of motor or perceptual powers, our body is not an object of an I think.
It's a grouping of lived through meanings which moves toward an equilibrium.
So far, you don't know whether it arrives or not, but it's important that it's always got to be moving toward an equilibrium at least.
Sometimes a new cluster of meanings is formed.
Our formal movements are integrated into fresh motor activity and so forth.
Our natural powers come together in a richer meaning, which hitherto has been foreshadowed in the perceptual or practical field.
That's the storm on the horizon tension story, and which has made itself felt in our experience by no more than a certain lack.
That's lack of equilibrium.
And which, by its coming, suddenly reshuffles the elements of our equilibrium and fulfills a blind expectation.
That's if you haven't got a goal.
A blind expectation is something's going to come around which is better than what it is now.
Some way of experiencing something is not as good as it could be, and there must be a way to make it better.
That's the blind expectation.
I'm just going to read you my favorite maximum good quotes because we need them in our minds as we go through this.
Okay, 292, 92, about five lines down, maybe more like eight.
My body is geared into the world when my perception presents, and this is one we haven't ever talked about, I think, presents me with a spectacle as varied and as clearly articulated as possible.
Those are the two important dimensions.
He has lots of names for it.
Clarity and risk and when my motor intentions, as they unfold, receive the responses they expect from the world, that's the third.
There are three criteria that go together.
You have to optimize them to get the optimal grip.
And they all have trade-offs, so you can't optimize.
And if you optimize only one of them all the way, you get rid of the other.
But so you want to get them all as much optimized as possible.
Okay, so we and then when my motor intentions they're told receive the responses they expect from the world, this maximum sharpness of perception and action points clearly to a perceptual ground, a basis of my life, a general setting, that's with the impersonal again, and which my body, it can coexist with the world.
Okay, that he should be doing maximum talk here because he's entering the space chapter isn't surprising, because as I almost blew it, then got clear.
Maximum plays a big role in the space check.
Now let's see, 293, I say.
Important stuff on it, but not that.
So let me go on and do another one.
Three steps way off on three steps.
It could be, you know, anyway, that's typical of the way the book is written.
So how about four lines down on 352?
For each object, for each picture in the art gallery, there is an optimum distance of which it requires to be seen.
And I want to say, I mean, I guess Rick raises the interesting question.
Is it required to be seen that way because you have some specific task and interest in it?
Or is it, if you don't, if your task and interest is just seeing the picture, then the picture tells you where to stand.
I don't know.
A direction view from which it valves the most of itself at a shorter or greater distance with an area of perception blurred through excess or deficiency.
We therefore tend toward the maximum, there it is again, of visibility and seek a better focus as with a microscope.
That's another important one.
Now, I want to say one more thing for five minutes, just because I want you not to be confused about something.
Because first I have to see something.
Do I have to read 342?
You won't read that.
Okay, the first thing he goes into in the space track is the craziest and the hardest.
And you don't really have to read it if you don't want to.
It's about up-down orientation.
He's got lots to say about the fact that if you wear goggles and invert your experience of the world so that the image on your retina don't get confused is already inverted, as you probably know.
And that's how you see the world up normally.
But you can wear goggles that make the image uninverted.
And then that makes your experience of the world inverted.
But if you move around a lot for a while, over about a week, the world re-inverts and it looks normal again.
And he has lots to say about that, what that shows, and the stages you go through and it happens.
And I want to say that it's probably all wrong and thereby very confusing.
And the way it's wrong is very interesting.
And if there were time, I would go through it and talk about it.
If I get time next time, I will.
But I want you to have the basic idea as you read it or reread it, if you want to read it at all, whether he can get away with explaining the fact that we've got up-down-oriented experience, there is an up and a down in our experience, without evergreening in gravity.
He claims that somehow, and it gets very worrying and funny as we start saying wilder and wilder things, somehow up-downness is just there in the basic being of things, and you just finally got to get in sync with it.
Well, it's not some mysterious up-down, it's gravity that's there, and you either get out of sync with it and you get in sync with it.
The puzzle is the reverse.
How, given that gravity is driven.
You could reverse this with these goggles and feel at home in the world upside down.
I mean, that is a puzzle, it seems to me.
Olivia is getting upset, talking to me about this later.
But it turns out that this stuff with who's the guy who does the Stratton goggles have been repeated by a guy named Kohler who got so he could even ride a motorcycle in traffic with his upside-down glasses on.
And you can get totally at home in the world.
But the amazing thing is, so the two questions to read is questions as you read this up-the-down part, which is so hard and puzzling.
How in the world does he manage to talk about up-down without ever mentioning gravity?
And how, given that there is gravity, does the inverting lenses enable you to live perfectly okay, even though you are now sort of well, I think I know the answer, by the way.
I think the answer is something like that: your coping skills all get reconfigured.
I mean, it's so that you, when you lift something, you lift it down, so to speak, and it feels hard to lift things down.
It's like the what's the blind spot?
What's this?
The mystery spot.
How many have been to the mystery spot here?
You know, where if by some perceptual illusion, it looks like things are, the gravity doesn't normally apply, and you get so you can live in it.
Anyway, I don't know myself what he thinks, because I think he never tells us why, how he thinks of it, that our experience for coping with it gets us to be able to cope with things, even though the perceptual, namely the these goggles, have put us out of sync with the vertical field, namely gravity.
And it's got something to do with the amazing plasticity of the coping body that we're able to do it.
But I find this section completely insane because he's like you tried to tell the story, but you leave out one of the crucial elements.
And then he says absolutely weird things.
Well, anyway, this happens, just so you know, between the body of 284 and where depth starts at the bottom of 294.
I think it's fun to read it, and I think you should read it, and you should be asking yourself, what in the world is he doing?
Is he trying to do it without gravity?
Does it matter that he's trying to do it without gravity?
Does he have an answer to this whole issue of how we experience the up-down without it?
I don't know.
But it turns out that it's done by magic, the very end of the 296, where he stops, where he finishes.
And I think that's a bad sign, but maybe that's just a metaphor.
Anyway, next time, I'm not going to do the space thing because I don't know how to do the space, the orientation up-down chapter.
I don't want to sort of spend all your time showing you how weird it is, and I don't know how to make coherent sense out of it.
I'm going to start with depth on 297 and go on to the end of the space chapter.
Hopefully, you know, that's a long way to go.
And as a possible paper topic, I would love to have someone who thinks they've got a grip on you and explain what's going on in the orientation chapter.
So don't do it unless you really know what you're doing.
Talk to your TA.
Okay.