The two questions are the basis of intersubjectivity.
How we ever get open to other beings, other human beings, as independent human beings and react to them in terms of them as other, I don't even know how to say it, minimally, somehow uh demanding a kind of response from us that that natural things don't.
So we're going to talk about that.
And then the other one, I think it's a really interesting issue that I was on the edge of my seat wondering how he's going to figure it out, is how he's going to get together the fact that we see the world from a perspective, but we are all it's always the same world that we see.
We don't get caught in our perspective.
The way I would put it is, the second issue is the priority of the world to my world, where you try to keep my world somehow into this story too.
And they keep flipping over back and forth, the dialectic goes on and on between my world and the world for the second half of the chapter until it ends in total obscurity, I think.
But I know what he wants, and I could be right.
He wants somehow to keep hold of both.
That is, somehow we have our own, each of us has our own perspective on one shared world.
Now, here we are, ready to start.
So the first thing is that we want to, why have I got this?
It's already in serious other mindset.
Let me look at four things.
Oh, yes, Defici could.
But it turns out to be this is such a disorganized thing.
He launches out into a criticism of objective thought at the bottom.
But I wanted you to notice that it's tell you, as I always try to, that it's, oh, I want to just start.
Let me talk about confusion.
I wanted to do one thing first, which is sort of separate, so I just want to get it out of the way.
Something he says at the top of 405, which because this issue keeps coming up in office hours, that I, even if I walk down the street, the students who seem to me sometimes to be strangers come up and worry about my view that the natural object is somehow prior to and more basic and the grip we get on it.
The grip we get on it is non-task dependent, and the object we get a grip on is some kind of natural object that is prior to social and culture.
We've gone through it again and again.
I just wanted to show you on 105.
He says it again.
And I'm going to tell you what I think it means in a way that's become clearer in discussions in office hours maybe than I was before.
About four lines down on 405.
And every object will be in the first place and in some respect a natural object made up of colors, tactile, and auditory qualities insofar as it's destined to enter my life.
What I want to talk about is that first, obviously there's this natural object, the top of 405, which we perceive.
If you're in a different book, who's got the concordance this time?
Anybody?
Alva, you should.
Okay, just the end of a paragraph.
The next paragraph right after is just as nature fine.
Very top of 405.
347.
Okay, so right before that new paragraph, every object will be in the first place, in some respect, a natural object.
I don't know what the in some respect is, but I think I understand what in the first place it is and why it bothers people when I say it, because it doesn't mean that genetically we first experience natural objects before we experience them relative to our interests or relative to our culture or as equipment or whatever.
That can't be what he wants to say.
It isn't genetically first.
What is it then?
Well, I think it's what phenomenologists call a founding kind of relation.
That is, you could experience a natural object.
You don't very often, but he does talk about how you could do it in the Place de la Concorde if you just stop and stare at a wall.
You can experience natural objects without past relative and without culture relative characteristics.
But you can't experience cultural relative characteristics and past relative characteristics without a perceptual object there which has its, remember that Sean was talking about, it has its color, its tactileness, it makes its sound when you hit it, and so forth, and so its faith and all that.
Those perceptual constants that are in the chapter on the thing in the natural world all have to be there as the properties or characteristics of an object before you can have these higher order of things, like past relative and culture relative.
I just thought I, I mean, I now think that's a sensible thing to say, and I think it maybe gets rid of people's feelings that I go around thinking, and I do really, but I shouldn't, that we just have this kind of general body schema which gets us into relation with sort of near objects which are just there with their aspects and their colors and shapes and so forth.
It's not like that.
By the time we are conscious and dealing with objects, they've already got a style that goes with our culture.
They already, you know, rattle already something already for a culture where kids are allowed to make noise and it's already got its already in equipment and you can pay attention to some aspect of it task-wise and so forth.
Okay, that's all I want to say about that.
Is there something puzzling about that?
Alva, yeah.
Okay, I'm trying to exclude on the one hand the claim that we start by genetically, either in a culture or in the history of the race or in the history of the individual, these natural objects, and then add cultural predicates and task-relative predicates later.
I think that he doesn't want it, he shouldn't have to say that.
I think we get them all at once.
Any object you get now, like this book, is going to be task-relative.
You're interested in some page, remember, and there your optimal grip is relative to your task, and so forth.
So I want to say, now I don't want to claim that that's the sense in which the body schema and the natural object are basic.
So that's why I'm excluding the priority of that.
I want to say, but I want to exclude, on the other hand, a kind of constructivism, maybe I never made that clear, which says there's nothing basic at all.
I mean, once you see that it's permeated with culture and task relativity, you see that there isn't any and there never was any natural object at all.
That's what I was resisting.
There is still some sense in which there is a level of natural object, which according to Merlowe Pointillan seems right to me, and a level of the body schema, which is, of course, the thing latches onto it and is the key to unlocking it, that there is that level, and that level is, in some sense, what's the word prior here?
I've actually gotten the word I was talking all about.
In the first place.
And every object will be in the first place.
I'm just trying to explain first place.
That if there is a natural object, it isn't cultural all the way down, but it isn't as if the natural object ever shows up as independent or needs to.
That's what I'm trying to say.
Want any better?
He wants that it's not cultural all the way down, but that the better is experienced independently of the cultural object.
That's right.
Although I never seems to be too strong because he gives this example of staring at the wall in the classical concord.
It could be, there's nothing in principle against you're latching on with your body schema to the natural object which is not equipment, it's lost its cultural style, you're just staring at it and haven't got any task in mind.
You can do it.
There's a painter whose name I've been trying to find, which somebody once gave a lecture on.
I know who, so I have to just call it, who's apparently made it his life's work to try to paint objects as mere objects.
And they're sort of weird and their color is sort of vague and it's clear that they've got some kind of shape, but it's not very this very specific and so forth.
And I think that's a real experience.
I think this is the sort of seismic of mere objects that they're trying to kind of put it on his canvas.
I'm wondering whether you're the moving to this light with the thought that in some sense the natural properties are something that's more real for more crazy, not in an experiential sense, because they owe their nature to nature, whereas the other properties only show up against the cultural background, the absence of work.
Well, that's what I think about this founding thing.
Yes, there's a level of nature, and the nature is something that our body schema has, I would say, evolved to be exactly in tune with.
I mean, he never, I guess, evolutionary kind of thinking wasn't in the game then.
But anyway, there is this natural us, and we've got this natural body schema, and it's linked, it's in sync with these natural objects, and that can be independent of everything, of all these other levels.
That's the sense in which it's in the first place.
But it almost practically never experienced it, and that's all right, because it's always already transformed by all these overlays.
But it's never transformed away.
That would be the other mistake, that it's culturally so determined that there isn't any natural object in it.
You need to feel the cultural background to understand the experience of the cultural properties.
That's what I would say.
And then the idea is that the body schema is itself not conditioned by culture.
Well, is that culture independent?
That's a good question.
I would have thought that it was the same as the object, that it could be independent, that it is a level, it doesn't require culture and it doesn't require tasks, but that once you've got a culture and a task, that ought to be get into your body schema just the way it gets into the way the object shows up.
They ought to become a complete Corellium.
Yeah.
Well, yes, she's right.
I mean, if the culture, she could put it this way, but it's what she said.
The cultural schema is innate, whereas whatever else comes along is based upon our habits.
It's true that there is the innate part and the acquired part.
And of course, obviously, the cultural part's got to be acquired.
It couldn't be innate because it's different for all these different people.
And it's, and if you want to use the body schema, and you should probably, as the innate, already, always already given a history that has a prehistory, all these funny ways he talks about it, and the inborn complex, weird things he says.
If you want to find this, then you find it, then you better call that the body schema.
So I'll take back the idea that the body schema gets changed, but what you get to is a lot more body sets than this original body schema, where you're set to see all sorts of cultural things, stylistic things, and they go together on the side of the object, and they go together in the intentional arc.
That is, the world that showed up, that might show up, in principle could show up, as mirror, mirror, he loves them, so I call them mirrors, as objects with all kinds of wonderful inter-synergistic, inter-sensorial properties.
That world, which is a product of the intentional arc, because it shows up for me because of my body schema.
Thanks to the intentional arc, not only does all this other stuff get added to the body schema, but of course all of this other stuff gets added to the world.
It shows up in our world.
That to talk about as P.I.J.
does, that Rick mentions every once in a while.
Mailboxes show up as mailboxes, and they show up as four mailing letters, and they look like that.
And that's all I that just shows that there's a lot added to the original schema, to that good word.
You don't need any more.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Did I say that?
It could be.
I know I meant Gibson.
Oh, really?
Gibson takes you over.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's not engineering.
I don't want to say that the personal discovery are disrupted.
Is it what?
Disruption.
No, I don't think it's.
I want to resist that.
Absolutely resist that.
Does he say that somewhere?
Well, let's find it.
Good if you're quoting.
But let me say, well, I'll resist it first, but then I'll be shot down.
At least he'll know what's happened.
I mean, I want to say that what's built into the body innate and the objects with their kind of, we call it, lost the word for a minute, stable, but that's not the word I'm looking for.
The properties like the constant, the constant properties that objects have of size and shape and remember and keep telling yourself this and color and texture and so forth.
That, I'd be very surprised, but I'm ready to be surprised, that that would ever be disrupted by what the tasks we had the kind of equipment we had the cultural style we had why would that disrupt it instead of add to it now tell me where he says the other 85 38 by the way I can't I might forget so let me say right now my example would be how many seen the gods must be crazy okay well I'm thinking I'm on the side of the coke bot that is I take it that those natives who never saw anything like the coke bottle saw a green cylindrical solid thing which they then had to figure out why the gods dropped it into their world from nowhere but they didn't it didn't it and they didn't and when they did it didn't disrupt it it just they finally thought it was for rolling things and for hitting people and so forth uh okay now yeah didn't they first you and what you just said didn't they first see something that's all from the gods and not just the nearby property about it before that's interesting i guess i want to say to that i don't think that that was the way things look uh that that it did or i want to say i don't know which we don't have to we have to interview maybe it did look like it fell from the gods so we want to say that's added on to the coke bottle shape but then my example is gone i was hoping it was a a natural object that fell rick's got me there maybe you have to where's the 385 okay for those who want to know the other pages when we're 330 right before the new paragraph?
Okay, I'll read it to myself.
Everybody reads it to themselves, starting with the natural world is the horizon.
I think that's what i said.
If they're given unity underlying all the disruptions of my personal life and historical life, that doesn't mean a unity disrupted by my personal historical life.
It says exactly what I said.
There's this unity which that's a I love it.
I mean, that's the founding relation I'm trying to talk about, isn't it?
I mean, it doesn't say it gets changed by the disruptions of my personal life.
Maybe the next sentence, 10 minutes, we're given general pre-personal existence of my sensory functions, which would just, that's exactly what I was saying.
I mean, your sensory functions don't change.
Your eyes do what they did, your hands and all of them, your ears, and it stays there as a pre-personal that would certainly be task-free and I think culture-free, something or other, no matter what happens.
It underlies them.
Why do you think it says the opposite?
Anyway.
What I mean of that is that I don't see anything about disrupt the disruptions.
I see, well, I see you mean, I see how you're reading it now.
A unity underlying in spite of the way my personal and historical life disrupts it.
Well, even then, whatever that would mean, the unity stays there underlying it, the way the sentence is.
I mean, whatever disruptions there are, they don't change the constants.
We have to think of an example of what it would what would you think what are you thinking of?
What would disrupt it?
We're back to the Torah and the sacred baby.
Something somebody declares it sacred, and that even I, my picture is, yeah, it's sacred, that'll do funny things to your maximal grip and where you're going to stand, but it doesn't.
It still keeps a constant color, constant shape, constant weight, constant size, and so forth and so forth.
And nothing can disrupt that.
That's what I think.
And this passage doesn't change my mind about it.
And I like the idea of underlying that's the sense of first.
I mean, not first, not first in the tempered genetically first, but always there with a certain peculiar kind of priority, which I will repeat one last time.
You can have that level without any of these disruptions from these higher levels, but you can't have any of the personal and historical levels if you didn't have already the pre-personal thing.
Yeah.
I'll just give it a way of thinking about natural audience.
Is there a way of thinking about yourself as a natural self which steps on and extends away from raising your gender, your nationality, all these things?
Yeah, I think there is.
And I think it's relevant to this chapter.
It's probably one of the many balls in the air in this chapter which I can't keep track of.
The natural self would be the body FEMA, which we share with all human beings, and we perceive in the same way.
And our eyes, you know, we get death in the same way, and we follow brightness attracts us in the same way, and we go to the brightest light, or the light is right to see what we're seeing.
All that stuff, that would be the natural self, which underlies the social self.
I'm sure, I think we know that.
And so that's sort of related to this.
It's pre-personal, meaning not personal and not historical.
And the body, of course, this is also true of the fact that the body has arms and legs.
It moves forward more easily than backward, it balances any gravitational field, the kind of things that Samuel Torres is interested in, that we share with all human beings.
That's not the body in the L Ponte.
The body of Heloponte is this schema for inter-translating all of the sensory input.
Okay, Saturday, what you want to say?
I don't think it does anything else.
Anything you do is going to be in action, which will be constituted by humanity constituting the body.
It's not.
But in some sense, anyways, you can eat or anything that would get you to with your body is not schema.
I know, but you know what you mean, like what you were going to be doing.
Good, that's just social.
Yeah.
Okay, so that's all right.
It's not, I see now a new distinction.
It's not that there's some kind of animal thing that your body organism does that's not social, like eat or sex or breathe.
Let's suppose that's all social.
That every culture has their own style for doing it.
That's not the issue.
The issue is whether the body schema is pre-personal and not social, and whether the object that it gives you is, remember, no matter how you eat, you've got to eat something that keeps its shape, or at least you do, keeps its shape and size and color and texture and weight.
I could get a list and just hold it up every once in a while.
Anyway, I'm glad I brought this up.
I knew that it was a tiny fan of worms that's sitting there in the background.
And I don't think we need to bring it up again because it's not, I don't think it's the issue in this chapter.
I think that there are these two other issues, so let's go to them.
Okay, and as I say, I think they're interesting issues.
So we go to 407.
Now, what's happening on 407 is, well, that's why we have to go there, to warn you that it starts being all, at the bottom of 405, he asks the question about how an action of human thought can be grasped in the mode of the one.
But that then he sort of drops that and goes on to other things.
I don't want to read all this.
I just want to tell you that 406 is not narrow quantity from five lines down.
You may be getting used to this now.
I should probably take a poll.
Do you realize that it's five lines down?
The reply will at once, once more be that I see a certain meeting made by other men and implements, I interpret their behavior, an analogy with my own.
Do you realize that's not his view?
He doesn't think we interpret other people.
He doesn't think it's a mental activity.
He doesn't think that it's, but he do it by analogy, they do that, and if I do that, I'm an increase, so they must be an increase, and so forth.
So that's not narrow-quantity at all.
And then at the bottom, of course, it's still not narrow quantity, because now he's going off to say the existence of other people is a difficulty and outrage for objective thoughts.
And he thinks that.
But he then goes on, so that phrase isn't parallel quantity, but then he goes and develops objective thought anyway for all of page 407, which is also not narrow quantity.
Now I need to tell you something else.
How many from some other courts or something know Sartre's talk about being for others and being in time?
Well, anyway, who's got Sartre always in the background of this discussion?
If you're going to write on this, for instance, you better leave the section of being in nothingness called being with others or being for others.
I forget.
Anybody remember what it's called?
And it's also the subject of no exit, but no exit, the ontology started in the background.
And Sartre's got this whole story, which you get in here in clear, condensed form.
Merloponte is very good at summing up other people's views.
And the important thing to see is in the middle of 407, that for this person, for this captain who he is really discussing in this chapter without telling you, namely Sartre, there's two modes of being: being in itself, which is being an object, and being for itself, which is being conscious.
You see where that is, right?
Smack in the middle of that page.
In the middle from the top to the bottom, and in the middle from the right to the left.
And then there's only two ways of relating to other people.
You need to treat them as objects, or they treat you as an object.
And they're subjects.
And this is the story of no exit, whether they're the sadist.
One of them is sadism, and one of them is masochism, according to him.
Saddest wanted to stay for the self and treat everybody else as in itself.
They want to be conscious and free, and that's one kind of being.
And the only way to do it is to make sure that nobody else is conscious and free, treat them as objects.
Or some people, who are masochists, want to be objects, because that's very reassuring to get your property.
So they go around looking for somebody to do it because they treat them as an object.
And those are the only two modes of being, according to Sartre.
A little further down, he says, thus, there is no place for people in a plurality of consciousness in objective thought.
Sartre has now become the objective thought person.
And it stops, and all 407 is Sartre.
And now comes Merlot-Ponty finally, that we have, in fact, learned to shed doubt upon objective thought, and now we're off on Merloponty's own territory.
And just to finish this sort of thing, and his ontological answer to Sartre's ontology that there's only two modes of being, be a conscious subject or be a thing object, is to say there's a third mode of being.
That's just a little below the middle of 408.
At the same time, as the body withdraws from the objective world, it forms between the pure subject and the object, a third genus of being.
So it's very important that Merlot-Ponty thinks that his notion of the lived body is neither, and you should be used to this now, a lucid, conscious, free, meaning-giving subject, which is Sartre, nor is it to be a body, just a physiological, I mean, an object, a physiological thing that you just study as part of your nexus of causality in the world.
It's amazing that this view, just to tell you, how many of you come across Brandon in any of your courses yet?
It isn't as if this view is is gone.
It's just sort of metamorphosized.
I mean, and I Dick Lordy, another one, you've come across Horty.
I mean, for Brandon and Ordon, there's only two kinds of being, the being of all kinds of stuff in causal relations with each other.
And now it's no longer the consciousness, but the language using being.
Us as only as pure language users.
So somehow there's these language users who can make inferences and there are these pure things which are in causal relations.
And that's all there is.
That's just a new view of this.
And Merlot Ponty wants to say, no, there's a third kind of being.
It is meaningful.
It has intentionality of a sort.
It's got significance.
It's not the mere causal parts outside of parts of being.
But it's not a lucid consciousness either.
It's and Lord wrote me a note lately, this is why it's on my mind in an email saying, there is no other kind of intentionality than linguistic intentionality.
I don't know why you want to go around saying that children and animals and experts have a kind of intentionality.
Well, that's exactly what I want to say and what Merlot Fonty wants to say.
There's a kind of body intentionality which is in this meaningful relation with everything else and is a few words of it is an object.
That's what's going on here.
Pete Debden, a little and why he's saying next and do I want to talk about it?
I don't remember this before.
No, he just takes another hit at the sense data.
We might as well read it right after that.
Objects stand before me and throw this the subject loses its purity and its transparency in this third mode of being because we're meaningful, intentional, coping beings, but we don't have the purity that Sartre attributes to the fore itself.
Objects stand before me and throw on my retina a certain projection of themselves, and I perceive them.
That's everybody please to that.
There can no longer be any question of isolating in my physiology representation of the phenomena.
The retinal images and their counterpart form a total field, the actual and possible in which they appear.
Now, why am I reading this?
Why is he saying?
The physiological event was merely the abstract schema of the oh, he's saying, yes, he's against some any sort of view in which you can give a kind of mechanistic account of perception.
There is, and that would be some kind of physiological story about how the images hit the retina and then they get up to the central processor and so forth.
That's just not the perceptual event.
And you can't invoke under the name of mental images discontinuous perspective views corresponding to successful retinal images.
He's back again worrying about the view that we have a bunch of perspectives first and then schematized and ready to deal with and then we synthesize them.
I mean, that's the same thing as on 378, but it's always important to see it.
But then now we're going to get into the interesting thing.
That he's claiming, I want to come back to the middle of 409 at this time, by the way, just a little.
I'm going to signal it so we'll remember to come back to it, or at least you'll notice it.
I'll mention it now, because I think we probably won't come back to it given that we always go into discussions, and that's fine.
Notice the sentence in Middle of 409.
How many have come across Nagel's view that you couldn't possibly have an understanding in third-person form of our first-person experience?
Some of you, I'm sure.
Well, there's a Nagel sentence in here.
He says, all of a sudden, out of nowhere, exactly half on down in 409, how significance and intentionality could come to dwell in molecular edifices or masses of cells is a thing that can never be made comprehensible.
And here, Cartesianism is right.
Wrong.
So there we are.
There's at least this much truth.
The first-person perspective can never be reduced to the third-person perspective.
And one more, and following this, a kind of typical narrow-puncture assault on science, it is simply a question of recognizing that the body as a chemical structure or as an agglomeration of tissue is formed by a process of impoverishment.
That's, you've got to get used to him saying about science that it somehow leaves out a lot.
And what it talks about somehow isn't as real and isn't as causally basic as what it's explained.
I mean, I think that's a, I think, the wrong way to think about science and the wrong way to think about the physical organism.
But he wants to say that insofar as science describes the organism, it's leaving out whatever it is that's really important, namely, that it be the organism already has existence, has being in the world, copes with things.
And if you can't explain that, then you have things that you can't explain anything that's important.
I'm going to argue in a minute that science explains something very important that Meryl Ponte can't understand.
That's why I want to set this up.
I think he's wrong about this.
Okay, one more preparatory point.
All are running around on 409.
As always, I want to try to see how much he's going to get out of his optimal grip story.
And what he says at the bottom is that what we, through phenomenological reflection, I discover vision, not as a thinking about seeing, to use Descartes' expression, but as a gaze at grips with the visible world, and that's why, for me, there can be another gaze.
But all of a sudden, he's given a one-sentence solution to how I can see these objects moving around, you objects moving around, as if you were a conscious, meaningful, intention, entity with intentionality.
And how would I see it?
Well, I just see you coping with things.
No, no, no, you don't need optimal grip, but I see you out there trying to get a grip on things.
And that's, and just because I see that, I see intentionality.
I see your body already having this kind of purposive activity.
And immediately then, I see that you're a special kind of being.
And having defendered.
And on 4.11, we come back to it at the bottom of 4.11, no sooner than has my gaze fallen upon a living body in the process of acting, than the objects surrounding it immediately take on a fresh layer of significance and so forth.
That is, they now are understood as what this organism is coping with.
Now, that's as far as he ever gets to this interesting problem.
But I think he comes close enough that we can push him further.
The interesting problem is: how is it that I come to recognize other people as other meaningful acting beings like me?
And his answer is not by analogy.
That would be this objectivist mistake.
I see them making movements, and I figure if I make those movements, I feel so-and-so, so they must be feeling and thinking so-and-so.
He hasn't got any criticism to make of the equally wrong view I think he would surely hold, which is empathy, that I just have some kind of natural feeling for others.
Well, he's closer to that.
Maybe it's empathy.
He talks about how I can just directly see other people's anger and so forth at a certain point.
No, I don't think that's empathy.
Empathy is supposedly the view that I have feelings in me and that I then can have a direct sense that you have those feelings in you.
He thinks he's got a third view.
When I'm coping in the world, you could see me coping in the world, and I can see you coping in the world, and it's that that we manage to make me able to see you as a being like me, namely with intentionality.
That's what he keeps.
That's this, that's the claim with it back here anyway, that you can see the person, you can see this being coming to grips with the world, and when you see that, you see another being like you.
Yeah, Alan.
Um, I was doing so maybe you can just try to identify that.
Um, have you been in yourself, and then you can say other things?
Oh, okay, right, right.
Sorry, I did miss.
But that's just as bad for him, but it's better to get it right.
Yeah, but it's but it's too inner for him.
I mean, it's not a question of finding out to you that other people are also people by understanding their feelings.
That for him, I think he would, I don't know whether he'd say that that's impossible wrong or why, but he's not.
He agree is he wrong.
It's not an analogy view, but but I, but he, it makes it, but his view is not an empathy view, I think, because it's because it's not about feelings, it's about acting, he wants to say.
Yeah.
There's an argument in one sentence at the top of 409 that I don't believe.
Myself, in reflecting on perception, the perceiving subject appears to provide with primordial setting in relation to the world, drawing in its train that bodily thing in the absence of which there would be no things, other things for it, then why should other bodies, which I perceive, have similarly, being habitated by consciousness?
So the argument seems to take the form of saying having a body is a necessary thing for perceptual consciousness.
That's something we've learned already in the book.
But then he seems to go from that to the thought that certain kinds of bodies are therefore sufficient for consciousness at the end of the sentence.
And I don't understand what.
I don't think that's what he's arguing.
That is, all he's trying to argue, set up here is what he's going to kind of call out at the end of the page, that when you understand the kind of bodies we have, then you will understand them as having meaning and purposes, and see them as having, you can see them directly as having meaning and purposes acting in the world.
I don't know.
I can't tell.
I have nothing to say about it further.
Yeah.
I'm still not clear on Mello-Ponte's solution, so the argument.
Well, we haven't done it yet.
The solution.
Okay.
It was a fast solution.
We should go over that.
You're not clear about the fast solution that we can just see.
No, then he's got a much more interesting solution when he goes on on the next page on 410 and begins to spell out this solution about grips and gazes.
And then that's when I want to say he's got an interesting issue.
He's got an interesting answer, but in the end he thinks it's miraculous.
We'll talk at 410.
When I turn towards perception and pass from direct perception to thinking about perception, I reenact it, and I find it work in my organs of perception of thinking older than myself.
And those organs are merely the trace, of which those organs are merely the trace in the same way I understand the existence of other people.
Now, how is that?
Well, he says, whatever that same way is, and now it's going to take a while to figure out what he's talking about.
It's not a question of analogy.
And then he says, and that's because it's more direct, but he doesn't, just to keep the empathy ball in the air, too, he doesn't say it's a question of empathy.
He says it's something much more basic.
And then he says this fascinating thing in the middle of the page.
A baby of 15 months opens its mouth as I playfully take one of my fingers between my teeth and pretend to bite it, and so forth.
Well, there's more to this now.
I mean, you know that if you smile at a very, very early baby, I don't know the Tom Daniel.
What?
45 minutes, it smiles back.
And how about keeping your tongue out?
About that, too.
Sean tells me, since you know Sean, the funny story, he just had a baby.
So he tried this out, and he stuck his tongue out at the baby.
And lo and behold, then he stuck his tongue out at Sean.
And now every time, for a long time, and ever Sean came into the room, the baby stuck its tongue out.
So there is this.
So there is, anyway, this very important fact about kids.
Yeah.
They're reading by analogy, but that the very season, the coffee between early settings, the natural world, and I don't know if you can say.
Well, no, I don't know.
Well, I reenact the alien existence.
Never mind, though.
I don't want to talk, but I don't want to talk about that.
I just want to, in order to get cover what I want to cover, I've just got to say, sort of brutally every once in a while, we've got to go on.
I'm sorry, James.
I'm sorry, Sophie, but I'm going to come on.
Okay, so because I'm now, I want to talk about this biting business a little further down.
The biting has immediately for it an intersubjective significance.
It perceives its intentions in its body and my body with its own, and thereby my intentions in its own body.
That's what this is supposed to show.
Well, that seems a bit much to actually claim.
All we know is that he knows it's not an allergy because he knows the baby doesn't even.
Let's do the smile.
So you smile and the baby smiles back.
Well, that's strange.
How can it know even that it's got a face and a mouth and what muscles to pull to get it to its face which it doesn't know it has and its mouth which it doesn't know it has to do what your face which it's seen it has?
It certainly isn't normal kind of understanding of an intersubjective significance.
It's more basic than that.
And so later he wants to explain how it's more basic at the bottom of the page.
I think he's wrong.
But here's between my consciousness and my body as I experience it, between the phenomenon body of mine and that of another as I see it from the outside, there exists an internal relation which causes the other to appear as the completion of the system.
I take that that's supposed to explain the biting and sticking your tongue out and smiling.
The other is evident to me because I am not transparent to myself and because my subjectivity draws its body in its wake.
That seems to me very, very vague, what that's saying.
And it wouldn't have seemed vague if it hadn't the neuroscience has actually stumbled on what seems to be the real facts about what's going on here, and that is mirror neurons.
And I think it's fascinating.
I said I was going to tell you in a minute how Nero Panty is wrong, that science can't tell us anything about this, that just because the brain is a bunch of neurons all and nothing else in their physical things, we can't cast any light on significance.
Sure, we can.
The mirror neuron story, if I, if those of you who know more about it, could correct me, is that it's been discovered that there are certain neurons that fire when, what is it, a chimp or kind of monkey sees another pick up something.
Then the neurons that fire for seeing the monkey pick up something are the same neurons that fire when that monkey picks up something.
That is, there is an immediate connection between seeing a meaningful action on the part of the monkey and doing that meaningful action.
It isn't something you figure out.
It isn't something mental.
It's something just wired into the neurons that already interact with the organisms that do these kind of things in a way which picks up that gesture.
Now, I don't know why, but there must, I mean, I gather you inhibited most of the time, you who know more about mirror neurons, who don't go around always picking up something when we see somebody pick up something.
They think the monkeys, the manhacks have been inhibited, I suppose.
If you did the repeated colours hard, the gesture of the other, but that covers up the question.
And if there's some neuron that fires when I see it happening, and it's the same neuron that fires when I do it, why don't I do it?
And from then on, the stove looked, you know, and there's a you know, I can see the the repul the repulsion of the stove.
And I mean, it seems like a neuron.
Yeah, yeah.
It seems like a mirror-neuron explanation.
That sounds right to me, but that's not the question I'm asking.
Let me give you one second.
Now, well, yes.
And that the mirror neuron wasn't helping you down.
If it's the same neuron that fires, when you guys can help me out.
But first, okay, go ahead, Gabriel.
The proparation for doing that there is where the mirror neurons are fired.
Just because mirror neurons are fired, don't even know how to do that.
I think it's a good idea.
Okay, so it needs some other contribution from the brain to do it.
My pa my picture of mirror neurons, so I don't know if anybody's written about this, is yawning.
I mean, that's the pure case.
You see somebody yawn and you yawn.
And I mean, there I take it, that the shortcut between the see the seeing it and the doing it is really there.
But the eye as and I don't know how and maybe for the baby, the tongue's sticking out and the smiling must be like that.
You see somebody doing it, and you do it.
And and and that's that's mirror neurons that they're mirroring us.
And but what I want to say is, Meryl Fonte has no, of course, has no clue about this, so he says these very vague things.
There exists an internal relation which causes the other to appear as the completion of the system.
That's supposed to be the baby sticking its tongue out, I presume.
And we're going to just say one thing, Albert.
I want to find out where he tells you it's miraculous on the middle of 412.
Now it is precisely my body who perceives the body of the other.
That's right, all right.
I stick my tongue out, and the baby's body perceives my tongue going out and sticks its tongue going out, and discovers in that other body a miraculous prolongation of my own intentions.
So I stick my tongue out, and the baby miraculously sticks its tongue out.
It's big deal.
I mean, that's not any help.
But he, I mean, now we can say I stick my tongue out, the baby sees it, the same neurons that enable it to see it are turned on, and with nothing else needed, it automatically does it.
I take it.
I mean, that's supposed to be what's happening.
And that seems like an explanation.
It also seems like an idea that maybe you can understand some of the phenomena he wants to understand by understanding what's going on in the brain, which means that the brain isn't just an abstraction that leaves out everything important.
The brain might even be doing some of the things that are important.
So I find that all interesting.
Now, I asked if there was another hand up.
Yeah, James.
It's very important in that kind of way.
Is it important 409 that thousands of individual intentionality comes as well in a massive cell?
I guess you're right.
You're right.
I realized that, but I didn't say it, so I should have.
Yes, I mean, it the negative question is how consciousness really gets into the cells, that the cells could pick up what that something like the significance of what's going on without it having to pass through the mind or consciousness is seems to me a funny thing that he finds that actually could happen and that he can't understand.
We have to talk about this, but I mean, it certainly can't pick up consciousness, and maybe it's too, I see what you're saying, too automatic and too minimal to say that the cells are picking up the significance of my yawning and yawning back, or my tongue going out and going back.
How could cells ever pick up the significance of anything?
And, okay.
Well, there are models.
Walter Freeman comes back in here, of how cells could pick up the significance of something, but it would take a lot more cells and a lot longer story.
I'll buy your point.
Albert introduced something about back in the 60s, New York and Beetle discovered that certain cells had receptive fields, for objects here being certain orientation in the visual field.
And I always thought, wow, we can build up some accounts of how we experience physical copies of objects by the cognition of those receptive fields.
That is completely therapy.
There was no such theory in the audience.
All we know now, is that the moment any cells do live, some cells have to change receptive field property with your sense.
If they're showing those things, monkey does that.
We don't know yet.
There's no theory of human minds that makes any sense to dominate.
Well, I'll buy all that.
But in the context of whether he owns page 410, he's thinking about this deep story, supposedly, about the baby, and the baby, you know, sticking a pen out of that.
It came from a psychological theory of mutation.
Imitation, all you can say is imitation.
But uranium is what all neuron is playing.
Okay, I'll buy that.
But there must be a brain story about imitation, and it's not going to be there exists an internal relation which causes the other to appear as the completion of a system.
Or maybe there is, maybe that sort of sentence is just an empty placeholder for the story.
But the mirror neurons is a little piece of that story.
I agree with you.
Maybe it isn't even like the Google and Weasel cells never turned out to amount to anything.
I've always, I've been so happy about that.
I from the start who never believed in the Eogle and Weasel pages.
Well, good.
They can work on it.
Let me go back to this because time is getting short.
I think all I want to say is, let's see if I've got this, that there is something which Merrill Plantees got onto.
I mean, the phenomena is certainly important.
It's you got 129 414.
Now that's a different phenomenon.
I'm getting clear about something.
I wasn't clear.
So I talked about 410.
Okay.
Now let's switch.
What I want to switch to is what starts on the top of 414.
And that's really on 413.
It's nevermind this business of now a mirror neurons, of the well, as he puts it at the bottom of 412, another attempt to say something, the body image ensures the immediate correspondence of what he sees done and what he himself does, which is a statement of the baby thing again.
Then maybe that's all we can say yet.
We don't know anything more.
But it's probably not going to turn out to be miraculous.
It's going to turn out to be a complicated story.
But now I said all I wanted to say about that.
The other issue is a much later developmental story on 413.
So remember, on one I said, he sort of waves his hands and he says miraculous.
On this one, he goes on and on worrying about it and saying interesting things until at the end I think he just vanishes in a cloud.
The question is wonderful.
The question, it starts with some research again, which hadn't happened yet, but he's got a kind of version of it.
That is, on 413, two-thirds of the way down, the child lives in a world, the child is on the left margin.
The child lives in a world which he unhesitatingly believes accessible to all around him.
He has no awareness of himself or others as private subjectivities, nor does he suspect that all of us, himself included, are limited to one certain point of view on the world.
Now that's interesting.
Now there's been experiments done.
Children at the age of three begin the following experiment.
This just confirms what Merlot Fonte is saying here, only it's much more dramatic.
There's a box of a kind of candy, and you show the kid, the three-year-old, the box of the kind of candy, and you open it, and lo and behold, it hasn't got candy in it, it's got pencils.
Then you have some adult come into the room, and you ask the child, what does he think is in the box?
And interestingly enough, at the age of three, the child says, pencils.
You see what that means?
That means the child thinks that there's one shared world and we're all open on it and it knows there's pencils.
It's open to the world in which there are pencils, so this other person's open to that same world in which there are pencils in the box.
So that other person knows there's pencils in the box.
That's wonderful.
By four, the child doesn't know that.
It's funny, the bottom of 413, Narrow Ponchi thinks it's 12 years old.
Lots of progress has been made.
At about 12 years old, says Piaget, the child acquires the cobitof and reaches the truth of rationalism.
At this stage, he discovers himself as a point of view on the world.
Well, apparently at four, the kid discovers.
But that's not important.
What's important is how to make sense of this.
This is really the most interesting thing.
Now, what does the child learn when it learns that it's a point of view on the world?
Well, it's such an unstable thing that you see in the rest of the chapter.
I'll try to state it in its purest form.
The purest form of misunderstanding it, I think, is represented by Allison Goffnick in the psychology department.
And she knows I say this about her, so I've been wanting to give a seminar with her.
She says at four, the child discovers the idea idea, that it's got an eternal representation of the world, and the other person's also got an internal representation of the world.
And in the kid case, the kid now knows that in its representation of the world, there are pencils, and in the other person's representation of the world, there are this candy.
And there's something right about that, but it's gone to the whole switched over from we're open on a public world to we've each got a private representation, a private model of the world, and you have your model, and I have my model.
In my jargon, it's got it put my world prior to the world.
Is it that the three-year-old the world is prior to my world, it hasn't even got a my world?
At four, the child has flipped over into pure Sarkrean or cognitive science or Cartesian craziness, I think.
At any rate, you flip over into this view that my world is prior to the world.
It's on the basis of my model of my world that I'll have to figure out what your model of your world is.
And then we can construct a model of the shared world, which there really isn't any, of the shared world, that we've all got our, but we can make this whatever it is in common into a shared understanding of the shared world.
But you got your representation, all that you've got, really.
This is pure Sartre.
Sartre has worked this out in detail, and it's for Judy Speck.
That is, that from the point of view of each individual subject, that individual subject has got to have its own world.
And look at this on 415.
He's talking Sartre, though he doesn't say so, about halfway down.
Well, I think I jumped a little ahead.
Oh, yeah, one thing I want to say, which is very important, we're going to come back to it on 414 first.
So, there, the child achieves the coquette.
All of a sudden, the child turns into Descartes, discovers mental representation.
See, what I want to do is give a seminar with Alice and Dopnik and say, How do we know that the child discovers private mental representation?
How do we know that the child isn't brainwashed into your model of representation at this point?
All the child has understood, which is very important, is that it's got a perspective on the world, and it's different, and so have you, and yours is different than its.
But it doesn't say that you've got your private model of the world and the other person's got it.
But now comes the point I want to raise.
It's very hard to understand how to talk about this, which where you either looks like we've all got the same world, and then you get the view which he attributes, which is really a kind of Kantian view, where he's not, it's not his own view anymore.
There's all these non-views.
If I can refer to it so you know where it is.
Yeah, okay, the bottom of 417, he's doing, starting with after this failure, he does the view that we are all happy.
But let me try to say it just clearly first.
So either you think like the child, the three-year-old, you not only think, you experience like the three-year-old, but you are, as he puts it on the next page, an empty head turned towards the world.
Or someplace says that.
And where's the empty head turned towards the world?
Is somebody saying?
I'll tell you what it is.
I'm used to feeling these in the other version, which makes it hard for me to figure that way they are in this version.
I didn't underline it.
It's one of my favorite phrases.
You didn't underline it either?
Oh, no wonder I was.
I'm glad you.
Okay, well, well, I was behind it instead of, but I don't see it yet.
You see it?
The bottom.
413, the bottom.
Oh, yeah.
For him, that's the child.
Then our empty heads turns toward one single self-evident world where everything takes place.
That's wonderful.
That's very important.
That's the view of the three-year-old.
Now, and you can and then you flip from that to everybody's got their own perspective on the world, and all they can ever experience is their perspective on the world.
That seems to be what you flip to it for.
But it can't be.
That's what, I mean, that's what the theory theory people think you flip to.
But America Concy has this strange and interesting thing to say about it.
It's a top of 414.
It's not an answer.
It's a puzzle.
And the puzzle just gets more and more puggling for the rest of the chapter.
He says, at this stage, it is held, he, the child, discovers both as a discovered himself, both as a point of view on the world, and also called upon to transcend that point of view and construct an objectivity at the level of judgment.
But perceptually, he's now limited to his point of view.
Piaget brings the child to a mature outlook as if the thoughts of the adult were self-sufficient and disposed of all the contradiction.
Piaget and Albert Krumbotnik are the same in that.
All cognitivists are.
But in reality, it must be the case, and this is the funny claim that's interesting, but in reality, it must be the case that the child's outlook is in some way vindicated against the adult and against Piaget.
Now, what that means, in some way, it must still be true that we experience ourselves as open on a shared world.
And that's right.
I mean, look at this.
Here we are.
You're looking at me.
I'm looking at you.
We're all looking at this classroom.
You don't feel that you're in prison in your perspective and I'm in prison in my perspective.
We really feel, see, the phenomenon is that we are open heads turned toward the world from a point of view.
And that's what he's trying to say and preserve here.
And he says, with all these cognitivists, leave out the empty head part, but you've got to have both.
And the question is, for the rest of the chapter, how do you have both?
Because what he says is, then, okay, let's start at the top of 415.
When you can see other people's anger and without recourse to any inner experience of suffering or anger, aha, maybe that's the anti-empathy part.
I perceive the grief or anger of the other in his conduct, in his face, in his hands, without recourse to any inner experience of suffering or anger.
That's anti-empathy.
Where are we now?
And because grief and anger are variations belonging, variations of belonging to the world, undivided between body and consciousness, and applicable to others' conducts visible in his phenomenal body, as in my own conduct is presented to me.
But then the behavior of another and even his words are not that other.
The grief and anger of the other have never been quite the same.
And now, having said that there's some sense in which I can directly experience from the the shared world from my perspective, the shared world being your anger, you've got it, I've got it, and I can see it just like you could see it in your heavy breathing and red face and fist and so forth.
That's the total, we're just open to the world.
He goes back on the other side and says, yeah, but your anger is experienced by you and your grief in quite another way than mine.
They don't have the same significance.
You're really in grief.
And I'm feeling bad that you're in grief.
And now that's all a Sartrean story.
Sartre is definitely a believer in my world is prior to the world.
So you tell him the story about anger and stuff.
And then Sartre answers, yeah, but your anger is experienced by you as a private thing, and my anger would be experienced to me as a private feeling, an inner feeling.
And you can't get over that just by seeing this common sort of action that is angering him.
And so this is all on this page now.
It's, I guess, two-thirds down.
It's from the subjectivity of each of us, that each one projects this one and only world.
That is, it's not really a one and only world.
There really is the private subjectivity of each of us.
The one and only is in quotes.
That DeSarte thinks that the shared world is a kind of, I don't know, not exactly an illusion, but a projection.
Your experience is of your anger from inside, so to speak.
The difficulties inherent in the perception of others did not stem from objective thought, nor do they dissolve with the discovery of behavior, Merlot-upon-T viewed that the Tsar talking against Merlot-upon-T.
Or rather, objective thought and the uniqueness of the Covita which flows from it are not fictions but firmly grounded in the phenomenon.
All that is, that's all Sarah's answering him, Merrow-upon-T.
And then I guess the next paragraph is probably Merrill-upon-T, but it becomes SART again on 416, where he says, I, on the other hand, share no common ground with another.
This is to be really inside your perspective.
For the positing of the other with his world and the positing of myself with mine are mutually exclusive.
Now that's to say my world is prior to the world.
The true phenomenon is that each of us has our own world.
And there's whatever sense there is of the shared world, it's something we sort of each agree on, as something that we find to be common between our private worlds.
Once the other is posited, this is still Sartre.
Once the other's gaze is fixed upon, the other's gaze fixed upon me by inserting me into his field, stripped me of my part of my being, before itself has turned me into in-itself, in other words, it would readily be understood that I can recover it only by establishing relations with him and so forth.
Then you get all these relations of neutralizing the other guy and so forth.
We're not going to go into that.
And now, about 15 lines down of 417, there is here a solophysium rooted in living experience and quite insurmountable.
I take it that we're still inside.
And because I'm the only one, you talk about whatever happens, and it's in the middle of the page, I'm the only one by whom these experiences are experienced.
And there's something about inalienable subjectivity.
And then the paragraph ends on 417.
And now, this is the dialectic.
It's going back and forth.
First, it looks like you've got to be open to the world.
Second, it turns out, and it looks like there's phenomena that suggest you are, the anger, seeing the anger.
Then it looks like, no, each one of us has our own private world.
We're caught in our perspective.
That's what we just have.
Now, in the next paragraph, we flip back to the objectivist view.
And it turns out, and it's really like Kant, everybody shares the same universal understanding.
So there's only one impartial spectator, one universal subject, and there's no problem of other mind for the objectivist, reflective person.
I think, I don't know whether it starts with Kant, but he's certainly got Kant in mind.
He talks about how the ego, the individual, is, there is an impartial spectator, and that constitutes the individual self, the bottom of 417, as just another thing.
This general consciousness takes my empirical self to talk like Kant.
My transcendental consciousness, which is universal, posits my empirical self as that individual which has a view on the world, that I'm really this transcendental subject.
So then he's going to criticize that for a while.
But now you should have in the back of your mind as you read it, by the way, this goes to the middle of 418, did not Nero-Ponte.
Now it's not Scarte either.
It's Kant.
It's the opposite of Sartre.
Instead of everything is completely my world, there is only the world.
And me and my world are just constituted and posited.
Now he comes back to trying to find out a place for my world at the top of 419.
Remember what the question is.
I don't want to lose it.
How do we keep both the three-year-old and the four-year-old's truth?
We've got to keep the fact that we're empty heads turned toward the world, and we've got to keep the realization that I see things you don't see, and you see things that I don't see, that each of us have our own perspective.
And the idea is, somehow, Nero-Ponty thinks Piaget and Sartre all go in the direction of we're trapped in a perspective.
We stop thinking we're open heads.
And Kant, the transcendental ego, is like an open head turned toward the world.
All transcendental egos do the same.
And Nero-Ponty rightly says we've got to keep both.
And he hasn't told us how to keep both.
And so we keep looking.
And I'm going to tell you, we've got five minutes.
He never tells us how to keep both.
He keeps flipping back and forth.
And then finally, you'll see, he tells you something very important, but something that won't help much.
Yet.
So he says at the top of 419 that I have to be experiencing other people, and I don't need to talk about that.
On 420, it's started again, the middle of the page.
The other transforms me into an object.
He denies me.
I transform into an object and deny him.
It's asserted.
The middle of 420, that's straight star.
That is Dory, no exit.
And we're going around in circles back and forth.
So then he switches to solipsism and the question of solipsism, which is a different thing, whether I can understand what it is, whether the notion of other minds makes sense to me at all.
I'm not going to say anything about that.
And then he switches to the social world and goes on and on about Russian peasants and so forth on 422 and class consciousness.
It is a mess, an immense, crazy chapter.
The Russian peasants get completely analyzed in the freedom chapter.
He should have saved that.
So, and then at the bottom of 423, in italics, something interesting that he attributes to Husserl.
And it seems to be sort of hard to know which way to take it, but it's in italics, so we should certainly try to figure out how to take it.
We're now in the paragraph that begins, the problem of the existential modality of the social is here one with the problem of transcendence.
That then gets him out of the Russian Revolution and back into phenomenology.
So then, how the presence to myself, which establishes my own limits and conditions every alien presence, is at the same time depresentation and throws me outside myself.
That's what we have to figure out.
The topic's important.
I said, well, let me, okay, the problem of ex where should I start there?
Okay, I have a good idea.
That's a whether we are concerned with my body, the natural world, the past, birth, death, the question is always how I can be open to phenomena which transcend me, which nevertheless exist only to the extent that I take them up and live them.
Oh boy, is that important to use that sense?
Because that could sound terribly much like idealism.
But I don't think it's meant to be.
What?
Well, the one I just read is the one after it.
Let's get this.
I don't think he's saying that the question is how I can be open to phenomena which transcend me and which nevertheless exist only to the extent that I take them up.
That would be that nothing in the world exists except that I take it up.
That can't be right.
It's got to be something I wrote, but my translation of it into something you could possibly could possibly believe.
No, I don't see why I wrote it, but I'll tell you what I think.
It seems to me he's saying that we've got to understand that the significance of the phenomenon depends on.
That is, that the phenomena won't exist, that is, won't be significant unless I take it up, unless I take up the significance and live it.
I think something like that is what he wants to say.
Well, remember, you said that existence and significance are one and inseparable.
That's right.
Well, that's what I'm basing it on, right?
You don't think existence for him isn't existence objectively like electrons exist.
Electrons, I don't know what his word would be, but it would he's taken.
I guess probably electrons are real, he might say, or something.
But exist means for him, has significance.
And of course, something has significance for me, only to the extent that I take it up and give it significance.
Yeah.
Oh, really?
Oh, wow.
I don't see how to do that, but I love to do that.
How?
Tell me.
That's just a case of experiencing something in a way which is not the majority of the fine by just your own perspective.
So there's a certain similarity.
And so the funny man, by taking the light, is important to me from it.
Yes, of course.
And I see that so interesting.
So you take up the house and you take it up s from a perspective, but because you're open to the world from a perspective, but you're open to the whole house.
Maybe that's what the final thing.
Look, we've got just a few minutes and skim to the end.
Because that might be what he's trying to say when he gives his solution, which I couldn't understand.
Okay, this is on page 424, 425 at the end.
I will get it now.
Let's see.
There's all this stuff about death and birth.
I swear that's just smoke in our eyes when we're trying to deal with it.
I don't think for a minute that that's important.
But we could look at the last paragraph.
Let's see how we start.
Well, he thinks that it's a kind of contradiction that we are both open to the world and from our perspective, I think.
And now about eight lines down on 425, that perhaps he maintains that a philosophy cannot be centered around a contradiction.
That all our descriptions, as they ultimately defy thought, are quite meaningless.
The objection would be valid if we were content to lay there under the term of phenomenon or phenomenal field the layer of pre-logical or magical experiences.
For in that case, we should have no choice.
We would we should, for in that case, we should have to choose between believing the descriptions and abandoning thought, or knowing what we are talking about and abandoning our descriptions.
That's what Sartre is speaking about.
Sartre is saying that only his view is really make sense, his ontology and his understanding of all this.
What Mero-Conte is saying is just the magical dobbly loop from Sartre's point of view.
And Sartre in general, and Mero-Ponty has this wonderful relation.
Sartre has got this very clear ontology, and if the phenomena doesn't fit it, he just says so much the worse for the phenomenon.
So there is no mutuality, there is no love, according to Sartre, because those are just illusions.
And then Mero-Conte comes around and says, no, the most important thing is to get the phenomenon right.
If we have to do something for the ontology, we'll fix it.
In case you think this is a strange relationship, it's the Plato-Aristotle relationship.
Plato's always got all sorts of arguments and then denies change, denies all sorts of things that we see around it.
And then Aristotle comes along and says, no, the most real thing is this lectern.
And we'll fix our ontology.
So here we go now.
Now let's see.
These descriptions must become an opportunity, his phenomenology, his sort of Aristotelian attitude, for defining a variety of comprehension and reflection, altogether more radical than objective thought.
Remember, Sartre is objective thought.
To the phenomenology understood as direct description needs to be added a phenomenology of phenomenology.
We must return to the Kogeco in search of a more fundamental logos than that of objective thought, one which endows the latter with its relative validity and at the same time assigns to it its place.
I think these are just words.
I'm going to think more about what Alvis said, but let's finish it.
So far, I find that absolutely unhelpful.
At the level of being, it will never be intelligible that the subject should be both natural and naturalatis, that is, infinite and finite.
But now this is what I called at the beginning of the lecture, just explaining the obscure by the Morris here.
That if we rediscover time beneath the subject, and if we relate to the paradox of time, those of the body, the world, the the world, the thing, and others, we shall understand that beyond these, there is nothing to understand.
Well, maybe that's going to cash out as meaning something someday, but it certainly doesn't mean anything yet.
I don't understand, but Alvis said this now, I have to think about it, why he didn't just try to use the house story to do this instead of blow it up to Catherine's time and everything.
But anyway, I this is why I didn't want to teach this, and I'm not going to teach it again.
Okay.