After sort of taking time out for two that are not involved in the perception of objects and how our body plays a crucial role in the perception of objects, we're back with the question of how the body perceives now it's intersensorially the objects with various qualities and that's going to be the subject for a long time, sense experience and then space, which is hard, but at least I have a feeling anyway they're very important things in there if we can figure them out.
And then I sort of probably my favorite chapter is a thing in the natural world where all this comes together in the story about what it is to be an object in the world.
But anyway, here we are now on page 235 where he's giving us an overall view of the fact or the way the body and the world, as he puts it, the body and the world form a system.
Then you need to know, it's an interesting test to see how you're doing now.
I don't know whether to give you advanced warning or to see if you can get it.
Do you realize how many understood that at the bottom of 235, it suddenly becomes not Merle-Ponte?
You should know.
And he gives you a clue, which is unusual.
He says it will perhaps be objective that.
And then comes a whole intellectualist objection that goes on to the middle of 236.
That is the whole the idea that he's opposing is that in our experience there are separable elements that are of experience that correspond to various aspects of an object as we go around it, a cube in this case.
We see it from various projections, and that those can somehow be isolated as elements and then put together in some kind of intellectualist synthesis.
That's what he thinks is wrong, that you can't get behind the unity of the object, or you can't think that you find beneath the unity of the object some sort of elements that need to be synthesized or unified.
That's always constituted.
Those are always, almost always, bad things to say.
Sometimes he says in his own words, synthesize, and sometimes it says constitute.
At least that does confuse me.
And I'll point out a passage.
But generally, it's quite clear here that it's not Merhilopanti's view.
It's the intellectualist view.
And it's all about how we put together an object in conceiving of the whole cube, as he puts it.
When he's talking about conceiving, and then he talks about conceiving my body as a mobile object.
Well, that's surely all sort of as if I was doing all this standing outside, looking at the object as having these aspects and looking at my body as occupying some place in objective space.
Then my body moves around the object and reveals these various perspectives, and then my consciousness, my transcendental ego or whatever, puts together these perspectives as perspectives of one object.
That's exactly not his view.
There's when he looks 237, where he sort of tells you what his view is.
And he uses the word constitute, so you can use it in general ways.
But look on 237, he said the top.
The cube with six equal sides is not only invisible, but inconceivable.
It is the cube as it would be for itself.
So he doesn't believe in that.
He's going to talk, now skipping down about 15 lines.
If there is for me a cube, that is, that's the cube that you can understand, you can, we're really dealing with, with six equal sides.
And if I can link up with the object, this is not because I constitute it from the inside.
It is because I delve into the thickness of the world by perceptual experience.
One of the hard things about this chapter, it seems to me, it's so metaphoric.
Sometimes I can't really tell.
And if you can't tell, it's not your fault.
Well, I don't know whether, well, I'm assuming he understands it, so I can't say I can't tell whether he understands who he's talking about.
But I can tell that I'm not sure I understand what he's talking about because I find myself sort of having to go back and fall into his same metaphors and say it all in terms so close to his that I'm not sure I'm conveying anything to you that you either don't understand already or do understand already, but I'm trying.
But there's this alternative thing.
If you go too far from his way of talking, you end up talking like an intellectualist.
You end up close to some version of Husserl.
And we don't want that either.
So it's very hard to know.
I used to think, well, we'll just get rid of all the metaphors.
We'll just tell what literally happens.
And I'm not sure there's any language for describing literally what happens.
So you get things like, you delve into the thickness of the world by perceptual experience.
Let's try at least to say something, not in those exact words, which is something like, it's always, in my other jargon, engaged existence, blending into a world that you're always trying to get a grip on and you're always already involved in.
Sometimes it's called being in the world.
Just delving into the thickness of the world by perceptual experience is trying to describe your perceptual experience from the engaged attitude as a body moving around in a world, trying to get a maximum grip on things.
I presume this is just another way of saying that.
And that it's it if you have one worries about it, at least have I captured it?
I don't know.
But let's keep, I keep trying and you can decide.
I'm 237.
You hear what he says about it now.
Two-thirds down.
The cube is already there in front of me and reveals itself through the perspectives.
Well, we've got to get used to that.
That's the crucial thing.
Which comes first?
The whole object or the perspectives.
And if you think that the perspectives come first, then you're in a kind of intellectualist view, a view that I think Husserl held at some point anyway, where you have to have something external to the perspectives, which he called the noema, which is an intellectualist structure, like a conceptual thing, which holds together in your experience the experience of the perspectives.
And that's certainly what he doesn't want to say.
He wants to say that you always see the whole object from a perspective.
And that what comes first and doesn't need to be synthesized, and he's going to go on and on and try to tell you why, roughly to give you the feel for it, because your body schema takes it in and gives it to you as an object from a perspective.
And that's not a job your mind can do, or your transcendental ego can do, or your concepts could do.
It is a job that gets done by the body schema, that there is this object from a perspective.
But the body schema doesn't do it as a kind of copy of the mind, just unconsciously synthesizing the perspective.
So how the body schema does it, we're not told.
And that's fine.
I think that's the right thing to do.
Because if he told you how the body schema did it, we'd be in intellectualism.
And when I hear it, I always think, and I think I said this again in the last lecture or the one before.
I mean, you could think like this, your perceptual system does it, and you don't have the slightest idea how that works.
Nobody in the world has the slightest idea how these billions of neurons do it.
But it gets done in you and through your body.
And by the time your mind comes along and your consciousness and you're aware of it, it's already done.
And it's a big, it's the big intellectual mistake, intellectualist mistake, to think that you've got to somehow break it down into its elements and explain in some minutes way how they got unified.
They just are unified when you experience them.
And you can't get behind that.
You can say, I'm just repeating myself, the body schema did it, but the body schema can't be a rule or a hierarchy of rules, as Husserl calls the Nalima, for doing it, or you're in Kahn, or Husserl, or C.I.
Lewis, or some intellectualist view.
That's the view he wants to resist.
That much is clear to me.
So let's read this passage and many others, which I'll come across in due course, but we're still two-thirds down on June 37th.
The tube is already there in front of me and reveals it.
Well, I better go ahead.
I do not construct the idea of the geometrized projection which accounts to these perspectives.
That would be the rule that relates them all as perspectives of an object.
The tube is already there in front of me and reveals itself through them.
That was all I was speech was about.
He's always experiencing the object from a perspective, but you're not experiencing an isolated thing called a perspective.
This is holism.
You know, top-down holism is another name for it.
Or he's going to call it a...
That's enough for a minute.
I do not need to take an objective view of my own movement or take it into account in order to constitute the true form of the object behind its appearing.
That is, I don't have to worry about where I am in objective space relative to the objective space in order to make sense of why the perspectives are unfolding in the order they're unfolding in.
That's, again, to stand outside and look at yourself as if you were a computer trying to compute the object by the data that's coming in, and that's not how we do it.
I do not need to tell where I'm so important.
The account is already taken.
See, already the new appearance has composed itself with the lived-through movement.
So you don't know where you are in objective space.
You know that you and the object have some whole linkage, and as and you understand your movement through the way the perspectives are changing, and you understand how the perspectives are changing through your experience of your movement, and those are two sides of the same system, that they and they all are aspects of something more fundamental, how your whole body is already in touch with this whole object.
That's how he pictures it.
Let me see where it's going.
The thing and the world are given to me along with the parts of my body, not by any natural geometry, but in a living connection comparable or identical without existing between the parts of my body itself.
Well, again, I don't know, I don't find that very helpful, but I think I was just trying to, but I was trying to paraphrase it.
A living connection, I mean, these are the metaphors you've got to make sense of.
Why is there a living connection?
Well, it's a connection that only happens because you're living it, experiencing it, moving around in the world, doing it.
That's the point, I think.
And why is it like the connection of the parts of the body?
Well, because remember, the whole body is acquired to and gives the significance to and the position to the elements.
Now it's the whole body and the object within this kind of dance, which that whole thing gives the meaning and the significance to and relates whatever aspects.
I need two words.
You need two words.
I'm going to use them consistently from now on.
I think this way.
You need a name for a perspective thought of apart from the object.
It needs to be synthesized into an object.
Let's call that features of the object.
The features are prior to the whole.
You also need a name for the perspective view of the object, which is the object seen from a perspective.
Let's call that an aspect of the object, where aspect means situational already embedded in and defined by its place in the whole.
And he's really saying you never synthesize features, you directly experience aspects.
Anyone want to say anything about this?
Olivia and Alva, of course, wanted to say something.
I want to point out an expression that we are going to see in the introduction, in the beginning of the fourth chapter, the scenario film.
He talks about the constitution without ideal modeling.
Oh, good.
Okay.
This cuts both ways, but it's important to say.
It says that what's the pen.
Where it exists?
About one page after the beginning of the fourth chapter.
What's the fourth chapter?
In the introduction.
Okay, Alva will tell us what it is.
In our dictionary, okay.
Okay.
I love these phrases.
I'm surprised I haven't ever read this.
I don't think I ever have out loud.
Look at all.
I mean, this is all this metaphor, but it's nice to read it again, just what I've been saying.
And then we'll get to the place where, well, I suppose I'll just fall on the place that Olivia is mentioning.
Well, no, she talks about it's lower, but I'll get there.
But I like to read at the top here.
Sense experience, third line.
Invest the quality with vital value.
I mean, there's all vital, whenever you see vital, you could equally well say existential.
It always is meaningful coping.
Grasping it first in its meaning for us, for that heavy mass which is our body, whence it comes about that it always involves a reference to the body.
Let's skip some stuff here.
Two-thirds one sixty-one?
What, the other book?
Two-thirds of the one.
Yeah, on 61.
I see where it is, but we should tell everybody.
But I haven't got there yet.
Sense, I'm now about one-third down on 61.
Sense experience is that vital communication.
He's only got one metaphor, really.
It's alive, it's vital.
So that vital communication with the world, which makes it present as a familiar setting of our life, it is to that, it is to it that the perceived object and the perceiving subject owe their thickness.
That's another metaphor that he gets into every once in a while.
Think of the thickness when you just think of the house as you already see the house from the front.
The back is already present.
It's not a facade.
That would be a perspective.
It's an object from a perspective.
That's the thickness.
And then, really wonderful, it is the intentional tissue, which the effort to know will try to take apart.
That's a weird phrase.
Intentional tissue.
I once had an idea of how to say that.
Well, we'll get to what he means by intentional.
And tissue, I think, is like body tissue.
I mean, and it's the way the body and the world are so intertwined, finally, that you can't take them apart.
I guess now that I think of it, intentional tissue becomes flat, right?
Yeah, intentional tissue is what he'll later call the flesh, and it's just the way that there's one big whole of which the body and the and the object are aspects.
Now we're skipping down to what Olivier calls attention to.
I'm going to start a paragraph in a sentence so I know where I'm going.
Whereas these notions, what is these notions?
Association and passivity are volcano notions now, right?
But you're talking about it.
Whereas these notions take on their full meaning of sense experience as distinguished from quality, then association and affinity in a Kantian sense is the central phenomenon of the perceptual life since it is the constitution without any ideal model of a significant grouping.
I don't know what to think.
If God would attribute this to Kant of all people who are the arch intellectuals, is he saying that Kant doesn't have rules for synthesizing everything?
Well, this is a the re this is the rereading the rereading of of Kant by himself, but what he what he talks about here is the the the meaning he himself was against the Constitution.
So this is a good expression expression, I think, because he he remains talking that constitution throughout the world.
It means this without ideal model, without proof.
But sometimes Kant okay, oh, so hmm, I'll have to go back and look.
So keep your eye open, is all I can say.
And my guess is right now, there are two senses of constitution, because often the word constitution turns up in these passages which are clearly not narrow upon people and seem to have to do with this intellectualist move.
You're saying constitution never means intellectual.
I'm not.
I'm saying that the meaning here of what he proposes is it's an algorithm at the end.
You mean to use it both ways.
But when we see constitution in the text, are we supposed to always think that it's a way of putting something together in terms of its holistic significance and not in terms of any intellectualist move?
Or can it sometimes be intellectualist constitution, depending on the context you're reading?
Sometimes it means here.
Oh, the real meaning of theory.
Any ideal model is the real one.
So it won't be called, okay, let's check this.
It won't be called Constitution where I was just reading about it, because that was sort of insulting this by saying that an ideal model, right, on page 236.
Is that going to be called Constitution?
Let's hope not, because I'd be happy if he stuck to any meaning.
Well, 236 is this whole paragraph which is not narrow upon T.
It will be objective, starting at the bottom of R235, at the beginning of that section.
The theory of the body is already the theory of perception.
I don't think I usually mark it when I see Constitution, that he uses it.
Maybe I agree with this point.
Yeah, yeah.
Because what I'm saying is relevant to the interpretation of the...
Okay, yeah?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, as I understand you, Professor Verdez, what you're doing is portraying sort of a strongly intellectualist view, against what the same is the correct mode of my view, and strongly intellectual view as it.
But what we do is we're effectively aspect.
No, I mean, not to say aspects.
Right.
That is to say, isolable bottom line.
He doesn't mean it's fun remote, but that feature in this sense doesn't mean the radius or the post-he means what's presented from the perspective.
What?
No, wait, no, no, no, no, you can't say that.
I don't disconnect everybody.
Victor would be the perspective, the way I'm announcing the term.
Aspect would be the object of presenting.
So when you, the intellectual speech with the ones who reject, says here, can you see perspective and synthesize a sense of the whole out of that through some intellectual aspect?
And the good view says, no, we're always immediately aware of the whole.
But we always experience the whole from a point of view, from the perspective, and possibly use the word aspect in the good way.
And to make sense of that as a reading, you're forced to say that this large passage that you know is read exactly where it is not a point of view.
But if it were a passage, there's no passing.
Let me just say there's a third reading.
The third reading, which says that simultaneously, as we're, one can simultaneously, as a phronological matter, be aware of the whole by being aware of its aspect.
Yes, one experiences the whole in the aspect, through the aspect.
When it's over through the aspect, there's always a chance that it's true, both that one's experiencing the whole and that one's experiencing the aspect.
And there's no source of knowledge that you're saying that you're experiencing the aspect.
And if you're in perfect one of the finding that you have a plan to be able to change that first perfectly, because this is going to shoot down at you.
We're going to lose everybody.
This is a dangerous thing.
But it's interesting, so let's just keep everybody.
Oh, I wanted to tell you, when you get lost, because there have been complaints, and rightly so, that we get into these discussions and lose you.
That's a legitimate complaint up to now, but it's not going to be legitimate from now on because it's your job to raise your hand and say, I don't know what you're talking about, you've lost us, and then I will either drop it and we'll talk about it later, or I'll explain it.
That's what you're saying now?
Okay.
This one, a good point.
But I think this is so important that we won't lose you.
We'll just take you with us.
I mean, a lot depends on whether Merlot Conte is defending an intellect.
He's never defending an intellectualist view.
So the question is: is he presenting, as I think he is, an intellectualist view in this first paragraph, starting where it will perhaps be objective at the bottom of 135 and the top of 136 for us, which he is rejecting.
And that would be a view that what is ultimately, given, or given at all, but to talk to what Alva's interested in, that what's given at all is a perspective of an object, sorry, a perspective, which put together with other perspectives, adds up to an object.
And I'm saying he doesn't think that's the case at all, because the whole determines the parts.
And we're back to this thing, it's worth repeating endlessly because you have to keep saying we're back to the house and the girl on Telegraph Avenue.
There is a view that isolates the perspective as a feature says that there's something about the back of the girl or the front of the house that stays the same, whether you consider them in isolation or whether you consider them in looking at the object.
And I could be sure that Merlot-Ponty rejects that view.
He wants to say there is nothing in your experience that stays the same when you look at the back of a man walking down with a beard and a mustache walking down Telegraph Avenue and you look at the back of a beautiful girl walking down Telegraph Avenue.
Even if it's the same person, nothing stays the same.
If anything did stay the same, it would be a feature.
It would be a perspective.
It would be an element.
And it would need to be put together with other elements.
I want to say, he says that since you always see the whole object from a perspective, you'll have to see the back of a man with a mustache or the back of a girl.
You can't see the back of a human object, according to him.
You've got to see it with all of its other sides already implicated in the side you're seeing.
And that's what he's talking about.
And when he seems not to say that, I think I can always relearn to read the book, as I'm hoping to it.
I think whenever he ever says anything else, it's always the intellectuals you're getting at into and telling you that's not the way to think about it.
And the issue is really whether it's top-down and all the elements get whatever significance and perceptual character they get from their place in the whole, or whether the elements can be considered as separate from their place in the whole.
And I think he's very clear that they can't.
Are you unlocking?
If you're unlocked, we can go on.
Yeah, very good point, because I don't want to pass the front quote.
It's very important.
I'll just make one textual point.
I think that one, when he says it may perhaps the objective, that he makes the objection about one sentence, and then he picks up his red and his own voice after that one sentence.
Well, and I haven't seen any textual argument with that smile.
Okay, well, is he?
I think he says subsequently in his three-point development.
I mean, I'm going to look back at it because I think this is an important paragraph.
Go back at the Conference 236.
As I move around, I see the front face living to a square.
That's ambiguous.
And I don't mean it could mean I see the front face as something which you could isolate from the whole object, doing this little trip as you walk around.
Or you could see I see the object from the front, changing its aspect as I walk around.
So we don't know yet.
Well, the other side comes with the only one.
But the success is taking R4 means merely the opportunity of conceiving the whole cube.
You think conceiving the cube is relevant to his story?
The cube is directly given from the bottom, from the ground up in his story.
You think he conceives the cube?
Which side do you think?
Is this paragraph Merilloponte or not?
Not Merillo-Ponty?
Because on 237 at the last page, he talks about...
It precisely says in the intellectual sense of constitution that you do not constitute the cube from the inside.
So this is constitution with an idea, mother, which is the one he rejects.
That's what I think.
Okay, but that's what I think, Galva.
The thing is, you have an anticipation of what the whole cube might be when you begin grasping it from one part, when you're embedded in the world and everything.
But this anticipation doesn't give a meaning to the object that would be geometrical.
So the cube with six equal phases constituted it from the inside.
This is not the way you anticipate.
He says that's not only invisible but inconceivable because I don't really get it here.
If anybody can help me, let's do it while we're here.
Because you have to experience the cube by getting inside it.
This is the menu 237 where constitute comes up again.
If there is for me a cube, this is clearly his view.
Me is Merilloponte, a cube with six equal sides.
And if I link up with the object, this is not because I constitute it.
Ah, that's on my side for constitute.
Constitute it from the inside, but because I delved into the thickness of the world by perceptual experience, meaning that I just immediately have a house that's thick or whatever.
Right?
And so we're back to that again.
I don't, I mean, it's so obvious that.
Okay, let's read the next sentence.
The cube with six equal sides is the limiting idea whereby I express the material presence of the cube which is there before my eyes under my hands in its perceptual self-evidence.
What?
It comes after.
First you get the lived cube and then you can of course abstract the idea of the cube and he isn't against that.
Expressing it is not, you don't have to express it in order to dress the cube.
That's right.
You don't even have to have it.
The cube comes prior.
The lived experience of the cube is definitely supposed to be prior.
Yeah.
Don't get lost if you're if you're getting lost, that's fact.
But this is the crucial issue.
We're trying to get our debt clear about the difference between Merilloponte's position and this very attractive, very similar intellectual exposition, which comes to us from Kant and to me from C.I.
Lewis, who was my teacher, and the time I had a break out of it.
And it's so close to what Merlopony was saying and so seductive because it says you need a mental equivalent for every kind of meaningful organization of the elements that you've got.
It's worth spending a lot of time deciding, one, which you want to believe, and secondly, which Merlot-Ponty believes.
Yeah.
I actually want to change the subject.
Really?
Okay, I'm going to change the subject.
Okay, at the bottom of that paragraph.
No, no, naturally not.
We've got a whole, unless you use up the whole hour on this, I got lots of persuading passages.
We have to go on, yeah.
Okay, at the bottom of that paragraph in 237, he says that the object, the thing in the world is given along with the parts of my body in a living connection comparable or identical to that existing between the parts of my body.
That's the schema.
Yes.
And so but that suggests that the object is part of my body's schema.
That's how we're supposed to read that.
Yes, in the end, he says amazing things.
I can't open to them.
Olivia probably can't.
My body and the object are really just two sides of the face of two aspects of one thing.
And the body schema and the sentence.
Where is it then?
External perception and the perception of what's sort of conjunction.
Because they are two facets of one and the same act, right?
So it is the body schema.
But you can't, here's another way to put it.
And this is indeed very important.
You can't have any access to the body schema as something you could entertain in your mind, as something you could describe as rules.
What?
That's separated from the word.
It's separated from the actual living of it in contact with the object.
He's very clear about that.
You have no access to it.
It's not sensory, motor contingency spelled out as a rule.
There is no such rule.
You have no access to such rules because there aren't any.
All you have is your perceptual system is doing something we don't understand.
And so there's no middle story about some mental operations that we understand that don't happen to be there.
The brain is doing something, the visual system is doing something.
You're busy doing something.
And that is the only access you have to the body schema is that a unified object is showing up for you.
As soon as you think there's some third thing you can describe called the body schema, you've lost Mero-Ponte.
Now, maybe he's wrong, but that's his ways to say that.
I just want to point out how they external perception and perception of one going by, and he doesn't think that's important here and then make that perception and by appropriate action.
But that's kind of the opinion of this whole thing.
Yes, I mean, I like that slogan, which I came across in something you wrote, but I but I then I continued to be unhappy with that slogan.
Let me see if I can remember why.
Well, it was because of reading this, he didn't say it.
It struck me as odd that he never talked about my feeling of where my body was as if he thinks that I, in effect, know where my body is because I know where the object is, and vice versa.
I don't need that propriocept to find out.
You said it in terms of it.
Yeah, okay, but proprioception is so I wrote a note to myself, but I thought I was.
Okay, well, that's good.
Okay, if that's proprioception, that's fine.
Now, I do believe there is proprioception because we've got these, there are these brain-injured cases, which if anybody's interested, you should study, of people who don't have it.
Yeah, a sense of your own body, a feeling for your own body.
It's knowing where your body is just by being it in the activity of using it.
That's the wrong way you're saying it, knowing.
Okay, again.
Okay, yes.
Sensing where your body is, right, in the activity of using it, and only through the activity of using it.
That's me.
That experience is called proprioception.
And people who lack it can't even get across a room without having to see where the floor is and where their feet are and where their feet are, and that their feet are in contact with the floor.
They have a real rough life.
They are in their intellectuals.
They have to keep performing mental syntheses in order to do all this.
And of course, that's a disaster.
Yeah.
I understand that Berlin Plante is saying that the object is part of the body scheme, but I'm not happy about that because I don't know what it means.
Well, I thought I could tell you what it meant.
You can't describe the body schema except insofar as you can say that it's what's unifying the object when you're dealing with it.
It's a claim that, unlike Christero's no email, which Klisero thought he could describe as a hierarchy of rules for putting stuff together.
Now, I think, unlike Alva's story, that there are sensory, motor contingencies, and they are the sort of thing that we understand in the sense that we could write them out, and C.I.
Lewis's view that there are meanings in mind, which says if I do this, I will see the table from this way, and if I do that, I will see the table from that way, and can write all that out.
That's the concept in the concept table.
Merrill-Planty wants to deny that and say there's nothing you can say about the body schema except that if you get involved in coping, you will be presented with a thick, unified object.
That's fine.
What you said, I'm more concerned about the issue of idealism that we were talking about.
Okay, of course.
Well, that's because there's one thing to say unifying the object, but I'm not sure that's the right thing to say.
It constitutes our experience of the object.
What does?
The body schema.
So that the object is what it is for us because of the body schema, which is lack of background.
So it's part of the body's our experience of the object is wrapped up in the body schema in that sense.
But there's a way of agreeing this that think unification is very idealistic.
In what sense?
Why?
Where?
What?
The notion of unification is something that's not a good idea.
He's not in the unification business is that you said.
I said?
Yeah.
No, unification.
Did I say that?
When did I say that?
That's bad.
I mean, I want to say it's already unified.
Unification is idealist.
It suggests that there are elements and that you've got some kind of mental activity that unifies those elements.
I thought I said, or I meant to say, did I, will you, will you.
But anyway, I want to say, well, the perceptual system that you are, that's in your body somehow does it.
I mean, you have to put together from the incoming, what does Gibson call it?
The sensory array or sensory stimulus array.
You have to put together, moving around in a lot of energy inputs on the physical level, the experience of the world.
Somehow that gets done.
But it doesn't get done by unifying elements.
We don't have any.
It's so important to just get this insight.
Of course, something happens on the physical level, and then something else sends a home of the brain and does something.
And then there's an experience of unified objects.
You never have a mental operation unifying partial experience of objects in Merrill Kanti.
And Merochant's way of saying that is you don't have any access to the body schema except as you plunge into actively coping with unified objects, then you can say that happens thanks to the body schema.
But the body schema is sort of invisible.
You can't say, if you say anything about it, you become an intellectualist.
It's just the name for the fact that somehow or other the nervous system is doing this.
And that's all.
You can explain the quote on the next page.
Wait, wait, wait.
Good.
People are beginning to tell me when they're lost.
No, I have a quick question.
I think the other thing process here is the same thing, the intellectualism compared to the Pokemon.
The only difference is that the intellectualist even has some account of it.
They can actually say what it is.
Well, that's good.
That's good.
But that's not right, wait, wait, wait, wait.
No, that's important.
That's right.
But it's not quite right because the question is deeper.
What is being unified?
The intellectualist thinks he knows what's being unified, namely perspectives or features or what the sort of sense data-like stuff is being, but mental stuff is being unified.
What's very important is the Duo-Gibson move, which is just sort of outside of the Merrill Price's concerns, but that something's being unified, all right, but it's not anything mental, and the unification is not anything mental.
You were saying the unification isn't mental, but you've got to realize that there isn't any problem about how to unify any sort of experiences.
By the time you get to experiences, it's all unified already.
That's the picture.
If you keep that in mind, you will not go crazy and will not leave out, I'm afraid.
At least not as I understand it.
Yeah.
So the second sentence of the chapter is: when I walk around my class, the various aspects of the Duke of Aristoteli, did not possibly appear as views of one and the same thing if I did not know that each of them represents the flats and identified one another, and if I were unaware of my movements and of my values now, why isn't that being moved by his own voice?
Well, okay, well let's talk about it.
It's good to see.
It's a challenge.
I don't know whether yet I have to think about it, whether I think it's supposed to be something said at a level of generality that you can both give an intellectualist view of a story and his story, but let's see.
So our own body is in the world as the heart is in the organism.
That's another.
Notice again how the picture is supposed to be.
There's one big unity of the body in the world.
It keeps the spectacle constant alive.
It breathes into it.
Boy, our metaphors and so forth.
When I walk around my flat, the various aspects in which it presents itself to me, now I think that's fine, and I like to use the aspects, could not, and it's the whole flat presenting itself from various aspects, could not possibly appear as views of one and the same thing, that is, the room from an aspect, if I did not know that each of them, and no is going to turn out to be very important, did not know that each of them represents the flat seen from one spot or another.
That's odd.
Is that true in the French?
Knows and represents?
Now that's interesting.
Why is he?
You see, knows, I just don't want to lose you.
Knows sounds too intellectualist.
Represents sounds very intellectualist.
Why does he say anything that?
Well, it's not just knows.
Having some kind of access to the analyzed broken down hands of views.
So it seems that he's just a judge.
There's no line of view or individual experience.
Well, you know, I don't see any broken down points of view.
Where are they broken?
They're aspects, and in each of them, that is each perspective on the object.
That's the aspects in which it presents itself.
That's right.
The whole object presents itself to me.
The aspects of the intercept.
Of which I'm known.
And each of them represents.
That's very odd.
I got you.
Yes.
I can make sense of that.
I mean, but I don't know yet what to say.
I mean, to say it in Mero-Ponty's terms, you'd have to say each of the aspects is an openness on, or our access to, the flat, the whole flat, seen from some place or other in lived space, not in objective space, but someplace or other in the coping space.
And it would have to, and represents, couldn't be right, I mean, if it's from a Merlot-Ponty point of view, because then what would be represented?
I mean, it's all, I'm just open to the whole flat, and I'm, and I'm in a lived space with it, so I don't need to know objectively where I am, and I don't have to represent anything.
I mean, I don't know what you're able to make of it.
Yeah.
So 150 plus dollars flat again.
Okay.
Let's try it.
Okay, wait, 150 or 150 is.
Oh, is my flat screen?
No, wait, wait, wait, wait, we all go to 150.
This is important.
Just clear about Meryl-Ponty's flat.
Okay, I see that about 10 lines down.
Look, good.
My fly is for me, not as closely associated with images.
It remains familiar to the name of Romney Doggy is only as long as I still have in my hands or in my legs the main distances and directions involved.
And as long as from my body, intentional threads run out towards it.
Clearly, my party thoughts are not a final game.
They continue to draw their substance from my present thought, they often be immune, but I give it back to them.
I wish I could say that that was clinching.
Well, you get out of it.
I just thought it was talking about the state-brand situation in a way that does not depend on.
He doesn't say representation.
It doesn't say aspect.
That's nuts.
But he does back here, and that's what we're sort of struggling with.
What I think that I have, I'm a boy, this requires a careful reading.
But what about represents?
Why does he say they represent?
Why doesn't he say that they just open on the house?
I mean, representative intellectualism.
Represent is not written in the French sentence.
It's not in the French sentence.
It is.
There's a moment of hope.
Well, the thing is, there's two different meanings of representation in the book.
And I mean, in various passages that I could cite now or after the book, he says that a part of the world represents another.
Does he?
Yes.
Ah, so it's not.
I was going to talk about that today.
Wow, that's good.
You see, I'll explain this, not lose you now.
Represent could mean you could describe it separately.
Right.
It could mean that the representation can be taken apart from what it represents as a separate thing and then has a relation of representation.
That's how beliefs relate to the world.
That's how propositions relate to the world.
They are all separable from what they represent.
However, he has a kind of intentionality in which, and this is about intentionality, in which what does the representing and what is represented are not separable from the whole, but are aspects of the whole.
But what Olivier is saying, and I was going to come up to it in lecture in a little while, we'll get there, is that he has, I didn't know what two meanings represent, but he clearly has two meanings of intentionality.
For him, it's a case of intentionality that a spot on a background, a spot seems to have the background going on behind it.
Why is that intentionality?
Because the way it looks already implies that this is behind it.
It implies, again, not in an intellectualist way, it looks as if it's covering up this background.
As soon as anything in the whole looks like it does, because it's a part of the whole, that counts as intentionality in the L Ponty.
Very different, because it doesn't mean that you can take the intentional content.
I'm talking to Searleans now mostly.
You can't separate the intentional content from what it's about.
That's representational intentionality in the Searle sense, and it's propositional.
And then there's another view in the LOP where there is intentionality, but there isn't a content, something propositional, something that you can separate from what it's about.
If the pieces of the spot are all just about each other.
Everything that the spot is, every way the spot looks, lighter in the center, darker around the edges, lighting's covering up the paper it's a spot on, all that is intentionality.
All that has intentional threads, and it would be representational, I think, in one sense.
One part of the spot represents some other part of the spot.
You see?
Okay, good.
380 in the front edition.
He's saying that there is a transition between aspects of the objects.
So you never achieved any synthesis at all.
Yes, transition synthesis, yes.
But he says that this one is prior to the other one and that you can remain in the system.
See, now you're losing people.
So let me just say it.
What we're worrying about is that, well, now we've got something for you all to worry about.
When you see intentionality, you've got to be careful and pay attention to the difference between what he means by it and what you mean by it from any other course you've ever had, influenced by Frege, Thurley, and company.
Not that they're wrong.
There's a kind of intentionality for mental stuff.
Beliefs are about the world.
That's intentionality.
They represent the world.
But that's not his use.
It's neither his use of intentionality nor represent.
And what was the word we were just talking about?
Transition synthesis.
Oh, yeah, and synthesis.
Synthesis is going to have two meanings.
If synthesis means that there are elements and then some intellectual something that puts together the elements, that's intellectualism.
Whether it's hussarl or not, it would be a discussion we don't have to have here.
But it's intellectualism for sure.
And when he says synthesis, transition synthesis in the passage that Olivier is reading.
That just means that as you go around the house, and the passage that Al was starting with, you get changing aspects of the whole house.
That's the transition synthesis.
That's got a different meaning synthesis, different meaning of representation, different meaning of intentionality.
And you can always ask yourself which it is.
There are two ways to find out about which it is.
One is, does it believe that the elements are definable apart from their place in the whole?
If so, it's intellectualist.
And Merloponte doesn't believe it.
Does it think that there is some kind of mental, understandable operation that puts the elements together in the whole?
If so, that's intellectualist, and Merlopunge doesn't buy it.
Okay, you'll be willing to say something.
Maybe you're making it more positive than it should be, because why can't you just say that he's just Melopanti is just eating?
We talk about middle and representation.
Well, I would say that, except Olivier has says that it's all over the book like this, that there are two means of representation.
I really it's a perfectly sensible question.
I couldn't defend myself except by saying Olivier thinks that, and he said he does more than I have.
What?
Because it seems like there's you can also read him as saying, you know, saying that, you know, hasn't endorsed being holy.
Well, yes, you have to read it.
Okay, well, I'm not disagreeing with you with what you but I am making it hard uh I don't think I'm making it harder for I mean he he's basically saying what you're saying, but he's just using like those right.
Right.
But once you do, there's no disa disagreement between us.
Once you do, I'm not making it harder than it is, that there then there are two meanings of represent running around, and you've got to keep your eyes open for which.
And two meanings of no, and you've got to keep your eyes open for which.
Two meanings of intentionality.
And I'm just telling you that, and it's difficult.
But in the end, I'm saying just what you're saying.
Don't worry about the fact that he says represent and no.
He doesn't mean no in the sense that it's sort of accessible to the mind, and he doesn't mean represent in the sense that it's about anything that's separate from him.
Look, so it goes.
Yeah.
Okay, let's go right to that because we're so close to that.
I'll just jump ahead in the lecture.
I have a whole section on where he just goes off and decides to tell you, pretty late in the game, what he means by intentionality.
So where is it now?
If anybody finds it in my notes, let me tell them, I mean, it must be in here.
We want you to talk about it.
I may not call it by that name.
Maybe.
Well, let's look at 213.
No marks to me.
There's a thing in here.
Well, I ought to be able just to find out.
Yeah, I think you'll.
Good.
That's weird.
I wrote this thing.
Ah, here it is.
It's on 248 of ours.
I wrote it on my notes, not in terms of intentionality, but you'll see why I could write it that way.
All figure ground structure is holistic and meaningful.
That's code for when we see that the holistic structure has its kind of internal kind of version of intentionality.
Now, let me see where it is on 248.
Now, okay, here it is.
Pop at 248.
Now, Mero Pandit is talking.
This is what we are doing when we define a sensation as coexistent or communion.
Never mind that yet.
The sensation of blue is not the knowledge or positing of a certain identifiable quality, that's one of those features things, throughout all the experiences which I have.
As if, let me just say, as if blue is like a color chip in which it's the same blue in a woolly carpet.
I think I like red better.
You mustn't think that just because the fire engine is red and the apple is red and the carpet is red, and that the same color chip for paint matches all three of them, that these reds look alike.
There's the woolly red of the carpet, he says, or blue.
In one place, he says one or two says another.
It doesn't matter.
There's the woolly, let's say, red of the carpet, the shiny red of the fire engine, the juicy red of the apple, and they look juicy or hard or fuzzy.
That's this whole issue that's going to come up next time.
I can see we're not going to get there, a synesthesia.
That is that all these, because the whole body is coming to grips with the whole object, all the properties aren't separable, like atoms of qualia.
But the blueness is already going to be given as permeated by woolliness or whatever.
Now let's go on.
The sensation of blue, but let me generalize.
Remember, whenever you see him denying, you'll always see him denying there are these sense data-like elements which remain the same and then get plugged into the experience.
For him, it's always holistic and top-down.
There are no elements.
Blue already shows up either as woolly's blue or shiny blue or whatever.
That's what he's saying.
The sensation of blue is not the knowledge of or positive of a certain indefinable quality throughout all the experiences that I have of it.
That would be fire engines, rugs, and so forth.
As the geometric circle is the same in Paris and Tokyo.
It is, in all probability, intentional.
I don't know about in all probability, I can't imagine what that does.
It is intentional, which means that it.
Is that in all probability in there, Olivia?
Oh, sorry.
Are you seeing where I'm reading?
Anybody in the French?
Okay, well, I'll go on.
I don't know, I'd be nice if that phrase went away because it doesn't do anything.
It is, I'm skipping it, intentional, which means that it does not rest in itself as does a thing, that it is directive and has significance beyond itself.
So, now that's the general definition of intentionality, having significance beyond itself.
It's in there, which can you imagine why he would say in all probability that quality is just intentional?
I mean, if it's normal.
Maybe he means if you've got some kind of mental breakdown or something, you could see pure blue.
I think he thinks that.
But maybe Schneider sees pure blue.
But if normal people are going to see only the quality from the aspect blue, the carpet, I'm now seeing under the aspect blue, but it's still a carpet.
Okay, and but now this is the crucial phrase.
Because he thinks intentionality means directed, and that means has significance beyond it.
Well, of course, one thing that has intentionality, let's keep repeating, is belief.
They're directed at the world.
And their intentionality is because they're about something.
And they have conditions of satisfaction, namely, the world can turn out to be like you believe it or not like you believe it.
How many people is that a familiar thing, I just say?
Okay, because it's something that you need to know.
I mean, that's the mentalist Surley and Serlean understanding of intentionality or the basic one.
Now, Merilo Ponte thinks, you could generalize that.
Intentionality is just when anything has a significance beyond itself.
So when the house looks like the front of a house, there's intentionality there.
Not from your mind being about the house, but the front of the house is, so to speak, about the back of the house.
And for him, that's a kind of intentionality.
Gurvich has a nice phrase that probably Merilo-Ponte got this for which.
He talks about, oh my gosh, I just certainly forgot it because I was going to say it.
Perceptual implications.
That means that the way the house looks, it implies the back, but it's not a rational implies, or therefore a logical implies.
Maybe Figurich is a double agent.
You never know.
So I'll stick to this.
The front of the house looks like the front of a house.
That's intentionality already.
Yeah.
I would say probably what?
Yes, the perceptual house, the house in this perceived world that we perceive, the front of the house has intentionality because it shows itself as the front of a house.
Now, wait, I've got other passages because that's such an amazing thing to say.
So on 249, about two-thirds down, he talks about the mutual, how each part of the whole is sensitive, in quotes, to what happens in all the others and knows them dynamically.
Well, there's a funny use of knows, which he puts in quotes, knows them dynamically.
He puts in quotes.
He's quoting Kerr, which all this.
But what's going on there is a way of talking about how the part, sorry, there are no parts.
Each part of the whole is an aspect to put in if you want.
Although part, you know, part could be an element or there are certain words you can talk about.
Yeah, I agree.
You can talk about parts as long as you don't think it's...
They're lined by the whole structure.
That's right.
You can talk about parts as long as they are like aspects.
They are not elements or features.
As long as they're not atomic, as long as you couldn't take them out, then it's all right, a part.
So, and the part is like the front of the house, the front of the house, which already is sensitive to and knows dynamically that there's a back.
And what does that mean?
It looks like it's hiding a back.
Yeah.
I just want to register the strangeness of this use usage.
I mean, it sounds like to me he's assimilating intentionality, the whole thing.
I think he's, well, I have to think about it.
But I mean, I think he wants to say that he would he needs some way, maybe intentionality is a bad word because it's already been taken.
Frega paid for it, and everybody is he's got he owns it.
But or well, whoever did, Brentano, I guess, owns it.
But anyway, there is a meaning for intentionality around, but he needs to say in some way how the aspects refer beyond themselves.
And it can't be refer in the way that representations, the way beliefs refer about the world.
But and so he needs a word for the sensitivity of the aspects to each other.
And maybe he shouldn't call it intentionality.
He calls it, you know, he's got intentionality in it's intentional tissue.
I mean it says intentional.
Yeah, okay, well there, but there's intentionality around.
Let's see, intentional there.
Carc knowing something.
I'll find an intentionality.
By the way, let me tell you, and then I'll find it.
There's the intentional tissue talk.
There's the intentional arc talk.
Those are all the same things.
Those are all holistic kind of intentionality talk.
But I hope I can find another invention that will help let's look around.
I thought I had several.
But Romero Ponty, I wrote him, meaningful equals intentional.
Oh, oh yeah, I thought I would try to explain what the this is a challenge.
You want intentionality always to have conditions of satisfaction.
That's what makes it intentionality.
So sort of an answer here, partly we can deal with what James said.
The excuse for calling this intentionality would be to say, but it's got conditions of satisfaction and therefore why shouldn't we call it intentionality?
Now look what happens.
If the front of the house looks like it's hiding the back, and that is, it has the, it implies that, it's got that intentionality, it refers beyond itself, and you go around and you discover there's no back, you just failed to satisfy the conditions of satisfaction.
It's a version of if you believe that there's a back and there's no back, your belief is false.
But it wasn't a back, that would be a kind of representing, the belief one.
But if this it has the characteristic of a representing without a representing, namely it looks already as if it's hiding a back.
And so how would you, I want you to know this because someday this problem is going to hit you and I might as well save you from a night of puzzlement.
But if the front looks like it's hiding a back, then how could it turn out that there wasn't a back?
And I've already said this with the girl on Telegraph.
Well, it will stop looking that way when you go back and look at it again.
That's how you can see that it's failed.
I mean, if the one place Pussyl says that no email explodes, you can't quite say that.
But you say, well, your expectations and all your sets for the house go clong, bong, like with the back of the girl, and all of a sudden it's different.
And then that's what happens.
That's falsification.
It gets, and the funny thing is, let's go through all this.
It gets retroactively crossed out.
What does that mean?
I can't even remember what the back of the girl looked like because it's clearly the back of a guy.
So that my memories get changed when it goes wrong.
I think that's generally right.
It's like if you see the cat in the trees, you'd be trying to solve this puzzle and all you see is trees.
And in one moment, bomb, you see the cat in the tree.
Can you remember the trees before the cat was there?
No.
Retroactively, it's got a new intentionality.
It's got a new conditions of satisfaction.
That is now a cat.
And so the important thing is, and I was going to do it with the block.
I decided I had to see if I could do it with the spot on the paper, because that's his minimal difficulty.
Remember, you seem like years ago when we started the book, there was a spot on a piece of paper and he went on and on about it.
I think I should tell you where it is, because I can't expect you to have a grasp of this book.
No one has where is it, the spot on the paper.
Oh, where's the woolly red carpet on page five?
Who would have thought?
Everything is everywhere.
He's written a holistic book, it occurred to me this morning as I was breaking my teeth.
No wonder you can't tell where anything is, because anything belongs everywhere.
Because everything else implies everything.
Well, you you can know your way around it in spite of that fact.
But what you can't do, you know, is nowhere to look for anything because who would have thought the carpet issue right in the middle of page five here is something which is really going to be discussed only when we get to the thing.
We haven't even got to the carpet issue.
But if we can sit in what I'm looking for, the spot.
The spot is very early on.
Can I just make a an observation?
Yeah.
You might think that just extending your thought about the intentionality of on the house, that the fact that it moves, Pizza Jets is being mentioned on the weird.
Well, because after all, a belief is the only about us to go so long as you do it.
Right.
And very false.
And in between, then it'll be false.
That's interesting.
That's very interesting.
That's right.
That's one of the important differences, whether you're a holist with your intentionality and representation story.
Right.
Notice your belief, even when it turns out to be false, that's a good thing to point out.
You still can have the belief, and now you know it's false.
But when your look at the girl from the back turns out to be a man from the back, you can't continue to have that look of the girl from the back and with the event attached to it, false, misleading.
It stiffs.
It starts looking completely different.
In fact, so life is in first person.
Once you know the belief is false, then you can't believe it.
That's true.
It loses a dystopic way to do that.
It's truth.
That's right, right.
Justice will have to do it.
Okay, good.
That's the other half of it.
It's, I mean, but you can separate the proposition you believe from and entertain it without believing it.
Whereas on this story, you can't entertain the look of the back of the girl while knowing that it's the look of, well, while you're looking at the back of what we now know is a man.
So let me tell you about the spot, the middle of page four.
This is the minimum intentionality, though he doesn't call it that.
He says, when Gestalt theory informs us that a figure on the background is the simplest Thanksgiving available to us, Thanksgiving is uh going to do this job of perceptual reburring.
We rely, we reply that it's not a contingent characteristic and so forth.
Huh, uh, no, I he's saying it's always part of a field, he says, but I where do you give a description of this?
Oh, here it is.
I'm sorry, page four, higher up.
Let us imagine a white patch on a homogeneous background.
All the points of the patch have a certain function in common, forming themselves into a shape.
The color of the shape is more intense and more resistant than the background.
The edges of the patch belong to part belong to it and are not part of the background although they join it.
The patch appears to be placed on the background and does not break it up.
And now comes the third intentionalist part.
H path arouses the expectations of more than it contains.
And this elementary perception is therefore already tied with meaning.
I would rather say sense.
I think you better leave meaning for belief.
Sense is is this more minimal thing.
So the word in French is sales, and so it's better to call it meaning.
I mean, sorry, call it sense.
Okay, and but here he's certainly using the this minimal meaning, no?
Okay, well, everything has two meanings.
That was crazy.
I don't forget I want to say anything more.
So it's one thing I'd love to say more.
Oh, I gave myself the puzzle of every if it's going to be intentionality, it's got to have conditions of satisfaction.
So we did it with belief.
That was we did it with houseburns.
What about the spot, which is covering up the background behind it?
Has it got it whoops as if the background continues behind it?
Well, if you picked up the spot, if you could, or or erased it and there was a hole behind it, and it covered exactly this hole, but there were but the white paper didn't continue, you'd be wrong.
And the spot would look different.
Because the spot, the spot, there are conditions of satisfaction for the way the spot looks.
That's what makes it intentionality.
And so that now just part of the answer to you, that's the generalist thing you can say about intentionality.
It refers beyond itself.
It could be mental content referring beyond itself to the world, but it could be a part of the gestalt referring beyond itself to the rest of the gestalt.
In either case, you've got conditions of satisfaction.
It can be misleading.
It can turn out to surprise you, and you turn out to be wrong.
It looked like it looked different than it now looks.
Yeah.
This just seems to exist about me.
I mean, lots of people have a view you just described, but if you have a representationalist view about a perceptual experience like this, you're not going to be experiencing the world.
You're not going to be involved in the world.
Well, I'm not being, I'm not lost to you.
I'm saying you can only experience seeing the front as the front of a house with a back if you're actively engaged with the house.
The same thing with the spot.
As soon as you stand back and look at them, he says this often.
They just become features.
But the problem is that if there's conditions of satisfaction, what you're telling of how things might or might not be.
Yeah.
And that the world is something, you know, removed from that, which, you know, is going to determine whether your experiences are horrible or not.
No, it's just more of the same.
I mean, when you go around the back, and if the back turns out not to be there, it's not comparing your first experience to the real world.
You're comparing your first experience to your next experience, which cancels it.
And maybe it'll get the weak canceled.
Maybe it'll turn out somehow that the they discovered how to make it visible backs, but when you try to quit what you could would you bump into it.
And who knows?
But it's all on the level of constantly negotiated and redefinable or re-experienceable as you find out more and more.
And you're already committed to the future unfolding of this investor conditions of satisfaction.
You're committed to the future unfolding of it as a certain kind.
And when it isn't like that, Zach, you have to retroactively change it, even your memory of it.
I had to say that sometimes, so this is as good a time as any.
Now, I didn't lose you, I hope.
Has anybody lost?
That's good.
Okay, you want to say something over here?
You tend to say that when you see that thing, either a real and telegraph idea or a man brothers, when you realize that it's a man on Telegraph and Union, you don't get down there.
So you mean that you cannot remember the moment when you have thought it was a girl?
No, I can remember.
I think.
But this is this nothing crucial interest on this, except just I think it's helpful if it's true.
I think you can't picture what it looked like when it looked like the back of a view.
You can't look at the use of it.
This is what he calls ambiguity.
Ambiguity, yes.
It's a very crucial word that he uses for the booming.
It means that it can be, maybe you expect it to be a girl because, well, there's a long hairload and this.
Yeah, but I mean that's you it could be that you I mean, this is just getting at sort of I'm afraid uninteresting.
It could be you kept an ambiguity.
Yeah, well it that depends.
This is too trivial.
But I mean, you could either look at it with ambiguity and s and look at it in a way which you saw uh you were trying to stay neutral as to whether it was a man or a woman, or it could be either.
That would be the ambiguity.
You just don't know yet.
If that's how you're looking at it, then it won't have to flip when you go around.
But that's a very abnormal way to look at it.
When you're looking at it, you're it's it's like trying to say, I don't know whether I'm in a movie set or not, so I won't look at this as a facade, and I won't look at this as a house from the front, I'll leave it ambiguous.
Well, then it whatever it turns out to be, you won't retroactively change.
But your basic coping involved thing is you look at it as the whole object, namely a girl or a a guy.
You don't look at it as ambiguous.
Not necessary.
You can stay ambiguous.
If you stay ambiguous, you can only do it.
I don't choose to stay ambiguous.
What the what this is is that the basic structure of perception is ambiguous.
Not in that sense.
Not in the sense that you not in the sense that the basic way of looking at a house remains neutral as to whether I'm looking at a facade or a house.
That would be unbelievable if you said that, because the whole thing-key thing is you have to do it from an already engaged coping attitude.
And boy, when you're coping, you don't stay neutral as to whether you're going to go through the front door.
The house could be a facade and not a facade, but boy, if you you gotta look like one of the other things.
That's what you don't know.
You can stand back intellectually and say that, but that doesn't but the house looks like you you either gonna go and be able to go through the door.
Yes, that's right.
It's open.
You're set to go you're involved.
You're set to go through the door, the front door.
And the front door looks like it leads to the interior of the house.
It looks like it, and your body's set to go through it, and it's looking that way of two aspects of one thing, and then now y you you could try and go through it, and bang, you hit the the wall.
But normally you wouldn't stand back and say, well, it's the inner facade of the house, it's a door, it looks ambiguous, it looks like maybe I can go through it, maybe I can't.
That's not the normal experience.
That's even worse.
I don't believe for a minute that the the house front looks sort of like a facade, it's sort of like a house.
Is it the indeterminacy that really wants to be a little bit more?
No, that's not the kind of indeterminacy.
It either looks like a house.
This is incredible.
This is an ingression.
It's a craziness.
It either looks like the front of the house, which I would think it's indeterminate.
What, whether it's how many windows it's got on the back, maybe it's got no windows on the back.
We'll never know about the cracks in the floor, he says, and all that.
That's it's never completely determinate.
But that doesn't mean it isn't at all determinate.
It doesn't mean that all I ever have is some possible something which could possibly be a front, possibly be a facade, possibly be a laser image, possibly be a hallucination, all ambiguous, and then I find out that's not that just makes no sense.
Yeah.
It seems like there's there's a problem that's actually inherently where there's three times the phenomenon, there's two times of experience.
So I think empiric would be the way it is, maybe an appearance in out the variance is not these ways.
So you need this thing, you need this kind of ambigenous to account for the fact of the illusion that you experience.
So that's all, that's all.
I think what you're saying is probably true, but I just don't want to answer it.
Another ask.
I don't want to bring in Heidegger.
No, I just want to do the same phenomenon.
So there is no problem.
There is no meaningless look of the object and ambiguous and massacres.
That is already one way or the other.
And the fact that it's already one way or the other is what makes it the difference.
Of course, if it's okay, if that's, I don't think that could be what they mean by ambiguous.
I mean, then it wouldn't be a way of looking.
Either it looks like it's already one way, or it looks like it's the other.
It doesn't look like it's one way or the other.
Okay, Jennifer wanted to say something.
Wait, wait, I want to hear one more question.
You sure?
You look very worried.
I am very worried.
Oh, tell me when you're worried about it.
I'll tell you later.
I'm worried when you're worried.
Okay.
Yeah.
I just wanted to say that I think that your discussion of the intentionality side of the house is really interesting.
Another question is, this goes back to what the man in the lab said.
What is the explanation then of the video, of the intentionality?
It's quite clear that you went to the story.
I'd say it again, because I think it's so important.
I mean, there is no medium of it.
If that means anything that you could ever think or analyze, in my reading of Merlot Ponte, something happens.
You know, I keep saying the physical energy comes in, and the perceptual system, which is just a more physical stuff, does its thing, and basins of attraction form in this piece of matter up here.
We don't know anything about that.
We've got theories, but they're all pretty pathetic.
And we've got an experience of houses from the front.
How it's a it's it's a falling into an intellectualist trap to think that they have to be out of their intellect.
When you say a sentence to the sentence refers to the world, right?
I can appreciate the significance of sentences.
It's intentionality with those beyond yourself because I understand the language.
Now, when I look at the cell in the house, I experiencing it, I experienced it according to you, has referred beyond itself to the back of the house.
Is that because I understand the language?
No.
Maybe it's because I understand if I look at the back of the house, I was here.
Yes, maybe.
See, Alva, it's great to have Alva.
He's the perfect example of what happens if you translate this into something intellectual.
That is made.
It could be that I understand something like a rule that for houses they have backs and if you go around, you'll find them.
And you can do that.
You can turn it into a belief.
You can turn it into something you understand.
But Merloponte at least thinks that basically you don't do that.
The body schema does it outside of consciousness and you don't do it.
Remember, one does it.
That's in our reading for this time.
The perceptual system does it.
And you can't ask, this is a Gibson light point, how the perceptual system does it.
It just does it.
And what you get is this world.
The burden of proof is, I don't know who has the burden of proof.
Either Alva has the burden of proof to say why we need evangelist explanation, or I have the burden of proof to say why we don't.
Here's what makes it public.
You say it happened outside of consciousness, right?
But what's not outside of consciousness is the anticipation.
Is that there are conditions of satisfaction?
That's right.
The object has conditions of satisfaction.
That is, it looks a certain way and it might not turn out to be that way.
But whether it looks that way because of any sort of mental operations, which might be, you know, we have a concept of house which tells us that there's a whole lot of things about what we could do and what we could see and synthesizes all that.
That would be the incentive.
It's not the object's conditions of satisfaction that don't matter.
Objects are neutral.
It's the experience of the object.
I experience the whole house despite only having immediate access to the front of the house.
So there's got to be some story about the way in which the beard of the house is present in my experience when it's hitted by the front of the house.
Yes.
And you can't just say the brain does it.
Why not?
Well, because that's not explaining how it seems present.
There's a phenomenal life that seems present.
That's right, but that's bigger bulk.
The code word for this, we have to both agree in there, Lafante, is the body scheme adjustment, right?
And now then we're trying to figure out what that means.
The body schema is precisely not really crazy.
But yes, this is precisely not judgment and it's representation in one sense but not another.
And it's intentionality in one sense but not another.
But the objection varies that when you've done you've taken the notion of intentionality and just by Kaga subtracted judgment and those kind of activities.
But what you've done is just taken out the explanatory framework.
Yes.
The moral of today's lecture we have to stop is don't ask for a mentalistic explanatory framework.
It's a trap that's been around since um well, no, you can well I'll keep intentionality.
I and only uh I I I I'll pay it when it comes around on Saturday is, as Lewis Carroll says.
Okay.