At the end of last session, Burke asked two questions today.
The first was what does existential mean existence of existential structure or typical single existential weather structure?
This thing, what is this supposed to mean?
And what's the use of this?
Why does Naropon have used it?
In this very section of the chapter.
And the second question, which is obviously related, is then what does the existence mean?
And the answer to the answer to these questions lies in Neuropotty evident data of the body, what the body means.
And what we see in this chapter, and this this is another reason why it's really helpful to understand the way NeuroPonte deals with the problems it successfully copes with influenza perception is that the body is here very clearly defined as a general function of transposibility.
But what you have to have in mind from the very beginning, and I will then develop this.
This general function of transposition means two things.
It means general means, and that's why I'm releasing it to the ambiguity of the body.
General means that the body is that, thanks to which you're sort of carrying out with yourself a various array of conducts that arise in different situations.
But the thing is, so what changes can be the situations?
And this is one of the meanings of general.
All is there.
And the second meaning of it, with which Maropony deals mostly or the that the pushed in this chapter.
The the second meaning of general, or the second part of this meaning, is that this generality is present in all of the layers that constitute the embodied life.
So it means that the existential structure is being present at the biological level, as well as at the personal level, as well as mean accessory level.
So that's why the existential the existential structure.
Why is that?
Because it shows that there's an internal connection between all these layers.
So it means that when and these two meanings are general, you sort of always carry with yourself this very existential structure.
And the meaning of being common to all the layers is related to the very same empirical tendency, you might want to say.
Because obviously you can the thing Melvonti wants to stress is that you can go from one situation to another that are completely different insofar as these layers are facilitated by the situation.
You can go from a purely biological situation to a purely personal.
And even so, you'd be carrying with yourself this very thing.
And what this heads towards is the fact that the body as being general has to be related with once again, but the also says in the preface that this the body is the only thing to which you can relate all the behaviors, the human beings, it's that sense to which you can have a global picture, a global picture.
So, in terms of mean, and this is this is how it's being phenologically presented.
You need it in order to have a center to relate all the dimensions, the common point.
And this means that, this is very important.
This is the way you have to understand what Heroes says when he says that the flow of existence runs through the body and everything.
All these kinds of metaphors.
It simply means that all these dimensions of existence are being related to the body.
They can be understood insofar as related to the body.
And it's various concepts that you might think are being separated.
But precisely, they're not.
And this is where Nero carries on and enters the sexual issue.
So, this is on page 158 in the old edition, so the last one is.
And in the new, it means the 180.
But it's just after the beginning of the paragraph.
For Freud himself, the sexual is not the genital.
Okay, the whole has to be the whole beginning has to be right.
So, for Freud himself, the sexual is not a genital, meaning that sexuality is a dimension of existence that cannot only be related to the pure reflex-like working of the genital organs.
I just mainly stated by Freud in the three dots on the theory of sexuality.
Sexual life is not a mere effect of the process of interest in the genital organs.
The legitimate is not an instinct, that is an activity naturally directed towards definite ends that intense.
It is the general power which the cytosomatic subject enjoys of taking root in different settings, of establishing himself through different experiences, of gaining structures of conduct.
So this is the what I call the existential further to sum it up.
This book causes a man to have a history.
Insofar as a man's sexual history provides the huge life, so is it does that mean he's being reductionist and so on?
It is because in his sexuality is projected his manner.
So this is the intentional arc, right?
Is projected his manner of being towards the world, that is towards time and other memory.
There are sexual symptoms at the root of all hymnosis, but these symptoms, correctly interpreted, symbolize a whole attitude, whether, for example, one of conquest or of flight into the sexual history conceived as the elaboration of a general form of life, all psychological constituents can enter because there's no longer an interaction of two causalities and because the genital life is geared to the whole life of the subject.
So the thing is this whole picture that I've been drawing you here used in order to show that it can sort of work to explore all dimensions of human life, even sexuality.
And here what's interesting is that, I mean, what's the use of all this?
Well, here it helps because you might want to use it to stress the different existential attitudes, right?
They can symbolize a whole attitude, whether, for example, one of inquest or of flight, which are not the same.
So this will be an alternative account for the or one of the broad aims of psychoanalysis, which has been, you could say, character study, which some very minimum psychoanalysis have been defended.
But the thing is, how can this be used be of use for us?
For us, we want to understand how the body has a general function of transposition.
It's at work here.
And to understand this, we need to reach towards the end of this, as usual, very long paragraph.
So 380, which means 40 could be 15.
Well, there there are two words in ideas, expression and meaning, and my piece is just over them.
So if the sentence starts with finally, as we have indicated above, finally hasn't had indicated above.
Yeah, okay, thanks.
Biological existence is synchronized with human existence, with this person, and never indifferent to its distinctive rhythm.
Nevertheless, we shall now add, living is a primary process from which, as a turning point, it becomes possible to live this or that world, meaning you experience.
And we must be and read before perceiving and weakening evolution of living, belonging to colours and lines through sight, through sounds through hearing, so the body of another through sexuality, before arriving at the biofuel.
The sight, hearing, sexuality in the body are not only the roots, the latter takes up and absorbs into itself their existence as it is.
What this means is that, as this is this is the concrete way, now the robotic begins to explore the relationship between these dimensions and to say that to him they're not or they shouldn't be conceived of as separated, thanks to this existential person.
And he gives and discusses a very very interesting very interesting case, both followed by Beanswanger.
So it's it's this if you're interested in in phenomenology, that guy might be worth reading, because he was the only person who was at the same time personally reading Heimager, Ulsero, and Freud articulating many perspectives.
And Foucault gave the preface of the first translation of his works in French.
I decided on the quite a few preface.
Just a moment earlier I've said that besides making constructions that you might like or dislike, wasn't the only aim that the body had in mind.
And so now he uses this interconnection between layers that are being articulated by the body to explore the case given to us by Beanswanger.
So I might just, okay, I'll read the beginning of the next paragraph and I'll stress what I a girl whose mother has forbidden her to see again the young man with whom she's in love, cannot speak, loses her appetite, and finally the use of speech.
An initial manifestation of this loss of speech is found to have occurred during her childhood after an earthquake and subsequently again following a series of might want to stress the importance of the the oral phase of sexual development.
But what matters is what the body says here, but what is fixed because he takes this issue and discusses it.
But what is fixated on the mouth, okay, so she loses appetite, use the mouth for this, and the speech uses the mouth as well.
What's fixated on the mouth is not merely sexual existence, but more generally those relations with others having the spoken word as their vehicle.
So that means it's the general personal level that's being lost.
Lots of speech then, just as you said a few lines after, stands for the refusal of coexistence, just as in other subjects, the phytophytics is the means of escaping from the situation.
The patient breaks with personal life, blah blah blah.
And then her inability to swallow food arises from the fact that swallowing symbolizes the movement of existence, which carries evidence.
So what does that quite coincide mean?
It means that to understand the various symptoms that the girl has, you have to relate them to a general structure of existence.
When he says that swallowing symbolizes the movement of existence, it means that this the symptom she has, this the fact that she won't eat, has to be understood first and foremost in relation to this existential structure that then allows you to understand the relationship between the different levels of life which are touched by the very same symptom that you have to understand not using the mouth in an existential so he proposes he proposes a particular example of psychopathoma you have to relate this or that symptom to the way the body symbolizes existence and then you can understand what the relation is between the fact that she won't eat which would seem to be and the fact that she won't talk to be only personal this isn't the loginical problem so the thing is you have to be careful with this with the concept of origin when you use it so what would it mean that it's it's it could be starting from sexual, from a sexual original experience that we will discussed today?
Is that what i mean i just mean isn't there a basic as to the sexual dimension of a problem?
Well, the thing is, to answer the question correctly, I would have to enter into the fact that for psychoanalysis, temporarily is not linear temporality.
And that the sexual dimension of the first episode, which is trauma, what it says is that the sexual signification of the trauma is required afterwards when you re-experience the second, a second occurrence of it that can be simplified related to the first.
This is probably.
I guess what it means is that sexual frustration.
The business.
Yes, but fair enough.
But the thing is, the first experience that she had was that of another split, which isn't.
I thought that the first one.
So you remember I just said that this was a way of dealing with a characteristic that is being the principal in psychopathology.
And now Melopoti clearly relates this, and the fact that obviously there's something with the body, all right?
It's really that provides structure that embodies.
And Melopoti has a sentence that consists of this.
So for me, it's 152, so for you probably.
187.
So he says, which says thus in hysteria and repression.
Don't you invite?
Okay.
But in hysteria and repression, we may well overlook something, although we know of it, because our memories and our body, instead of presenting themselves to us in singular and determinate conscious acts, are endolatic generality.
But there are a few sentences that are really important here.
But this first one is very important because you know that psychoanalysis has been heavily using the concept of repression, the thing that you don't want to see but that you know you don't want to see, and has been articulating the concept of you know, it's easy, there's just just one letter that changes.
The concept of regression means that you're drawn back the like the meaning of the comes from the fact that you've been experiencing situations somehow related, similar to so that's what we were just discussing.
So this is what we will be dealing with now.
And the way you understand the the the way you have to understand uh the character studies or the the personality studies, the embody personality studies will include here, is that yes, there's a precise organ that's the the the single egg center that allows you to understand that these dimensions are linked and that shows, obviously, that they are.
And the consequence of this is that the sent the sentence that comes just after, whatever, through this generality, meaning that the repression and hence the big importance of the mouth in the in this in this girl's erotical quality scheme, is that it helps under understanding that, as Dobby will see the next sentence, we discover in this way that sensory messages or memories are expressly grasped and recognized by us only insofar as they adhere generally to that area of our body and our life to which they're relevant.
It would be from the opposing point and sexuality in this whole analysis, trying to do a whole story on this this pace and do it in our dreams, et cetera.
We are end-booking that, but we would really just mention one.
I'll discuss this later because you need some other surgical frameworks for this.
And thus, allows to understand the unique, but ambiguous, because the unique meaning that's being displayed by the very disconnect of the body, this is what existential structure is about.
Yes.
Because the relevant comes from when you find that there are specific bodies or the area is the relevant.
How does the body area is chosen if not bisexual or anything?
Well, it doesn't mean that, well.
Yeah, but it's obviously sexual, but I'm just saying, okay, maybe there is no, I don't know the answer to that.
I'm just saying that there is a detention between the device.
Of course not, because precisely the fact that there's this zone of the generality means it's present in all situations and in all these layers.
That's what it means.
Only.
So this dimension, this the fact that the mouse is prominent, as far as you need to understand the pathological behaviors of a person in every situation or in every dimension that's that's what it means.
So there's no tension.
Only if you take these two words, say this and the general dimension there's no contribution whatsoever but then as far as the sexual origin is concerned you wouldn't say that you would say that sexual idea takes up and expresses something that has been as he as you know just said it in the in the sentence where he mentions all these layers.
Sexuality is a way to express other dimensions, which would which wouldn't mean that they weren't here before in a way, but they didn't have the sexual meaning.
Consider the relationship between the earthquake and the fact that they need to acquire the sexual meaning.
That's maybe where I would understand better with what I would say.
Does it say you in any way?
What's the problem with this?
What's the what's the uh the radical plan for another uh cheating division?
Well, it's a statement, you just see it.
Well, well, it's the same for psychoanalysis, right?
You see that this say this or what is it is what you want to say just that the robotism to psychoanalyst?
So how can we organize and interpret the data that he gets while listening to the patients and see that this or that dimension is symbolistically prominent?
Is that your problem?
I don't know.
Because anyway, this is the sentence that I just read, the the the one with that area of our body in our life to which is very relevant.
It's one eight I think.
The one I just read.
We discovered this way that sensory messages and thi this is this is this is how the robotic would would find a use for this existential purpose by relating it to the different kind of symptoms that can be seen in the different layers of endodinog.
But this obviously happens because ultimately, as we say in the beginning of the chapter, all the dimensions that underlie the personal dimension, which includes the personal dimension, takes up all the underlying dimensions and expresses them at the personal level.
This is what he says, so this is 192, I think, for you.
It says at the very end of the paragraph, 10 lines before me, the end of a paragraph that ends with abstract moments.
The sentence I'm starting with is: if we therefore say, if we therefore say that the body expresses existence at every moment, this is in the sense in which a word expresses thought.
Anterior to conventional means of expression, which reveal my thoughts to others only because already for both myself and the meanings are provided for each sign, and which in this sense do not give rise to genuine communication at all, we must, as we self-see, recognize the primary process of signification in which the thing expressed doesn't exist apart from the expression, and in which the signs themselves induce their significance externally.
In this way, the body expresses total existence, not only biological or perceptual oppression, not because it is an external accompaniment to that existence, but because existence realizes itself in the body.
So there's nothing else besides the body, but you have to conceive of it in such a way as to allow its different manifestations to have this existential relation between.
And this cannot be done if you use the empiricist account, purely organical accounts, or the intellectualist account.
Because then, if you do this, you think that the relationship between these dimensions has to be found within consciousness.
This is what Rogoti said at the very beginning of the chapter, which is impossible because the common structure to all these is a bodily structure insofar as it embodies existence.
But this embodying existence will only mean that it can allow for a switch or for the fact that this related dimension comes to be more prominent than the others on their global circle.
But then, obviously, you can say, well, you could reply, well, you're saying that all these dimensions are related, but then you say that some of them, say, the purely sexual inner, come to be more prominent than the others.
So, what's the point then in saying that they have a relationship if you say that one is more prominent than the others?
And this is what ambiguity, right?
And this is what ambiguity means precisely.
It means that even in sexual something, there's something more global that's always present that you call reality to what happens when you're in bed with the sexual.
Because the behavior you have at that very moment can only be understood on the basis of this existential nature, that is the core of everything.
So, this is my finally speak to this to this view that he calls the build ambiguity.
This is for me on page 168, probably for you on 195.
So, there's no there's no way to tell you.
My sentence is that it is true that it's freud we have generalized the notion of sexuality.
So is it generality just developed?
What?
Is 105 is the notion of generality?
Unconscious later.
Okay?
I go on and then I'll tell you what.
And how you can read it.
So the second is because I I'll keep about half an hour from that.
How can it have generalized the notion of sexuality?
How can we then talk about the distinctive development of sexuality?
How can we identify a content of consciousness as sexual?
Indeed we cannot.
Sexuality conceals itself from itself beneath a mask of generality and continually tries to escape from the tension and drama which it sets up.
Drama mean that it engages the whole existence.
Okay, so now you jump about ten lines after what I've just read to a sentence that frankly the dreamer just before the dreamer okay if sexuality is neither transcended in human life nor shown up as its center by unconscious representations it is at all times present there like an atmosphere now we can understand the fact that sexuality is present in all the devotions in a that and that does you can't reduce them all to the explicitly sexual situation because even in sexual situations there are other meanings in why.
The dreamer doesn't first visualize the latent content of his dream, what the dream really means, sort of, with his with what that is which is to be really relevant with the help of suitable images by the second account, which is the way second account in psychiatrists means when you relate the dream you have.
He doesn't first organize the story of genital origin as being genital, only subsequently translating the text into figures language.
For the dreamer indeed, who is far removed from the language on the week next day, this or that genital agitation or sexual drive is, without more ado, this image of the world being climbed or his face being steady.
We can think as how different texts.
Sexuality becomes gives you the images which derive from it only certain typical relationships, the typical existential relationship, that give vigoration to your only a certain general emotional feature that's present throughout the different layers of life and of personal life.
The dreamer's thing is becomes the surviving which appears in the manifest count.
So finally what you can say is that nobody goes on with his account of ambiguity and the fact that ambiguity ultimately means that sexuality is present throughout all these dimensions and within personal life in all the situations that you can encounter, even though it might not seem to present the same way when you're having the sexual content and when you're in a completely different attitude.
You remember what I the sentence I quoted about half an hour?
When he said that uh there are sexual symptoms at the root of all neurosis, but these symptoms, correctly interpreted, symbolize a whole attitude.
For example, one of contest, one of flight.
So I think you have to relate what I just said the fact that there's a particular part of the body that's being be it as a single or as a normal constituent of stack and type of life in all the dimensions.
And that for this very reason, there's no safe layer or dimension like the purely sexual.
That you would have to start from in order to understand the others.
So be well, which wouldn't mean that since you would have no meaning at all, but that if you really want to understand the sexual part, you would have to see how the rest of life can be related to it.
Not meaning that it has to be related.
One dimension in existence is being symbolized or acquires a meaning.
So it's a window through which you can see this existential structure that I've been talking about.
I think the first question that I don't need to answer, maybe keep it in mind as you go on, it really takes back just a moment, but I think I think it's a worthwhile question to interrupt you, but it has to do with the notion of the body as a general function transposition has become very, very general.
Quite far removed from one mundane, non-technical angles.
What do you mean by physical body as being more mundane?
You know, a lot of the senses that you have in the term body the true mind could have been used.
And then one sense that this way the body expresses significance experimentally.
He then goes on and learns this incarnate significance is present of the model of body and mind finding things.
Okay, so now we're facing the problem of the translation because Melopotty never did his one.
He uses escrit, which is spirit.
It makes a big difference because Melbourne's account of the relationship between escrit and body stems from the lecture of Hegel that was carried on in France in his years, especially from a Greece article from a Greece guy.
Meloponty, a screening subject.
It only subject, not mind.
Well, my real question is what body means.
And I just, because it's clear how sort of Dr.
Christian's story about maximum growth goes in the case of sensory body perception.
But it just begins to get much more metaphorical what it means about biology and the sexual and the subject.
And in other words, it's just a label for the problem.
What is the subject or what is the body?
It's not really clear that the body is.
So I just wanted to come back to that because you just...
Well, actually, I'm pretty much done with what I wanted to say.
So I can, I guess I come back.
But the thing is, first of all, Melbourne wants to describe and not to explain.
So he wants to find a way to relate these symptoms to these dimensions.
So it's not a I can do it, look how I do it.
I've been very persuaded, educated by your description of the ambiguity of the relation between the biological, the perceptual, the personal, the sexual, that there is a kind of an ambiguity.
But the body is a functional transposition within the theory as a kind of explanatory purpose.
If the body is a functional transposition, it is being to explain how it can be that we can move from one situation to another.
And I just want to ask you, it's meant to be the name of that thanks to which you can move from one situation to another, but certainly not to explain in the way you might consider it, except if you wanted to explain a more generally speaking epistemological intuition.
But the thing is, ultimately, what it refers to in all these situations is that.
And why does Melobotti talk about the body all the time?
If you read the preface carefully, you see that he says that the reduction as Terry Dunbar himself cannot be done completely.
There's something that remains from reduction.
And this is the body that's always, as he says about 200 times in the book, in front.
And this is how you have to understand this very peculiar experience.
This is how you have to understand what it means by value, because precisely it's the fact that Meloboti doesn't want to say that conscience is bullshit.
Yes, but let me think, because I have a lot of it just means that, generally speaking, in all these dimensions, the body is that thanks to which there's something happening to you prior to you having consciousness of it and orchestrating it or constituting it.
This is the only thing that body means.
It's that in all these layers and in all the various situations, personal life, be they sexual, there are things that happen that lead you to behave in such or such a way or another that give you, say, even personal fortunes, whatever, that you experience as oriented being you towards this or that.
And this is, and so you sort of receive, it's a matter of conceiving how the relationship between the body and the consciousness is in terms of receptivity.
This is the term that's very useful to understand.
So you're receptive because the body allows you to be receptive to all these different layers.
And thus, thanks to the body, then you're being drawn towards this or that.
And you act.
And that's why the body is useful.
It's to understand how you're being led, the world orients you, even in the perceptual level, as remember Malboff says it in the chapter of the thing.
And the same experience you live at the completely different level, say, in the sexual.
It's that you're not thinking because consciousness means reflection, right?
Thinking about what you're and there's a basic layer, pre-reflective layer of experience, which is in which the consciousness is only receptive to what's carried to what is caring towards it from the baby thing.
But when you say that the body is the only thing that enables you to relate all the different conducts and activities of life, it is that then which we have a global picture, it sounds as if body is something you've been using to explain why we go on this way or that, or how you manage the global picture.
But it's become so big that nature is what explains how you have a global picture.
Or the world is that very intelligent.
Well, no, nature does not explain why you have a global picture.
Because there can only be a subject insofar as you're embodying, because the body is that thanks to which there can be a subject.
Without body, there would be no subject, right?
It's only because of the body that you can understand, that you can see, finding that there's a subject, because there's a common structure that's being widespread throughout all the different behaviors of the person.
So there's not the valuability of the consciousness not thanks to the body.
It's thanks to the body that you can understand through regarding frustrating that they're developed.
And how does that work?
Well, because it has to understand the relationship between all the different.
It's not thanks to the consciousness that you can do this.
It's only thanks to the body because the consciousness couldn't find its way.
Because the experiences that you have when you're also hungry and well, the experience that you have when you're perceiving a chair can't be related only thanks to the consciousness because it would be purely formal, meaning it wouldn't be relate, you couldn't relate it to an experience.
Whereas through him, there's a way to relate all these dimensions to an experience, which is the fact that the body is in front ofward with the prior interface with the world.
In another philosophical tradition, people talk about consciousness not being reflection.
You might talk about conscious meaning experience, or consciousness meaning the idea that whatever you're in your body has some positive character for you.
So in that sense of experience, in that sense of consciousness, it sounds like the body is conscious.
And so there's no light appeal to the reflectivity of the intellect or understanding to make sense of the structure.
But there is some primitive conception of human experience, which is which we're talking about.
Except that, well, you would have to relate it to the fact that, as I mentioned previously at the beginning of the first lecture, there's this operative intentionality that is what you can characterize the subject like.
The subject is what relates the different moments of time and what actually in a way creates them as being intentional moments, the moments towards my grasping of birds recognizing, for example.
So the thing is then you would have to give another story in order to explain how and why you're being task related and how and why you can understand see someone being task related.
Thanks to the fact that you see his or her body moving and arguing that begins to sound problematic for me.
It begins to sound like just looking the statement.
Biology, perception, sexuality, they're all related.
That's what I'm going to put this.
What?
Except that it's it seems to be pretty much related with empirical work as far as for example psychopathology is concerned, right?
And I've read a few passages on this.
Yeah.
Can I get into this?
Yeah, this is this is a version of the question.
I've seen Alice problem.
It's it's hard to know once you say that all these layers are related if you added anything when you say thanks to the body.
But let me just switch to the sexuality question further.
Is that a specially privileged dimension?
Or could we say, you know, related to things is food is also an important uh existential dimension.
And if you tell me I'm not related to everything as food, I tell you what I'm requesting over the relation to some things food, and I don't know whether I've sublimated them, and I don't know it.
Why don't we think that it's a general capacity to relate to everything sexual?
Is that does Paranofungi think?
Does he believe for it?
Why should he?
That this is some special dimension of human experience.
I don't know what he proposed, you said to me last time, has corrupted or cleared my mind.
I have any one thing.
He owes us an explanation of why he thinks the sexuality is a more important dimension of human experience than, say, our relation to things that can be eaten or not eaten.
But I think this precisely that I said that I read when you say that you can have a personal experience if you don't eat, right?
Yeah, the thing you want to say is that you can't separate them all out.
Well, then sexuality is no special or than any of the others.
And he does.
No.
But did I say that it's more special than the others?
Well, yes, because I think to account for the personal level of behavior, sexuality is much more important than the need.
Maybe not the way you eat or this can be a different story.
But the fact that you need to eat is certainly not very personal.
I think many other people in the room should say, right?
Well, then let's take on the personal level your role in the culture.
You're given an identity or the lower job fit into the value.
That's very gentle.
And for that in sure, then say that you've got to take a stand on your own being, by the way, of some role.
Well, he doesn't say things are he doesn't say you're positive either of us.
No.
I guess I'm asking again why is why this chapter on sexuality rather than a chapter on say identity or on mood or on food and explanation of because you feel that something peculiar something bodily peculiar happening when you're first of all when you're having sexual and he say he starts from this and then he says okay how can I relate this to the rest of existence with regards to this specificity and to the specificity of the rest of existence knowing that you can't conceive of the existence as having contingent or necessary parts they're all interrelated.
Yes, this is what he says at the end of the relation.
Is it more of a special dimension than spending?
Because well, speech isn't speech isn't personal.
It's what allows you to have personal relations with other people.
So it's the condition of personal speech behavior.
But it's it's not a matter of being basic or more general.
Because I don't know what the right words are here.
It's not more general.
It's a part of the general.
Everything is a configuration.
I think by then all this appears into this and the human economy in which everything is related to everything.
And then the question is, well, why is things allowed say speech and sexuality over food, over uh the because food doesn't seem to be very personal once they get not very human, actually, because animals eat a lot.
So but it doesn't have the same it doesn't have the same dimension.
No worries you can talk of you can you can talk of sexual instincts for animals, whereas for humans it's worth much more confusing to push the configurations at the beginning of the chapter.
But it gets to the point where having hair and fingernails and everything is equally essential to being human.
In in the I don't forget whether it's in this chapter.
But when everything is equally different, then I don't understand him why because you're you're you're just skipping what's going on this goal into the chapter.
I don't understand this problem.
Well I've been talking about it for an hour now so you're and I think one doesn't have a problem.
I kept answering them or trying to at least hold on there's people on the line.
Whoever is next now I don't know who's next to you that you have you were.
Well originally but originally then.
Okay, right.
I don't know if it helps but what struck me when when you compare the the capital mortality for the personal motility together and sexuality and it's could it turn out as Keiner has a problem which is very much related in both chapters.
You you can't make this possible.
I think I've got less very because you can't point to something.
So it means you can't be attractive to something uh in our side hopefully situation like maybe perfectly or or and the same structure you have here sexuality.
You mustn't quite understand how something can be uh affected by something or by someone or by some experience.
And so I would say this is the same in essential structure again as that gesture and can be attractive to Skinner itself.
Well it doesn't have.
And so he explains this practice.
But I don't know the next sentence.
It helps to understand the beginning of the chapter, but maybe what we mentioned enough is that all the end of the chapter is a discussion.
So most of what I've been discussing today is the only aim of this is to show that you can't reduce everything to sexuality.
No, that's true.
My example shows absolute notable.
Yeah, it's explained.
It still understand that there are, there's a peculiar positive way of experiencing a specific kind of operative intentionality in two origins.
So this means there's an original dimension that's called sexuality in life.
Three, most people say it's beyond the dimension in life.
And most predictive interpretations of Freud say that is it true.
And then discuss it.
The whole one is a problem in general, but hello.
He said that to him, you can interpret Freud as saying that, and he doesn't agree with it, but I think Freud is more complicated, and it's related to the question about the unconscious that's been raised previously because the fact is it can turn into very technical discussions.
But the thing is, for Freud, once again, in three states of sexual theory, he says that he builds his whole people and they say that there's a force that's called individual sexual drive that is the dynamical pattern to which you have to relate everything that happens in life.
And what he says, well, yes and no, it's irreducible, but still you can't relate everything to it as if it would really be the basic.
It gives you an insight on many things that no other dimension can give you an insight on.
That means that it's the thing that you have to reduce everything to.
Okay, but that I'm back to my generality atmosphere thing.
But they claim that it's a special dimension, that for Maori's and people in Bali, everything that people do is colored by the relation to their sexuality doesn't seem to be plausible at all.
He just takes it over dogmatically from Freud and then gives it his first spin.
But I don't understand where the basic claims that the generality of the sexual atmosphere comes from.
I doubt if it's even always claiming that it's double named something, but I mean it is obviously in many people's religious relationship things that sexuality is in there at all.
That's going to say there's a point where you have to be right.
Yeah, well, that's the point.
I don't mind.
The way I'm saying you guys, I'm not exactly sure what I'm about to say.
I'm sorry, I haven't lost in this book.
But there are a few key passages that I think might be a little amazing.
So you want to explain us right now and read the key passages now?
I'm not going to read the passages.
So I think between trying to see the body and your certainty of a subjective experience and collapse all the dimensions of what we want to do.
But I think he says in the other song, I think you have to expand your susceptibility and see that there are no world, which doesn't take each body as a singular subjective.
I mean, they are subjective.
And this is what the end of the book is about.
He says, because he has inherited his shared world, the fact remains that it is not a lesson subjectivity of each of us that each one projects this one and only world.
He talks about health freedom where my freedom, it is a state for me to be free.
I'm giving to myself.
And it all goes about how there can be a subjective experience that we're also eastern.
But okay, so I think you brought enough topics to discuss for a year.
I'm trying.
Okay, so in the other cells, when you do a long chapter, at the end, he says, henceforth, he's talking about how you recognize our own self, and he's talking about recognizing people you already know in the world and your integrity, he said, henceforth is the parts of my body together compromising systems.
So my body and the others are one whole two-sided one-seem phenomenon and the anonymous existence of which my bodies that everyone would face, henceforth, and have exposed bodies simultaneously.
So you have to get away with your body and go and talk about the anonymous.
So first of all, you have to talk about all the dimensions and from a more than comprehensive formula.
Well, the thing is that things to each person are.
I don't have a really subjective world.
I have a really, I have a very well-being.
Subjectivity is not something that normal asserts.
There has to be.
But first of all, when you say you're certain of, no, you're not certain of anything big.
You're not certain of anything, but you are certain of the world in general and hold that not only contributions.
That you have to differentiate from the graphical first.
Then we talked about the anonymous level of experience and that's that comes thanks to the body, because there can be experience.
When we were discussing with Alpha what this finger body meant, and I said that the body is the name of the experience that you have, that things come to your consciousness and that you're motivated to act in such or such a way.
So this is what anonymous means.
It means that it hasn't yet reached the consciousness, but it's already providing a meaning that you choose to accomplish or not.
And precisely, then you've been talking about freedom and freedom.
What is freedom?
It's the fact that you can choose amongst different meanings that are available to you thanks to the fact that the situation has always, it's always ambiguous within the personal dimension.
That's why these cases marks two pages at the end of the sexuality chapter.
This is this is and that's why you need the sexuality chapter to understand what you say in the freedom chapter because for novelty freedom is ambiguous.
It's the fact that a situation has different meanings and that you can choose among them.
So this this might be a way for you to relate all the the the topics that you mentioned.
So there can be no freedom without the body, which is against self.
Says that you just choose at every moment what you're doing.
Involved he says, well, choose what you're going to be doing thanks to the fact that you're being led to differentiate directions of action.
And this is thanks to the first offense.
I I think there's two problems here, isn't it?
One is that you think that you make sexuality too too important and the other one is that it becomes all the extra and that you can't differentiate anymore between biological, the perceptual and asexual compounds.
I think both are not really a problem.
And first of all, because I think it's this the sexual sexuality is not to make sexuality the most important dimension of human starts to say that you shouldn't have discrete perceptual.
There's also what I like to get this more clear is this little footnote at the end of the book which I didn't like because of the biomarker of the I didn't like it but it well don't matter.
But what's happening there is speaking about history and he's speaking about the various ways to look at history from a point of economic from a point of law, common point of management, and all these variants do have something to them.
And you cannot reduce reality to just one of them.
But he says anyway, it's not what suit but another equation.
But in each particular case, one of the order can be redirected dominant.
So in each particular situation you can look uh what's what's going on there and still conclude that in this particular situation that uh the economic was most important and in the last situation it can be uh the related situation at that time.
So perhaps if you can never assert it you know that's right.
That's what your total donality does.
That indeed when I'm eating a steak it's the biological food is a or food situation and when I'm having sex it's the sex situation.
But this is probably what he said, otherwise maybe we we don't have to spend three hours on this.
It's not that you're just being in this or that situation.
Eric is right because on the one hand you say, well there's so much sexuality in it.
And when you try to explain how it's related, we'll still differentiate it from the other situation.
You say, well, it's a big soup.
Well, I don't understand how it's different.
It seems to be a big soup.
And and when you tell me that in eating in each situation, I understand something dominant.
That's not how we lose models.
And for I didn't think that just in the sex sexuation sex was dominant in the economic situation.
Anybody would think that Marx thought there is something special about the ideology.
And for you that there's something special about the sexual this is something he he disagreed with well if you don't agree then that there are nothing more to tell.
Of course he has because if you're in the chapter on the fiddlism of the merchandise in the capital, one you have to understand that obviously you can't produce everything to know you because there's an ideological tension with it.
Then why is there also claim let's go back to sexuality that sex is the least important because of everything, then you got a real point.
You can claim that in some situations it's more important than others, but that no situation comes to us any of that without sexuality anymore.
That's very distinct.
But that's what you're talking about.
That's not that's not realistic at all.
Now the best uh could be hold that every sexuality if every situation also has some economic significance?
Yes.
And now it's become and presumably gastronomic and so forth.
And because they're trying to be kind of other purposes, right?
Is it originary in itself?
I mean, if it's a blend of the biological beach and the culture, right?
So it would not be original as originary as a person.
That would be something.
So they're going to give me criteria or something, right?
And I'm an asking and asking, because then we can see whether sex was and economics was.
And if that religion wasn't, for instance, then I'm going to understand something.
And to say that in any situation something is behind them.
So the thing is, what you're trying to say is that maybe you should say that they're stressing particular parts on the nature of commandment.
That's right.
This is why you were saying that he was using this French-style quarrel.
But I was coming back to that.
Yes, I think this is the background that Oli and I are sort of sharing that I'll mention.
Then Shakespeare has to talk.
But just back in 1945, when this was read, no intellectual friends doubted that Florida Marx had understood something super deep, universal, important, and they couldn't buy anything without taking a stand.
Like Marcuse was teaching that earlier, right?
Like Marcuse who was teaching at Santa Cruz.
But I'm sure there was somebody at Berkeley.
No, it's Henry Edith.
But there was somebody here I'm sure teaching me it too.
It isn't French, but it was these people who were in France, and that's why they had to take a statement on it.
And then Fukuca came along, I just called it in the question and said something like, but I just said, why should we believe that the atmosphere involved with sexual girl and food?
Or he put it that way, but I mean, why should we believe this for a moment?
This whole thing is based on an assumption.
Freud Marx does something right.
Let's figure out the wrong way.
I think you're being responsible, but I will go further in it.
But if you're being privileged influenced by your frequentation of Fukushima response, which I don't see.
Yeah, yeah, but I shouldn't be talking about that.
It's a blender talk, just people whoever has their hands on it.
I was wondering if there could be a background story that explains why the foreground or their significance here.
We mean the left being able to begin the 20th century or all the sexualized role in the food.
But that would be the first.
Okay, it's a great point.
Yeah, I think he meant towards this.
Well, obviously the fact that sexual genes is an atmosphere, perhaps understanding how you can integrate it into the background.
Intermingled, yeah, okay.
That's right.
Yes.
That's why all the dimensions are always too brilliant, even though there might be some one of them that could be more prominent depending on the situation.
Not meaning that you would have to concretely exclude the others, because I think it would be if you didn't believe in the background.
Yeah.
So I'm also trying to figure out exactly what to make of all this.
And I think one thing that you might talk with the discussion that we've been having is to zoom out a bit and remember what the whole book is about.
So, and what is the home book about that?
Well, and what does perception about that?
Well, rather than answering your question, let me sort of put the way I was understanding of it and see if it makes sense to you.
The one thing that I've been slowly getting convinced of as we've read the book, and that what you have said, today in particular, really I'm really convinced by is the idea that these accounts of perceptual consciousness, whether they're sort of reflective intellectualist understanding of consciousness or even the one that Albo mentioned earlier, can't make sense of the phenomenon of perception because they don't make sense of embodiment.
Now, when you start to take embodiment into account in different ways that we've discussed in the class, you have to start to consider all of the baggage that embodiment brings with it.
And one of the dimensions that it brings is the sexual dimension.
So there is a way in which there's a strong claim that sexuality is an atmosphere for our whole existence.
And that's important, in a way, I just wanted to revert in a book about perception, because if perception is going to be based not on one of these forms of consciousness, but rather on a kind of embodiment, which except then the sexual dimension of embodiment is going to also be starting to be available.
Yeah, exactly.
And do we have to breathe, and do we have to be?
I mean, why does that equal privilege?
That's the question.
Can I speak just to that really?
There's wonderful passages on page 157 of the old edition that I'm reading where he talks about intentionality as a as a sort of within as having its own part of the intellectual art.
Sexual art is not an autonomous cycle, though.
It has internal links to the whole active and trouble with being.
The claim that is made is that within the domain of the personal, there's three significant ways of relating to the world.
Not that one is more basic than the other.
There's knowing about the world, and that's hypothetical.
That seems possible.
But the point is sexuality is a mode of pursuit.
When you perceive things in a sexual way, then everything is colored by sex.
And when you're not, there's no sense of, there's no sense of reduction to it.
And by the way, this is the key answer to your question on people just that comes to standard.
Is that sexuality is a mode of proceeding.
And it's not the case that when you're engaged in impersonal or a pre-personal proceeding, that you're implicitly or impressively involved in sexual proceeding, no.
But there is a way of relating to the world which is sexual, which is a mode of perceptual relationship to the world, and which is a component structure within the personal.
All in this atmosphere of all that is.
Which means that you can't take away this dimension, or you couldn't assert that it's absolutely contingent or unnecessary more than about any other dimension.
That's what you're going to remember.
I'm going to say exactly what you say.
I have a neighbor who experiences the world through grief.
I mean, she sees everything as a walking hand with her or whatever.
I mean, that's not her mode of structure, conscious structure.
I think that's just something that you're instructing your worldview.
It could be the ridiculous facial way.
But we've got it backwards.
The problem is to understand, the problem is to understand how having a concept and how sexuality could be.
What is the exact question?
We discovered both of the sexuality, one more form of original intentionality.
That's what Christ is asking.
How sexuality can be a form of intentional original?
Originally.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
I don't know.
Of course not.
It means a sort.
It means a story.
It doesn't mean general.
How can you be a force of intentionality?
That is how it can be a loaded refugees of the world.
But in fact, what it is at all times are not.
It doesn't mean that it's that what determines what you're doing and dance.
Freedom comes into play.
That's it's present as an atmosphere that you can ignore.
It cannot be the notes of what you're doing.
But why should I believe it's present as an atmosphere and not ignoring it?
Why not just believe it's no more present as an atmosphere?
That's cool.
That's not the main credit of the chapters.
Some of the fraudulent claims.
You could delete that sentence in the chapter and find lose all the positives that I'm saying about other values of original source and detail.
I believe it would finally be what takes its place in kind of making the sexual dimension more originary than the outer dimensions.
That's the question.
But you can't explain.
You can't explain.
Yeah, there's a part of the experience that you can't explain.
That's it.
No, no.
I'm just going to say a bit more precisely.
You can't explain the sexuality to the world and truly.
So it's the personal experience.
But what's the problem?
Is it just the fact that he puts home sexuality as being in original dimension?
Because it's I mean it's obvious that in some some behaviors it's what comes into play first and foremost.
That's about everything he's done.
Some day you don't find explaining all uh at least of course but that's why I was but for I I I thought I was here that the fact that he wouldn't go as far as to say that the video is the thing that you would have to reduce everything to.
Okay, so he says this.
So he doesn't agree with FOIA, right?
Okay, right, right, right.
Which is pretty important to understand the chapter.
And then the reason I said uh his brain and freedom comes to play is that you could say or you could disagree with the fact that there the other demotions are co-present in say an experience that that's not primarily sexual blazing.
Well then fine, you're doing something else.
Unless people draw away the line, which I don't think is so absolute, but at all times it's the atmosphere.
And that's a claim about the background.
Yeah, why not?
But think think of the fact that you might be you might be there for a reason that you don't even imagine.
In this or that situation, say you're working down the street and then you're you you're going to the grocery store, right?
To buy whatever.
I think money dump people by what you're in.
And then you're trying to well then you begin you begin there's this sexual background that comes into your mind.
So you you begin sensitizing whatever.
And then if you use your mind that's not indicating that you can conclude that it was always already there.
That is, that it came into my mind shows that in every case it could have come into my mind, but it all detailed in the background.
You're really not.
I mean, maybe that's true, but FOIA at least argument so that they're also specific when we say sexuality.
I think it'll help us understand the chapter when he says sexuality is general in sense of being all three declares of existence.
While talking about the sexual intercourse or general organs or you know, our desire for sex, but it's like sexuality, I think it means the effect of life.
My question for you is: what do you think by the effect of life?
Affected like what's in the beginning of the chapter.
Let me just read the variables.
We then want to turn it like the first feature of the paragraph of the chapter.
Yeah, the end of the first paragraph.
We then want to bring it along further genes for us.
We want to find within that area of our experience, which clearly has significant reality only for us.
And there is our effective life.
So I was trying to see how the figure genes begin to exist for us with desire for love and each other.
You know, you can dial things and being skinny in general.
Only point sensitive to the chapter.
And the second sentence is important too.
Ordinarily, affectivity is conceived as a motivation of effective states of players and pain, each stealing within itself, usually incomprehensible and inflictable only into the body of the system.
In that simply referring to the sexual habits, okay, so you mean it's not a good idea.
No, no, that the second sentence that you write is an account that you completely reject.
And here's what?
It's an account that you complete your rejects.
Or the second paragraph is positively rejected.
So it's it's what's related to sexuality.
But you one thing you're supposed to say that um Then he goes on and says if you like he doesn't say that has to be related to a sexual half.
You know, right in fact they're talking about the sexuality.
It's funny your desires and your what I don't see what this is.
I think it's actually a more general concept that isn't applicable to values in general, not all three dimensions of that.
I think that there's a specialized case that goes right into Agenstein's sexuality and then he goes into void and then goes like a bin style.
You don't get anything about any other activities.
But the point is not that Schneider can't have sex.
The point is not that Schneider can't have sex.
The point is that he can't feel desire.
No attractiveness, that's the point.
So the examples in this chapter are of women.
But you can't perceive them as attractive.
You can't perceive them as attractive as sexual.
It's a vote of perception.
It's a kind of perception that isn't explicable in terms of pre-personal perception.
I don't know what we're disagreeing about now.
It's actually a kind of perception, the homosexual perception.
Okay.
But then you can goes back and I think if he if you did what he's wanting you to do, I think it would be a much more interesting challenge and he talks to be talking about I think all the families kind of and that's the process.
I think the first thing the rest of the program maybe the and uh totally total access point you know if I you know but then that everything is totally unconscious we don't have total so we don't have anything but uh in access to it.
So taking this program so what is the notion of responsibility, right?
He talks about the guys who are okay.